<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">The EXPath Packaging System</textual></title><subtitle class="po-block e2 e2"><textual class="po-textual">A framework to package libraries and applications for core XML technologies</textual></subtitle><info class="po-record e3 e3"><confgroup class="po-record e4 e4"><conftitle class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2010</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e6 e6"><textual class="po-textual">August 3 - 6, 2010</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e7 e7"><para class="po-block e8 e8"><textual class="po-textual">This paper introduces the EXPath Packaging System. It describes the problems
            addressed by application and library packaging, and the current lack of existing
            solutions for XML technologies, before describing the Packaging System itself, its
            structure, its usages and its implementations. It introduces briefly other systems built
            (or that could be built) on top of this system, like a packaging for web applications
            written using only XML technologies, an online repository of libraries and applications,
            or standard structures for XML projects.</textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e9 e9"><personname class="po-record e10 e10"><firstname class="po-field e11 e11"><textual class="po-textual">Florent</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e12 e12"><textual class="po-textual">Georges</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e13 e13"><para class="po-block e14 e14"><textual class="po-textual">Florent Georges is a freelance IT consultant in Brussels who has been involved in
               the XML world for 10 years, especially within the XSLT and XQuery communities. His
               main interests are in the field of XSLT and XQuery extensions and libraries,
               packaging, unit and functional testing, and portability between several processors.
               Since the beginning of 2009, he has worked on EXPath, to define "standard" extension
               function libraries that can be used in XPath (so in XSLT, XQuery and XProc as
               well).</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e15 e15"><jobtitle class="po-field e16 e16"><textual class="po-textual">XML Architect</textual></jobtitle><orgname class="po-block e17 e17"><textual class="po-textual">H2O Consulting</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e18 e18"><textual class="po-textual">fgeorges@h2oconsulting.be</textual></email></author><legalnotice class="po-container e19 e19"><para class="po-block e20 e20"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright ©Florent Georges</textual></para></legalnotice><keywordset class="po-table e21 e21" role="author"><keyword class="po-field e22 e22"><textual class="po-textual">EXPath</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e23 e23"><textual class="po-textual">extension</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">packaging</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e25 e25"><textual class="po-textual">webapp</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e26 e26"><textual class="po-textual">XPath</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e27 e27"><textual class="po-textual">XSLT</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">XQuery</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e29 e29"><textual class="po-textual">XProc</textual></keyword></keywordset></info><note class="po-container e30 e30"><title class="po-block e31 e31"><textual class="po-textual">Quote</textual></title><para class="po-block e32 e32"><quote class="po-inline e33 e33"><emphasis class="po-inline e34 e34"><textual class="po-textual">You're supposed (in the new order) to give everything (stylesheets,
               you, your fridge) an absolute URI and just use that; then the URI used to refer to
               your stylesheet never need to change.</textual></emphasis></quote></para><para class="po-block e35 e35"><textual class="po-textual">--David Carlisle, on XSL List</textual></para></note><section class="po-hcontainer e36 e36"><title class="po-block e37 e37"><textual class="po-textual">Introduction</textual></title><para class="po-block e38 e38"><textual class="po-textual">EXPath has been launched in early 2009. Its goal is to go behind the standards for core
         XML technologies by specifying extensions to those technologies in a consistent and
         standard way across different processors, collaboratively by the relevant
         communities.</textual></para><para class="po-block e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">Most of these core XML technologies are based on XPath, hence the decision to focus
         principally on XPath. The whole project is divided into small parts, the
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e40 e40"><textual class="po-textual">modules</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, more or less independent on each others. A specific
         processor can thus chose to implement only some of those modules, regarding what is
         relevant to the technologies it supports or what is relevant to its users.</textual></para><para class="po-block e41 e41"><textual class="po-textual">Even though the idea is to provide the several vendors with a set of
            (</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e42 e42"><textual class="po-textual">de-facto</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">) standard modules to implement themselves, people may
         chose to implement a module as a commercial or open-source product for a specific processor
         (given this processor provides the appropriate extension mechanism). Actually some modules
         are currently directly supported by some processors while other implementations exist as
         third-party products. The EXPath community itself provides several open-source
         implementations, as well as support for such projects.</textual></para><para class="po-block e43 e43"><textual class="po-textual">This paper focuses especially on the Packaging System defined by EXPath as a way to
         package and deliver XML libraries or applications </textual><footnote class="po-popup e44 e44"><para class="po-block e45 e45"><textual class="po-textual">By </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e46 e46"><textual class="po-textual">XML libraries and applications</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, we mean libraries and
               applications for (or written in) XSLT, XQuery, XProc, XML Schema, or other XML
               technologies.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> and to allow a user to rely on tools to automatically install (or deploy) such
         packages.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e47 e47"><title class="po-block e48 e48"><textual class="po-textual">The problem</textual></title><para class="po-block e49 e49"><textual class="po-textual">To introduce the packaging system, let's try to answer the initial question:
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e50 e50"><textual class="po-textual">what is such a system useful for?</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Let's try to do so by using a
         specific example.</textual></para><para class="po-block e51 e51"><textual class="po-textual">You are in charge of an XQuery application which, very imaginatively, you called MyApp.
         As several other XQuery applications, MyApp uses the FunctX library (an XQuery and XSLT
         library providing general-purpose functions, like date and string manipulation functions).
         In order to ease the integration of FunctX into MyApp, you decided to simply copy the
         source file into your own code base. You then use the same rules to import the library as
         for the import statements for your own XQuery modules:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e52 e52" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">import module namespace f = "http://www.functx.com"
   at "../../lib/functx.xq";</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e53 e53"><textual class="po-textual">So far, so good. Later on, you decide to use another library providing support for XBRL
         (a standard language for business reporting). It turns out that this library actually uses
         also FunctX. So you install the library into your code base, and you modify its source code
         to adapt the import statements related to FunctX to follow your own rules for import
         statements. Indeed, you feel guilty to modify the source code of a third-party library just
         to be able to use it (as in the first place you did feel guilty to copy the source code of
         a third-party library into your own code base). But you don't have any other choice, have
         you?</textual></para><para class="po-block e54 e54"><textual class="po-textual">You then use yet another library. You follow the install instructions. Manually of
         course. Anyway those instructions are more or less: </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e55 e55"><textual class="po-textual">Copy the files "somewhere"
            and use whatever mechanism your processor provides you with to import the library
            modules</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. So once again, you copy the whole source code into your own code
         base. You don't know it, but actually that library also uses FunctX (yes, FunctX is really
         useful) and you end up with two FunctX implementations into your own code base (hopefully
         the same implementations).</textual></para><para class="po-block e56 e56"><textual class="po-textual">We could continue this example for ever, with troubles updating FunctX or any of the
         libraries using it, or by describing the pain of manually installing or updating any new
         library. And yet, those are only the issues a library user can find on his way. Let's now
         pretend your are a library author. You are in a maze, struggling with dependency management
         and installation instructions. You feel there should be a simple solution. You are getting
         sleepy. Very sleepy. Your eyelids are heavy. Very heavy...</textual></para><para class="po-block e57 e57"><textual class="po-textual">To make the long story short, dependency management is a complex problem and has always
         been. And there is no standard addressing this problem accross several XML technologies.
         Typically, each standard get rid of this problem by making it an implementation-defined,
         optional feature. This is a reasonable decision at the level of each independent standard.
         But having a specification addressing those issues accross several standards allows to
         address the most common use cases and to build packaging tools compatible with several
         processors. From the above example, we can list the following issues, that the Packaging
         System tries to address:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e58 e58"><listitem class="po-container e59 e59"><para class="po-block e60 e60"><textual class="po-textual">to solve the common problem of installing a third-party library, we always have to
               think about similar technical solutions;</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e61 e61"><para class="po-block e62 e62"><textual class="po-textual">the way to install a library is always slightly different, because of differences
               in the way the libraries themselves are packaged, whilst the concepts are always the
               same;</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e63 e63"><para class="po-block e64 e64"><textual class="po-textual">library packaging (i.e. the other end of the delivery cycle) has the same
               problems: no standards, no tools, and at the end of the day we always end up with
               something different whilst the concepts are the same;</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e65 e65"><para class="po-block e66 e66"><textual class="po-textual">this situation prevents writing tools to help the developer to automate the build,
               delivery and install cycle (for other languages, some tools provide a way to create
               automatically a new project, from which they can automate the build process, and at
               the other end systems provide the user with a way to automatically install those
               packages).</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></section><section class="po-hcontainer e67 e67"><title class="po-block e68 e68"><textual class="po-textual">The Packaging System</textual></title><para class="po-block e69 e69"><textual class="po-textual">To address this problem, EXPath defines a packaging system to help library and
         application authors to package and deliver their products without having to take care of
         specific install procedures and of every possible existing processors, now or in the
         future.</textual></para><para class="po-block e70 e70"><textual class="po-textual">The basic idea is simple. A package is a set of components, and contains enough
         informations about those components for a processor to install them properly, and to let a
         user refer to them within his own applications or libraries by using always the same
         absolute URI, resolved by the processor at compile-time. As soon as a library is packaged
         using this format, it is usable in all processors supporting the packaging system, without
         the need for any further instructions for the users.</textual></para><para class="po-block e71 e71"><textual class="po-textual">So a package is a set of components. A component is any piece of code of a supported XML
         technology, e.g. an XSLT stylesheet, an XQuery module, an XProc pipeline, or a schema (XSD,
         Relax NG, NVDL, Schematron, etc.) The packaging system has been designed to be extensible,
         and an implementation can support other kinds of component: a standard not supported yet
         like BPEL, or even processor-specific components like a Java implementation of extensions
         for Saxon (several implementations for Saxon of EXPath modules are actually delivered this
         way).</textual></para><para class="po-block e72 e72"><textual class="po-textual">The several components are packaged as a single file by creating a ZIP file. In order to
         provide enough information to the installer, the structure of this ZIP file must follow a
         few simple rules, and contains in addition a package descriptor. The package descriptor is
         a simple XML file defined in the specification, providing informations about the components
         and the package.</textual></para><para class="po-block e73 e73"><textual class="po-textual">A central concept in the packaging system is the concept of public URIs. Each component
         is associated with such a URI. In turn, this URI can be used to access the component. For
         instance, if a library contains an XSLT stylesheet, a public URI for this stylesheet is
         defined in the package descriptor. The user can then use this URI in an
            </textual><code class="po-atom e74 e74"><textual class="po-textual">xsl:import</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> instruction to import this stylesheet:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e75 e75" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;!-- the user's stylesheet can import the library's stylesheet --&gt;
&lt;xsl:import href="http://example.org/the/public/uri/of/the-stylesheet"/&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e76 e76"><textual class="po-textual">The package structure (i.e. the structure of the files and directories in the ZIP file)
         is simple. It must contain the file descriptor at the top-level of the ZIP file (an XML
         file named </textual><code class="po-atom e77 e77"><textual class="po-textual">expath-pkg.xml</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">) and a sub-directory with the actual components. The
         library author is free to organize this sub-directory as he/she wants. If we take again the
         example of FunctX, which contains an implementation of the functions both as an XQuery
         module and as an XSLT stylesheet, it could have the following structure:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e78 e78" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">- expath-pkg.xml
- functx/
    - functx.xq
    - functx.xsl</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e79 e79"><textual class="po-textual">The package descriptor itself (i.e. the file </textual><code class="po-atom e80 e80"><textual class="po-textual">expath-pkg.xml</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">) provides a few
         informations about the library itself (a name, a version number, etc.) and associates a
         public URI to each component in the package:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e81 e81" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;package xmlns="http://expath.org/ns/pkg"
         name="http://www.functx.com"
         version="1.0"&gt;

   &lt;title&gt;FunctX library&lt;/title&gt;
   &lt;desc&gt;The FunctX library, both for XQuery 1.0 and XSLT 2.0.&lt;/desc&gt;

   &lt;xquery&gt;
      &lt;namespace&gt;http://www.functx.com&lt;/namespace&gt;
      &lt;file&gt;functx.xq&lt;/file&gt;
   &lt;/xquery&gt;
   &lt;xslt&gt;
      &lt;import-uri&gt;http://www.functx.com/functx.xsl&lt;/import-uri&gt;
      &lt;file&gt;functx.xsl&lt;/file&gt;
   &lt;/xslt&gt;

&lt;/package&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e82 e82"><textual class="po-textual">This is a simple package descriptor. It describes both components in the FunctX package:
         the XSLT stylesheet and the XQuery module. The </textual><code class="po-atom e83 e83"><textual class="po-textual">file</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> element points to the
         actual source code within the package, while the elements </textual><code class="po-atom e84 e84"><textual class="po-textual">import-uri</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and
            </textual><code class="po-atom e85 e85"><textual class="po-textual">namespace</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> set the public URI of each component. There are elements to
         configure other kind of components like XProc, RNG, RNC, XSD, Schematron and NVDL. An
         implementation can also define its own elements (in its own namespace). For instance, the
         package for the Java implementation for Saxon of the EXPath HTTP Client contains the
         following:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e86 e86" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;java xmlns="http://expath.org/ns/pkg/saxon"&gt;
   &lt;jar&gt;saxon/jar/expath-http-client-saxon.jar&lt;/jar&gt;
   &lt;function&gt;org.expath.httpclient.saxon.SendRequestFunction&lt;/function&gt;
   ...
   &lt;saxon&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e87 e87"><textual class="po-textual">The Packaging System specification defines the format of the packages. That is required
         to ensure compatibility accross different implementations. So while everything else is
         implementation-defined, an implementation will typically use the following components:</textual></para><para class="po-block e88 e88"><textual class="po-textual">
         </textual><mediaobject class="po-container e89 e89"><imageobject class="po-container e90 e90"><imagedata class="po-meta e91 e91" fileref="../../../vol5/graphics/Georges01/Georges01-001.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><textual class="po-textual">
      </textual></para><para class="po-block e92 e92"><textual class="po-textual">The central piece is the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e93 e93"><textual class="po-textual">repository</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, where the packages are
         installed. It can be dedicated to one product (or even one instance of a product, e.g. for
         a database), or be shared accross several products. The </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e94 e94"><textual class="po-textual">processors</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> are
         the products you want to be able to use the packages with (that is, your usual XQuery or
         XSLT or XProc processors). A </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e95 e95"><textual class="po-textual">manager</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (part of the processor or
         provided as a separate program) is used to actually install the packages into the
         repository (or remove them, list them, etc.)</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e96 e96"><title class="po-block e97 e97"><textual class="po-textual">Integration</textual></title><para class="po-block e98 e98"><textual class="po-textual">As for other modules, and even more for the packaging system, the goal is to have to
         implemented directly by the several processors. This is the case for eXist for instance.
         Third-party implementations have been written for Saxon and Calabash too.</textual></para><para class="po-block e99 e99"><textual class="po-textual">Even though a processor is allowed to implement the packaging system in any way, the
         specification defines a standard on-disk repository layout. If such an on-disk repository
         makes sense for a specific processor, it can then benefit from standard tools to manage the
         repository (install new packages, remove existing one, install directly from the Internet,
         etc.) The packaging support in Saxon and Calabash for instance are open-source third-party
         implementations. Those implementations resolve at compile-time the URIs within the user
         stylesheets and pipelines to the imported components in the repository:</textual></para><para class="po-block e100 e100"><textual class="po-textual">
         </textual><mediaobject class="po-container e101 e101"><imageobject class="po-container e102 e102"><imagedata class="po-meta e103 e103" fileref="../../../vol5/graphics/Georges01/Georges01-002.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><textual class="po-textual">
      </textual></para><para class="po-block e104 e104"><textual class="po-textual">The repository itself is managed by a standalone application, dedicated to that purpose.
         Because this repository format is defined in the specification, if an implementation chose
         to support it, it does not have to take care at all about repository management, and the
         user can then use one single tool to manage repositories, even for several processors. But
         for some processors, such an on-disk repository just does not make sense, or is not the
         best design choice (e.g. for embedded systems or processors that can pre-compile packages
         on a distributed environment).</textual></para><para class="po-block e105 e105"><textual class="po-textual">Let us look at a concrete example. A stylesheet uses FunctX to build a date from three
         integers (the year, the month and the day). Note that it uses an absolute URI to import the
         FunctX stylesheet, and this URI does not point to an actual location. This is just a name,
         and will be used to resolved the FunctX stylesheet from the repository:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e106 e106" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;xsl:stylesheet xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
                xmlns:f="http://www.functx.com"
                exclude-result-prefixes="f"
                version="2.0"&gt;

   &lt;xsl:import href="http://www.functx.com/functx.xsl"/&gt;

   &lt;xsl:output indent="yes"/&gt;

   &lt;xsl:template name="main"&gt;
      &lt;result&gt;
         &lt;xsl:sequence select="f:date(1979, 9, 1)"/&gt;
      &lt;/result&gt;
   &lt;/xsl:template&gt;

&lt;/xsl:stylesheet&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e107 e107"><textual class="po-textual">This stylesheet is also used in an XProc pipeline:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e108 e108" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;p:declare-step xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
                xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
                xmlns:f="http://www.functx.com"
                version="1.0"&gt;

   &lt;p:input port="parameters" kind="parameter"/&gt;
   &lt;p:input port="source"/&gt;
   &lt;p:output port="result"/&gt;

   &lt;p:xslt template-name="main"&gt;
      &lt;p:input port="stylesheet"&gt;
         &lt;p:document href="user.xsl"/&gt;
      &lt;/p:input&gt;
   &lt;/p:xslt&gt;

&lt;/p:declare-step&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e109 e109"><textual class="po-textual">We have to install FunctX in the repository in order for those components to run
         properly. The command </textual><code class="po-atom e110 e110"><textual class="po-textual">xrepo</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> is the standalone repository manager. It can
         manage several repositories, list the content of a specific repository, install and remove
         packages. In a first time, FunctX is not installed yet, so the transform fails. Then we
         install the package, and run the transform again:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e111 e111" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&gt; saxon -xsl:user.xsl -it:main
Error at xsl:import on line 6 column 56 of user.xsl:
  XTSE0165: java.io.FileNotFoundException: http://www.functx.com/functx.xsl
Failed to compile stylesheet. 1 error detected.

&gt; calabash user.xproc
Apr 18, 2010 3:02:05 AM com.xmlcalabash.core.XProcRuntime error
SEVERE: Pipeline failed: [...]: Failed to compile stylesheet. 1 error detected.
Apr 18, 2010 3:02:05 AM com.xmlcalabash.core.XProcRuntime error
SEVERE: Underlying exception: [...]: Failed to compile stylesheet. 1 error detected.

&gt; xrepo install functx.xar
Install module FunctX library? [true]: 
Install it to dir [functx]: 

&gt; saxon -xsl:user.xsl -it:main
&lt;result&gt;1979-09-01&lt;/result&gt;

&gt; calabash user.xproc
&lt;result&gt;1979-09-01&lt;/result&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e112 e112"><textual class="po-textual">The format of the repository itself is simplistic. This is a directory on the
         filesystem, which contains one sub-directory per installed library. Each of those
         sub-directory has the same structure as the XAR file it was created with, with possibly a
         few informations generated during the install process in order to simplify the resolving
         mechanism at runtime. For instance, if the package contains extension functions written in
         Java for either Saxon or eXist, a simple file is generated containing the classpath needed
         by this module in order for an application to find it:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e113 e113" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">/usr/share/expath/repo/
   .expath-pkg/
      ...
      [management infos, to help building efficient implementations]
      ...
   functx-1.0/
      expath-pkg.xml
      functx/
         functx.xql
         functx.xsl
   google-apis-0.2/
      expath-pkg.xml
      google-apis/
         xq/
            gdata.xql
            gdata-impl.xql
         xsl/
            gcontacts.xsl
            gdata.xsl
            gdata-impl.xsl
            gdocs.xsl
            gcode.xsl
            gmaps.xsl
   expath-http-client-0.6/
      expath-pkg.xml
      .exist/
         classpath.txt
      .saxon/
         classpath.txt
      expath-http-client/
         exist/
            expath-http-client-exist.jar
         saxon/
            expath-http-client-saxon.jar
            expath-http-client-saxon.xql
            expath-http-client-saxon.xsl
         lib/
            apache-mime4j-0.6.jar
            commons-codec-1.4.jar
            commons-logging-1.1.1.jar
            httpclient-4.0.1.jar
            httpcore-4.0.1.jar
            tagsoup-1.2.jar</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e114 e114"><textual class="po-textual">Let us have a closer look at this particular repository. Three libraries have been
         installed: FunctX 1.0, the Google APIs 0.2 and the EXPath HTTP Client for Saxon and eXist
         0.6, an implementation in Java of the EXPath HTTP Client module. The first directory,
            </textual><code class="po-atom e115 e115"><textual class="po-textual">.expath-pkg</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, contains internal informations about what is installed, and
         how to use it. It is not used already, but its first usage will probably be to record for
         each package the longest URI prefix common to all its components. This in turn can be used
         by the runtime resolvers to know in which package look for a particular component, given
         its public URI. This is important for standalone processors like Saxon which during one
         execution will typically use only a few components from the repository, as this enable it
         to only parse the package descriptors for those packages, and not for the whole repository.
         In general, the directory </textual><code class="po-atom e116 e116"><textual class="po-textual">.expath-pkg</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> is a place to put management data about
         the repository as a whole.</textual></para><para class="po-block e117 e117"><textual class="po-textual">The second directory, </textual><code class="po-atom e118 e118"><textual class="po-textual">functx-0.1</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, contains the FunctX library. This
         directory has exactly the same structure as the XAR package. Put another way, this
         directory is the result of unzipping the XAR file. The package descriptor, that is
            </textual><code class="po-atom e119 e119"><textual class="po-textual">expath-pkg.xml</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, contains all the information to resolve a public URI to an
         actual component at runtime. The third directory, </textual><code class="po-atom e120 e120"><textual class="po-textual">google-apis-0.2</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, contains
         another example of a package, just a bit more complex. Especially, we can see the package
         directory internal structure is preserved (the subdirectories </textual><code class="po-atom e121 e121"><textual class="po-textual">xq</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and
            </textual><code class="po-atom e122 e122"><textual class="po-textual">xsl</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">).  This is important for relative import statements to work.</textual></para><para class="po-block e123 e123"><textual class="po-textual">The last directory, </textual><code class="po-atom e124 e124"><textual class="po-textual">expath-http-client-0.6</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, shows a library implemented in
         Java. It contains an implementation for both Saxon and eXist. In addition to the usual
         content of the package (the package descriptor and the package directory), we can see we
         have two subdirectories, containing additional infos about the package for different
         implementations (here, Saxon and eXist). The classpath.txt file, in both cases, contains a
         line-separated list of JAR files that must be added to the classpath in order to use the
         extension. Simply speaking, this contains the JAR within which the extension has been
         compiled, and a list of the libraries it depends on. Those files are generated at
         install-time by the installer, based on the package descriptor. They are used by the
         launchers to properly set the classpath, because this must be done at launch time, when we
         don't know yet which libraries we will use, and we don't want to parse every package
         descriptor every time we launch the application (and typically a few libraries only will
         define Java extensions).</textual></para><para class="po-block e125 e125"><textual class="po-textual">One of the advantages of having such a standard layout for the repositories is to be
         able to share the implementation (as it is actually shared between Saxon, eXist and
         Calabash), which means better maintained and up-to-date software. It is also very
         lightweight, and it is possible to create several repositories for dedicated purposes.
         Typically a general repository will be created on a machine to be used by interactive tools
         like Saxon and Calabash, and maybe IDEs like oXygen. Then specific repositories can be
         created for large projects like a Java Enterprise application, for which we want to control
         precisely the set of dependencies.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e126 e126"><title class="po-block e127 e127"><textual class="po-textual">Going further</textual></title><para class="po-block e128 e128"><textual class="po-textual">The Packaging System specification tries to be extensible and generic enough to allow
         different kind of tools as well as other specification to be built on top of it. We
         introduce here three of those related projects: a standard structure for XML projects and
         its associated tools to automatically build the packages, an online directory of packages a
         la CPAN, and an extended version of the packaging system itself for web applications
         written only with XML technologies (as defined in the EXPath Webapp module).</textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e129 e129"><title class="po-block e130 e130"><textual class="po-textual">Standard project structure</textual></title><para class="po-block e131 e131"><textual class="po-textual">The packaging system specification is a low-level specification. It is interesting
            for a user to understand how this system works and how it has been designed, but ideally
            he/she should never need to read it in order to use it. The user should never be
            bothered with the low-level details of the package's ZIP file structure nor even by the
            package descriptor. How many Java developer do really build their JAR files using the
            UNIX tar command, and write the JAR Manifest file by hand? In some case that can be
            useful, but usually a Java developer just rely on its IDE to create a (more or less)
            adapted project structure, and to provide the action </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e132 e132"><textual class="po-textual">build</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> to
            automatically build the JAR file.</textual></para><para class="po-block e133 e133"><textual class="po-textual">Java is indeed only an example, but all mainstream languages do have such tools. And
            that is a good thing as this allows the developer to focus on what is really important:
            the business logic. The packaging is of course important as well. But usually the
            packaging, and more generally the build system of a project, involve always the same
            steps and can be handled automatically by a program.</textual></para><para class="po-block e134 e134"><textual class="po-textual">This idea is to create a well-defined directory structure for a new project, so a
            packaging program can use be used to package the project as a XAR file. Different kinds
            of structure can be defined, or different flavors for different needs (e.g. a plain
            XProc library, a web application, or an extension for eXist written in Java).</textual></para><para class="po-block e135 e135"><textual class="po-textual">This is only a research area for now, but a simple structure has been defined for
            plain libraries (i.e. packages of standard components), and a tool has been created that
            use this structure to automatically build the XAR file. This tool is called
               </textual><code class="po-atom e136 e136"><textual class="po-textual">packager</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">. The directory structure of a new project must have a
               </textual><code class="po-atom e137 e137"><textual class="po-textual">build/</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> subdirectory for the build infos, as well as a </textual><code class="po-atom e138 e138"><textual class="po-textual">src/</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
            subdirectory for the actual sources of the components. Here is the structure of an
            hypothetical project </textual><code class="po-atom e139 e139"><textual class="po-textual">hello-world</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e140 e140" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">hello-world/
   build/
      project.xml
   src/
      hello-world.xq
      hello.xql
      hello.xsl</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e141 e141"><textual class="po-textual">The </textual><code class="po-atom e142 e142"><textual class="po-textual">build/</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> dir is used by the build process, and contains a file
               </textual><code class="po-atom e143 e143"><textual class="po-textual">project.xml</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> provided by the user. This file give the packager all the
            infos it needs and that it cannot infer from the directory structure and from the source
            files themselves. Principally, those are the infos like the name and the version number
            of the package to build:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e144 e144" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;package xmlns="http://expath.org/ns/packager"
         name="http://example.org/hello-world"
         version="1.0"&gt;
   &lt;title&gt;Hello, world!: an example project&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;/package&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e145 e145"><textual class="po-textual">In order to build the package, the packager needs to know which files to include as
            components. Those are simply the files in the </textual><code class="po-atom e146 e146"><textual class="po-textual">src/</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> directory with a
            specific extension (like *.xql, *.xproc, *.xsl, etc.) And for each of them, it also
            needs to know the public URI to associate to the component. Instead of requiring the
            developer to maintain an external document with this information (like the package
            descriptor), those public URIs are directly set into each component. That makes more
            sense as this public URI can be seen as the name of the component, and there is no
            better place for this name than within the component itself.</textual></para><para class="po-block e147 e147"><textual class="po-textual">The exact way a URI is associated to a component depends on the kind of component.
            For components that are also XML documents, like XProc pipelines and XSLT stylesheet,
            this is done by adding an element </textual><code class="po-atom e148 e148"><textual class="po-textual">pkg:import-uri</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">. For XQuery, the component
            is either a library module and thus already has a target namespace, or it is a main
            module and the public URI is set as the value of the global variable
               </textual><code class="po-atom e149 e149"><textual class="po-textual">$pkg:import</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">. For instance, this is an excerpt of these kind of
            components:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e150 e150" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">(:~
 : an XQuery main module, sets $pkg:import-uri
 :)
declare namespace pkg = "http://expath.org/ns/pkg";
declare variable $pkg:import-uri := 'http://example.org/hello-world/hello-world.xq';
...

(:~
 : an XQuery library module, already contains enough information
 :)
module namespace hw = "http://example.org/hello-world";
...

&lt;!--
   an XSLT stylesheet, uses a user element pkg:import-uri
--&gt;
&lt;xsl:stylesheet ...&gt;
   &lt;pkg:import-uri&gt;http://example.org/hello-world/hello.xsl&lt;/pkg:import-uri&gt;
   ...

&lt;!--
   an XProc pipeline, uses an element pkg:import-uri
--&gt;
&lt;p:pipeline ...&gt;
   &lt;pkg:import-uri&gt;http://example.org/hello-world/hello.xproc&lt;/pkg:import-uri&gt;
   ...</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e151 e151"><textual class="po-textual">With the public URIs set directly within the component, with the well-known directory
            structure, and with the few infos in </textual><code class="po-atom e152 e152"><textual class="po-textual">build/project.xml</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, the packager tool
            has all it needs to create automatically the package. The developer does not have
            neither to maintain the package descriptor when adding new components, he/she just has
            to set properly the public URI within the component.</textual></para><para class="po-block e153 e153"><textual class="po-textual">The packager itself is an XSLT stylesheet using the EXPath Files and ZIP modules to
            navigate the file system and create the actual package in </textual><code class="po-atom e154 e154"><textual class="po-textual">build/</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> (either
            for a library or a web application). This is all the packager does for now. But it will
            be extended to support XSpec (to automatically run unit tests), deployment of a web
            application on a Webapp container, documentation generation, and other tasks we usually
            find in project managers and IDEs.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e155 e155"><title class="po-block e156 e156"><textual class="po-textual">CXAN</textual></title><para class="po-block e157 e157"><textual class="po-textual">The Packaging System defines the format and the structure of one package. So it can
            be built from sources by a packager tool, and be installed in a processor or a local
            repository by the user. It contains also meta informations like a name and a version
            number. This provides the needed mechanisms to create a global directory of known
            libraries and applications in and for XSLT, XQuery, XProc, etc.</textual></para><para class="po-block e158 e158"><textual class="po-textual">Like CTAN for TeX and LaTeX, CPAN for Perl, or also the APT system for Linux
            programs, the Packaging System makes it possible to create CXAN, the
               </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e159 e159"><textual class="po-textual">Comprehensive XML Archive Network</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (or the
               </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e160 e160"><textual class="po-textual">Comprehensive X* Archive Network</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> if you prefer a stronger
            difference between XML and the XML technologies we are discussing here).</textual></para><para class="po-block e161 e161"><textual class="po-textual">CXAN (pronounce it </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e162 e162"><textual class="po-textual">c-zan</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">) is composed of two parts. First a
            website which contains all the uploaded packages and provides a way to navigate through
            them, search for them and download them. And second a client program to retrieve a
            package over the Internet and install it locally. This is a good example of the benefit
            of using the standard repository layout for a processor implementing the Packaging
            System, because there is an open-source implementation of a CXAN client that supports
            local on-disk repositories with the standard layout. Other implementations can of course
            support CXAN as well, but then they have to implement this support themselves.</textual></para><para class="po-block e163 e163"><textual class="po-textual">The client part is similar to the programs </textual><code class="po-atom e164 e164"><textual class="po-textual">cpan</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><code class="po-atom e165 e165"><textual class="po-textual">apt-get</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">.
            It provides the ability to look into the package database and directly install the
            package on a local repository. In the example about the standard repository manager,
               </textual><code class="po-atom e166 e166"><textual class="po-textual">xrepo</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, in the above section, we shaw how to install the FunctX package,
            provided it has already downloaded somehow:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e167 e167" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">xrepo install functx.xar</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e168 e168"><textual class="po-textual">If this package has been uploaded to CXAN, under the name </textual><code class="po-atom e169 e169"><textual class="po-textual">functx</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, we can
            easily adapt this example to CXAN by using the following command instead:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e170 e170" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">cxan install functx</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e171 e171"><textual class="po-textual">In this case, there is nothing on the local hard drive (except the local repository
            of course), and the CXAN manager will automatically retrieve the FunctX package on
               </textual><code class="po-atom e172 e172"><textual class="po-textual">http://cxan.org/</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and install it in the local repository.</textual></para><para class="po-block e173 e173"><textual class="po-textual">CXAN is only a prototype at this stage, but the concepts are quite simple and the
            technical part almost trivial once we have a packaging system. The crucial work will be
            the amount of libraries uploaded, their quality and the quality of their meta-data. But
            there are plenty of talented X* developers out there with a lot of interesting ideas of
            libraries. Reaching a large audience with an XML library is quite difficult for now,
            because of the differences between the processors, and the lack of automatic install
            processes even for one single processor. But with the help of a proper packaging system
            and a system like CXAN, it is finally possible to write a general-purpose library and
            diffuse it over the whole community.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e174 e174"><title class="po-block e175 e175"><textual class="po-textual">Webapp packaging</textual></title><para class="po-block e176 e176"><textual class="po-textual">EXPath contains several modules for several needs. A typical EXPath module is a set
            of XPath functions, defined in a specification. The Packaging System is a bit different
            as it defines instead a whole system and a file format to package XML libraries. There
            is another EXPath module which defines a system rather than a library of functions: the
            Webapp module. Its goal is to make it possible to write web applications entirely with
            XML technologies. The Webapp module defines an abstract web application container, the
            services it provides to the deployed web applications, and the way it maps HTTP requests
            and responses to and from those applications (as well as a mechanism to package such
            applications). This is a well-known abstraction used by several major frameworks for web
            applications, like the Java Servlet technology.</textual></para><para class="po-block e177 e177"><textual class="po-textual">Basically, a web application based on this module is written in plain XSLT, XQuery or
            XProc, with some entry points respecting an interface defined by the Webapp module.
            Those entry points (function, template, pipeline...) receive a representation of the
            HTTP request as input and return a representation of the HTTP response as output. They
            are configured in a web application descriptor to be mapped to some URIs or URI
            patterns. When the server receives a request on a URI, it looks for a matching
            component, calls it with the proper input and return its result as the coresponding HTTP
            response, as shown on the following diagram:</textual></para><para class="po-block e178 e178"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><mediaobject class="po-container e179 e179"><imageobject class="po-container e180 e180"><imagedata class="po-meta e181 e181" fileref="../../../vol5/graphics/Georges01/Georges01-003.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><textual class="po-textual">
         </textual></para><para class="po-block e182 e182"><textual class="po-textual">The packaging of those web applications is based on the Packaging System. The Webapp
            module specification does refer to the specification of the Packaging System, and
            extends it by adding the web descriptor. The web descriptor maps URI patterns to
            specific components in the package, or to specific functions, templates or steps within
            those components. But all the packaging machinery itself is already defined. Just to get
            an idea, here is an excerpt of such a web descriptor:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e183 e183" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;webapp name="http://h2oconsulting.be/ns/website"
        ...&gt;

   &lt;title&gt;H2O Consulting website&lt;/title&gt;

   &lt;!--
       The Freedom page.
   --&gt;
   &lt;servlet name="freedom"&gt;
      &lt;xslt function="free:backup-servlet"&gt;
         &lt;import-uri&gt;http://h2oconsulting.be/ns/website/freedom.xsl&lt;/import-uri&gt;
      &lt;/xslt&gt;
      &lt;url pattern="/freedom"/&gt;
   &lt;/servlet&gt;

   &lt;!--
       Serve main pages, transformed from XML files to XHTML.
   --&gt;
   &lt;servlet name="pages"&gt;
      &lt;xslt function="h2o:pages-servlet"&gt;
         &lt;import-uri&gt;http://h2oconsulting.be/ns/website/servlets.xsl&lt;/import-uri&gt;
      &lt;/xslt&gt;
      &lt;url pattern="/([-a-z0-9]+)?"&gt;
         &lt;match group="1" name="page"/&gt;
      &lt;/url&gt;
   &lt;/servlet&gt;

   ...

&lt;/webapp&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e184 e184"><textual class="po-textual">You can see that the principal role of this web descriptor is to map URIs (or URI
            patterns) to entry points (functions, templates, pipelines, etc.) Note in particular
            that those entry points, behind their name, are identified by an import URI (and not by
            a file name for instance). This import URI is the one defined by the Packaging System
            and is set in the package descriptor. The Webapp module does not have to worry about
            such a mechanism to resolve stylesheets or XQuery modules. It can simply reuse the
            Packaging System mechanism, by extending it with entry points name in order to point to
            specific functions, templates or pipelines within those components.</textual></para><para class="po-block e185 e185"><textual class="po-textual">Servlex is an open-source implementation of Webapp, using Saxon and Calabash as the
            processors to execute the components. It uses the same standard on-disk repository
            layout to deploy the web applications on the server. Thanks to this, it can reuse the
            existing open-source implementation of the Packaging System, and its integrations within
            both Saxon and Calabash, and needs just to process the webapp descriptor to initialize a
            map between URIs and components.</textual></para><para class="po-block e186 e186"><textual class="po-textual">Because the Packaging System specification has been designed to be extensible, it is
            possible to use it in other specifications, and to reuse some existing tools for more
            specific needs.</textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e187 e187"><title class="po-block e188 e188"><textual class="po-textual">Conclusion</textual></title><para class="po-block e189 e189"><textual class="po-textual">The lack of a proper packaging format to publish XML libraries has prevented people to
         write and publish such libraries in an implementation agnostic way (implementations usually
         do not provide such a facility anyway). The EXPath Packaging System aims to solve this
         problem, by defining an implementation-independent packaging format. This format is
         extensible and can be reused for other needs, like the web application packaging. This
         system is not only a way to distribute packages, but can also be the missing piece for a
         lot of different applications, like CXAN and the project structures. And other ideas we
         have not thought about yet...</textual></para></section></article></classedDocument>