<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">How to Play XML: Markup Technologies as Nomic Game</textual></title><info class="po-record e2 e2"><confgroup class="po-record e3 e3"><conftitle class="po-field e4 e4"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">August 11 - 14, 2009</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e6 e6"><para class="po-block e7 e7"><textual class="po-textual">What is a </textual><quote class="po-inline e8 e8"><textual class="po-textual">game</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">? A definition is famously difficult.
        Wittgenstein, for example, after having described language as a game in
        his </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e9 e9"><textual class="po-textual">Philosophical Investigations</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, goes on to ask
        what a game is and how we know what's a game, using the word
          (</textual><quote class="po-inline e10 e10"><textual class="po-textual">Spiel</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> in German) as a vivid example of the provisional
        and contingent nature of the supposedly clear concepts communicated by
        language. Game theory, a branch of mathematics, solves this question by
        avoiding it, providing its own definition of </textual><quote class="po-inline e11 e11"><textual class="po-textual">game</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, which
        only partially fits many or most games as we know them. And talking
        about games becomes really interesting when we reflect, as is
        inescapable since Peter Suber coined the term </textual><quote class="po-inline e12 e12"><textual class="po-textual">nomic game</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">
        in 1982, that part of the action of many games, and indeed the essence
        of some, is in the process, play or competition of providing the game
        itself with its rules and hence its definition. Originally developed in
        reference to legislative systems as an illustration of </textual><quote class="po-inline e13 e13"><textual class="po-textual">a game of
          self-amendment</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, Suber's rule set for the game
          </textual><quote class="po-inline e14 e14"><textual class="po-textual">Nomic</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> quickly took on a life of its own and spawned a
        small thought industry among gamers and philosophers, implicating
        economics, sociology and anthropology, life sciences, psychology and
        politics.</textual></para><para class="po-block e15 e15"><textual class="po-textual">Markup technologies such as HTML, XML and everything that goes with
        them, from schemas to processing languages to public specifications and
        standards, have many gamelike aspects. We have players, equipment, and
        opportunities to compete and cooperate. When applications work as well
        as or better than planned, there are victories. When projects fail or
        initiatives collapse, there are defeats. As in many games, much of the
        activity of markup technologies is devoted to rules enforcement; it
        also, in nomic fashion, extends to breaking received rules and making
        new ones. (Illustrations and examples are offered at micro and macro
        levels.) An engagement with markup technologies, or with any media
        production or software application design that relies on them, demands
        tactics and strategy, presenting us with problems and tradeoffs enmeshed
        in complexities both on and off the board, and challenging us to decide
        not only how we play, but what game we wish to be playing. And the
        deeper we go, the more nomic it gets. As we ponder what we are doing
        with markup technologies and how they are changing what else we do – as
        technologists, publishers, scholars, teachers, and creative producers –
        it is well if we reflect on who is making the rules and how; for whose
        benefit; whether, when, to what extent and how we should follow their
        rules or make our own; and finally how the rules we make about the games
        we play can have far-reaching effects even beyond the game we thought we
        were playing.</textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e16 e16"><personname class="po-record e17 e17"><firstname class="po-field e18 e18"><textual class="po-textual">Wendell</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e19 e19"><textual class="po-textual">Piez</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e20 e20"><para class="po-block e21 e21"><textual class="po-textual">Wendell Piez develops XML and XSLT applications for Mulberry
          Technologies, Inc., and its clients. He serves as general editor of
            </textual><link class="po-inline e22 e22" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Digital
            Humanities Quarterly</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></personblurb></author><legalnotice class="po-container e23 e23"><para class="po-block e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright 2009 by the author.</textual></para></legalnotice></info><section class="po-hcontainer e25 e25"><title class="po-block e26 e26"><textual class="po-textual">What is a game?</textual></title><para class="po-block e27 e27"><textual class="po-textual">Ludwig Wittgenstein, in his </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">Philosophical
        Investigations</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, famously describes language as a game with
      words, and then contextualizes and complicates the suggestion by
      demonstrating how the term </textual><quote class="po-inline e29 e29"><textual class="po-textual">game</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> itself
        (</textual><quote class="po-inline e30 e30"><textual class="po-textual">Spiel</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> in the original German text) does not admit of a
      simple, clearcut definition. As he demonstrates, there is no single
      definition that can be used, in any abstract analytical way, to
      distinguish those things we call games from other things we do not. While
      games frequently or generally have players, rules, equipment, scores,
      plays or moves or tricks or turns or timing, none of these is present in
      all things we call games, or serves to distinguish a game as such from
      other things that are not games. Solitaire is a game, if only in a loose
      sense; so are catch, tag, or (when playing with a cat),
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e31 e31"><textual class="po-textual">string</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. The first definition given under
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e32 e32"><textual class="po-textual">game</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> in a dictionary will tend to be something like
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e33 e33"><textual class="po-textual">A diversion or amusement</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> (American Heritage, although
      there are many diversions or amusements we do not ordinarily call games),
      or </textual><quote class="po-inline e34 e34"><textual class="po-textual">Sport or amusement of any kind; fun</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> (Webster's). Yet we
      can all think of diversions or amusements that we would not call
      games.</textual></para><para class="po-block e35 e35"><textual class="po-textual">The mathematical field of game theory is, similarly, both a help and a
      hindrance. While game theory sets out to describe game-like situations,
      these correspond only somewhat to those things we call games outside
      mathematics. Intriguingly, this limitation of game theory is necessary to
      its greater project as </textual><quote class="po-inline e36 e36"><textual class="po-textual">a universal language for the unification of
        the behavioral sciences</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> (H. Ginnis as quoted by Don Ross), which
      it achieves by means of a generalized application of its terms well beyond
      those of the social and cultural phenomena we call games. Accordingly,
      while game theory is by no means irrelevant to the analogy proposed by
      this paper (and the application of game theory as such to markup languages
      would by no means be without interest), it is also somewhat tangential to
      the argument here.</textual></para><para class="po-block e37 e37"><textual class="po-textual">The reason for this is fairly simple, but subtle. What this paper
      shares with game theory is a recognition that games can, in general, be
      characterized as rules-based systems; that is, as systems in which the
      relation and interaction of parts or participants are regular in ways that
      are susceptible to formal definition and even prescription. But while game
      theory considers what happens – what patterns emerge, how outcomes are or
      are not determined, how strategies interact – within such systems, it
      necessarily treats each such system as closed. The allowance that a system
      may not be fully defined or definable in formal terms – something that is,
      for better or worse, characteristic of many games and gamelike activities
      – will tend to frustrate any straightforwardly mathematical approach.
      Accordingly, any consideration by game theory of systems whose rules are
      not fully determined or known by the theorist – which are thus, in a
      crucial sense, undefined – will be, at best, by analogy.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e38 e38"><para class="po-block e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">This necessary limitation tends to be obscured by definitions of
          "game" offered by practitioners of game theory. For example:
            </textual><quote class="po-inline e40 e40"><textual class="po-textual">All situations in which at least one agent can only act to
            maximize his utility through anticipating (either consciously, or
            just implicitly in his behavior) the responses to his actions by one
            or more other agents is called a </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e41 e41"><textual class="po-textual">game</textual></emphasis></quote><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual><citation class="po-atom e42 e42"><textual class="po-textual">Ross, Stanford Encyclopedia</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">. This would certainly
          allow the treatment of open-ended systems within game theory; but when
          it comes to describing them, open-ended systems are always considered
          by game theory in terms of closed (definable) systems to which they
          are likened. That is, the claims of game theory to relevance are
          asserted by its comparison, implicit or explicit, of the well defined
          (what it calls the </textual><quote class="po-inline e43 e43"><textual class="po-textual">game</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">) to the less well defined (what
          it calls the </textual><quote class="po-inline e44 e44"><textual class="po-textual">world</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">). Accordingly and incidentally, game
          theory fails to distinguish what in common parlance we call
            </textual><quote class="po-inline e45 e45"><textual class="po-textual">games</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> from just about any other activity in a social
          context, including markup technologies, because it is simply not
          interested in this distinction.</textual></para><para class="po-block e46 e46"><textual class="po-textual">The game designer Raph Koster puts his finger on this somewhat
          pointedly: game theory </textual><quote class="po-inline e47 e47"><textual class="po-textual">. . . has something to do with games, a
            lot to do with psychology, even more to do with math, and not a lot
            to do with game design. Game theory is about how competitors make
            optimal choices, and it's mostly used in politics and economics,
            where it is frequently proven wrong</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual><citation class="po-atom e48 e48"><textual class="po-textual">Koster 2004, p. 12</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">. </textual></para></footnote></para><para class="po-block e49 e49"><textual class="po-textual">This analogy (</textual><quote class="po-inline e50 e50"><textual class="po-textual">certain formal systems of interest to us shall be
        called </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e51 e51"><textual class="po-textual">games</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e52 e52"><textual class="po-textual">games</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> as we
        call them are like systems we can observe</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">) is less the focus of
      this paper than another one, closer to home at least for some of us:
      markup technologies, and the forms of media based on them, which have
      formal aspects, are like games, like chess, Scrabble or (with apologies)
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e53 e53"><textual class="po-textual">tag</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, which also have formal aspects, though they may not
      always be fully definable in merely formal terms (that is, without any
      reference to social context or occasion). In view of this, it turns out
      that game theory is interesting for this treatment at least as much for
      its showing what games (or markup technologies) are
        </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e54 e54"><textual class="po-textual">not</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> as for its theorizing what they are, casting
      into relief the vital distinction between formal systems as such, and
      systems as we encounter them as part of social, cultural and economic
      life. For example, one consequence of its deliberate definition of scope –
      a game is a system subject to formal definition of options and outcomes in
      interaction – is that game theory can make no provision for cheating (as
      distinguished from </textual><quote class="po-inline e55 e55"><textual class="po-textual">defecting</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">: the distinction is important</textual><footnote class="po-popup e56 e56"><para class="po-block e57 e57"><textual class="po-textual">To </textual><quote class="po-inline e58 e58"><textual class="po-textual">defect</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, in game theory terms, is to choose not
          to cooperate, which may include adopting a strategy in opposition to
          the presumed terms of the game as a whole as well as to other
          participants.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">). This is because when a game is identified with a given set
      of constraints on play and dispositions of rewards, to break these rules
      is simply to end or invalidate the game as defined (even if play
      continues), and to play a game outside its rules is a logical
      impossibility (while one might well continue on to play something else).
      Similarly and by extension, if allowances are made in the definition of a
      game for breaking a set of nominal rules (since game theory does not
      require that all participants in a game know all the rules or agree on
      them), then to break them is merely to demonstrate that the game nominally
      being played is not the game actually being played. Accordingly,
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e59 e59"><textual class="po-textual">cheating</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> from the point of game theory does not mean what
      it ordinarily means, that is to break the rules while continuing to play.
      Instead, it amounts to a particular kind of subterfuge, i.e., to pretend
      to be playing one game while actually playing another.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e60 e60"><para class="po-block e61 e61"><textual class="po-textual">A recent Scientific American article on doping in bicycle racing
          makes this point nicely when it treats cheating as a special kind of
          defecting </textual><citation class="po-atom e62 e62"><textual class="po-textual">Shermer, 2008</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">. Indeed, by failing to
          account adequately for the possibility of doping in its actual
          incentive structure, professional bicycle racing nicely makes the
          point that game theory fits only awkwardly with games as they are
          commonly understood, since in order to apply game theory to bicycle
          racing (which it does fairly successfully), this article must
          distinguish between the sport that players pretend they are playing,
          and the sport as it is actually played. To describe the actual
          phenomenon and even, by extension, to prompt strategies for addressing
          it, game theory can be applied, as it can to many complex situations
          in economics and social life. But you will not find the rules of this
          game, as actually played, written up in any regulation manual. That
          is, the game of </textual><quote class="po-inline e63 e63"><textual class="po-textual">bicycle racing</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, which players pretend
          they are playing and which forbids the use of performance-enhancing
          drugs, exists only as a fiction and an ideal, and the actual game of
          interest to the analyst is a competition between racers, who wish to
          win races, and organizers, who wish to restrict the means by which
          racers may do so.</textual></para></footnote></para><para class="po-block e64 e64"><textual class="po-textual">But cheating at sports and games (and </textual><quote class="po-inline e65 e65"><textual class="po-textual">gaming</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> them, an
      interesting and illuminating variation) has a long and illustrious
      history, as long as that of games themselves. And it happens all the time
      – yet somehow games continue, maintaining some sort of identity and
      integrity even if only as a premise. If a football coach cheats by reading
      the other team's signals, or a baseball player cheats by corking a bat or
      spitting on a ball, we do not usually say they have stopped playing
      football or baseball, even when this might be a vivid and cogent
      formulation of our complaint against them. More generally, a game as
      defined mathematically makes no provision for creativity or improvisation
      outside the choices between more or less obvious or innovative selections
      of strategy, for moves that </textual><quote class="po-inline e66 e66"><textual class="po-textual">change the game</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. This is not to
      say that creativity </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e67 e67"><textual class="po-textual">within</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> constraints is not
      creative (on the contrary), nor that the mathematics are therefore
      uninteresting. Yet the constraints themselves, the rules of the game, are
      sometimes themselves most at issue; and how and by whom they are decided
      is precisely what game theory must leave aside.</textual></para><para class="po-block e68 e68"><textual class="po-textual">This being the case, this treatment proceeds with a much rougher
      definition of </textual><quote class="po-inline e69 e69"><textual class="po-textual">game</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, which will nonetheless prove to be
      serviceable, inasmuch as it does not contradict a mathematical accounting,
      if one should be wanted, but also looks beyond the formal mathematical
      definition of any particular game, real or notional: a game is an
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e70 e70"><textual class="po-textual">agreement to play</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. This is broad enough to capture most
      or all real games; but it entails a couple of important ideas. First, in
      order to have an agreement, we need to agree with someone – if only with
      ourselves, as in solitaire. Second, an agreement to play consists often of
      more particulars than the simple act of playing. We can agree to all kinds
      of rules and requirements. And it is this set of rules and requirements
      that constitutes the game.</textual></para><para class="po-block e71 e71"><textual class="po-textual">In other words, we might be less concerned with what constitutes games
      in general, as games, as what constitutes a particular game, as a game.
      And indeed we are in rich territory as soon as we bring attention to the
      social and material contexts of any agreement to play, and to the
      constitution of such an agreement, both implicit and explicit. While this
      all varies greatly from one situation to another, whenever we find such an
      agreement, and to whatever extent we can find the agreement to be stable
      and to consist of particular provisions governing play, we usually find we
      can say there is a game there.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e72 e72"><para class="po-block e73 e73"><textual class="po-textual">I am aware that an important question is begged, namely how we
          should define </textual><quote class="po-inline e74 e74"><textual class="po-textual">play</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. I leave this aside deliberately,
          not because it is not important but because it is.</textual></para></footnote></para><section class="po-hcontainer e75 e75"><title class="po-block e76 e76"><textual class="po-textual">Rules and rule systems</textual></title><para class="po-block e77 e77"><textual class="po-textual">While it is very difficult to generalize meaningfully about the
        context and nature of such agreements, if we are to try to extend an
        argument like mine – markup technologies are games or are like games, or
        at least provide occasion for games – it is necessary to do so at least
        in a rough way. Along these lines, I would like to propose several
        categories or terms of art, which we might use to distinguish the
        outlines of any agreement to play.</textual></para><variablelist class="po-table e78 e78"><varlistentry class="po-record e79 e79"><term class="po-block e80 e80"><textual class="po-textual">Constraint space</textual></term><listitem class="po-container e81 e81"><para class="po-block e82 e82"><textual class="po-textual">If a game is defined by its boundaries, those boundaries can
              be considered to define a </textual><quote class="po-inline e83 e83"><textual class="po-textual">constraint space</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. A
              constraint space comprises all the lawful states of a game.
              Something that happens inside the constraint space may be part of
              the game; outside the space it necessarily is not. If the state of
              the game exits the given constraint space, the game must either be
              modified to extend into the new space, or come to an end.</textual></para><para class="po-block e84 e84"><textual class="po-textual">Generally a game comes to an end either when it comes to a
              steady state and its players decide to stop (thereby ending the
              agreement to play), or when the constraint space itself is
              dissolved. For example, a number of points is acquired or a clock
              runs out, thereby bringing the game, as defined by its own rules,
              to an end state, or bringing to an end a condition on which the
              game depends (</textual><quote class="po-inline e85 e85"><textual class="po-textual">we'll play until it gets
              dark</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">).</textual></para><para class="po-block e86 e86"><textual class="po-textual">For purposes of this discussion, constraint spaces may be
              further distinguished into three kinds:
                </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e87 e87"><textual class="po-textual">terrain</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e88 e88"><textual class="po-textual">rule space</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
              and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e89 e89"><textual class="po-textual">regulation space</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Terrain is the most
              general; rule space appears or occurs within or on the terrain;
              regulation space is a further refinement on rule space.</textual></para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry class="po-record e90 e90"><term class="po-block e91 e91"><textual class="po-textual">Terrain</textual></term><listitem class="po-container e92 e92"><para class="po-block e93 e93"><textual class="po-textual">A game always takes place within some medium, which I will
              call its terrain. The terrain may be identified with the material
              conditions of the game: its playing field, apparatus or equipment.
              Every game has a terrain at least implicitly, although the terrain
              may shift in the course of the game.</textual></para><para class="po-block e94 e94"><textual class="po-textual">The rules of play may specify or designate a terrain, but they
              do not constitute it. Nevertheless, the notion that a terrain is
              relatively stable, distinct from the rules of play, and
              nonetheless introduces its own constraints, is important. Not only
              may the terrain shift while the rules stay constant; also the
              rules may shift while play continues on the same terrain.</textual></para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry class="po-record e95 e95"><term class="po-block e96 e96"><textual class="po-textual">Rule space</textual></term><listitem class="po-container e97 e97"><para class="po-block e98 e98"><textual class="po-textual">While the terrain bounds the set of possible game states given
              its material conditions, rule space comprises a set of lawful
              states. It is possible, for certain kinds of loose or informal
              games, that rule space covers the entire terrain. In other words,
              the agreement to play consists only of </textual><quote class="po-inline e99 e99"><textual class="po-textual">we'll play
                here</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><quote class="po-inline e100 e100"><textual class="po-textual">we'll play with this</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, and all
              states given this agreement are legal. Generally speaking,
              however, for play to remain play, at least some rules are followed
              at least implicitly. Even animals at play together will handicap
              themselves so the stronger does not entirely dominate the weaker.
              The existence of such implicit rules seems to be part of what
              makes </textual><quote class="po-inline e101 e101"><textual class="po-textual">tug</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><quote class="po-inline e102 e102"><textual class="po-textual">chase</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> a game.</textual></para><para class="po-block e103 e103"><textual class="po-textual">Importantly, rules do not only define legal states within the
              terrain. Typically they also define legal transitions between
              those states: tactical alternatives, </textual><quote class="po-inline e104 e104"><textual class="po-textual">moves</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> or
                </textual><quote class="po-inline e105 e105"><textual class="po-textual">plays</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, some of these being legal, while others
              are not. This further restriction also opens a further possibility
              of cheating, which can include not simply a move or play that
              exits rule space (the set of lawful states), but also a move or
              play that advances the game to another state – even one that might
              otherwise be lawful – by means of an unlawful transition.</textual></para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry class="po-record e106 e106"><term class="po-block e107 e107"><textual class="po-textual">Regulation space</textual></term><listitem class="po-container e108 e108"><para class="po-block e109 e109"><textual class="po-textual">Given the possibility, or even the likelihood, that either
              game states or the transitions between them may be unlawful –
              balls do go out of bounds, and players do attempt to cheat – many
              games also include rules to govern rule space. Mechanisms of
              resolution or adjudication are introduced in order that the
              agreement to play may continue by a restoration of rule space when
              it has been violated. Regulation space may introduce agents of its
              own (such as umpires or referees) and its own apparatus (a
              referee's whistle). In any case, there are rules to be followed
              for enforcing the rules (</textual><quote class="po-inline e110 e110"><textual class="po-textual">when the referee blows the
                whistle, play must stop</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">). Such mechanisms, which we can
              generally call </textual><quote class="po-inline e111 e111"><textual class="po-textual">regulators</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, occupy a middle space
              between the rule space and terrain, one where an unlawful state
              (or the immanence of one) is recognized, but instead of forcing an
              end to the game, a kind of </textual><quote class="po-inline e112 e112"><textual class="po-textual">meta-rule</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, a regulation,
              is applied to restore lawfulness. This ensures that the game
              remain within rule space. (Usually this is accomplished by
              changing the game state. It can also be accomplished by altering
              rule space itself to accommodate the state in question.) As long
              as this happens in a way acceptable to the players, the agreement
              to play can be sustained. More often than not, prior agreements on
              how this agreement is to be secured help to validate such
              rulings.</textual></para><para class="po-block e113 e113"><textual class="po-textual">Because they add new constraints and restrictions to a wider
              rules space, a game that is regulated is actually a formal subset
              of the same game when unregulated (that is, when regulated only
              informally, by its players in the course of play) – not because it
              always makes some otherwise lawful game states unlawful, but
              because it clarifies and manages the boundaries between lawful and
              unlawful. It narrows the class of </textual><quote class="po-inline e114 e114"><textual class="po-textual">lawfulness</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> from
                </textual><quote class="po-inline e115 e115"><textual class="po-textual">anything the players accept as lawful</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> to
                </textual><quote class="po-inline e116 e116"><textual class="po-textual">anything determined to be lawful by
              regulation</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para><para class="po-block e117 e117"><textual class="po-textual">For example, Scrabble™ is a game played on a terrain
              consisting of a board and tiles; the rules entail players taking
              turns, placing tiles on the board to spell words, and drawing new
              tiles to replace the ones played. Commonly, a dictionary is used
              as a neutral arbiter (a regulating device) to determine whether a
              disputed word is allowable.</textual></para><para class="po-block e118 e118"><textual class="po-textual">But the National Scrabble Association also publishes a set of
              Official Tournament Rules, which specify a particular reference
              book (not just any dictionary agreed to by the players), along
              with many additional rules governing tournament play. Since the
                </textual><quote class="po-inline e119 e119"><textual class="po-textual">rules of Scrabble</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> as printed on the box and
              played at home in your living room comprise only a subset of these
              rules, Official Tournament Scrabble is a subset or
                </textual><quote class="po-inline e120 e120"><textual class="po-textual">profile</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> of Scrabble in general. (More rules
              define a narrower rule space.)</textual></para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist><figure class="po-container e121 e121"><title class="po-block e122 e122"><textual class="po-textual">Rule spaces and regulation spaces</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e123 e123"><imageobject class="po-container e124 e124"><imagedata class="po-meta e125 e125" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-001.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><mediaobject class="po-container e126 e126"><imageobject class="po-container e127 e127"><imagedata class="po-meta e128 e128" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-002.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><mediaobject class="po-container e129 e129"><imageobject class="po-container e130 e130"><imagedata class="po-meta e131 e131" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-003.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><figure class="po-container e132 e132"><title class="po-block e133 e133"><textual class="po-textual">Lawful and unlawful states in Scrabble™</textual></title><para class="po-block e134 e134"><textual class="po-textual">Although all of these represent states on the terrain, only one of
          them represents a lawful game state according to conventional rules.
          (According to the Official Tournament Rules, another one is legal if
          no player chooses to challenge it before another move is made.)</textual></para><mediaobject class="po-container e135 e135"><imageobject class="po-container e136 e136"><imagedata class="po-meta e137 e137" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-004.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></section><section class="po-hcontainer e138 e138"><title class="po-block e139 e139"><textual class="po-textual">How are markup technologies like games?</textual></title><para class="po-block e140 e140"><textual class="po-textual">Markup technologies, considered generally (that is, including
        HTML/CSS and wiki markup as well as XML/XSLT) have a number of game-like characteristics:</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e141 e141"><listitem class="po-container e142 e142"><para class="po-block e143 e143"><textual class="po-textual">An apparatus (the computer, the software, the network)
              constituting a terrain.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e144 e144"><para class="po-block e145 e145"><textual class="po-textual">Rules (syntactic rules, tagging rules, usage and </textual><quote class="po-inline e146 e146"><textual class="po-textual">best
                practice</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">), procedures (editing, validating, executing
              stylesheets), styles of play.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e147 e147"><para class="po-block e148 e148"><textual class="po-textual">Regulators (rules enforcement mechanisms), working on several
              levels. For example, we have XML with its rules (well-formedness
              constraints over the syntax and the usage of particular mechanisms
              such as namespaces) enforced by parsers; we have applications of
              XML using particular tag sets, with schemas to validate instances
              intended for these applications; and we have profiles of these
              applications entailing even further constraints over both the
              construction of markup instances and how they are deployed and
              used.</textual></para><para class="po-block e149 e149"><textual class="po-textual">Much of the regulation occurring in markup technologies is
              achieved informally by players monitoring and providing feedback
              to one another. Regulation mechanisms are also frequently
              formalized, codified and automated. Sometimes regulations
              conflict, requiring (usually informal) arbitration.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e150 e150"><para class="po-block e151 e151"><textual class="po-textual">Social networks and roles.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e152 e152"><para class="po-block e153 e153"><textual class="po-textual">Opportunities for interaction, feedback, and cooperation among
              players.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e154 e154"><para class="po-block e155 e155"><textual class="po-textual">Payoffs or </textual><quote class="po-inline e156 e156"><textual class="po-textual">victory</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para class="po-block e157 e157"><textual class="po-textual">Notably, </textual><quote class="po-inline e158 e158"><textual class="po-textual">competition</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> is excluded from this list.
        While competition is clearly part of activities related to markup
        technologies, it is not obviously necessary to them: win/lose outcomes
        are not inevitable at least within the straightforward practice of
        markup. While one might allow that successfully validating or publishing
        a markup instance is </textual><quote class="po-inline e159 e159"><textual class="po-textual">winning</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> in some sense, such a
        victory would not ordinarily require anyone else to lose.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e160 e160"><title class="po-block e161 e161"><textual class="po-textual">Markup technologies as game</textual></title><para class="po-block e162 e162"><textual class="po-textual">Just as games come in more or less strict and regulated forms, so
          do markup language applications.</textual></para><mediaobject class="po-container e163 e163"><imageobject class="po-container e164 e164"><imagedata class="po-meta e165 e165" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-005.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e166 e166"><textual class="po-textual">Yet beyond those just listed, there is a more striking similarity.
        Markup technologies show the same systematic elaborations as games do
        between games-as-rules (rule spaces) and games-as-regulated-rules
        (regulation spaces). Just as we have board games (games played, usually
        in turns, on a board at a table), Scrabble (a particular such game,
        whose terrain is a board with a grid and tiles carrying letters with
        point values), and then NSA Official Tournament Scrabble™, we have
        text-based markup, then XML, then an application of XML such as TEI or
        Docbook, then an application profile of one of these (or of some other
        common tag set, or a private tag set) in use by a particular publishing
        system or organization, and so on.</textual></para><para class="po-block e167 e167"><textual class="po-textual">Moreover, the regulatory systems that are deployed to manage and
        support markup applications, including schemas, documentation,
        stylesheets and so on, are themselves subject to a kind of game play.
        Certainly, proponents of TEI, Docbook and other widely-used tag sets
        have been known to feel themselves in competition, as if to be widely
        used is to </textual><quote class="po-inline e168 e168"><textual class="po-textual">win</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. Browsers and commercial toolkits compete
        with one another over who gets to define the rules of how markup is to
        be handled, as a guarantor, in their case, of commercial viability; this
        is a reflection and an outgrowth of the fact that even proprietary
        applications may be used as regulators (sometimes the only regulator) to
        manage the rule space of even a supposedly non-proprietary,
        standards-based technology such as HTML or CSS. At a higher level still,
        standards organizations and industry consortia are enlisted as
        regulators of this competition; then standards bodies themselves compete
        over markets. Evidently there is plenty of zero-sum (or at least the
        players behave this way) and plenty of competition.</textual></para><para class="po-block e169 e169"><textual class="po-textual">However, the fact that markup technologies are not inevitably or
        inherently competitive is only one instance of a more general
        distinction, namely that markup technologies as a whole, for all their
        rules and rigidities in some respects, do not make for the same kind of
        stable bounded system that a game is, even when this is true of
        particular markup-based applications. Markup technologies are more
        complex than games, even complex ones, and more specifically situated
        within (less isolable from) particular economic and cultural projects or
        endeavors.</textual></para><para class="po-block e170 e170"><textual class="po-textual">Also, participants in markup technologies usually have less clearly
        defined tasks or roles than players of games do; indeed our work
        commonly mixes together the roles of </textual><quote class="po-inline e171 e171"><textual class="po-textual">player</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> (someone who
        acts within game play to achieve aims within the game) and regulator
        (with responsibilities to monitor and maintain the game play as such).
        Nor is this because the game is simple enough not to require external
        regulation; on the contrary, markup technologies are also characterized
        by the opportunity to make and change the rules of play. All this makes
        them less like games, and more like nomic games.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e172 e172"><title class="po-block e173 e173"><textual class="po-textual">Nomic games</textual></title><para class="po-block e174 e174"><textual class="po-textual">In some ways, nomic games are the most gamelike of games, in that
        they afford the greatest opportunity for self-structured play: they are
          </textual><quote class="po-inline e175 e175"><textual class="po-textual">agreements to play</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> in their most essential form. Yet
        they are also </textual><quote class="po-inline e176 e176"><textual class="po-textual">un-games</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, in the sense that they cannot be
        defined in terms of particular sets of rules. That is their point. To
        the extent that a game most closely approaches the mathematical ideal of
        a closed system in which moves, tactics, payoffs and their interactions
        are fully defined (and hence, at least in principle, fully
        intelligible), it is not a nomic game – even as the outcome of those
        interactions becomes too complex to be predictable. A nomic game is a
        system that is gamelike in one crucial respect – there are rules
        governing play – but critically ungamelike in another: those rules are
        not fixed, but instead are themselves in play. </textual></para><figure class="po-container e177 e177"><title class="po-block e178 e178"><textual class="po-textual">Games and nomic games.</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e179 e179"><imageobject class="po-container e180 e180"><imagedata class="po-meta e181 e181" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-006.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e182 e182"><textual class="po-textual">The term </textual><quote class="po-inline e183 e183"><textual class="po-textual">nomic game</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> was coined by Peter Suber in
        1982, in reference to legal and constitutional systems, to designate
        precisely the sort of game or gamelike system in which the players have
        scope to change the rules.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e184 e184"><para class="po-block e185 e185"><textual class="po-textual">The name is derived from the Greek </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e186 e186"><textual class="po-textual">nomos</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">,
            for </textual><quote class="po-inline e187 e187"><textual class="po-textual">law</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><quote class="po-inline e188 e188"><textual class="po-textual">custom</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> or
              </textual><quote class="po-inline e189 e189"><textual class="po-textual">convention</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, as in </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e190 e190"><textual class="po-textual">agronomy</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">,
              </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e191 e191"><textual class="po-textual">astronomy</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e192 e192"><textual class="po-textual">economy</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">,
            and as distinguished from both Greek </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e193 e193"><textual class="po-textual">gnomê</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (a
            saying or </textual><quote class="po-inline e194 e194"><textual class="po-textual">something known</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">) and Latin
              </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e195 e195"><textual class="po-textual">nomen</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (</textual><quote class="po-inline e196 e196"><textual class="po-textual">name</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">).</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> Beyond this, it is necessarily somewhat difficult to
        generalize how nomic games work (as indeed this is up to the players)
        without resorting to group psychology or social dynamics. Although
        accounts of nomic games are not hard to locate on the Internet, they are
        nevertheless difficult to research, since as actually played they
        typically become highly introspective, self-involved, encumbered or
        elaborated with peculiar terminology (as nomic games are inevitably
        language and logic games, as well as opportunities for the display of
        linguistic prowess), and apparently all-consuming for their players
        (since they lack firm boundaries between game play and activities not
        within the game). Consequently, actual nomic games, even when their
        proceedings are archived in public, have a way of becoming insular and opaque.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e197 e197"><para class="po-block e198 e198"><textual class="po-textual">To make matters worse, many of the archives of nomic games
            played on line in the past are no longer available, and links to
            them are dead. It may be that nomic games of the purer sort, as
            represented on line, were an outgrowth of a particular historical
            moment. In the mid-to-late 1990s, several circumstances including
            the emergence of a viable terrain (platform) for game play (namely
            the Internet itself) seem to have combined to stimulate a growth in
            interest in nomic games, which subsequently died back when the games
            themselves proved to be too insular, obscure and self-involved to be
            interesting to many for very long.</textual></para><para class="po-block e199 e199"><textual class="po-textual">It is perhaps to play theorists (a loose group that includes
            animal behaviorists, anthropologists, sociologists, psychologists,
            and educators) that one must turn for a wider understanding, since
            most play has nomic aspects. But here, researchers are generally
            interested not in nomic games as such, but rather in the contexts
            within which games occur and the purposes to which they are put.
            Hence they are not likely to make firm distinctions between nomic
            games and the fixed sort.</textual></para></footnote></para><para class="po-block e200 e200"><textual class="po-textual">But many activities or endeavors we do not ordinarily consider to be
        games are nomic in the sense Suber describes (which of course is what
        motivates his proposal). Indeed, the capability of defining their own
        boundaries by their rule-making activities might be an essential
        characteristic of cultural activities in general, considered as such,
        whether they be political and economic, artistic or creative, or
        technological. Herein lies much of the fascination of nomic games.
        Public institutions such as the law or commerce, which proceed in and by
        agreements among their participants, public and private institutions
        such as governments, clubs, corporations, and universities, are all
        characterized by the way their participants and stakeholders make and
        remake the rules of play, and sometimes challenge or avoid them. Art and
        poetry can be similarly identified with rules-making, to rhetorical and
        aesthetic ends. And so can technology, where the ends are practical and
        task- or (and) market-oriented. These various activities can be
        distinguished from one another by their various terrains – their
        material, social and economic contexts – as well as by the rules they
        follow and regulatory frameworks they enact. When we distinguish them in
        this way, we might almost be talking about games – a fact that has not
        escaped the notice of structuralist anthropologists.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e201 e201"><title class="po-block e202 e202"><textual class="po-textual">Human culture and nomic games.</textual></title><para class="po-block e203 e203"><textual class="po-textual">Many of the activities most distinctive of human culture and
          civilization, including law, technology, the arts, and various
          economic activities, may be thought of as nomic games. This etching by
          Blake both illustrates and exemplifies the principle of
          rule-making.</textual></para><mediaobject class="po-container e204 e204"><imageobject class="po-container e205 e205"><imagedata class="po-meta e206 e206" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-007.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e207 e207"><textual class="po-textual">Yet even casual observation suggests some properties of such
        activities that distinguish them from more conventional games. Beyond
        the fact that we do not call them </textual><quote class="po-inline e208 e208"><textual class="po-textual">games</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> or identify them
        as such except metaphorically (which we may do often), nomic games
        differ from conventional games in several respects, all of which have to
        do with how their boundaries are defined and maintained. For example,
        while ordinarily games are temporally ordered – either they proceed
        until a given conclusive state of play has been reached, at which point
        they end, or play continues for a definite and determined period until a
        score determines the outcome – nomic games, precisely since any rules
        governing time or sequence can be changed, tend to be temporally
        open-ended (even while there may be rules stipulating terms or rounds),
        and either unsustainable and short-lived, or interminable, sometimes
        making no provision at all for their own cessation. Also, conventional
        games are </textual><quote class="po-inline e209 e209"><textual class="po-textual">allogenic</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> in the sense that they are motivated
        and staged by something outside them, whereas nomic games will be
        autogenic and even </textual><quote class="po-inline e210 e210"><textual class="po-textual">autopoietic</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> (the term Maturana and
        Varela use to distinguish </textual><quote class="po-inline e211 e211"><textual class="po-textual">living systems</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> as such), which
        accounts for their self-obsessed, </textual><quote class="po-inline e212 e212"><textual class="po-textual">self-consuming</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> nature:
        nomic games frequently descend into rules lawyering. Perhaps most
        intriguingly, nomic games also tend to spin off or spawn other nomic
        games: they are replicative of themselves as well as mutable.</textual></para><para class="po-block e213 e213"><textual class="po-textual">Finally, just as it is difficult (for reasons discussed earlier) to
        apply the idea of </textual><quote class="po-inline e214 e214"><textual class="po-textual">cheating</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> in game theory, the notion of
        cheating only applies with difficulty to a nomic game, but for the
        opposite reason: the rules of a nomic game are mutable and always at
        issue, so nothing is by definition out of bounds. A nomic game may, at
        one moment, define a rule space (in the sense of a set of lawful
        states), and at the next, redefine it. It may enter into a paradoxical
        state in which the nominal rule space has been violated, but the
        agreement to play has not been suspended, so the game continues. And it
        may retroactively change the rules to make earlier moves (transitions)
        or conditions (states) legal or illegal, in order to invoke or to avoid
        invoking regulatory action as part of the game play.</textual></para><para class="po-block e215 e215"><textual class="po-textual">To the extent that any game allows this (like professional bicycle
        racing, with its doping scandals) it is revealed as more nomic and less
        gamelike: players (a category which for these purposes will include the
        game's regulators, for example race officials and organizers) can take
        the rules into their own hands, and alter or break them, without ending
        the game. As long as as the agreement to play is sustained, even while
        the integrity of the game as a game (a transparent and
          </textual><quote class="po-inline e216 e216"><textual class="po-textual">fair</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> competition) is compromised, as a nomic game (a
        self-sustaining but only </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e217 e217"><textual class="po-textual">relatively</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> rules-bound
        activity), it may be reinforced. Thus, nomic games alter and stretch the
        notion of a </textual><quote class="po-inline e218 e218"><textual class="po-textual">game</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> away from general principles of formal
        definition and into more socially located, problematic and provisional
        contexts. This helps account for why both games and nomic games, as
        actually played, are interesting, as each is always in the midst of
        becoming the other, in a Yin/Yang dynamic relation, in which
          </textual><quote class="po-inline e219 e219"><textual class="po-textual">cheating</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> delineates precisely the in-between space
        where a game goes nomic (at the risk of collapse, if the agreement to
        play should become unsustainable), and where, conversely, an accusation
        of cheating may be a ploy that seeks to circumscribe a game-going-nomic
        back within the parameters of the game it is assumed or claimed to be –
        to regulate it.</textual></para><para class="po-block e220 e220"><textual class="po-textual">Indeed, to recognize this is to come some distance to understanding
        of why thinking about games is useful for understanding phenomena and
        problems in the </textual><quote class="po-inline e221 e221"><textual class="po-textual">real world</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, a place where mathematical
        regularity is as often the exception as it is the rule. We might say
        that the reason we can so easily compare real-world activities (such as
        real estate speculation or international relations) to games (such as
        Monopoly or Diplomacy) is that the purpose of games is precisely to
        offer and encourage such analogies. As rules-bound and regulated
        systems, games are like the real world, only more so, with the special
        advantage of being more clearly bounded, delineated and self-contained,
        and hence more observable and intelligible – which makes them suitable
        occasions for practicing skills and abilities that may be useful outside
        them. Yet paradoxically, part of their resemblance to real-world
        activities is in their capacity to fly off, to become something other
        than themselves. And it is when games become more serious, when the
        stakes go up, that they have this tendency most strongly.</textual></para><para class="po-block e222 e222"><textual class="po-textual">Yet just as games become more like nomic games as they become more
        serious and their players seek to take control of the rule space and
        shift it to their advantage, real-world nomic activities such as legal
        and political systems become more gamelike, more regular and
        rules-bound, as their participants find common interests in preventing
          </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e223 e223"><textual class="po-textual">ad hoc</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> nomic redefinition on the part of other
        players, and in thwarting and punishing those who engage in it. That is,
        regulation spaces, both in games and in ostensibly more serious
        activities, are attempts to manage and control their nomic tendencies,
        to regularize and reduce complexity and seeming arbitrariness and
        instead offer systematic control or some sense of it. Intriguingly, such
        rules and regulations are what make </textual><quote class="po-inline e224 e224"><textual class="po-textual">game theory</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> useful
        and relevant – at any rate, the kind of game theory we compulsively
        engage in as social animals, which is to say our more or less systematic
        reasoning about motives, options, objectives, tradeoffs, strategies and
        tactics. Within such systems (again, think of constitutional
        governance), although they remain nomic at their core, not just anyone
        is permitted to change the rules at any time, and there are complex
        rules, built-in checks, and regulation of regulations for determining
        who may engage in rules making, by what mechanisms, with whose
        participation or acquiescence, and within how wide a scope.</textual></para><para class="po-block e225 e225"><textual class="po-textual">Again, for our purposes (and at the risk of anticlimax), it hardly
        needs to be stressed how markup technologies fit into this description
        of things, as both a technological and a cultural and economic
        phenomenon. A successful markup practitioner will soon have the
        opportunity to participate in rules-making activities, whether that be
        defining a schema, implementing a production or processing framework
        (where we frequently discover a fine line between interpreting presumed
        rules and making new ones), or merely developing ad-hoc conventions to
        systematize identifiers and taxonomies. Even writing stylesheets for
        presentation (to say nothing of code that converts from one markup
        format to another) will entail making new rules and, sometimes, ignoring
        or breaking old ones, if only to handle anomalies and edge cases.
        Successful schema designers and software developers will be pulled into
        standards work, to help define standards by which systems may be
        specified and which conformant applications and implementations of a
        technology must reference. And so on.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e226 e226"><title class="po-block e227 e227"><textual class="po-textual">Entailment between states and rule spaces in nomic games</textual></title><para class="po-block e228 e228"><textual class="po-textual">In a nomic game, every game state also implies a rule space, since
          no game state can be fully specified without also specifying the rules
          at that point in the game.</textual></para><mediaobject class="po-container e229 e229"><imageobject class="po-container e230 e230"><imagedata class="po-meta e231 e231" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-008.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e232 e232"><title class="po-block e233 e233"><textual class="po-textual">Making rules for markup</textual></title><para class="po-block e234 e234"><textual class="po-textual">To turn from the very abstract to the very concrete, three
      illustrations serve to demonstrate how applicable these concepts are when
      considering actual problems in and with markup technologies. The examples
      are all close to home. The reader can probably provide many more.</textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e235 e235"><title class="po-block e236 e236"><textual class="po-textual">Valid, but not useful</textual></title><para class="po-block e237 e237"><textual class="po-textual">Here is a valid fragment from a Balisage paper, </textual><quote class="po-inline e238 e238"><textual class="po-textual">valid</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">
        being defined as </textual><quote class="po-inline e239 e239"><textual class="po-textual">conformant to the rules expressed in the
          Balisage
        DTD</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">:</textual><programlisting class="po-block e240 e240" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;personblurb&gt;
  &lt;para&gt;&lt;/para&gt;
&lt;/personblurb&gt;</textual></programlisting><textual class="po-textual">A
        DTD can validate that an element is present, but not that it contains
        actual content. Even a schema language that can constrain the content to
        prohibit empty string values, such as XSD, cannot solve the general
        problem of ensuring that such content is correct or useful:
          </textual><quote class="po-inline e241 e241"><textual class="po-textual">XXX</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> will usually suffice. In other words, schema
        validation is rather severely restricted in what kind of
          </textual><quote class="po-inline e242 e242"><textual class="po-textual">validation</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> it can support.</textual></para><para class="po-block e243 e243"><textual class="po-textual">This much is evident to any XML veteran – so evident that we may
        have stopped noticing. And the boundary between the rules enforced by a
        schema, and the rules that remain the concern of authors and editors
        (the human kind), is one of the first things newcomers to XML must get
        used to. Even if it never becomes entirely clear exactly where this
        boundary is placed – and it does vary from one application and one
        validation technology to another (which makes things worse for the
        learner) – the simple fact that the boundary is there (and indeed may
        move) is an important one. The XMLer who never catches on that the
        machine can check some things, but not others, will always remain at a
        loss.</textual></para><para class="po-block e244 e244"><textual class="po-textual">What is at issue here is the authority and reliability of a schema
        as a regulator of rules. As such, practice shows that for a system to be
        sustainable, schemas – in addition to being well-fitted to the
        application(s) of the data, which should go without saying – must be
        consistent and as transparent as possible; hence the importance of
        documentation. Where they do not, in fact, enforce any meaningful
        constraints (such as the constraint that an author's biography should
        give some account of who the author is), users who are not experts in
        schema validation need to be helped to understand this. The differences
        between rules that are being validated, rules that might be validated
        but are not, and rules that cannot be validated by automated means, are
        often subtle.</textual></para><para class="po-block e245 e245"><textual class="po-textual">One of the most difficult myths to dispel among newcomers to markup
        has to do with this authority, and to what extent a schema can or should
        be relied on as a warrant for correctness or fitness. The notion that a
        schema, as a regulator, performs some sort of punitive function – a
        validation error being construed to be some kind of warning that a
        document is </textual><quote class="po-inline e246 e246"><textual class="po-textual">wrong</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, which it is only in a fairly narrow
        and entirely convenient sense (inasmuch as the rules enforced by a
        schema may be motivated only by the need for the system to ensure a
        certain level of predictability in the data) – is probably less accurate
        than an alternative idea that a schema is just a piece of equipment that
        helps make game play feasible, by supporting (</textual><quote class="po-inline e247 e247"><textual class="po-textual">encoding</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">)
        the specifics of the agreement to play. In the game of tennis, the rules
        require a racket to be used, and kicking or throwing the ball is not
        allowed; this is not because there is anything wrong with kicking, but
        because this game (on this court, with this ball) is more fun for
        players and spectators when played with rackets. Maybe we should be
        teaching that schemas in XML are like tennis rackets for users, helping
        them get the ball over the net, rather than bludgeons used by developers
        to keep users in line.</textual></para><para class="po-block e248 e248"><textual class="po-textual">So, what is a document creator saying when he creates a
          </textual><code class="po-atom e249 e249"><textual class="po-textual">personblurb</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> element containing a </textual><code class="po-atom e250 e250"><textual class="po-textual">para</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
        element with no content? Leaving aside the possibility that an empty
          </textual><code class="po-atom e251 e251"><textual class="po-textual">para</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, particularly inside a </textual><code class="po-atom e252 e252"><textual class="po-textual">personblurb</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">,
        should be taken positively and frankly to assert </textual><quote class="po-inline e253 e253"><textual class="po-textual">there is nothing
          to say about this person</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, it is hard not to see this as a play
        of resistance (if that possibility does not in itself represent such a
        play). The schema says </textual><quote class="po-inline e254 e254"><textual class="po-textual">there must be an element here</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, and
        implies by the element's stated semantics (implicit in its name and
        perhaps explicit in documentation, as at
          </textual><link class="po-inline e255 e255" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.balisage.net/DocumentModels/BalisageTL/index.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">)
        that its data content should constitute some meaningful account of the
        document's author. But the document's actual tagging says, in effect,
          </textual><quote class="po-inline e256 e256"><textual class="po-textual">I see your </textual><code class="po-atom e257 e257"><textual class="po-textual">personblurb</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> element and choose to
          ignore it</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. The document is formally valid and enters the
        system. A warrant is made implicitly that information is given, which is
        missing. If, following the formulation of Sperberg-McQueen, Huitfeld and
        Renear, an element's semantics constitute </textual><quote class="po-inline e258 e258"><textual class="po-textual">the set of inferences
          licensed by the markup</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">
        </textual><citation class="po-atom e259 e259"><textual class="po-textual">Sperberg-McQueen, et al. 2001</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">, in the case of an
        element that is present with no meaningful content, an incorrect
        inference (</textual><quote class="po-inline e260 e260"><textual class="po-textual">there is a bio here</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">) is being licensed;
        moreover, the more general capability to make such an inference when it
        needs to be made is confounded. And indeed, this much might be said of
        any case of tag abuse.</textual></para><para class="po-block e261 e261"><textual class="po-textual">The system maintainers then have a choice: either they redefine
        processing logic to allow for this information to be missing (by
        changing the schema, and perhaps introducing defensive processing logic
        that tests whether </textual><code class="po-atom e262 e262"><textual class="po-textual">personblurb</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> has any content before doing
        anything with it), which is as much to concede tag abuse as normal. Or
        they can validate the document further through some means other than the
        schema, such as a Schematron or an old-fashioned editorial process, and
        use this as the basis of a counter-move, returning the document to its
        originator for correction. Or they can do neither, and allow the system
        subtly to degrade.</textual></para><para class="po-block e263 e263"><textual class="po-textual">Sometimes system maintainers or process designers have no control
        over the data, and the third option is the only viable one. (One only
        needs to think of the history of HTML.) In this case, there may be
        system-wide changes in markup semantics as players (including document
        creators, publishers, systems developers, and tools vendors) learn how
        much (or rather, how little) they can trust, and make moves in response
        to one another.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e264 e264"><title class="po-block e265 e265"><textual class="po-textual">Look ma, no hands</textual></title><para class="po-block e266 e266"><textual class="po-textual">This problem of the role of the schema is also apparent, in a
        different way,
        here:</textual><programlisting class="po-block e267 e267" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;!-- &lt;!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD HTML 4.01 Transitional//EN"
                           "http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/loose.dtd"&gt; --&gt;
&lt;HTML&gt;
  &lt;HEAD&gt;
    &lt;TITLE&gt;&lt;/TITLE&gt;
  &lt;/HEAD&gt;
  &lt;BODY&gt;&lt;/BODY&gt;
&lt;/HTML&gt;</textual></programlisting></para><para class="po-block e268 e268"><textual class="po-textual">Is this document valid? According to both SGML and XML, validity
        requires </textual><quote class="po-inline e269 e269"><textual class="po-textual">an associated document type declaration</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, and
        this document has none.</textual></para><para class="po-block e270 e270"><textual class="po-textual">Yet frequently, especially when working with other schema
        technologies, we work with documents that are not formally valid, but
        that would be when associated with their schema and validated, like the
        example above. Perhaps we might, in order to be clear, call such a
        document </textual><quote class="po-inline e271 e271"><textual class="po-textual">validable</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, to stress that it follows all the
        rules stipulated by its (presumed, but unassociated) schema, but
        actually has no formal association given, and can therefore not be valid
        in the strict sense.</textual></para><para class="po-block e272 e272"><textual class="po-textual">At this point, readers who are experts in XML-based systems probably
        want to introduce qualifications, arguments and counter-arguments. For
        example, the schema language RelaxNG stipulates no formal mechanism by
        which an association such as that not made by this fragment should be
        made. Does this mean that documents cannot actually be valid to RelaxNG
        schemas? Presumably, in the context of RelaxNG, the definition of
          </textual><quote class="po-inline e273 e273"><textual class="po-textual">valid</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> must be taken to be more like
          </textual><quote class="po-inline e274 e274"><textual class="po-textual">validable</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> in the sense just given. (W3C XML Schema
        Definition Language takes something of a middle course: it offers a
        mechanism for documents to invoke schemas but does not require that it
        be respected, saying it might be </textual><quote class="po-inline e275 e275"><textual class="po-textual">just a hint</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">.)</textual></para><para class="po-block e276 e276"><textual class="po-textual">A similar problem arises when using XML catalogs, which can be used
        to intercept references to normative copies of schemas or DTDs and
        replace them at validation time with local copies. This is convenient
        because it reduces network traffic, but it introduces a source of
        potential error, in that if a local copy goes out of sync with a
        normative schema, local instances valid to it are not only not valid to
        the normative version (that is, to the schema actually named), they may
        not even be validable.</textual></para><para class="po-block e277 e277"><textual class="po-textual">This much would be merely an academic argument, were it not common
        practice for XML developers to remove or comment out references to
        schemas as in the case above (where in fact, the schema named in the
        comment is an SGML DTD). This might indeed be considered a hazardous
        practice, like riding a bicycle without a helmet, except that it appears
        to be mandated by XML itself, which does not require a DTD or schema for
        processing.</textual></para><para class="po-block e278 e278"><textual class="po-textual">At issue, again, is the question of who gets to make the rules –
        although this time, what we see is not the kind of power struggle within
        the game that is represented by tag abuse, but rather, a more
        fundamental difference in the way game regulators (in this case,
        schemas) are deployed on the game's terrain (the processing platform,
        which may be the entire network). The shift from SGML to XML, in which
        validation need not be performed, represents a highly significant shift
        in responsibility, from schema and system designers to local users and
        developers, who now get to determine whether and when to be valid at
        all, and (or) when to continue processing without schema validation (or
        any validation at all over and above syntactic well-formedness). This
        shift was possible for a number of reasons (including a number of
        syntactic restrictions and adjustments in XML to ensure that a
        non-validating parse would always be possible) and may have been
        intended primarily not as a way to increase options for users so much as
        for tool and application developers (since XML processing can, without a
        schema, be so much more lightweight). Yet it is highly
        consequential.</textual></para><para class="po-block e279 e279"><textual class="po-textual">Generally, any time code in the document is commented out, the
        intended audience for the document is bifurcated between those who can
        see and make us of the commented information (whoever works directly
        with the raw code, including the developer who makes the comment) and
        those who cannot (any downstream users who cannot see the comments, but
        more importantly, the processing system itself). Again, this is a play
        of evasion, although different from the case of an empty
          </textual><code class="po-atom e280 e280"><textual class="po-textual">personblurb</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><code class="po-atom e281 e281"><textual class="po-textual">title</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> element, in that it is
        not the spirit of the rules that is being evaded or </textual><quote class="po-inline e282 e282"><textual class="po-textual">faked
          out</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, but the processing system itself.</textual></para><para class="po-block e283 e283"><textual class="po-textual">In this particular case (as long as the example is taken at face
        value), it is document validation that is being suspended. This may be a
        good or a bad idea; to determine which, we would have to know more.
        Either way, to allow (or require) documents themselves to carry the
        information that permits or implicitly requires them to be validated is
        itself a design decision on a meta-architectural level (a fact that
        RelaxNG and W3C XML Schema both recognize). Given XML's design, there is
        nothing here that actually prevents system designers from performing
        validation in any case, to any schema they choose. This single
        difference between SGML, where to comment out a </textual><code class="po-atom e284 e284"><textual class="po-textual">DOCTYPE</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
        declaration would have been a futile gesture (preventing a fully
        conformant system from parsing the document), and XML, where it may (or
        may not) be a useful gambit, is one of the most important single reasons
        why XML can actually work on the web, a much wider, more open-ended,
        less well controlled and more resource-rich terrain than the systems for
        which SGML processing was developed.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e285 e285"><title class="po-block e286 e286"><textual class="po-textual">And what do we have here</textual></title><para class="po-block e287 e287"><textual class="po-textual">A final example is not an instance of game play in quite the same
        way as the previous two, but rather points to an issue in game design.
        Here's some code, valid to the NLM/NCBI schema (the text is from Bill
        Watterson's </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e288 e288"><textual class="po-textual">Calvin and Hobbes</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> of May 27,
        1990):</textual><programlisting class="po-block e289 e289" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;boxed-text&gt;
  &lt;speech&gt;&lt;speaker&gt;Calvin&lt;/speaker&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don't have to sing the song!
    I was in the "No Song" Zone!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/speech&gt;
  &lt;speech&gt;&lt;speaker&gt;Hobbes&lt;/speaker&gt;&lt;p&gt;No you weren't. I touched the
    "Opposite Pole", so the "No Song Zone" is now a "Song Zone".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/speech&gt;
  &lt;speech&gt;&lt;speaker&gt;Calvin&lt;/speaker&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;bold&gt;I&lt;/bold&gt; didn't see you 
    touch the Opposite Pole! You have to declare it!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/speech&gt;
&lt;/boxed-text&gt;</textual></programlisting></para><para class="po-block e290 e290"><textual class="po-textual">The interesting thing here (at least as far as the markup is
        concerned) is the </textual><code class="po-atom e291 e291"><textual class="po-textual">boxed-text</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> element. The semantics of this
        element are arguably underspecified. The </textual><quote class="po-inline e292 e292"><textual class="po-textual">text</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> named by
        the element is presumably its data content, as is generally the case
        with descriptive markup. But this appears to be less descriptive, in the
        sense that it identifies the kind or type of text it marks, than
        presentational, asserting how it would appear in rendition. Yet it is
        also not clear whether it should be taken to be retrospective (the text
        appeared in a box in an earlier version) or prospective (the text should
        be placed in a box in a rendition generated from this markup). For the
        moment, we leave aside the possibility that </textual><quote class="po-inline e293 e293"><textual class="po-textual">boxed</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> should
        mean something other than </textual><quote class="po-inline e294 e294"><textual class="po-textual">appears displayed in a
        box</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para><para class="po-block e295 e295"><textual class="po-textual">Yet perhaps not. The formal element description given in the
        NLM/NCBI version 3.0 Tag Library is somewhat more specific but also
        problematic. It offers examples of what kinds of thing might be tagged
        as </textual><code class="po-atom e296 e296"><textual class="po-textual">boxed-text</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, but directly answers none of the questions
        just posed:</textual><blockquote class="po-container e297 e297"><para class="po-block e298 e298"><textual class="po-textual">Textual material that is part of the body of text but outside
            the flow of the narrative text, for example, a sidebar, marginalia
            [sic], text insert (whether enclosed in a box or not), caution, tip,
            note box, etc.</textual></para></blockquote><textual class="po-textual">Interestingly, this definition rejects the single thing we
        thought we knew about a boxed text, that it should appear in a box.
        Apparently the </textual><quote class="po-inline e299 e299"><textual class="po-textual">box</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> is not a renditional box but some kind
        of abstract rhetorical artifact: we know only that this text is
          </textual><quote class="po-inline e300 e300"><textual class="po-textual">outside the flow of the narrative</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para><para class="po-block e301 e301"><textual class="po-textual">What does this kind of markup say about itself; what licenses does
        it inference? Perhaps not much. Yet this is nevertheless more, I submit,
        than certain other </textual><quote class="po-inline e302 e302"><textual class="po-textual">escape hatch</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> kinds of encoding, such
        as a TEI </textual><code class="po-atom e303 e303"><textual class="po-textual">ab</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> (</textual><quote class="po-inline e304 e304"><textual class="po-textual">abstract block</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">), or an HTML
          </textual><code class="po-atom e305 e305"><textual class="po-textual">blockquote</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">. About these one cannot even say whether they
        are inside or outside the </textual><quote class="po-inline e306 e306"><textual class="po-textual">narrative flow</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. (In other
        respects these are of course not perfect analogues to
          </textual><code class="po-atom e307 e307"><textual class="po-textual">boxed-text</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, for which either TEI or HTML might give
        better alternatives, but the point stands.)</textual></para><para class="po-block e308 e308"><textual class="po-textual">I would describe semantics such as NLM/NCBI boxed-text as
          </textual><quote class="po-inline e309 e309"><textual class="po-textual">soft</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, as distinct from (say) XSL-FO
          </textual><code class="po-atom e310 e310"><textual class="po-textual">block[@border='thin sold black'][@padding='2em']</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, which
        is </textual><quote class="po-inline e311 e311"><textual class="po-textual">hard</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> by virtue of being bound to certain application
        semantics. And yet the element semantics of </textual><code class="po-atom e312 e312"><textual class="po-textual">boxed-text</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> are
        not as soft as those of </textual><code class="po-atom e313 e313"><textual class="po-textual">ab</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><code class="po-atom e314 e314"><textual class="po-textual">blockquote</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
        (which indeed might have harder semantics if it had not been subject to
        widespread tag abuse: the more </textual><code class="po-atom e315 e315"><textual class="po-textual">blockquote</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> has been used for
        things other than block quotes, the less useful the element has become
        for marking block quotes as opposed to other things that look like
        them). Maybe the meaning of </textual><code class="po-atom e316 e316"><textual class="po-textual">boxed-text</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> ought to be
        considered </textual><quote class="po-inline e317 e317"><textual class="po-textual">pliable</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">: hard enough to mean something in
        application, but soft enough to be flexible in use and indeed capable,
        in consonance with its application semantics, of expressing more than
        one meaning.</textual></para><para class="po-block e318 e318"><textual class="po-textual">How well this works is a matter of whether it sustains its semantics
        (such as they are) within its application domain. And since the purpose
        of the NLM/NCBI tag set, primarily, is to support the normalized
        aggregation into a single repository of data already marked up
        (typically by journal publishers), many or most of whose markup schemes
        have </textual><quote class="po-inline e319 e319"><textual class="po-textual">harder</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> semantics of their own (usually but not
        necessarily display semantics), it has to establish a balance. When
        aggregating disparate data, to try to capture every detail of source
        encoding means risking both over-elaboration, and a failure in its goal
        of providing unified access and processing (a goal that is frustrated
        whenever there are many ways to do any given thing). But to erase the
        details of source encoding means, potentially, to lose information. The
        balance is in erasing incidental, insignificant differences and
        capturing meaningful ones. But ordinarily, the design of a tag set to do
        this has to be established up front, which is to say before the proper
        unification of data from disparate sources can be established (when this
        is even possible, which it may not be when source document types are
        themselves mutable and open-ended). The solution to this problem, as to
        many others related to it, appears to be in deploying a mix of element
        types, some of which are </textual><quote class="po-inline e320 e320"><textual class="po-textual">hard</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> in the sense just
        described, and some of which are pliable or even soft, to serve as a
        kind of spackle or carpenter's putty (or the blank tiles in Scrabble or
        wild cards in poker). Indeed this is the case of all the tag sets
        mentioned here. HTML in particular is noteworthy for having taken on, in
        its history, both elements with harder semantics, such as </textual><code class="po-atom e321 e321"><textual class="po-textual">b</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
        or </textual><code class="po-atom e322 e322"><textual class="po-textual">i</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> or the elements out of which browser forms are built,
        and softer ones such as </textual><code class="po-atom e323 e323"><textual class="po-textual">div</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><code class="po-atom e324 e324"><textual class="po-textual">span</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para><para class="po-block e325 e325"><textual class="po-textual">That is, rules are given, but latitude is also given to the players
        of the game to interpret how to apply the rules within their own
        situations. If this balance is found, then play can continue, since
        players can adapt. If this balance is missed, then either an overly
        rigid scheme is the result, in which individual publishers and projects
        are unable to achieve local goals (and eventually have to shift or adapt
        their schema, contrive workarounds, or stop playing entirely), or we
        have chaos, a markup free-for-all in which people pretend to be working
        together but meaningful aggregation or interchange is impossible.</textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e326 e326"><title class="po-block e327 e327"><textual class="po-textual">What's the point?</textual></title><para class="po-block e328 e328"><textual class="po-textual">There are actually three sets of conclusions one might draw from this
      comparison, if not conclusively. That is, all these are directions for
      further thought and examination.</textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e329 e329"><title class="po-block e330 e330"><textual class="po-textual">The ethics of play</textual></title><para class="po-block e331 e331"><textual class="po-textual">All of the examples explored above serve as examples of a more
        general point, having to do with the way we make judgments, as we
        approach both large-scale and minute problems working with markup
        technologies – that is, as we face both strategic and tactical
        decisions. What is useful and interesting about a game is that it is
        both isolable and insulated from the world, and yet at the same time, a
        mirror or model of it. This makes a game a kind of a microcosm within
        which moves and manners have their own significance in relation to one
        another, making for a kind of ethical laboratory. To consider right and
        wrong in a game is not to consider right and wrong in the abstract: a
        game defines its own ethical universe, wherein (as long as the game
        itself is respected) virtue, if it is to be virtuous, is always aligned
        with some sort of victory – if only of the </textual><quote class="po-inline e332 e332"><textual class="po-textual">moral</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> sort.
        (The very notion of a </textual><quote class="po-inline e333 e333"><textual class="po-textual">moral victory</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> points to the paradox
        that even in defeat can be a kind of success.) In other words, we are
        interested in games because they are arenas for the display and
        recognition not of abstract </textual><quote class="po-inline e334 e334"><textual class="po-textual">goodness</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, but of virtue in
        something more like the Latin sense than the modern one – that is, of
          </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e335 e335"><textual class="po-textual">particular</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> virtues, of strengths such as
        persistence, fidelity, ingenuity, generosity, prudence, integrity,
        imagination, versatility, elegance or what have you. Some of these
        virtues, of course, may contradict others, and on occasion they may even
        stand in the way of victory – which is exactly why they become
        interesting when demonstrated in game play. The way games serve not only
        as training grounds but as arenas for the demonstration of such virtues
        goes a long way to explaining why we find them so compelling. Nor is
        this unimportant. Different games will foster different kinds of
        behavior in their players, depending on what sorts of strategies and
        tactics lead to better outcomes within the game.</textual></para><para class="po-block e336 e336"><textual class="po-textual">Interestingly, to consider markup technologies in this light allows
        us to set aside from our consideration of markup-based systems, which as
        technologies, are social and economic and even political, rather than
        simply (like spectator sports) entertaining, the reflexive ethical
        judgements that so often seem to accompany them. For example, to prefer
        openly specified, standards-based technologies to proprietary
        alternatives, or to choose one tag set over another, is often if not
        usually characterized as a kind of ethical imperative. To use standard X
        or Y, in a standard way – or to be valid to a particular schema, or to
        use a particular schema language, or to prefer a certain processing
        platform, or a certain company's product – is considered
          </textual><quote class="po-inline e337 e337"><textual class="po-textual">good</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, and not to do so is condemned, stigmatized or
        derided as </textual><quote class="po-inline e338 e338"><textual class="po-textual">bad</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, without much reflection on why that
        should be. To see such a choice as a strategic or tactical decision
        within game play is both to relieve, and to resituate this ethical
        component. At one level, to prefer one schema (or schema language or
        naming convention or coding style or software product)`over another
        often seems to reduce to a kind of tribalism, the way the fans of one
        team or club must always show contempt for the fans of another; as such,
        a preference of this sort requires no explanation or apology beyond the
        play itself. Yet at another level, we can see that all such alignments
        have consequences in terms of strategy and the goals of a strategy, and
        as strategic choices, can make success in the game easier or harder to
        achieve – and not only because to make such a choice is to adopt the
        colors of one team and set oneself in opposition to others. One schema
        (to pursue that example) may actually be better suited than another to
        the task at hand. And yet, even when it is not, to forge a serviceable
        alliance with others who might help fit a particular schema to your
        purposes, may be to turn a tactical misstep into a strategic advantage.
        To understand such maneuvers as game play, rather than simply as
        conflicts of interest (although they are that), is to see how we can
        (and must) make sense of such complex considerations. In short,
        considering markup technologies as games can be a way of reframing our
        assessments and choices – this editing tool, that schema, even one
        pattern of tag usage versus another – within the assumptions,
        predispositions and prior commitments that otherwise drive them, to see
        how they might be more carefully considered and deliberate, less
        reflexive and driven by the demands of constituencies, audiences or
        authorities, even while those commitments remain real.</textual></para><para class="po-block e339 e339"><textual class="po-textual">This is important because it allows us to discriminate real ethical
        imperatives – here, </textual><quote class="po-inline e340 e340"><textual class="po-textual">real</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> means </textual><quote class="po-inline e341 e341"><textual class="po-textual">outside the
          game</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, and has to do with conduct in the world – from fictive
        and factional ones that have only to do with the play. These are easily
        fused, and their fusion is easily recognized by anyone who does not have
        a stake in the game, but the very essence of play – to play with
        commitment, with heart – is to fail to recognize this distinction.
        Perhaps the best players make this commitment, identifying the good of
        their cause with the Good in the abstract; this helps motivate them. But
        the very best players might ultimately be those who are able to step
        away from it again, having won or lost, motivated only by love of the
        game itself, and having done what they could to make the game itself
        worth the playing, whatever the outcome.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e342 e342"><title class="po-block e343 e343"><textual class="po-textual">Lessons for practitioners</textual></title><para class="po-block e344 e344"><textual class="po-textual">Another reason the analogy is important is that it enables us, as
        practitioners of markup, to look to game design and game play for ideas
        about how to go about our work. There are three general characteristics
        of games, in particular, which might be considered by users and
        especially designers of technology. All of them, I submit, have been at
        the root of the success of the SGML family of markup technologies
        (including HTML and all XML-related technologies) over the last twenty
        years, and in particular of the most successful application built on
        this platform, namely the web itself.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e345 e345"><title class="po-block e346 e346"><textual class="po-textual">Markup technologies on the web</textual></title><para class="po-block e347 e347"><textual class="po-textual">A successful nomic game is one that both grows and spins off
          variations.</textual></para><mediaobject class="po-container e348 e348"><imageobject class="po-container e349 e349"><imagedata class="po-meta e350 e350" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-009.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><section class="po-hcontainer e351 e351"><title class="po-block e352 e352"><textual class="po-textual">Transparency</textual></title><para class="po-block e353 e353"><textual class="po-textual">An important element of a game is that it be transparent. We know
          who has done what – which players have performed which feats of
          strength, dexterity or cunning – and the game itself offers the frame
          within which we can interpret their motives. Of course this
          transparency need not be complete while the game is ongoing, inasmuch
          as a game can involve misdirection and subterfuge; but ideally,
          everything becomes clear by the game's conclusion. (Games like poker,
          where this is not always the case, demonstrate this principle by
          showing its limits.) To the extent a game is both complete (that is,
          well-defined) and transparent, it becomes a kind of self-contained
          demonstration of prowess that becomes worth playing, or worth
          watching, despite and because of its isolation from the larger
          world.</textual></para><para class="po-block e354 e354"><textual class="po-textual">As such, transparency is one of the main differentiators between
          games and real life. And it is by no means similarly necessary in the
          design of technology. Indeed, a technology might be defined as a
          process that is made deliberately opaque, at least some of the time,
          to at least some of its users or beneficiaries. (As Arthur C. Clarke
          famously suggested, </textual><quote class="po-inline e355 e355"><textual class="po-textual">Any sufficiently advanced technology is
            indistinguishable from magic</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. Motorists do not need to know
          how an internal combustion engine works in order to drive their cars.)
          Because markup-based information processing systems are ultimately not
          games, but technologies with application to real-world tasks, a
          requirement for transparency is perhaps not fundamental to them in the
          same way as it is in game design.</textual></para><para class="po-block e356 e356"><textual class="po-textual">Nevertheless it is an important consideration, especially when
          designing loosely coupled systems that are meant to be, by their
          adaptability and extensibility, the basis of positive-sum outcomes
          (that is, games where for one player to win does not mean others must
          lose). When hands are not hidden, participants have a better idea of
          whose interests are being served by decisions at all levels, and so
          they can be made with more consideration of all the tradeoffs. A more
          transparent game is one that is less about deception, guile, and
          intrigue (and perhaps assertiveness, knowledge and discretion), and
          more about consistent and plain dealing (at the risk of rigidity and
          insensitivity). Again, it is a matter of what kinds of virtue one
          wishes to cultivate.</textual></para><para class="po-block e357 e357"><textual class="po-textual">Even more basically, a game that is not transparent is one that
          will tend not to attract attention or interest from either audiences
          or potential players. This is related to the next point.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e358 e358"><title class="po-block e359 e359"><textual class="po-textual">Simplicity</textual></title><para class="po-block e360 e360"><textual class="po-textual">Similarly, the world defined by a game must be complex enough to
          be interesting but simple enough not to be simply bewildering. It may
          have a terminology or a language of its own (part of what makes a game
          both fun and learnable may be its distinctiveness), but it must be
          intelligible. The rules for beginners must be simple enough to follow
          even as beginners, even while our interactions with more elaborated
          rules, as game play continues, might also be part of the fun.</textual></para><para class="po-block e361 e361"><textual class="po-textual">We must not suppose that simple rules make for a simple game. Even
          straightforward combinatorial possibilities make a game like Go or
          chess imponderably complex and endlessly variable (that is, humanly
          endless if not mathematically infinite), despite rules that can be
          learned in minutes. And this is to say nothing of the possibilities
          that are opened when direct human interaction and negotiation are made
          part of game play.</textual></para><para class="po-block e362 e362"><textual class="po-textual">XML has become more complex since it was first sprung on an
          unsuspecting world, even in its core standards (schema languages,
          namespaces, APIs and data models, query and transformation languages),
          to say nothing of its applications. In itself, this is not necessary
          indicative of a problem. Such complexity in the standards
          (elaborations in the rules of the game), if it is a reflection of
          complexity in the problems they address, can serve, by reducing the
          need for purely local solutions to common problems, to reduce
          complexity in the system at large, and thereby open the game. Assuming
          a standard solution to a problem is a reasonably good one, everyone
          benefits by being able to use the standard. At the same time, complex
          problems are often best addressed by layering them, a fact that XML in
          its proliferation of different initiatives has taken advantage of. For
          example (as described above), by distinguishing markup syntax from
          tagging semantics more discretely than SGML had done, XML was
          simplified for the marketplace, where parser developers can now work
          without being directly concerned with application semantics. By
          separating these two games (following rules to interpret a character
          stream, vs. following rules for applying markup structures to solve
          problems in publishing or data processing), XML lowered the costs of
          adopting markup technologies for everyone.</textual></para><para class="po-block e363 e363"><textual class="po-textual">Yet even when it is moved to the system at large, such an
          elaboration of complexity becomes a barrier to play. XML is easier to
          use, but harder to understand, when every developer has to learn when
          and how to distinguish </textual><quote class="po-inline e364 e364"><textual class="po-textual">processing</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> from
            </textual><quote class="po-inline e365 e365"><textual class="po-textual">parsing</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. (Indeed, there remain situations where the
          cost imposed by this distinction is too high and benefits accrue by
          ignoring it.) On the other hand, insofar as the game allows players to
          work such rules and principles out themselves, it also becomes a nomic
          one and this problem may paradoxically be exacerbated in the other
          direction, as players elaborate their own local solutions and
            </textual><quote class="po-inline e366 e366"><textual class="po-textual">speciation</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> occurs. (Nomic games beget nomic games,
          games within the game, spin-offs, knock-offs, games in exile.) Either
          way, the capacity of the game to build upon and elaborate itself
          creates negative feedback, dampening play by increasing its costs to
          players, and sending prospective players away before they can even get
          started. Eventually, the casual player stands no chance, and only
          devotees may participate.</textual></para><para class="po-block e367 e367"><textual class="po-textual">In short, balance is called for. It is a truism of both
          mathematics and engineering that parsimony is a virtue, as in the
          quote attributed to Albert Einstein (mainly, it seems, because it is
          simplest to do so), that things should be </textual><quote class="po-inline e368 e368"><textual class="po-textual">as simple as
            possible, but no simpler</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e369 e369"><para class="po-block e370 e370"><textual class="po-textual">As described at
                </textual><link class="po-inline e371 e371" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.entish.org/wordpress/?p=638</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">, the
              attribution is apocryphal and the principle itself is widely
              expressed; but whoever did put it this way first is apparently not
              memorable enough to give the line any authority.</textual></para></footnote></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e372 e372"><title class="po-block e373 e373"><textual class="po-textual">Fun</textual></title><para class="po-block e374 e374"><textual class="po-textual">Another factor related to both of these is how much pleasure a
          game provides to its players and spectators. One characteristic of
          play in general (or so reports Stuart Brown) is that it is
          self-sustaining: play begets play, exercising us until we tire. And
          then when we have recuperated ourselves, we want to play again. In the
          cultural marketplace, what makes a successful game is that it is both
          fun for its players, and attractive enough to win new players.</textual></para><para class="po-block e375 e375"><textual class="po-textual">Of course, </textual><quote class="po-inline e376 e376"><textual class="po-textual">fun</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> is impossible to define or even
          really characterize without delving into psychology or cognitive
          science. On the other hand, we can probably agree on two things: we
          can all look at our own experience to recognize what is fun; and
          whatever that is, we can also observe how it is not the same for
          everyone. Just as people have different learning styles, they find
          different things and different kinds of things to be fun. One
          important aspect of games as social phenomena is that they enable
          people who find similar things to be fun to have fun together, while
          those who don't find a particular activity to be fun can opt out of
          playing, or play a different sort of game.</textual></para><para class="po-block e377 e377"><textual class="po-textual">Technology, similarly, might be fun, and sometimes it is; or at
          any rate, there are people who have fun with it. (Those who find
          technology to be interesting and entertaining are also, evidently, the
          same people who enjoy certain sorts of games.) At the same time, there
          are others who would rather not think about technology, or a
          particular technology, at all. Of course, this brings us back to the
          transparency issue: technologies are fun when they help us think about
          what we enjoy thinking about, and don't demand we think about what we
          would rather not think about.</textual></para><para class="po-block e378 e378"><textual class="po-textual">Designers of markup technologies and their applications need to
          consider, like all designers, what kinds of problems their audience,
          stakeholders, and users want to have solved for them, and what kinds
          of problems they would rather (and might better) solve for themselves.
          A good technology will be one that is both fun (or satisfying) and
          useful to its users. This is a different design goal from simply
          solving a problem. Indeed, if technology designers find solving
          problems to be interesting and fun, why should they deny this
          satisfaction to others? We need to avoid situations where, in order to
          help, we have designed all the fun out.</textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e379 e379"><title class="po-block e380 e380"><textual class="po-textual">The big picture</textual></title><para class="po-block e381 e381"><textual class="po-textual">At Balisage 2008, Eduardo Gutentag drew attention to a paradox at
        the heart of XML. Its proponents have proposed as its </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e382 e382"><textual class="po-textual">raison
          d'être</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> the principle that the encoding of an electronic
        document, inasmuch as it secures the document's intellectual content,
        must be accessible to the document's creator and indeed owned by the
        document's owner. Standards – which is to say, externally specified,
        published sets of rules that provide the basis for commodity markets in
        technologies and toolsets, so that the rules of the game are not
        absolutely controlled by proprietary interests, and anyone, at least in
        principle, can play – are critical to this accessibility. Yet the
        networked media that have been built on the foundation of open text
        encoding (that is, on XML and its sister, HTML, along with their
        associated specifications), allow and in fact foster a radically
        open-ended exchange of data that undermines the very premise that
        information may be owned. To be accessible to anyone is, in a certain
        respect, to be owned by no one, at least insofar as gaining access means
        gaining control, just as a ball, once the game has begun,
          </textual><quote class="po-inline e383 e383"><textual class="po-textual">belongs</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> to anyone holding it. Given this tension, what
        will be the rules of this new information economy? Gutentag was not able
        to offer any definite prognostications.</textual></para><para class="po-block e384 e384"><textual class="po-textual">If space, time and materials are no longer factors (once the
        platform is in place, the cost of copying a document declines to nil),
        and technical barriers (such as copy-protection schemes or opaque,
        binary formats) are not interposed between users of information and the
        technical and material infrastructure within which that information is
        created, maintained, transmitted and manipulated, then seemingly only
        social and legal barriers remain to prevent me from appropriating your
        data however I see fit. And even if such social and legal means are
        introduced, they may not suffice, at least for the purposes of those who
        have depended in the past on maintaining some measure of exclusive
        control over information they have managed. More deeply and more
        problematically, however, if the rules of the game are part of the play,
        the game is a nomic one, and runs the risk of all nomic games, that in
        the process of self-reinvention it becomes unsustainable, collapsing in
        on itself. Then there can be no winners, at least until a new game
        emerges with new rules. These and related anxieties are at the heart of
        why, for example, Open Access policies, such as those now being
        developed at major universities, are so controversial.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e385 e385"><para class="po-block e386 e386"><textual class="po-textual">See, for example, Split Over Open Access in </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e387 e387"><textual class="po-textual">Inside
              Higher Ed</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (June 4 2009), at
              </textual><link class="po-inline e388 e388" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2009/06/04/open</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> On the one hand, producers of knowledge, such as researchers
        and scholars offered the opportunity (and perhaps the requirement) to
        make their work available through open access channels, have new and
        more powerful means of fulfilling their purpose of making their work
        available. On the other, to the extent that old institutional
        arrangements are imperiled (including implicit or explicit exchanges of
        value), so also are the securities offered by those arrangements.</textual></para><para class="po-block e389 e389"><textual class="po-textual">As legitimate as these concerns are, however, there is a deeper
        issue that may prove to be a critical determinant. The basis of the new
        information economy, if it proves sustainable (and it seems fair to
        expect that some sort of sustainable model will emerge), is and will be
        largely in non-proprietary technologies; sooner or later, this would
        seem to be necessary for a system that is truly global. Yet if the
        technologies grow so complex that to play XML, or to work with markup,
        means you have to devote a career to it despite its openness in
        principle, then the removal of merely legal encumbrances counts for
        less, and it is also up to us technocrats: our loyalties will determine
        what masters XML will serve. In that case, even in an open-access world,
        where theoretically anyone can play the game of publishing, not everyone
        will be able to play the game of technology that underlies and supports
        it (to say nothing of kindred activities such as data interchange,
        curation and archiving, aggregation and analysis), and a corporate
        oligarchy based on property rights will at best be replaced by a
        technological meritocracy based on access, education and knowhow. More
        likely, an uneasy hybrid between these two alternatives will emerge, at
        least until a new set of standards emerges to attract new players with
        new rules, more open to the self-taught. In any case, much depends on
        how markup technologies are promulgated: who teaches them, and who
        learns them, and for what purposes.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e390 e390"><title class="po-block e391 e391"><textual class="po-textual">Markup technologies: stages of play.</textual></title><para class="po-block e392 e392"><textual class="po-textual">Win a round, and you may be asked to help make the rules for the
          next one.</textual></para><mediaobject class="po-container e393 e393"><imageobject class="po-container e394 e394"><imagedata class="po-meta e395 e395" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-010.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e396 e396"><textual class="po-textual">Since this is a game, in short, that is played for keeps, within a
        larger world with larger stakes, XML, the design of markup technologies
        and applications, and the promotion of digital literacy in general, will
        all matter, at every level. Whether you are designing a document, a tag
        set, a transformation, a publishing system, a schema language, a
        processing language, a standard, a standards organization or a corporate
        strategy, keep this in mind. It is up to you and how you play that will
        determine the character, if not always the outcome, of the game.</textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e397 e397"><title class="po-block e398 e398"><textual class="po-textual">Acknowledgements</textual></title><para class="po-block e399 e399"><textual class="po-textual">This paper started as a page of notes scribbled in response to Eduardo
      Gutentag's 2008 Balisage paper </textual><citation class="po-atom e400 e400"><textual class="po-textual">Gutentag 2008</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">. In
      nomic fashion, one Balisage paper begets another.</textual></para><para class="po-block e401 e401"><textual class="po-textual">I am especially grateful to Matthew Kirschenbaum and his colleagues at
      the Maryland Institute of Technology in the Humanities, who offered
      essentially useful feedback to an early version.</textual></para><para class="po-block e402 e402"><textual class="po-textual">Additionally, credit is due to the Balisage peer reviewers for several
      invaluable suggestions, especially to one annoyed, anonymous reader, whose
      objections to a number of points led to many important refinements.</textual></para></section><bibliography class="po-hcontainer e403 e403"><title class="po-block e404 e404"><textual class="po-textual">Bibliography</textual></title><bibliomixed class="po-block e405 e405"><textual class="po-textual">Anonymous. nomic.net: home of nomic stuff.
        </textual><link class="po-inline e406 e406" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.nomic.net/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e407 e407"><textual class="po-textual">Brown, M.D., Stuart, and Christopher Vaughan. 2009. Play: How
      It Shapes the Brain, Opens the Imagination, and Invigorates the Soul.
      Avery, March 5.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e408 e408"><textual class="po-textual">Carse, James P. 1987. Finite and Infinite Games. Ballantine
      Books, August 12.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e409 e409"><textual class="po-textual">Fisher, Len. 2008. Rock, Paper, Scissors: Game Theory in
      Everyday Life. Basic Books, November 3.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e410 e410"><textual class="po-textual">Gutentag, Eduardo. 2008. XML: It was not televised after
      all.... Balisage: The Markup Conference. 12 - 15 August. Abstract at
        </textual><link class="po-inline e411 e411" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/html/2008/Gutentag01/Balisage2008-Gutentag01.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">. doi: </textual><biblioid class="po-atom e412 doi e412"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol1.Gutentag01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e413 e413"><textual class="po-textual">Koster, Raph. 2004. Theory of Fun for Game Design. 1st ed.
      Paraglyph, November 6.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e414 e414"><textual class="po-textual">Maturana, Humberto R., and Francisco Varela. 1992. Tree of
      Knowledge. Rev Sub. Shambhala, March 31.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e415 e415"><textual class="po-textual">National Scrabble Association. NSA Official Tournament Rules.
        </textual><link class="po-inline e416 e416" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.scrabble-assoc.com/rules/</textual></link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e417 e417"><textual class="po-textual">National Center for Biomedical Informatics, National Institutes
      of Health (NCBI/NIH). Journal Publishing Tag Set Tag Library version 3.0.
        </textual><link class="po-inline e418 e418" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/tag-library/3.0/index.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e419 e419"><textual class="po-textual">Ross, Don. Game Theory.
        </textual><link class="po-inline e420 e420" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/game-theory</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e421 e421"><textual class="po-textual">Shermer, Michael. 2008. “The Doping Dilemma.” Scientific
      American: April.
        </textual><link class="po-inline e422 e422" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=the-doping-dilemma</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e423 e423"><textual class="po-textual">Sperberg-McQueen, C. M., Claus Huitfeldt, and Allen Renear.
      2001. “Meaning and interpretation of markup.” Markup Languages: Theory
      &amp; Practice 2.3: 215-234.
        </textual><link class="po-inline e424 e424" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.w3.org/People/cmsmcq/2000/mim.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">. doi: </textual><biblioid class="po-atom e425 doi e425"><textual class="po-textual">10.1162/109966200750363599</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e426 e426"><textual class="po-textual">Suber, Peter. The Paradox of Self-Amendment.
        </textual><link class="po-inline e427 e427" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.earlham.edu/~peters/writing/psa/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e428 e428"><textual class="po-textual">Watterson, Bill. 2005. The Complete Calvin and Hobbes. 3 vols.
      Andrews McMeel Publishing: October 4.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e429 e429"><textual class="po-textual">Wittgenstein, Ludwig. 1991. Philosophical Investigations: The
      German Text, with a Revised English Translation 50th Anniversary
      Commemorative Edition. G. E. M. Anscombe and Elizabeth Anscombe, trans.
      3rd ed. Wiley-Blackwell, January 15. </textual></bibliomixed></bibliography></article></classedDocument>