<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2" xml:id="HR-23632987-8973"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">Documents Cannot Be Edited</textual></title><info class="po-record e2 e2"><confgroup class="po-record e3 e3"><conftitle class="po-field e4 e4"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">August 11 - 14, 2009</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e6 e6"><para class="po-block e7 e7"><textual class="po-textual">Most definitions of </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e8 e8" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">document</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> current in the
                document processing and digital publishing communities, would, if take literally,
                imply that documents are extensional entities that cannot undergo changes such as
                editing or revision. In other domains as well, such as textual criticism and library
                science, one can also find notions of text or document that are similarly difficult
                to reconcile with modification. We describe the problem and sketch some possible
                resolutions. Although the issues are conceptual and foundational the practical
                significance is real. Formal representation in logic-based ontology languages,
                increasingly important in information management, requires that familiar idioms,
                however serviceable and entrenched, be converted to expressions that support literal
                interpretation.</textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e9 e9"><personname class="po-record e10 e10"><firstname class="po-field e11 e11"><textual class="po-textual">Allen</textual></firstname><othername class="po-field e12 e12"><textual class="po-textual">H.</textual></othername><surname class="po-field e13 e13"><textual class="po-textual">Renear</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e14 e14"><para class="po-block e15 e15"><textual class="po-textual">Allen H. Renear is the Associate Dean for Research and an Associate Professor
                    at the Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University of
                    Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e16 e16"><jobtitle class="po-field e17 e17"><textual class="po-textual">Associate Dean for Research and Associate Professor</textual></jobtitle><orgname class="po-block e18 e18"><textual class="po-textual">Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University of Illinois
                    at Urbana-Champaign</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e19 e19"><textual class="po-textual">renear@illinois.edu</textual></email></author><author class="po-record e20 e20"><personname class="po-record e21 e21"><firstname class="po-field e22 e22"><textual class="po-textual">Karen</textual></firstname><othername class="po-field e23 e23"><textual class="po-textual">M.</textual></othername><surname class="po-field e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">Wickett</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e25 e25"><para class="po-block e26 e26"><textual class="po-textual">Karen M. Wickett is a doctoral student at the Graduate School of Library and
                    Information Science, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e27 e27"><jobtitle class="po-field e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">Doctoral Student</textual></jobtitle><orgname class="po-block e29 e29"><textual class="po-textual">Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University of Illinois
                    at Urbana-Champaign</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e30 e30"><textual class="po-textual">wickett2@illinois.edu</textual></email></author><legalnotice class="po-container e31 e31"><para class="po-block e32 e32"><textual class="po-textual"> Copyright © 2009 Allen H. Renear and Karen M. Wickett. Used by permission.
            </textual></para></legalnotice><keywordset class="po-table e33 e33" role="author"><keyword class="po-field e34 e34"><textual class="po-textual">document</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e35 e35"><textual class="po-textual">text</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e36 e36"><textual class="po-textual">XML</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e37 e37"><textual class="po-textual">ontology</textual></keyword></keywordset></info><section class="po-hcontainer e38 e38"><title class="po-block e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">The Problem</textual></title><para class="po-block e40 e40"><textual class="po-textual">Document modification seems to be routine and widespread. Editing is a familiar
            practice to almost everyone, and revision a fundamental feature of publishing workflows.
            Yet document modification would appear to be an illusion. Common accounts of what
            documents are seem to imply that documents cannot undergo genuine modification.</textual></para><para class="po-block e41 e41"><textual class="po-textual">The W3C XML specification defines an XML Document as a string that meets certain
            formal constraints. Strings are mathematical constructs that are defined, ultimately, in
            set theoretic terms. They are therefore purely extensional entities constrained by the
            axiom of extensionality, common to all standard set theories. As a consequence, strings
            have all of their non-relational properties essentially and cannot be altered or
            modified in any way. Although we can of course identify functions that map one string to
            another, the existence of such functions does not, by itself, provide a explanation of
            what constitutes the modification of a document. </textual></para><para class="po-block e42 e42"><textual class="po-textual">This consequence is not unique to the definition of a document as a string. Familiar
            alternative definitions fare no better. Documents (in the relevant sense) have been
            defined as graphs, relations, Ordered Hierarchies of Content Objects [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e43 e43" linkend="derose90"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], and sentences in formal logic [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e44 e44" linkend="renear06"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].
            But these are all also extensional entities: graphs, relations, tuples, and strings all
            have mathematical definitions in virtue of which they are kinds of sets. Nor is the
            problem particular to formal definitions that make explicit use of mathematical
            constructs. Many of the concepts of document (or text) used in library science, textual
            criticism, aesthetics, and other fields appear, upon examination, to be similarly
            problematic. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e45 e45"><title class="po-block e46 e46"><textual class="po-textual">A Simple Example: The Verona Sentence</textual></title><para class="po-block e47 e47"><textual class="po-textual">The problem can be made introduced with a simple example that makes no explicit use of
            mathematical or philosophical notions [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e48 e48" linkend="renear08"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].</textual></para><para class="po-block e49 e49"><textual class="po-textual">Consider the sentence "I remember Verona." Let this be the first sentence of the first
            chapter of a draft of a novel.</textual></para><para class="po-block e50 e50"><textual class="po-textual">Suppose that the author decides to edit that sentence and revises it to read: "I
            remember, but dimly, Verona".</textual></para><para class="po-block e51 e51"><textual class="po-textual">It is natural to say that the first sentence of the chapter has been changed, that it
            is now longer. But exactly </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e52 e52" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">what</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> has been changed?
                </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e53 e53" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">What</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> has become longer? The new first sentence, "I
            remember, but dimly, Verona", has not changed. That sentence has never consisted of
            fewer than five words. The original sentence, "I remember Verona", has not changed
            either. It is not now longer than it was; it still consists of three words. It is true
            that "I remember, but dimly, Verona" is a longer sentence than "I remember Verona", but
            it did not </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e54 e54" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">become</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> a longer sentence than "I remember
            Verona" -- it has always been a longer sentence than "I remember Verona".</textual></para><para class="po-block e55 e55"><textual class="po-textual">One might attempt to address the problem by shifting the scope of attention and
            propose that it is the text of the chapter that has changed. However, the chapter as a
            whole is simply another, if longer, textual entity, and has the same identity
            conditions. So the puzzle will arise again. The chapter has been revised, but neither
            the new text nor the original text undergoes any change during this process. And the
            same argument may be made for the entire text of the novel.</textual></para><para class="po-block e56 e56"><textual class="po-textual">In short: While it is natural to speak of sentences or other textual entities changing
            when they are edited or revised, it appears that these entities themselves do not really
            change. So what does change? </textual></para><para class="po-block e57 e57"><textual class="po-textual">The Verona puzzle may feel like a parlor trick, but the significance is real enough:
            we do not have a clear conceptual understanding of what is happening when documents are
            modified. Of course truth values can be correctly assigned to modification sentences
            such as "The sentence was changed", but only if we treat these sentences as idioms, as
            we do sentences like "The average plumber has 3.2 children". Such sentences do not have
            compositional semantics or support existential instantiation and there is often little
            systematic guidance for their interpretation. Up until now we have largely avoided these
            problems, relying ad hoc solutions and human intervention. But the increasingly formal
            nature of new semantic approaches to information management and publishing, and the
            continuing minimization of human intervention, will inevitably require us to more
            systematically to develop robust literal interpretations of fundamental concepts.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e58 e58"><title class="po-block e59 e59"><textual class="po-textual">An Inconsistent Triad</textual></title><para class="po-block e60 e60"><textual class="po-textual">Consider the following three assertions:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e61 e61"><listitem class="po-container e62 e62"><para class="po-block e63 e63"><textual class="po-textual">All documents are strings.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e64 e64"><para class="po-block e65 e65"><textual class="po-textual">Strings cannot be modified.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e66 e66"><para class="po-block e67 e67"><textual class="po-textual">Documents can be modified.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e68 e68"><textual class="po-textual">As any two of these assertions will together logically imply the negation of the
            remaining assertion it is not possible for all three to be true. And yet each has some
            initial plausibility. </textual></para><para class="po-block e69 e69"><textual class="po-textual">In favor of the first assertion, that all documents are strings, we begin by observing
            that in the definition of an XML Document in the W3C XML specification the first clause
            has as a consequence that XML Documents are strings: </textual><blockquote class="po-container e70 e70"><para class="po-block e71 e71"><textual class="po-textual">Definition: A textual object is a well-formed XML document if:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e72 e72"><listitem class="po-container e73 e73"><para class="po-block e74 e74"><textual class="po-textual">Taken as a whole, it matches the production labeled document.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e75 e75"><para class="po-block e76 e76"><textual class="po-textual">It meets all the well-formedness constraints given in this
                            specification.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e77 e77"><para class="po-block e78 e78"><textual class="po-textual">Each of the parsed entities which is referenced directly or indirectly
                            within the document is well-formed.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></blockquote><textual class="po-textual">
        </textual></para><para class="po-block e79 e79"><textual class="po-textual">Understanding documents (or a relevant sense of "text") to be sequences of characters
            or words is also consistent with approaches in library cataloguing [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e80 e80" linkend="frbr98"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] and textual editing [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e81 e81" linkend="tanselle89"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].</textual><footnote class="po-popup e82 e82"><para class="po-block e83 e83"><textual class="po-textual">In this analysis we are using string based definitions of documents as a proxy
                    for broader class of definitions, including those that define a document as a
                    kind of graph, a kind of relation, or an "Ordered Hierarchy of Content Objects".
                    So what follows from identifying documents as a kind of string is intended to
                    also follow from definitions that imply that a document is a graph, a relation,
                    an OHCO, or any other relevantly similar entity.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
        </textual></para><para class="po-block e84 e84"><textual class="po-textual">In favor of the second assertion it may be argued that modification of an entity
            necessarily involves the loss of a property and that strings have no properties which it
            is possible for them to lose and survive the loss. [We assume losing a property and
            gaining the complement of that property are equivalent characterizations of the same
            event.] The string "13571" has the property of having a length of five tokens, the
            property of having one token type occur twice, and the property of having the substring
            "35". But these are all properties that "13571" cannot lose. That is, the string in
            question, "13571", which has property of having "35" as a substring, cannot at some
            point in the future lose the property of having "35" as a substring. There is no
            plausible entity that will serve as the reidentifiable persistent object that could
            undergo such a change. Cf. the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e85 e85" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Functional Requirements for
                Bibliographic Records:</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> "...if a text is revised or modified, the
            resulting expression is considered to be a new expression, no matter how minor the
            modification may be" [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e86 e86" linkend="frbr98"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] </textual><footnote class="po-popup e87 e87"><para class="po-block e88 e88"><textual class="po-textual">It might be argued that "13571" does have the property of "being thought about
                    by someone" (at this moment, as you read this paper), and that this is a
                    property that it can lose. But the loss of properties of this sort (</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e89 e89" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">relational properties</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">) does not seem to be genuine
                    modification. We do not say that the second-tallest person in the room has
                    undergone a modification when he becomes the tallest person in the room not in
                    virtue of getting any taller, but in virtue of the previously tallest person in
                    the room leaving the room. Genuine modification requires the loss or gain of a
                    non-relational property. But strings, sets, relations, graphs, and such things
                    have no non-relational properties they can lose: all of their non-relational
                    properties appear to be in some sense essential to their identity. Furthermore,
                    even if we allowed that the loss or gain of a non-relational property was a
                    genuine modification, this would not appear to be much help with the larger
                    problem, as editing changes would in any case seem to be changes in the inherent
                    and non-contingent properties of a string, and not its relational
                properties.</textual></para></footnote></para><para class="po-block e90 e90"><textual class="po-textual">In favor of the third assertion, that documents can be modified, we simply observe
            that this is an assumption that for most of us is so deeply entrenched in our common
            understanding that the title of this paper probably seems more senseless than
            provocative. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e91 e91"><title class="po-block e92 e92"><textual class="po-textual">Responses</textual></title><para class="po-block e93 e93"><textual class="po-textual">One sort of response to a triad claimed to be inconsistent is to deny the
            inconsistency. Typically this takes the specific form of claiming that one of the
            assertions in the triad has two possible interpretations. Interpreted one way the
            assertion is true but the triad consistent. When the assertion is interpreted in the
            other way the triad becomes inconsistent, but the assertion is no longer plausible. When
            this is the situation the problematic nature of the triad is an illusion created by
            trading on this ambiguity.</textual></para><para class="po-block e94 e94"><textual class="po-textual">As modal locutions well-known for generating ambiguity and paradox are evident in our
            triad we shall now indicate exactly how the English sentences are to be interpreted and
            confirm that given the intended interpretation the triad is in fact inconsistent. We do
            this by expressing the assertions in elementary predicate logic.</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e95 e95"><listitem class="po-container e96 e96"><para class="po-block e97 e97"><textual class="po-textual">(x)[(isaDocument(x) -&gt; isaString(x)]</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e98 e98"><para class="po-block e99 e99"><textual class="po-textual">(x)[(isaString(x) -&gt; ~isModifiable(x)]</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e100 e100"><para class="po-block e101 e101"><textual class="po-textual">(Ex)[(isaDocument(x) &amp; isModifiable(x)]</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e102 e102"><textual class="po-textual">On the standard interpretation of quantifiers and connectives these three formulas
            clearly form an inconsistent set. </textual></para><para class="po-block e103 e103"><textual class="po-textual">Once the inconsistency of a triad is granted the remaining responses are typically
            classified according to which assertion in the triad is rejected. We will consider
            responses that reject the first and third assertion; we do not here consider responses
            that deny the second assertion.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e104 e104"><para class="po-block e105 e105"><textual class="po-textual">Responses to an inconsistent triad of plausible assertions usually reject just
                    one assertion. It is true that combinatorially there are seven possible
                    combinations of assertions that might be rejected, but solutions rejecting more
                    than one assertion bear a prima facie higher burden of defense and consequently
                    are rare. We do not consider any such response here, although the final response
                    we discuss qualifies, without actually rejecting, the first assertion as well as
                    denying the third assertion.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
        </textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e106 e106"><title class="po-block e107 e107"><textual class="po-textual">Responses that Deny Documents are Strings</textual></title><para class="po-block e108 e108"><textual class="po-textual">These responses reject the standard definitions of a document as a kind of string
                or relevantly similar entity, such as graph, relation or OHCO. For this to be a
                plausible response a suitable alternative definition must be proposed.</textual></para><para class="po-block e109 e109"><emphasis class="po-inline e110 e110" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">The Materialist Strategy:</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> This strategy holds
                that a document is not a string, but a concrete arrangement of a quantity of matter
                and energy. On this view modification of a document does literally occur:
                modification consists in physical changes to the material document, with the
                document preserving its identity across these changes (otherwise it would be
                destroyed rather than modified).</textual></para><para class="po-block e111 e111"><textual class="po-textual">Against the Materialist Strategy: The identification of a document with a
                particular concrete arrangement of matter and energy instead of a string appears
                inconsistent with many of the things that we say about documents. For instance we
                speak of </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e112 e112" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">the</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> document even when there may be many
                physical instances, intending not to refer to any one of them, or the set, but
                rather to something they all represent or instantiate. Whether this apparent
                reference to an abstract object can be paraphrased away remains promissory.
                Documents certainly have physical representations, and these representations are
                often materially involved in scenarios of putative document modification. But
                whether a document can be defined as one of, or even the class of, these separate
                individual representations remains to be seen. </textual><footnote class="po-popup e113 e113"><para class="po-block e114 e114"><textual class="po-textual">Although we describe this response as "materialist" because it asserts
                        that documents are material things rather than strings, materialism
                            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e115 e115" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">per se</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> neither entails, nor is entailed
                        by, the materialist strategy described here. The materialist strategy can be
                        adopted by the non-materialist who holds that while there are non-material
                        things, documents are not among them. More significantly a materialist may
                        decline the materialist response, allowing that documents are strings, but
                        holding that strings are material things, choosing another assertion from
                        the triad to reject. This last observation reveals that the materialist
                        response requires the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e116 e116" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">elimination</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> of
                        strings (from the definition). Mere </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e117 e117" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">reduction</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> of strings to material things does not provide, in
                        itself, any response at all to the inconsistency. </textual></para></footnote></para><para class="po-block e118 e118"><emphasis class="po-inline e119 e119" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">The Social Object Strategy:</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> This response posits
                as the modifiable document a </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e120 e120" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">social object</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> which is
                    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e121 e121" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">constituted by</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (but not identified with), one
                string at one time and another string at another time, the changes being determined
                by social (including institutional and linguistic) circumstances. This approach
                abstracts from the physical and is consistent with the common belief that documents
                can be modified. The document presumably maintains a coherent identity across
                various textual changes and may be associated as well with any number of different
                physical representations. A theoretical basis for this strategy can be found John
                Searle's work [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e122 e122" linkend="searle95"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] although Searle's theory appears to be
                primarily one of natural facts that in certain social circumstances "count as"
                social facts rather than natural objects that that in certain social circumstances
                count as social objects. Barry Smith has defended a theory of social objects that
                allows social objects to exist even without natural objects that "count as" or
                constitute them [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e123 e123" linkend="smith03"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. Another related perspective is Brian
                Cantwell Smith's notion of holding objects in the "middle distance" [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e124 e124" linkend="cantwellsmith96"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]</textual></para><para class="po-block e125 e125"><textual class="po-textual">Against the social object strategy: The social object strategy preserves the
                intuition that documents are modifiable, but at a considerable cost. First, it
                requires an ontologically challenging entity, social objects that cannot be
                identified with physical objects, abstract objects, or even mental states. There is
                also a corresponding new distinctive metaphysical relation as well: </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e126 e126" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">constitution</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, the relationship that obtains between the
                social object and the different strings that constitute that object at different
                times. That this relation cannot be simple identity is evident from the fact that it
                is not transitive: while the document qua social object may be constituted by one
                string at one time and a different string at another time, this does not imply that
                the two strings are themselves identical. Searle's notion of "counting as", if
                applied to social objects, may avoid some of the traditional problems with
                constitution, but it will still be hard to reconcile social objects with a
                naturalistic view of the world.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e127 e127"><title class="po-block e128 e128"><textual class="po-textual">Responses that Deny Documents can be Modified</textual></title><para class="po-block e129 e129"><textual class="po-textual">These strategies accept the first assertion of the triad, that a documents is a
                string, and rejects the third assertion, that documents can be modified. If such an
                approach is to be plausible it must provide a convincing alternative account of what
                is happening in the situations which we would ordinarily describe as "modifying a
                document".</textual></para><para class="po-block e130 e130"><textual class="po-textual">The title of this paper notwithstanding, denying document modification does not
                necessarily require claiming that sentences like "John edited a document" never
                express facts about the world. These sentences may be considered idioms. As such
                they sometimes communicate true assertions, but they are not</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e131 e131" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">literally</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> true. Consider again the sentence "The average plumber has
                3.2 children". This sentence might indeed be used to make a true assertion. And if
                it does make a true assertion then it is certainly reasonable to say that the
                sentence is a true sentence. However we would not conclude from the truth of the
                sentence "The average plumber has 3.2 children" that there is therefore an entity in
                the world which </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e132 e132" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">is</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> the average plumber and which
                actually </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e133 e133" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">has</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> some fractional number of children, as
                a naive Russellian interpretation of the definite description would entail. What is
                being denied in the rejection of the third assertion of the triad is not the truth
                of sentences like "John edited a document", but rather that such sentences imply a
                claim such as the one suggested by the first order formula: </textual></para><para class="po-block e134 e134"><textual class="po-textual">
                </textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e135 e135"><listitem class="po-container e136 e136"><para class="po-block e137 e137"><textual class="po-textual">(Ex)[(isaDocument &amp; edited(john,x)]</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></para><para class="po-block e138 e138"><emphasis class="po-inline e139 e139" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">The New Document Strategy:</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> This response
                maintains that the modification of a document is actually the creation of a new
                document. </textual></para><para class="po-block e140 e140"><textual class="po-textual">Against the New Document Strategy: The new document strategy has new strings
                created with each document modification. This seems peculiar, contrary to general
                notion of strings, and generally difficult to reconcile with a naturalistic view of
                the world. Consider the string "13571". Was that string created? How did that
                happen? And when? Can it be destroyed? Can it be re-created? Unless strings are
                material objects the conceptual apparatus of creation and destruction seems entirely
                metaphorical.</textual></para><para class="po-block e141 e141"><textual class="po-textual">The </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e142 e142" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Selection Strategy:</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> This approach holds that
                in a typical scenario of alleged modification a new but already existing string is
                    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e143 e143" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">selected</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> for attention. When we say that a
                document has been modified we mean that a different string has been selected for the
                purpose at hand by some particular person or persons. The physical infrastructure of
                analog or digital document development and publishing, in combination with social
                conventions and practices, is a system for recording and communicating which string
                is currently distinguished in this way.</textual></para><para class="po-block e144 e144"><textual class="po-textual">Against the Selection Strategy: The selection strategy identifies documents with
                already existing strings. But this seems strange. Either these already existing
                strings came into existence at some point in the past or they have always existed.
                If the former then this strategy has no advantages over the new document strategy;
                it must still somehow account for how strings can come into existence, from what
                materials and in what causal circumstances. But if the latter, if strings have
                always existed, then assuming only that the further requirements for being a
                document are non-contingent (such as matching a production) we will have documents,
                and not just strings, existing eternally -- apparently even before cognitive agents.
                This seems peculiar.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e145 e145"><title class="po-block e146 e146"><textual class="po-textual">A Strategy that both Redefines Document </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e147 e147" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">and</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
                Denies Modification.</textual></title><para class="po-block e148 e148"><textual class="po-textual">Strictly speaking the strategy we are about to take up denies only the third
                assertion of the triad (documents can be modified). However because it proposes a
                substantially new definition of document it has much in common with strategies that
                deny the first assertion and so we are placing it in a separate category.</textual></para><para class="po-block e149 e149"><textual class="po-textual">The </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e150 e150" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">String-in-a-role Strategy:</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> This strategy
                holds that a document is a string in a particular communicative role. The string
                itself may be an uncreated and pre-existing entity, but the strings which are
                documents need not always have been documents. Being a document is a property that
                strings have only in particular contingent social/linguistic situations. So on this
                account </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e151 e151" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">documents</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> have not always existed, even
                though documents are strings, and strings have always existed. This is because while
                a string which is a document has always existed, that string has not always been a
                document -- a string becomes a document only in the appropriate social
                circumstances.</textual></para><para class="po-block e152 e152"><textual class="po-textual">Although this strategy, like the strategies that reject the first assertion of the
                triad (documents are strings) involves a new approach to the definition of document,
                it affirms rather than rejects the first assertion of the triad. After all, if a
                document is a string in a communicative role, then a document is a string. However,
                the string-in-a-role definition of document is unlike definitions such as the one in
                the XML specification in that it places a contingent rather than necessary
                constraint on strings satisfying the definition. If a document is defined as a
                string with certain purely formal constraints (as it is in the XML specification,
                where it must match a particular production in a grammar), then the things which are
                in fact documents are documents necessarily. This is because not only is it
                impossible for a string to cease to be a string or have been anything other than a
                string, it is also impossible for a string that matches a particular production to
                have ever failed to match that production or to fail to match that production in the
                future. </textual></para><para class="po-block e153 e153"><textual class="po-textual">According to the string-in-a-role strategy the property of being a document is
                what Guarino and Welty refer to as a "rigid" property [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e154 e154" linkend="guarino00"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].
                Guarino and Welty define rigidity using modal logic and model theory, but the basic
                idea is simple: a property is rigid if and only if nothing that has that property
                could have failed to have that property, or could come to lose that property, (and
                still exist). For example, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e155 e155" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">being a person</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> is rigid
                because the things that are persons could not have been anything but persons and
                cannot cease to be persons (although they can cease to be). But </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e156 e156" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">being a student</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> is not rigid because the things that are
                students (i.e. persons) might not have been students and can cease to be students
                (without ceasing to be). According to Guarino and Welty rigid properties indicate
                    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e157 e157" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">types,</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> fundamental kinds of things, while
                non-rigid properties indicate </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e158 e158" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">roles</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> that things of
                some particular type may enter into. On this view a document is not a type of thing,
                but a role that things of some type or other have in particular contingent circumstances.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e159 e159"><para class="po-block e160 e160"><textual class="po-textual">A result in some respects similar to one that was reached in response a
                        different puzzle about XML documents. </textual><xref class="po-milestone e161 e161" linkend="renear06"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">
                        </textual><xref class="po-milestone e162 e162" linkend="renear07"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></para><para class="po-block e163 e163"><textual class="po-textual">The redefinition of document as a "string-in-a-role" is not itself a response to
                the inconsistency of the triad; if a document is a string-in-a-role then it is still
                a string, and strings cannot change. The string-in-a-role strategy rejects the third
                assertion, and denies that, strictly speaking, documents change. </textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e164 e164"><title class="po-block e165 e165"><textual class="po-textual">Concluding Remarks</textual></title><para class="po-block e166 e166"><textual class="po-textual">There is much more to be said pro and con on the strategies we have described here,
            and there possibly better strategies to consider. We have intended only to suggest some
            of the possibilities. Formal representation and inferencing is increasingly widespread
            and increasingly important, and systematically making information computationally
            available in logic-based ontology languages requires literal interpretation. Human
            beings may effectively communicate with natural language sentences such as "The document
            was edited" or "The average plumber has 3.2 children". But to support inferencing in the
            semantic web environment these idioms must be represented formally in languages that
            rely on compositional semantics, existential instantiation, and valid deductive
            consequences.</textual></para><para class="po-block e167 e167"><textual class="po-textual">Or... </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e168 e168" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">perhaps not.</textual></emphasis></para><para class="po-block e169 e169"><textual class="po-textual">One has to wonder whether all this logic-chopping subtlety is going to be worth it. It
            isn't clear exactly how to finish the job, and yet it is clear that some of our most
            familiar -- and effective -- ways of conceptualizing our domain will revised if we
            continue along this path. Particularly troublesome is the prospect that the revisions
            anticipated will add not only complexity in design and use, but increase computational
            complexity as well. As we have suggested elsewhere "denormalized" ontologies may be more
            appropriate for much of the practical work ahead. </textual></para><para class="po-block e170 e170"><textual class="po-textual">Acknowledgements: This paper draws on work carried out collaboratively at the Graduate
            School of Library and Information Science, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.
            Much of the early work was organized by Dave Dubin and sustained by various research
            groups.</textual></para></section><bibliography class="po-hcontainer e171 e171"><title class="po-block e172 e172"><textual class="po-textual">Bibliography</textual></title><bibliomixed class="po-block e173 e173" xml:id="buckland97" xreflabel="buckland97"><textual class="po-textual"> Buckland, M. K. "What is a
            "document"?" </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e174 e174" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Journal of the American Society for Information
                Science,</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 48 (1997),804-809. doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e175 doi e175"><textual class="po-textual">10.1002/(SICI)1097-4571(199709)48:9%3C804::AID-ASI5%3E3.0.CO;2-V</textual></biblioid></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e176 e176" xml:id="cantwellsmith96" xreflabel="cantwellsmith96"><textual class="po-textual">Cantwell Smith,
                B.</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e177 e177" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">On the origin of objects</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Cambridge: MIT Press,
            1996.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e178 e178" xml:id="derose90" xreflabel="derose90"><textual class="po-textual">DeRose, S. D., Durand D. G., Mylonas,
            E., Renear, A. H. "What is text really?" </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e179 e179" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Journal of Computing in
                Higher Education</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 1 (1990), 3-26. Reprinted in ACM/SIGDOC </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e180 e180" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Journal of Computer Documentation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 21 (1997). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e181 doi e181"><textual class="po-textual">10.1145/264842.264843</textual></biblioid></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e182 e182" xml:id="guarino00" xreflabel="guarino00"><textual class="po-textual">Guarino, N. and Welty, C. A. A formal
            ontology of properties. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e183 e183" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of the 12th European
                Workshop on Knowledge Acquisition, Modeling and Management.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Lecture Notes
            In Computer Science. Springer-Verlag, (2000), 97-112.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e184 e184" xml:id="frbr98" xreflabel="frbr98"><textual class="po-textual">International Federation of Library
            Associations (IFLA). Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records: Final Report.
            UBCIM Publications-New Series. Vol. 19, München: K.G.Saur, 1998.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e185 e185" xml:id="renear03" xreflabel="renear03"><textual class="po-textual">Renear, A. and Dubin, D. "Towards
            Identity Conditions for Digital Documents". In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e186 e186" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of the
                2003 international Conference on Dublin Core and Metadata Applications</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
            (Seattle, Washington, September, 2003). International Conference on Dublin Core and
            Metadata Applications. Dublin Core Metadata Initiative, 1-9. 2003. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e187 e187" xml:id="renear06" xreflabel="renear06"><textual class="po-textual">Renear, Allen H. "Is An XML document a
            FRBR Manifestation or a FRBR Expression? -- Both, Because FRBR Entities are not Types,
            but Roles." in Extreme Markup Languages 2006 Proceedings, Montreal, Canada. 2006. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e188 e188" xml:id="renear07" xreflabel="renear07"><textual class="po-textual">Renear, A. H., Dubin, D. "Three of the
            Four FRBR Group 1 Entity Types are Roles not Types." In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e189 e189" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings 70th Annual Meeting of the American Society for Information Science and
                Technology</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (Milwaukee, WI, October 2007).</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e190 e190" xml:id="renear08" xreflabel="renear08"><textual class="po-textual">Renear, A. H., Dubin, D., and Wickett,
            K. M. "When Digital Objects Change * Exactly What Changes?" In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e191 e191" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings 71st Annual Meeting of the American Society for Information Science and
                Technology</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (Columbus, OH, October 2008).</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e192 e192" xml:id="searle95" xreflabel="searle95"><textual class="po-textual">Searle, J. R. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e193 e193" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">The
                Construction of Social Reality</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. New York: The Free Press, 1995.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e194 e194" xml:id="smith03" xreflabel="smith03"><textual class="po-textual"> Smith, B. "John Searle: From Speech Acts
            to Social Reality", in </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e195 e195" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">John Searle</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">,
            B. Smith (ed) Cambridge University Press 2003. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e196 e196" xml:id="tanselle89" xreflabel="tanselle89"><textual class="po-textual"> Tanselle, T. G. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e197 e197" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">A Rationale of Textual Criticism,</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Philadelphia: University of
            Pennsylvania Press, 1989 </textual></bibliomixed></bibliography></article></classedDocument>