<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">The high cost of risk aversion</textual></title><info class="po-record e2 e2"><confgroup class="po-record e3 e3"><conftitle class="po-field e4 e4"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2010</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">August 3 - 6, 2010</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e6 e6"><para class="po-block e7 e7"><textual class="po-textual">Avoiding risk is not always the way to minimize risk.</textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e8 e8"><personname class="po-record e9 e9"><firstname class="po-field e10 e10"><textual class="po-textual">B. Tommie</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e11 e11"><textual class="po-textual">Usdin</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e12 e12"><para class="po-block e13 e13"><textual class="po-textual">B. Tommie Usdin is President of Mulberry Technologies, Inc., a consultancy
          specializing in XML and SGML. Ms. Usdin has been working with SGML since 1985 and has been
          a supporter of XML since 1996. She chairs the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e14 e14" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          conference and was co-editor of </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e15 e15" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Markup Languages: Theory &amp;
            Practice</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> published by the MIT Press. Ms. Usdin has developed DTDs, Schemas,
          and XML/SGML application frameworks for applications in government and industry. Projects
          include reference materials in medicine, science, engineering, and law; semiconductor
          documentation; historical and archival materials. Distribution formats have included print
          books, magazines, and journals, and both web- and media-based electronic publications. You
          can read more about her at </textual><link class="po-inline e16 e16" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.mulberrytech.com/people/usdin/index.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.mulberrytech.com/people/usdin/index.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e17 e17"><orgname class="po-block e18 e18"><textual class="po-textual">Mulberry Technologies, Inc.</textual></orgname></affiliation></author><legalnotice class="po-container e19 e19"><para class="po-block e20 e20"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright © 2010 by the author. Used with permission.</textual></para></legalnotice></info><note class="po-container e21 e21"><title class="po-block e22 e22"><textual class="po-textual">Editor’s Note</textual></title><para class="po-block e23 e23"><textual class="po-textual">This talk was given in the opening session of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2010.</textual></para></note><para class="po-block e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">Welcome to Balisage: The Markup Conference 2010. I am delighted to see you all here. 
    This is — someone has probably already told you this — the biggest “Balisage” conference ever. And I hope it will
    be one of the best. I look forward to Balisage, even as I wonder what, if anything, I can say in the opening
  that will start the conference off on a the right tone.</textual></para><para class="po-block e25 e25"><textual class="po-textual">They tell me I have to pick a topic  ... they tell me ... that’s not
    fair. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e26 e26" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">I</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> tell me that I have to pick a topic for my talk when we put the conference 
    program together, so I pick one, and then months later I have to turn that topic into a talk. One of these years
    I’m going to learn that when I pick my topic I should at least make notes on
    what I think I’m going to talk about.  When I sat down to write "The
    High Cost of Risk Aversion" to open this conference, I thought, “I wonder what I thought I
    was going to talk about when I wrote that title. There are a lot of possibilities.” </textual></para><para class="po-block e27 e27"><textual class="po-textual">I love conferences, and this conference in particular. I want your help with the culture of
    this conference. I want Balisage to be friendly and courteous. I want us to be able to
    respectfully disagree with things we all feel passionate about without being disrespectful or
    rude, without resorting to mudslinging or fisticuffs, even if that might feel appropriate. What
    did I just say? Don’t call anybody names and don’t hit anybody. Be
    passionate but not personal. Challenge the ideas that a speaker has just presented, the logic
    behind the argument made, or the practicality of the proposals; question the approach,
    background, and possibly even mastery of the facts. Don’t question the intent or the
    character of the speaker. And, of course, do all questioning from the microphone, please.</textual></para><para class="po-block e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">Is it necessary for me to tell you this? Well, it shouldn’t be. But we’ve had
    a few people who were a little excessively passionate in previous years. So, one of the kinds of
    risks we take is really getting into it at Balisage.</textual></para><para class="po-block e29 e29"><textual class="po-textual">I haven’t done it, have I? Avoiding risk is not always the way to minimize risk.
    That’s still my topic, and it’s not what I’m talking about yet.</textual></para><para class="po-block e30 e30"><textual class="po-textual">Alright, I’ll go farther. Avoiding risk is sometimes a way to maximize risk. And that
    happens particularly, I think, in the technology area. As we become fearful what we do is make
    things worse, not better. And at least for this week at Balisage, I would like for you to leave
    some of your fears at home. Be willing to take some risks and to advocate risk-taking.
    Let’s let go of arguing for perpetual backwards compatibility of everything all the time
    because it’s too risky to break anything. Let’s let go of advocating the safe path
    all the time because it’s easy.</textual></para><para class="po-block e31 e31"><textual class="po-textual">Be willing to take some risks yourself. For those of us who are consultants, I am beginning
    to believe that if you haven’t been fired from at least one consulting project for
    advocating something that made your client sweat, you aren’t a very good consultant.
    Okay, how many of you in the audience have ... no, I’m not going to ask. [laughter] But I have.</textual></para><para class="po-block e32 e32"><textual class="po-textual">You know, I’m not actually the conventional image of a risk-taker. (I do have a
    mirror.) I’m short, and I’m fat,  I’m on the trailing edge of
    middle-aged, and I’m gray-haired. I could bore you for at least an hour with my medical
    problems, and I don’t swear or spit or drink. But I do take risks — selected
    risks. I think as a community we are taking too few risks right now, and I think we should
    reconsider that.</textual></para><para class="po-block e33 e33"><textual class="po-textual">Some of those risks are personal. I was recently at a conference I had not previously attended. 
    The topic was interesting; the program was interesting; the speakers included some
    people whose works I had read and was quite impressed by; and the location was reasonably
    convenient. So I went.</textual></para><para class="po-block e34 e34"><textual class="po-textual">And when I got there, not too surprisingly, I didn’t see anybody I knew. (I
    didn’t see anybody I knew until the second afternoon.) So, there I was,
    surrounded by interesting people with whom I shared an interest but who I had never met. 
    The least risky thing for me to
    do, personally at least, was to mind my own business and sit in the corner and listen. And the
  shy child inside me (it is my opinion that EVERONE has a shy child inside them) wanted to 
  do just that.</textual></para><para class="po-block e35 e35"><textual class="po-textual">But I like conferences; I do conferences. I jumped in. At the first break, I got in line to
    get a cup of coffee, and I said to the person ahead of me in line, “What’s your
    interest in ’name the topic of the conference’?” And she answered,
    “I teach it,” and turned away, got her coffee, and walked away. Oh, well. That was
    a failure.</textual></para><para class="po-block e36 e36"><textual class="po-textual">So, now I have my cup of coffee, and I’m looking around the room, and there’s
    a man on the edge of the crowd, not talking to anybody, watching what’s happening in the room.
    So, I walked over and stood next to him and said, “I don’t know a single person in
    this room, do you?” And he said, “I know all the ones who matter.” before taking 
    a step away from me.
    “Oh.”, I said.
    [laughter] Well. This was not my morning.</textual></para><para class="po-block e37 e37"><textual class="po-textual">I drank my coffee and I realized I had another couple of minutes, there
    was still a line at the coffee machine, and, well, I needed something to get through the day
    with these friendly people, so I got back in that line, and I said to the woman in front of me
    “So, what’s the
    most interesting thing you’re expecting on the program this afternoon?” And she
    turned around and said, “I speak tomorrow.” [laughter] And then she said to the
    person standing behind me, “Becky, how nice to see you!” She grabbed Becky's hand,
    pulled her past me in line, and said, “Stand with me, so we can catch up.”</textual></para><para class="po-block e38 e38"><textual class="po-textual">This really happened. Ouch. But you know what? I still wasn’t actually bleeding, and
    I did attend the next two and a half days of the conference. Why am I telling you all this
    stuff? Is it because the next thing I’m going to tell you is: And the
    next day I met the new love of my life, and I’ve just gotten back from six bliss-filled weeks on a
    Caribbean island, I’ve still got sand between my toes; it was wonderful. Well, no. But I
    did end up meeting a couple of people I will call if I have 
    questions on a particular topic. And I did learn a few things that were interesting and will
    possibly, even probably, prove useful in the future. It was not a waste of
    time. </textual></para><para class="po-block e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">I would like for us at Balisage to have better manners that the people I have just been describing. 
    I would like for us to assume,
    unlike the people at that event, that if somebody is here, you probably do have an interest in
    common with them. They might be interesting to talk to, and blatantly snubbing them is not only rude, it is
    foolinsh because it deprives you of the opportunity to talk with someone you may find interesting if not 
    professionally useful in the future. I would like for you to assume if you don’t know anyone here 
    that your overtures to others will be welcomed, so you will take the risk of talking to people. And if somebody you
    don’t know startles you by starting to talk to you, I want you to think about how you
    would like to be treated in that position.</textual></para><para class="po-block e40 e40"><textual class="po-textual">I used to say that managing life and work was a balancing act between three things that are
    in limited quantity, not only in my life, but in everyone’s life, those three things
    being time, energy, and money. There’s never enough of any of them, and you can
    frequently trade one for another. For example, I spend money on having the grass cut at my
    house. I could spend time and energy on it, but  it’s a task I absolutely
    despise, and there are things I can't pay to have someone do that I would rather do with my energy and time. 
    And as
    we do projects at work, we frequently also have the opportunity to balance time, energy, and
    money.</textual></para><para class="po-block e41 e41"><textual class="po-textual">But I’ve actually left something important out of that equation; the real equation is
    time, energy, money, and risk. It never even occurred to me at my house, for example, when my
    furnace broke to replace the furnace myself. That was partly about time and energy and money,
    but it was also about risk. Why did the furnace need replacing in the first place? Because it
    had a cracked heat exchanger, and if I used it, it might fill the house up with carbon monoxide
    and kill the occupants. Why didn’t I replace that cracked heat exchanger, or stick some duct
    tape on it and hope all would be well? [laughter] Because it might then fill the house up with carbon
    monoxide and kill all the occupants!</textual></para><para class="po-block e42 e42"><textual class="po-textual">I guess I’m very fortunate in that nothing that I do for work could actually kill
    lots of people. But I can certainly do things that would waste a whole lot of time and energy
    and money, and have risks to balance in terms of each of those is used. When you start thinking
    about how you’re going to approach anything, including, for many of you in this room,
    the way you are going to talk at this conference, think about the balance you are discussing
    between time, energy, money, and risk.</textual></para><para class="po-block e43 e43"><textual class="po-textual">In a very important, as least important to me, sense, you are all risk-takers. You’ve
    chosen to invest your time and energy and money and, to some extent, your reputations in
    Balisage, an event that is far from the center of any of your universes. I suspect that for most, if
    not all of you, if somebody were to say “What is </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e44 e44" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">the</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 
    conference in your field,”
    this wouldn’t be it. It would be a conference on some subject matter; it would be a
    conference about aircraft or pharmaceuticals or libraries or whatever it is that you really do
    as opposed to how you do it, which is most of what brings us here. I want to make sure you are
    rewarded for the risks you have taken in coming to Balisage. Balisage is an event at which we
    are all allowed — maybe encouraged — to think about and talk about our ongoing
    work, to talk about what we could do better and what we can’t do at all and what we want
    to do and what we want not to do. This is a place where we can talk about things that
    don’t work and things that we may not want.</textual></para><para class="po-block e45 e45"><textual class="po-textual">If you’re here, it’s likely that you feel as I do about people telling me what
    I can do and what I can think about. A few years ago — quite a few years ago now —
    I was doing work in my kitchen, and one of the things I needed to do was buy a new oven. And I
    walked into an appliance store and said to the salesman, “Do you have an oven with these
    three features?” I don’t even remember what they were. And he said to me,
    “Women don’t want that.” And I stopped and thought about it for a moment
    and said, “I’m going to walk out of this store, and then I’m going to walk back
    in, and I’m going to ask the same question, and you’re going to give me a civil
    answer.”  I walked out of the store, and I waited a minute, and I walked back in and
    looked at a very confused salesman and said, “Do you have an oven with these three
    features?” And he said, “I’m not aware of any manufacturers who make
    that.” Okay, that’s a fair answer. And at that point, I was willing to 
    have a conversation with him about what was available and what I could buy and ended up buying
    something.</textual></para><para class="po-block e46 e46"><textual class="po-textual">That was not a unique experience. I also remember a time, actually not so long ago, when I
    called the user support line for some software I use on a regular basis and said, “I
    can’t figure out how to do .... This is what I’m trying to accomplish.” And
    the person on the other end of the telephone said, “You don’t want to do
    that.” Now, in fact, I did want to do that! What he really meant was “Our software
    can’t support that.” And after a little questioning/negotiation, we finally
    established that and established that we didn’t really need to discuss what I wanted; we
    needed to discuss what this tool would allow me to do and how. I ended up with an acceptable
    workaround and filing an enhancement request. I don’t actually know whether enhancement
    requests to this particular vendor go anyplace but the circular file, but at least they asked
    for it. And that helps. At Balisage, I hope none of us are going to be told “We
    don’t want that.” We may be told that nobody knows how to do it.</textual></para><para class="po-block e47 e47"><textual class="po-textual">Daniel Shore — how many of you know who Daniel Shore was? Okay, many of the North
    Americans and nobody else. Daniel Shore was a reporter and a news analyst and a free speech
    advocate; a radio commentator, a newspaper reporter, a television
    reporter — Daniel Shore was one of my heroes. (I don’t have a lot of heroes.)
    He died recently so I’ve been reading or re-reading some of his work. One of the things 
    he said seems appropriate. He said:</textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e48 e48"><para class="po-block e49 e49"><textual class="po-textual">There are today more pressures than ever to conform, to avoid rocking the boat. I’m
      prone to advise at least once in your lifetime take a risk for a principle you believe in even
      if it brings you up against your bosses.</textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e50 e50"><textual class="po-textual">And he said:</textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e51 e51"><para class="po-block e52 e52"><textual class="po-textual">It really is true that I would sometimes stand up for a principle at the risk of my
      job.</textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e53 e53"><textual class="po-textual">But he was honest. He also said:</textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e54 e54"><para class="po-block e55 e55"><textual class="po-textual">It is also true that when I lose my job, I get terribly nervous.</textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e56 e56"><textual class="po-textual">I think those are some things to think about. And I am not telling you when you go home you
    should tell your boss that you really are not interested in how many steps his granddaughter
    took last weekend, or how much fun your supervisor had on her vacation in Iowa City or Eindhoven
    or wherever she went. Nor am I suggesting that you insist on getting your way on everything all
    the time, but rather pick your battles and know what’s important. And take this time at
    Balisage to think about what’s important in the technology we work on.</textual></para><para class="po-block e57 e57"><textual class="po-textual">I know some people who have a lot of very important data. What do I mean by “a
    lot”? Well, when they talk about things you can count, the unit is usually millions. How
    many documents? It’s in the millions. How many searches? It’s in the millions. How
    many users? It’s in the millions. They have a lot of data,by
    anybody’s count, they’ve got a lot of data.</textual></para><para class="po-block e58 e58"><textual class="po-textual">And what do I mean by “their data is important”? Well, not only does their
    organization live off their data, if they and their data cease to exist, there are a whole lot
    of other people and a whole lot of other organizations who would be seriously disaccommodated
    and who would have to scramble to find some way to meet this need. So, they have a lot of data
    that a lot of people think is important. And they have a fifteen-year-old — well, almost
    twenty-year-old — data lifecycle architecture. Not all the pieces of it are twenty years
    old, but the way they handle their content is between fifteen and twenty years old.</textual></para><para class="po-block e59 e59"><textual class="po-textual">And they have a group — I think they call it a “team,” but maybe
    it’s a “task force” or a “committee”; it’s one of
    these organizational things — looking into new storage options because they’re
    having a hard time serving their data fast enough for their users. And they’re looking
    toward getting a big, fancy, new database of the same sort that they’ve already got; only
    this one will be bigger and better and faster and newer. And the brochure has the word
    “XML” in it to plug into this architecture and solve all their problems. And most
    of this task force thinks that’s the right answer because the thing that’s slow is
    serving the documents, and if they get a bigger, better, faster database, all will be well. And
    if they get the same kind of database they already have, then all of their training will still
    be good, and they will still be valuable to the organization because they know how to work in this
    environment, and it is the least risky thing they can do, and it will solve the problem.</textual></para><para class="po-block e60 e60"><textual class="po-textual">Fortunately, they have an irritant on their task force, and this irritant keeps saying to
    them, “That’s not safe.” “What do you mean, it’s not
    safe?” “We have to look at the whole lifecycle; we have to look at receipt and
    validation and storage and maintenance and archiving and all the things we do with our documents
    before it makes sense to just replace one component of this architecture.” And my friend 
    (my friend is that irritant, wouln't you know) 
    is hearing, “That’s really risky; that’s going to be really disruptive.
    It’s going to touch everybody in the organization if we do that; we can’t do
    that,” to which my friend is arguing, “If you don’t do that, the whole
    thing may crash. If we don’t look at the whole system, when we remove the bottleneck, we
    may create a whole bunch of new bottlenecks, and the whole thing may break, besides which this
    organization does not have the stamina to sustain two major system changes in ten years. And if
    we use up our once a decade major system change on a logically-minor upgrade, we then can’t fix
    anything else. The least risky approach is very dangerous.” I’m not sure how this
    is going to come out. I know who I’m cheering for.</textual></para><para class="po-block e61 e61"><textual class="po-textual">We at Balisage are the people who can, should, and often do speak up and say, “The
    safe approach is unsafe. The emperor has no clothes.” If you’re going along to get
    along, and that feels safe, be aware that that may be safe in the short run, but it may be very
    unsafe in the long run.</textual></para><para class="po-block e62 e62"><textual class="po-textual">Let’s talk about Balisage for another minute. There are conferences where all of the
    presentations are comfortable, safe, and non-controversial; where everybody loves everyone else;
    where bluebirds flit decoratively through the hallways without soiling anybody; and where
    anybody who sounds a sour note and talks about anything that doesn’t work or can’t
    be done is not invited back (quietly behind the scenes so as not to upset the paying customers).
    You’re not at one of those conferences.</textual></para><para class="po-block e63 e63"><textual class="po-textual">There are conferences where every talk is expected to give the audience members something
    they can use next week. They want a “take-away” from every forty-five minute
    presentation of something practical that is implementable immediately. You are not at one of
    those conferences, either.</textual></para><para class="po-block e64 e64"><textual class="po-textual">This is a place where you should expect to have your ideas challenged and to hear about some
    work that you don’t understand or that you don’t understand the logic behind or
    the reasons for. Expect to hear about projects unlike yours and organizations with priorities
    different from yours. Expect to hear some stuff you don’t quite understand. (I know I
    will. I read all the papers; I know there’s going to be stuff here I don’t
    understand. With luck, I will get some of it.) Expect that in the next year or two or three,
    some of the things that you heard here will come to mind as you are thinking about a 
    problem or decision.  It’s possible some of them will actually
    be practically useful; it is more likely that they will get you thinking about things that will
    help you in the future, get you out of places where you’re stuck. Expect the payback on
    Balisage to be real, substantial, difficult to document, and significantly delayed.</textual></para><para class="po-block e65 e65"><textual class="po-textual">As you speak at Balisage, stick your neck out a bit. Tell us about the good stuff: what have
    you done well? Tell us about the unfinished stuff: what do you want to do next? Tell us about
    the things that unexpectedly don’t work. Tell us about what you want to do in the future,
    about what you’re thinking.</textual></para><para class="po-block e66 e66"><textual class="po-textual">We have some first-time speakers. One of the things I really enjoyed this year when the
    submissions came in is we got submissions from a whole lot of people I’d never heard of.
    That’s really good! Please don't misunderstand me, I am very happy to see old friends 
    and familiar faces here, but I am particularly pleased to see all of these new people. 
    So, I say particularly to the new speakers, be warned: discussion here will be courteous 
    but lively. People will question your assumptions. They will question your methods. They may
    agree with you for some very odd reasons. That’s the most disconcerting — when somebody
    gets up to the microphone and says, “Yes, you are absolutely right because the moon is
    made of old socks!” (Talk to them in the hallway afterwards.)</textual></para><para class="po-block e67 e67"><textual class="po-textual">Expect lively discussion. Be aware that, at least in my opinion, the best contributions to
    Balisage will end up on our evaluation forms on both the “best of” lists and the
    “worst of” lists. When you look at the evaluation form, it asks you to list the
    talks you liked the best and the talks you liked the least. There are some talks that will end
    up only on the “best” list, and that’s nice; somebody gave a good talk. I
    like that. And there are some talks that will end up only on the “worst” list, and
    well, that happens, and it’s unfortunate. I don’t which it will be, but I expect that
    we’ll have at least one total dog of a talk this week. But the really good ones will end
    up in both places because they will polarize people, and that’s what makes people think.
    That’s what we’re here for. So, welcome to Balisage; let’s start thinking.</textual></para></article></classedDocument>