<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">Informal Ontology Design</textual></title><subtitle class="po-block e2 e2"><textual class="po-textual">A Wiki-Based Assertion Framework</textual></subtitle><info class="po-record e3 e3"><confgroup class="po-record e4 e4"><conftitle class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2008</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e6 e6"><textual class="po-textual">August 12 - 15, 2008</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e7 e7"><para class="po-block e8 e8"><textual class="po-textual">
     Wiki software has historically provided little support for any form of
     organizational structure. Even given the assumption that the majority of wiki
     users have previous experience with file system-like hierarchies, most wiki
     systems keep things simple (as is the wiki way) and employ a flat page structure.
     As a wiki grows beyond a few dozen pages, some form of organization becomes
     increasingly necessary. This has typically been accomplished by adding
     “category links” to each page, essentially
     </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e9 e9" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">ad hoc</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> terms from an unstructured and
     uncontrolled vocabulary. Because these terms are themselves
     often undefined it can be difficult to ascertain the reason why a given page
     belongs to a category. Even when this is done carefully, as the number of terms
     in the categorization grows a classification scheme for the terms themselves
     likewise becomes increasingly necessary.</textual></para><para class="po-block e10 e10"><textual class="po-textual">This paper describes problems with existing wiki and “semantic
     wiki” categorization schemes and outlines an approach to information
     organization that avoids the pitfalls of computer-based ontologies by instead
     looking to library science for solutions. It describes the design and
     implementation of a wiki system permitting user-authored
     </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e11 e11" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">assertions</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, which are dynamically harvested to
     create a Topic Map graph mirroring the explicit structure of the wiki and providing
     it with an underlying classification system.
     </textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e12 e12"><personname class="po-record e13 e13"><firstname class="po-field e14 e14"><textual class="po-textual">Murray</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e15 e15"><textual class="po-textual">Altheim</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e16 e16"><para class="po-block e17 e17"><textual class="po-textual">
    Through 2005 he was a Ph.D. student reading in Knowledge Representation and Artificial Intelligence
    at the Knowledge Media Institute, until he realized the futility of it all and after some time in
    the Mediterranean decided he'd rather be near the sea in a much warmer place. Through January of 2002
    he was employed in the XML Technology Center at Sun Microsystems in Menlo Park, California. Through
    February 1997 he was a Program Manager of Software Engineering at Spyglass, Inc. in Cambridge, MA.
    Through mid-January 1996, he was an Information Systems Analyst with the National Technology Transfer
    Center in Wheeling, West Virginia. Previously he was a Senior Systems Analyst contracted to NASA
    Headquarters' Office of Advanced Concepts and Technology, where he created and administered the NASA
    Commercial Technology Network web site. Prior to NASA he worked as a consultant and systems analyst
    at California State University in Sacramento, where he developed an executive information system for
    university planning and policy development. Prior to that he worked in the university's computer
    center for 357 years. Prior to that he was a mollusk.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e18 e18"><textual class="po-textual">
    He is author of various proposals on modularizing the HTML DTD, such as a draft proposal of a modular,
    XML version of HTML 4.0, as well as earlier documents such as the Structured HTML (SHML) DTD, available
    even today as a working draft, although one might prefer the W3C Recommendation Modularization of XHTML.
    He has functioned as Sun's representative to the W3C HTML Working Group, where he was co-author of a
    number of XHTML-related specifications and principal editor of the modular XHTML DTDs. During most of
    2000-2001 he devoted a lot of time and energy to XML Topic Maps. He's also been enthusiastically
    involved in discussions regarding the Open Hyperdocument System (OHS), part of Doug Englebart's
    bootstrapping strategy, and in the past has been actively involved in the Standard Upper Ontology,
    Conceptual Graphs, and Common Logic mailing lists. All of this allows him to use a lot of big words with
    impunity.
    </textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e19 e19"><orgname class="po-block e20 e20"><textual class="po-textual">Ceryle.org</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e21 e21"><textual class="po-textual">murray08 (at) altheim.com</textual></email><link class="po-inline e22 e22" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.altheim.com/murray/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.altheim.com/murray/</textual></link></author><legalnotice class="po-container e23 e23"><para class="po-block e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright © 2008 Murray Altheim</textual></para></legalnotice><keywordset class="po-table e25 e25" role="author"><keyword class="po-field e26 e26"><textual class="po-textual">assertion architectures</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e27 e27"><textual class="po-textual">classification systems</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">computer-based ontologies</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e29 e29"><textual class="po-textual">social software</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e30 e30"><textual class="po-textual">thesaurus</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e31 e31"><textual class="po-textual">Topic Maps</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e32 e32"><textual class="po-textual">XTM</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e33 e33"><textual class="po-textual">wiki</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e34 e34"><textual class="po-textual">Z39.19</textual></keyword></keywordset></info><section class="po-hcontainer e35 e35"><title class="po-block e36 e36"><textual class="po-textual">Introduction</textual></title><para class="po-block e37 e37"><textual class="po-textual">
    As with any document collection, as a wiki grows its need for some form of organization increases
    proportionately. It's not uncommon for wikis to have hundreds or even thousands of pages, without
    even considering the rather atypical Wikipedia (which as of July 2008 claims “approximately
    ten million articles in 253 languages”). Yet Wikipedia has no explicit classification scheme.
    </textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e38 e38"><title class="po-block e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">Category Links</textual></title><blockquote class="po-container e40 e40"><para class="po-block e41 e41"><textual class="po-textual">
    […] knowledge is all sort of knitted together, or woven, like cloth, and each
    piece of knowledge is only meaningful or useful because of the other pieces.
    </textual></para><attribution class="po-block e42 e42"><textual class="po-textual">Gregory Bateson, Steps to an Ecology of Mind</textual></attribution></blockquote><para class="po-block e43 e43"><textual class="po-textual">
    A common (some might say traditional) approach to categorization</textual><footnote class="po-popup e44 e44" xml:id="fn01"><para class="po-block e45 e45"><textual class="po-textual">
      We define </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e46 e46" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">category</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> as an ad hoc division within a subject domain
      absent an explicit classification scheme. Whereas classification may be said to be systematic,
      categorization need not be. Categorization is a preliminary process in the creation of a classification
      scheme but in informal or colloquial systems may be the only process. In library science a category is
      sometimes considered synonymous with a </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e47 e47" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">facet</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (from Faceted Classification).
      </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
    on wikis relies on untyped web links,
    usually camel-case prefixing a category name with the word "Category" (e.g.,
    “CategoryHomePage”, “CategoryDiscussion”, etc.). Any wiki page containing such a
    link is considered categorized under that category. There a number of problems with such a system. First,
    any wiki page containing a given link is categorized accordingly even if that was not the intention of
    the link author, as the mere presence of a link – not its traversal – establishes the categorization.
    Another is that as the categorization of a given wiki page must be expressed on the page itself, there is no
    way to categorize a collection of pages from a different page, via a list or other external structure. The
    categorization naming scheme is also bound to the link names; there are no synonyms, homographs, equivalent
    terms; no way of characterizing the relations between terms, no thesaurus-like hierarchy, indeed, no explicit
    structure at all. One can add or remove categories from a page, but to change the categorization of a page one
    must change its name, which breaks existing links, and there is no facility for synthetic or combinatory categories
    apart from creating longer and more complicated wiki page names. It is a simple system and works reasonably well
    for small document sets.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e48 e48"><textual class="po-textual">
    In library science, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e49 e49" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">free language indexing</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> permits the assignment of any word
    as an indexing term. One type often performed via an automated process, the terms used in
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e50 e50" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">natural language indexing</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> are derived from the natural language of a document
    rather than a controlled vocabulary of a classification system. Like free language indexing, user-created wiki
    categorization suffers in the same way due to mismatches between content and search terms and a lack of
    terminology control. One of the main questions faced in the design of our own system was trying to mitigate
    these problems.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e51 e51"><title class="po-block e52 e52"><textual class="po-textual">Classification Systems</textual></title><para class="po-block e53 e53"><textual class="po-textual">
    Despite being a Linux user, like most people buying a new laptop I had no choice but to purchase Microsoft
    Vista. One of the first things I did was remove all of the anti-virus software since it was so horribly
    annoying, such that subsequently going online would be akin to putting my head in an electric oven. Given that
    my use of Windows is strictly offline, deciding to write this paper in Word became a matter of discipline.
    Admittedly it does have rather beautiful typography.</textual></para><para class="po-block e54 e54"><textual class="po-textual">
    Now, while scanning the shiny new Vista menus I came upon OneNote, a software application I didn't even
    know I owned. OneNote is touted as something I might be very interested in:
    </textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e55 e55"><para class="po-block e56 e56"><textual class="po-textual">
    OneNote is an idea processor, a notebook, an information organizer — some even call it
    an "add-on pack for your brain." … a place for gathering, organizing, searching,
    and sharing notes, clippings, thoughts, reference materials, and other information. All your
    notes will be visible here — organized by notebooks, sections, and pages.
    </textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e57 e57"><textual class="po-textual">
    So how does it organize information? Typical of most software applications devoted to the organization
    of notes, it uses the staid metaphor of folders, which in the library world might be called an
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e58 e58" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">enumerated classification scheme</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">: every subject gets a folder. In
    OneNote's case the central innovation is that you can put folders inside folders, and change the
    folder of an item at will. Even in their introductory documentation one can see a foreshadowing of the
    unfolding nightmare:
    </textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e59 e59"><para class="po-block e60 e60"><textual class="po-textual">
    As you use OneNote and create more notes, you may want to organize your notes differently:
    </textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e61 e61"><listitem class="po-container e62 e62"><para class="po-block e63 e63"><textual class="po-textual">If you find yourself creating a lot of pages for a topic, try dragging them into a new section</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e64 e64"><para class="po-block e65 e65"><textual class="po-textual">If you find yourself creating many sections in one notebook, try putting some of them
              into a separate notebook</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e66 e66"><para class="po-block e67 e67"><textual class="po-textual">Make navigation between notes more convenient by creating several notebooks at the
              top level, rather than putting everything inside one notebook</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></blockquote><para class="po-block e68 e68"><textual class="po-textual">
    As any librarian will tell you, the problem with enumerated schemes is that they are inflexible,
    don't take account of the fact that most resources don't fit neatly into one category
    (e.g., a book on 19th century French seascape paintings fits into at least four), and there is no
    ability to map context. OneNote users go through the same process as a librarian classifying a collection
    of books in the early 19th century: as a book arrives it gets put on a shelf next to books at that moment
    deemed similar. If there isn't a suitable shelf a new shelf is created. If a suitable category
    isn't clear, one doesn't have the time or has abandoned all hope, OneNote includes the obligatory
    category “Unfiled Notes”.
    </textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e69 e69"><para class="po-block e70 e70"><textual class="po-textual">
    It's okay if this section gets big. You can drag the pages to other sections later,
    or just use search to find them in this section.
    </textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e71 e71"><textual class="po-textual">
    Do you get the feeling a lot of people store most of their notes in Unfiled Notes? The perennial question
    “where did I put that?” is once again answered by search. This is not an innovation.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e72 e72"><title class="po-block e73 e73"><textual class="po-textual">Knowledge Representation</textual></title><blockquote class="po-container e74 e74"><para class="po-block e75 e75"><emphasis class="po-inline e76 e76" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Suzy said, "You mean I'm fish?"</textual></emphasis></para><para class="po-block e77 e77"><emphasis class="po-inline e78 e78" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">"You're fish," said Fauna.</textual></emphasis></para><attribution class="po-block e79 e79"><textual class="po-textual">John Steinbeck, Sweet Thursday</textual></attribution></blockquote><para class="po-block e80 e80"><textual class="po-textual">
    “Knowledge representation” is a strange concept, when you think about it. What exactly is
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e81 e81" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">knowledge</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">? How does one </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e82 e82" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">represent</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> knowledge?
    A world of difficulty is opened up by the decomposition of even the simplest statements in
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e83 e83" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">natural language.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> While one might agree that the above sentences communicate
    information, do they also represent knowledge? Does the spoken word? How does the word “fish” relate
    to our conception of the word, its meaning in our minds? How is the concept of the word altered by its being
    composed within the context of the above statements, with their strange (perhaps erroneous) grammatical
    constructions? Does what we know about the author or our realization that the characters are fictional influence
    our understanding of the word? If we've not read the book, might we assume Suzy is a fish, instead of
    understanding that (in the “reality” or context of the book) Fauna is explaining Suzy's horoscope
    to her, that she was born under the sign of Pisces, the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e84 e84" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">sign of the fish</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">? Are
    the statements </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e85 e85" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">correct</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, and given any notion of judgment of such correctness,
    in what context can they be evaluated? And more obliquely, what does "being a Pisces" really mean?
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e86 e86"><textual class="po-textual">
    Apart from astrology, these questions are properly in the realms of </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e87 e87" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">linguistics</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">,
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e88 e88" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">semiotics</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e89 e89" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">phenomenology</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, the study of the
    relationship between directly-experienced reality and phenomena (i.e., our awareness of reality, as received via
    our perceptions) and how meaning is imparted to phenomena by culture.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e90 e90"><textual class="po-textual">
    Any system dealing with the interplay of knowledge representation and phenomenology is also complicated by the
    presence of ambiguity in natural language. While considered a favorable quality of poets and writers it isn't
    appropriate for description within the sciences, even though the terminology found in the domains of knowledge
    representation and ontological engineering is rife with it. As Allen Newell noted in his influential address to
    the AI community, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e91 e91" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">The Knowledge Level</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual><xref class="po-milestone e92 e92" linkend="Newell"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, the use of the term
    “knowledge” within that community is “informal”. Despite people's common anthropomorphization
    of machines, “intelligent systems” are not actually intelligent in any real sense; “knowledge
    based systems” do not operate based upon human knowledge but on a fixed program or set of rules;
    likewise “common sense reasoning” relies on mistaken notions of a “common sense” and
    “reasoning”. The list goes on. The historical use of seductive marketing language as a means of obtaining
    grant funding made the introduction of “semantic” to the lexicon of the Web almost inevitable. Now
    everything is “semantic”.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e93 e93"><title class="po-block e94 e94"><textual class="po-textual">Semantics, Shemantics</textual></title><blockquote class="po-container e95 e95"><para class="po-block e96 e96"><textual class="po-textual">I don't know who invented water, but it wasn't a fish. – </textual></para><attribution class="po-block e97 e97"><textual class="po-textual">Alan Kay</textual></attribution></blockquote><para class="po-block e98 e98"><textual class="po-textual">
    The extant literature on the "Semantic Web" — as promulgated by the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)
    and the plethora of academics now beavering away under its auspices — suggests a world populated by engineers
    with little grasp of the last half-century's progress in either philosophy or library science, designing systems
    that promise abilities that cannot possibly be delivered, ignoring profound epistemological issues, linguistic and
    cultural chasms that have never been breached, at the same time passing over the enormous successes within the field
    of library science in organizing and classifying information.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e99 e99"><textual class="po-textual">
    In what might be considered part of the ongoing tradition of 1920's visions of bubble cities on Mars, 1970's visions
    of chatty household robotic butlers enlivened by “artificial intelligence” as they deliver our
    martinis</textual><footnote class="po-popup e100 e100" xml:id="fn02"><para class="po-block e101 e101"><textual class="po-textual">subsequently, “SW”</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">,
    the “Semantic Web” often appears as merely the latest flight of future fantasy (italics courtesy of the
    author):</textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e102 e102"><para class="po-block e103 e103"><textual class="po-textual">
    The Semantic Web is an evolving extension of the World Wide Web in which the semantics of information
    and services on the web is </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e104 e104" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">defined</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, making it possible for the web to
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e105 e105" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">understand</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e106 e106" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">satisfy</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> the requests
    of people and machines to use the web content. It derives from W3C director Tim Berners-Lee's vision
    of the Web as a </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e107 e107" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">universal</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> medium for data, information, and
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e108 e108" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">knowledge exchange</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.
    </textual><xref class="po-milestone e109 e109" linkend="WikipediaSW"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e110 e110"><textual class="po-textual">
    Even the short excerpt above, taken from Wikipedia's SW page (and typical of the hype), is riddled with
    terminological problems. Decomposing any one of these terms raises issues that are never addressed
    in any except the most hand-waving fashion, not to mention the anthropomorphization of the Web itself. We are meant
    to understand that machines will “comprehend semantic documents and data”
    </textual><xref class="po-milestone e111 e111" linkend="BernersLee2001"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">,
    where “comprehend” is defined by the Random House dictionary as </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e112 e112" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">to understand
    the nature or meaning of; to grasp with the mind</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. This is surely the realm of science fiction.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e113 e113"><textual class="po-textual">
    Other elements of the SW are expressed in a large number of formal specifications; in their entirety they
    are intended to provide a formal meta-framework for description and use of concepts, terms, and
    relationships within a given knowledge domain.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e114 e114"><textual class="po-textual">
    If the language describing these designs is to be believed, the systems themselves must have found
    solutions to some rather nagging epistemological problems, in particular the connection between
    informal language usage, computational linguistics and formal logic. The reality of the SW hardly
    seems to be the following of a unified vision, but merely the ongoing collection of normative
    specifications for markup syntaxes, several dozen “vocabularies” and roughly fifty
    technologies and assorted software projects that purport to be part of this grand vision.
    </textual><xref class="po-milestone e115 e115" linkend="SWOver"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e116 e116"><textual class="po-textual">
    While this profusion of activity might seem to indicate success, there is nothing in any of this work
    to indicate that </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e117 e117" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">any</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> of it has broached the real problems of
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e118 e118" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">representing knowledge</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, if indeed that is something that is actually
    possible. Robert Brandom suggests
    </textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e119 e119"><para class="po-block e120 e120"><textual class="po-textual">
    When we try to understand the thought or discourse of others, the task can be divided initially into
    two parts: understanding what they are thinking or talking about and understanding what they are
    thinking or saying about it. My primary aim here is to present a view of the relation between what
    is </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e121 e121" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">said</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e122 e122" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">thought</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> and what it is
    said or thought </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e123 e123" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">about</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. The former is the propositional dimension of
    thought and talk, and the latter is its </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e124 e124" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">representational</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> dimension.
    The question I address is why any state or utterance that has propositional content also should be
    understood as having representational content. (For this is so much as to be a question, it must be
    possible to characterize propositional content in nonrepresentational terms.)
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e125 e125"><textual class="po-textual">The answer I defend is that the representational dimension of propositional contents should be
    understood in terms of their </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e126 e126" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">social</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> articulation – how a
    propositionally contentful belief or claim can have a different significance from the perspective of
    the individual or claimer, on the one hand, than it does from the perspective of one who attributes
    that belief or claim to the individual, on the other. The context within which concern with what is
    thought and talked </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e127 e127" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">about</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> arises is the assessment of how the judgments
    of one individual can serve as reasons for another. The representational content of claims and the
    beliefs they express reflect the social dimension of the game of giving and asking for reasons.
    </textual><xref class="po-milestone e128 e128" linkend="Brandom"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e129 e129"><textual class="po-textual">
    A key proposition here is that the entire enterprise of shared representation is a form of
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e130 e130" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">social agreement</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, an instance of human communication, not an expression
    of a universal truth, and that the value of a proposition is not its truth but its
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e131 e131" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">utility</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. This viewpoint is not necessarily shared by a unanimity of
    philosophers but Brandom's argument does reflect a distinct break from analytic philosophy within the
    ranks of contemporary philosophers following the work of Ludwig Wittgenstein, whose
    </textual><citation class="po-atom e132 e132"><textual class="po-textual">Philosophical Investigations (Philosophische Untersuchungen)</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">
    was published in 1953, denouncing the “dogma” in the earlier analytic philosophy of his
    </textual><citation class="po-atom e133 e133"><textual class="po-textual">Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">. More generally, this line of pragmatists and
    “neo-pragmatists” influenced by Wittgenstein includes John Dewey, Wilfred Sellars, Richard Rorty,
    Jürgen Habermas, and Hilary Putnam, among others.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e134 e134"><title class="po-block e135 e135"><textual class="po-textual">Informality</textual></title><blockquote class="po-container e136 e136"><para class="po-block e137 e137"><textual class="po-textual">
    Words are not just wind. Words have something to say. But what if what they have to say is not
    fixed, then do they really say something? Or do they say nothing? People suppose that words are
    different from the peeps of baby birds, but is there a difference, or isn't there?
    </textual></para><attribution class="po-block e138 e138"><textual class="po-textual">Chuang Tzu, ~320 B.C.E (Burton Watson, trans.)</textual></attribution></blockquote><para class="po-block e139 e139"><textual class="po-textual">
    It should be noted that as described above, we could hardly design a system that relied on formal logic.
    The design is therefore distinctly </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e140 e140" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">informal</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, i.e., it is not backed by
    a formal model conforming to any foundationalist or otherwise representational logic. Its organizational
    structure is instead considered as a form of human communication — a classification system with no
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e141 e141" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">a priori</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> terms — where the meaning of a term is identified entirely
    with its usage, akin to Inferential Role Semantics </textual><xref class="po-milestone e142 e142" linkend="IRS"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">.
    In this regard the system should not be considered formal in any sense; it is by definition a system
    that supports an </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e143 e143" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">informal ontology</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e144 e144"><textual class="po-textual">
    That said, the use of terms that in other contexts might denote an expression of logic (e.g.,
    “type”, “class”, “subclass”, etc.) should not be considered as bridging any
    logical chasm — they are just convenient natural language terms; no claims are made to Platonic,
    universal terms or self-justifying beliefs.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e145 e145"><textual class="po-textual">
    This is epistemologically a delicate balancing act. In what is known as
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e146 e146" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">deductive-nomological</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> theory, the causality of declarative sentences is
    replaced by what are termed </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e147 e147" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">constant regularities</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, where rather than say that
    </textual><code class="po-atom e148 e148"><textual class="po-textual">A</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e149 e149" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">causes</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> </textual><code class="po-atom e150 e150"><textual class="po-textual">B</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> we only state that
    </textual><code class="po-atom e151 e151"><textual class="po-textual">A</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> is </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e152 e152" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">regularly followed</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> by </textual><code class="po-atom e153 e153"><textual class="po-textual">B</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">. As Manuel DeLanda
    notes, </textual><quote class="po-inline e154 e154"><textual class="po-textual">it is only theory-obsessed philosophies that can afford to forget about causal connections
    and concentrate exclusively on logical relations.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> </textual><xref class="po-milestone e155 e155" linkend="DeLanda"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">
    We need to be clear that this is not an attempt to subordinate what might otherwise be considered statements
    of causality or truth claims behind linguistic statements, rather to claim that this is
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e156 e156" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">all</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> they entail – the interpretation (and thus error-checking) of the
    system is entirely in human hands.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e157 e157"><textual class="po-textual">
    It could be argued that all computer-based ontological systems such as the SW fall under this same set of
    constraints; a further discussion is out of scope for this paper. Suffice it to say that I consider the flaws
    in putatively formal systems due to epistemological issues as so profound as to demonstrably render them
    useless, or worse, useful (and therefore dangerous). It is much safer to design a system that is by design
    an informal toy and is delivered with a healthy disclaimer of having no truth conditional claims, again, as
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e158 e158" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">merely</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> to facilitate expressions of human communication.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e159 e159"><textual class="po-textual">
    One of the central tenets of the philosophical investigation of the past century is an understanding of the
    failure of logic to describe the world
    </textual><footnote class="po-popup e160 e160" xml:id="fn03"><para class="po-block e161 e161"><textual class="po-textual">
      To be fair to the SW folks, these charges are hardly new, and reflect the same issues present over three
      decades ago with the similar academic flourish of “artificial intelligence”, which assuredly
      after all these years still deserves quote marks.
      </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">, and that the role of philosophy is not to provide a framework (logical
    or otherwise) for understanding the world but, as someone like John Dewey or Jürgen Habermas might advocate,
    the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e162 e162" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">therapeutic</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> tools to improve it. This has had a profound effect on the
    nature of epistemological inquiry, indeed, some to suggest that it, like God, has died. But whether or not
    epistemology has died, it's perhaps time to pay a bit more attention to it even as it wriggles on the ground.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e163 e163"><title class="po-block e164 e164"><textual class="po-textual">Semantic Wikis</textual></title><para class="po-block e165 e165"><textual class="po-textual">
    There exist a growing number of “structured” and “semantic” wiki projects, many basing
    their structure on category and/or typed links, others incorporating formal ontology (e.g., RDF or OWL)
    features directly into the wiki. Some, like Wikipedia's </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e166 e166" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Semantic MediaWiki</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual><xref class="po-milestone e167 e167" linkend="SMW"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, use “semantic annotations” to characterize content
    according to an implicit or explicit vocabulary of terms.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e168 e168"><textual class="po-textual">
    In many cases these “semantic wikis” may provide a logical framework but often no classification scheme
    whatsoever, so we may have </textual><code class="po-atom e169 e169"><textual class="po-textual">IsSubclassOf</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> but nothing to subclass. It's a wiki categorization
    scheme on steroids, i.e., this is categorization, not classification. There are a number of difficulties with
    this approach, including the complexity of the augmented wiki syntax; weak or absent metadata; a lack of
    user-friendly schema documentation; the requirement of user expertise; lack of support for synonymous, homographic
    and polysemous (multireferential) terms, and other limitations in the available classification schemes (where they
    exist at all). Categorization terms or annotations are themselves often ungrounded, undefined, or when they are,
    they force users into a predefined schema, often defined in a formal logic not otherwise followed by, related or
    appropriate to the user-created structure, such as using set-theoretic language to describe the genealogical
    relationships.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e170 e170"><textual class="po-textual">
    This is in addition to the more profound problems of: linguistic/grammatical ambiguity (e.g., homographs,
    polysemes, unconnected synonymous terms); lack of context (e.g., temporal, spatial, cultural, individual
    use of language); ill-, undefined, or misspelled terms; ill- or undefined subject identity; the recursive
    requirement for a core of </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e171 e171" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">a priori </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">terms based on closed-world, monotonic
    reasoning, or other epistemological and ontological errors. Many if not most of these problems are
    insurmountable unless one forces users to understand and follow proscriptive rules, lives in ignorance or denial,
    or throws one's hands up declaring defeat.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e172 e172"><title class="po-block e173 e173"><textual class="po-textual">The Wrong Solution to the Wrong Problem</textual></title><blockquote class="po-container e174 e174"><para class="po-block e175 e175"><textual class="po-textual">When you have an effective enough technology so that you can really act upon your epistemological
    errors and can create havoc in the world in which you live, then the error is lethal.</textual></para><attribution class="po-block e176 e176"><textual class="po-textual">Gregory Bateson, Pathologies of Epistemology, Ibid.</textual></attribution></blockquote><para class="po-block e177 e177"><textual class="po-textual">
    These ambitious projects are typically “knowledge modeling” tools and are
    not a suitable fit for use by anyone except those whose expertise and expectations comes
    from the world of artificial intelligence,  knowledge representation, expert systems and
    the like, people who already understand and/or at least accept terms and technologies like
    RDFS, OWL, XSDT, SPARQL, and GRDDL.
    Even for those who putatively do, how many truly understand the ontological commitments
    they are making? Given that the entire RDF-based world of the SW is predicated on a
    principle of </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e178 e178" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">entailment</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, defined by Pat Hayes in
    </textual><citation class="po-atom e179 e179"><textual class="po-textual">RDF Semantics</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual"> as
    </textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e180 e180"><para class="po-block e181 e181"><textual class="po-textual">
    the key idea which connects model-theoretic semantics to real-world applications. […] Through the
    notions of satisfaction, entailment and validity, formal semantics gives a rigorous definition to a notion
    of "meaning" that can be related directly to computable methods of determining whether or not
    meaning is preserved by some transformation on a representation of knowledge. (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e182 e182" linkend="RDFSemantics"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, §2)
    </textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e183 e183"><textual class="po-textual">
    Should we expect the layperson to understand and accept this? Pat is trying to be
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e184 e184" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">helpful</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> when he writes:
    </textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e185 e185"><para class="po-block e186 e186"><textual class="po-textual">
    Readers who are familiar with conventional logical semantics may find it useful to think of RDF as a
    version of existential binary relational logic in which relations are first-class entities in the
    universe of quantification. Such a logic can be obtained by encoding the relational atom </textual><code class="po-atom e187 e187"><textual class="po-textual">R(a,b)</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
    into a conventional logical syntax, using a notional three-place relation </textual><code class="po-atom e188 e188"><textual class="po-textual">Triple(a,R,b)</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">;
    the basic semantics described here can be reconstructed from this intuition by defining the extension
    of </textual><code class="po-atom e189 e189"><textual class="po-textual">y</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> as the set </textual><code class="po-atom e190 e190"><textual class="po-textual">{&lt;x,z&gt; : Triple(x,y,z)}</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and noting that this would be
    precisely the denotation of </textual><code class="po-atom e191 e191"><textual class="po-textual">R</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> in the conventional Tarskian model theory of the original
    form </textual><code class="po-atom e192 e192"><textual class="po-textual">R(a,b)</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> of the relational atom.
    (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e193 e193" linkend="RDFSemantics"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, §1.1)</textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e194 e194"><textual class="po-textual">
    If we build systems for use by the public with the knowledge that those systems seldom define or follow
    a formal model theory</textual><footnote class="po-popup e195 e195" xml:id="fn04"><para class="po-block e196 e196"><textual class="po-textual">
      It seems that few researchers and/or developers understand </textual><citation class="po-atom e197 e197"><textual class="po-textual">RDF Semantics</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual"> much less
      follow it in practice, given that the majority of projects I've reviewed bear little relation to the RDF
      model theory, either in definition or stated references. Indeed, many seem to be in direct conflict with
      one or more RDF axioms or have extended it in ways contradictory to the model theory (e.g., reference to
      non-FOL logics, non-monotonicity). I've long thought that the buzz over RDF is simply a misplaced
      enthusiasm for basic graph theory.
      </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">,
    and knowing that the average user will hardly pay attention to this, much less
    understand it, can we be said to be acting responsibly as designers and engineers?
    </textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e198 e198"><para class="po-block e199 e199"><textual class="po-textual">
    First, it's not the Web that is monotonic (whatever that would mean) but the reasoning from
    Web resources that must be monotonic. […] Nonmonotonic reasoning is therefore inherently
    unsafe on the Web. In fact, nonmonotonic reasoning is inherently unsafe anywhere, which is
    why all classical reasoning is monotonic; this isn't anything particularly new. But the
    open-ended assumption that seems to underlie much thinking about reasoning on the semantic
    web makes the issue a little more acute than it often is in many of the situations where
    logic has been put to use in computer science.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e200 e200"><textual class="po-textual">
    For example, if you are reasoning with a particular database of information, it is often
    assumed that the dbase is complete, in the sense that if some item is missing, then it is
    assumed to be false […]. But open-ended domains are not like this, and it is very dangerous
    to rely on this kind of reasoning when one has no license to assume that the world is closed
    in the appropriate way. If there were ever an open-ended domain it is surely the semantic web. […]
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e201 e201"><textual class="po-textual">
    The global advantages of monotonicity should not be casually tossed aside, but at the same
    time the computational advantages of nonmonotonic reasoning modes is hard to deny, and they are
    widely used in the current state of the art. We need ways for them to co-exist smoothly.
    </textual><xref class="po-milestone e202 e202" linkend="Hayes2001"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e203 e203"><textual class="po-textual">
    John McCarthy and Pat Hayes were publishing papers on the situation calculus while Richard
    Nixon was president of the US </textual><xref class="po-milestone e204 e204" linkend="McCHay69"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">,
    and it's not that there hasn't been significant research in knowledge representation
    in the decades since. The frame problem and calculus accounts for time, concurrency, processes,
    uncertainty, and decision theory within the situation calculus provide an “embarrassing
    richness” of proposed solutions (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e205 e205" linkend="Reiter2001"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, 44-46; 149; 283; 335);
    there has been halting but steady progress in common sense ontologies, including the open source
    release of the Cyc ontology and associated tools as OpenCyc </textual><xref class="po-milestone e206 e206" linkend="OpenCyc"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">;
    and there is a lively and ongoing bi-yearly conference schedule on context
    </textual><xref class="po-milestone e207 e207" linkend="Context07"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">.

    After all, NASA has a couple of semi-autonomous robots very successfully roaming around Mars.
    Still, almost nothing has been done to breach the epistemological divide between knowledge
    representation theory and the real world of language and human culture, and contemporary research
    in related and relevant disciplines such as computational linguistics, narratology and philosophical
    inquiry hardly seems to be on SW researchers' radar. Much of the work has been focused on
    syntax and schema development.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e208 e208"><textual class="po-textual">
    One approach might be to use these sophisticated tools without fully understanding them, as
    Tim Berners-Lee writes that </textual><quote class="po-inline e209 e209"><textual class="po-textual">Semantic Web researchers […] accept that paradoxes and unanswerable
    questions are a price that must be paid to achieve versatility</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual><xref class="po-milestone e210 e210" linkend="BernersLee2001"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">.
    The problem here is not so much the possibility of paradox, it is the premise that the Web and
    its users can be made to behave according to rules of entailment rigid enough to produce
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e211 e211" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">satisfactory</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> results. If money, health, safety, or security
    are involved this hardly seems responsible.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e212 e212"><textual class="po-textual">
    Another approach might be to chill out, not take life (in particular, machine reasoning and
    computer-based ontologies) so seriously, or perhaps to stop using formal logic to describe the
    informal world and go elsewhere for a solution to the problem of organizing information.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e213 e213"><title class="po-block e214 e214"><textual class="po-textual">Librarians are Sexy</textual></title><para class="po-block e215 e215"><textual class="po-textual">
    In addition to not paying much if any attention to epistemology, the SW folks at the W3C
    don't seem to have paid much attention to the demonstrable success of metadata and
    classification schemes within the field of library science. Now, not all the problems the
    SW is trying to address are related to information organization (e.g., “intelligent”
    agents, military surveillance) but it does seem telling that library science has been so
    summarily ignored. It's perhaps not as sexy as AI, but is demonstrably a lot more
    important in this age of </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e216 e216" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">infoglut</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">:  we need information
    organization a lot more than we need robotic butlers, even if we did have
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e217 e217" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">complete trust</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> in their ability to make important
    decisions for us.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e218 e218"><textual class="po-textual">
    Despite the close ties between the W3C and the Online Computer Library Center (OCLC) and
    its Dublin Core metadata project, a recent search of the over 115,000 pages on the W3C Web
    site for the word “librarian” returns only 59 hits, and only 324 for
    “digital library”</textual><footnote class="po-popup e219 e219" xml:id="fn05"><para class="po-block e220 e220"><textual class="po-textual">accessed 21 April 2008</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">. So perhaps it's not too surprising that a site search
    for an important text on information organization published by the MIT Press – MIT
    is the founding organization of the W3C – produces no hits. Not a one.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e221 e221"><textual class="po-textual">
    For those not acquainted with Elaine Svenonius' book
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e222 e222" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">The Intellectual Foundation of Information Organization</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual><xref class="po-milestone e223 e223" linkend="Svenonius2000"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">,
    they might be surprised to find lucidly stated solutions to many of the thorny
    “semantic” problems of information systems, vocabulary and metadata design, as
    well as other issues germane to the SW. This is not simply theory but a description of
    demonstrably functional approaches to information organization that are current practice
    within the library world. We'll revisit this later; suffice it to say that Svenonius'
    book has been highly informative in the design of this project.
    </textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e224 e224"><title class="po-block e225 e225"><textual class="po-textual">Background</textual></title><para class="po-block e226 e226"><textual class="po-textual">
    This section describes the goals, history and requirements of the
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e227 e227"><textual class="po-textual">Ceryle Project</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, and the requirements that led to its design and
    implementation of the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e228 e228"><textual class="po-textual">Assertion Framework</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.
    </textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e229 e229"><title class="po-block e230 e230"><textual class="po-textual">The Ceryle Project </textual></title><para class="po-block e231 e231"><textual class="po-textual">
    The original intent of the Ceryle Project – now in development for over seven years, admittedly a bit
    of a kitchen sink – was to develop a software application to organize notes, planning documents,
    bibliographic references and other research materials, a document management system that permitted user
    creation and management of its own classification system, a bounded (but only partly-controlled)
    vocabulary of terms and relations between those terms, where each term must be defined, and all relations typed,
    again by a defined term.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e232 e232"><textual class="po-textual">
    This was simply the next in a long line of attempts at organizing the matériel for a work of historical
    fiction that had overflowed dozens of paper notebooks since the early 1990s. Transcribing those notes to a
    computer hadn't solved the problem, as there were still neither any organizational principles nor tools; I
    found myself spending almost as much time in wading through the morass as I did in research and writing (and as
    a writer I'm an </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e233 e233" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">expert</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> procrastinator).
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e234 e234"><textual class="po-textual">
    After my involvement with the XML Topic Map 1.0 (XTM) specification, the project was also a means of exploring
    how XTM and other XML markup might be merged with various types of library classification systems in supporting
    such a software application.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e235 e235"><textual class="po-textual">
    The Ceryle Project began as a content management system (CMS) marrying a text editor, an embedded XML database,
    search engine, various categorization and classification features, and a graph visualization engine. Originally,
    Ceryle was a standalone UI application, but after a few years an embedded web server and wiki were added –
    largely to provide a local rich text editing environment as an alternative to the Java Swing UI. It now resembles
    a digital library application with a relatively sophisticated user interface as well as a web interface and
    nascent RESTful web services.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e236 e236"><title class="po-block e237 e237"><textual class="po-textual">Māori Subject Headings &amp; the Iwi Hapū List</textual></title><para class="po-block e238 e238"><textual class="po-textual">
    The National Library of New Zealand has been a sponsor in the development of two projects that use a thesaurus
    database to organize Māori-related cultural materials:
      </textual><figure class="po-container e239 e239" xml:id="fig01"><title class="po-block e240 e240"><textual class="po-textual">Ngā Ūpoko Tukutuku structure</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e241 e241"><imageobject class="po-container e242 e242"><imagedata class="po-meta e243 e243" fileref="../../../vol1/graphics/Altheim01/Altheim01-001.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></para><variablelist class="po-table e244 e244"><varlistentry class="po-record e245 e245"><term class="po-block e246 e246"><emphasis class="po-inline e247 e247" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Ngā Ūpoko Tukutuku / Māori Subject Headings (MSH)</textual></emphasis></term><listitem class="po-container e248 e248"><para class="po-block e249 e249"><textual class="po-textual">
        expresses a set of library subject headings in te reo Māori, with mappings to their English subject
        heading equivalents. Documentation (scope notes) and relations between terms are expressed in both languages.
        </textual></para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry class="po-record e250 e250"><term class="po-block e251 e251"><emphasis class="po-inline e252 e252" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Iwi Hapū Names List (IHL)</textual></emphasis></term><listitem class="po-container e253 e253"><para class="po-block e254 e254"><textual class="po-textual">
        expresses the structure of Māori </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e255 e255" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">whakapapa</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (genealogy) from
        </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e256 e256" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">waka</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (canoe) to </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e257 e257" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">whakaminenga</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (confederation)
        to </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e258 e258" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">iwi</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (tribe) to </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e259 e259" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">hapū</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (sub-tribe
        or family group)</textual><footnote class="po-popup e260 e260" xml:id="fn06"><para class="po-block e261 e261"><textual class="po-textual">
          It does not currently include the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e262 e262" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">whānau</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (family unit), but in
          the future a public version of the site may permit individuals to create pages for their own whānau.
          ‘wh’ in te reo Māori is pronounced as an ‘f’, e.g., whānau is
          pronounced “faah′-na-u”.
          </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">.
        </textual></para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist><para class="po-block e263 e263"><textual class="po-textual">These databases use the standardized thesaurus structure </textual><xref class="po-milestone e264 e264" linkend="Z3919"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> to represent existing relationships between records (see Domain Ontology below
    for details).</textual></para><figure class="po-container e265 e265" xml:id="fig02"><title class="po-block e266 e266"><textual class="po-textual">Iwi Hapū List structure</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e267 e267"><imageobject class="po-container e268 e268"><imagedata class="po-meta e269 e269" fileref="../../../vol1/graphics/Altheim01/Altheim01-002.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e270 e270"><textual class="po-textual">
    The source materials exhibited hierarchical, mereological, collection, and other relation types, which were shoehorned
    into the existing thesaurus relationships. For example, the reflexive </textual><code class="po-atom e271 e271"><textual class="po-textual">HasIwiOf</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><code class="po-atom e272 e272"><textual class="po-textual">IsIwiOf</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
    relations are subclasses of the Z39.19 </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e273 e273" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Broader Term</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> and
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e274 e274" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Narrower Term</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> relations, respectively.  The use of thesaurus software as a means of
    library classification system development is not uncommon (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e275 e275" linkend="Turner"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, 111-117).
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e276 e276"><textual class="po-textual">
    One benefit of the project is that it has permitted these two databases to be merged into one system while still
    maintaining their respective scopes. We were lucky in that of the thousands of records there were only two name clashes.
    Had there been a substantial number we may have had to resort to a Wikipedia-like name disambiguation strategy.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e277 e277"><title class="po-block e278 e278"><textual class="po-textual">Requirements</textual></title><para class="po-block e279 e279"><textual class="po-textual">
    In a nutshell, the basic requirements of the Assertion Framework were to provide a wiki environment that permitted
    expression of an underlying structure using a relatively simple wiki-like syntax. In more detail, the system should:
    </textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e280 e280"><listitem class="po-container e281 e281"><para class="po-block e282 e282"><textual class="po-textual">presume no underlying model; that the design be able to declare its semantics over clear and
                uncluttered ground</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e283 e283"><para class="po-block e284 e284"><textual class="po-textual">avoid the problems of the simplistic wiki category links but neither require users to learn a
                classification scheme, a set of rules for its use, nor any arcane, complicated syntax — the
                system was to be as "wiki-like" as possible. Any augmentation to wiki functionality
                should also be “wiki-like” and use a syntax that is easy to learn and understand, an
                informal system usable by untrained, lay people, not just “knowledge engineers”
          </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e285 e285"><para class="po-block e286 e286"><textual class="po-textual">permit structuring of the wiki based on explicit typed links (relations) between pages (with page
                names as terms), expressing a graph structure implemented as a user-editable, REST-conforming Web
                service </textual><xref class="po-milestone e287 e287" linkend="REST"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, where each URL could be used as a subject identifier
          </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e288 e288"><para class="po-block e289 e289"><textual class="po-textual">permit the user-modifiable structure to be based on an underlying, unmodifiable
                </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e290 e290" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">endorsed</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> structure, protecting the endorsed structure while
                permitting view differentiation of the endorsed- from the user-edited structure. This is not to
                advocate a set of truths but permit an expression and differentiation of a
                </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e291 e291" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">corporate</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e292 e292" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">public</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> opinion.
          </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e293 e293"><para class="po-block e294 e294"><textual class="po-textual">substantial parts of the semantics (particularly domain-specific predicates) should be
                community-definable
          </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e295 e295"><para class="po-block e296 e296"><textual class="po-textual">all terms in the vocabulary must be defined (and those definitions readily accessible)</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e297 e297"><para class="po-block e298 e298"><textual class="po-textual">expose the structure for improved user navigation</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e299 e299"><para class="po-block e300 e300"><textual class="po-textual">the underlying ontology (structure) must be exposed and shareable across multiple wikis, and use a
                standardized notation (in this case, XTM 1.0 was chosen since the wiki structure is maintained as a
                Topic Map)
          </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e301 e301"><para class="po-block e302 e302"><textual class="po-textual">the overall system must be capable of being archived in such a way as to permit reconstruction of any
                given moment in its history (so as to be able to reconstruct the context of a given assertion), likewise
                users must be able to view snapshots of a set of wiki pages at any given point in the wiki's history
          </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e303 e303"><para class="po-block e304 e304"><textual class="po-textual">be based on modifiable, popular (i.e., relatively stable) open source software</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e305 e305"><title class="po-block e306 e306"><textual class="po-textual">Design</textual></title><para class="po-block e307 e307"><textual class="po-textual">
    This section describes the design of an </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e308 e308" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Assertion Framework</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, a software library
    that provides capabilities for categorizing, classifying and organizing a repository or corpus of documents; how
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e309 e309" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">classification</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e310 e310" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">ontology</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> are defined and used
    in the project; the abstractions used in creating </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e311 e311" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">assertions</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> and finally how these
    assertions fit together to create an </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e312 e312" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">informal ontology</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e313 e313"><textual class="po-textual">The following section then describes the implementation of this design.</textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e314 e314"><title class="po-block e315 e315"><textual class="po-textual">Classification vs. Ontology</textual></title><para class="po-block e316 e316"><textual class="po-textual">
    We have a readily available solution for an organizational structure that avoids the epistemological conundrums of
    computer-based ontologies by appealing to the functional (i.e., functionalist) approach of classification systems
    within library science.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e317 e317"><textual class="po-textual">
    Svenonius describes a </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e318 e318" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">subject language</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> as an artificial language that is used to
    depict what a document is </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e319 e319" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">about</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. It is the language providing the terms used to
    compose a classification scheme. The chapter </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e320 e320" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Subject Languages: Referential and Relational
    Semantics</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e321 e321" linkend="Svenonius2000"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, 147-171) begins:
    </textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e322 e322"><para class="po-block e323 e323"><textual class="po-textual">
    This chapter looks at the semantic treatment needed to transform a natural language into a
    subject language. […] a subject language is based on a natural language but differs from
    it primarily in the semantic structures it uses to normalize vocabulary by setting up a
    one-to-one relationship between terms and their referents. The referential semantics of a
    subject language deals with the generalized homonym problem. It consists of methods for
    restricting term referents so that any given term has one and only one meaning. The relational
    semantics of a subject language deals with the generalized synonym problem and consists of
    methods for linking terms within similar or related meanings.
    </textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e324 e324"><textual class="po-textual">
    If we consider each page on a wiki as the community's “canonical” information about a
    given subject, with its unique page title serving as a descriptor of that subject, the set of page
    titles taken as a whole comprises the subject language of the wiki. The wiki page name and its associated
    URL act as unambiguous subject identifiers; each use of a term is also a link to its reference documentation.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e325 e325"><textual class="po-textual">
    The terms in a subject language differ referentially from those in ontology or in natural language in that
    they do not refer to entities or concepts in the real world but to </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e326 e326" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">subjects</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.
    The extensional meaning of a term in a subject language does not refer to the class of all entities denoted by
    the term but to the class of documents that the term denotes. From an inferential role semantics point of view,
    the evolutionary development of a classification structure based on user design and behavior would (assuming
    active usage) tend towards validating those terms and relations between terms within the classification system
    that are frequently traversed, with infrequently or unused assertional links potentially deprecated or at least
    called into question. This warrants further investigation.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e327 e327"><title class="po-block e328 e328"><textual class="po-textual">Homographs, Polysemes and Other Multireferential Words</textual></title><para class="po-block e329 e329"><textual class="po-textual">
    One of the problems in classification schemes is due to the multireferentiality of words. Briefly,
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e330 e330" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">homographs</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> are words that are spelled the same but have different meanings.
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e331 e331" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Polysemes</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> are words that are spelled the same, have different meanings, but
    their meanings are related. These constitute only two of a variety of what are called
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e332 e332" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">multireferential</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> words. Even words that aren't usually considered
    multireferential may be interpreted with subtly different meanings when used in different contexts, domains of
    discourse, in different grammatical constructions, or by different people or groups of people (e.g., children
    vs. adults).
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e333 e333"><textual class="po-textual">
    Library classification systems have dealt with the issue of multireferential terms in various ways. Svenonius
    notes that this can be accomplished either semantically, via domain specification, qualifiers and/or annotations,
    or syntactically (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e334 e334" linkend="Svenonius2000"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, 148-155).
    The latter, called </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e335 e335" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">nonsemantic disambiguation,</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> is a natural solution for wikis
    where the use of camel-cased combinatory terms as wiki page names is the norm.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e336 e336"><textual class="po-textual">
    Over the years wiki communities have discussed at length and less frequently experimented with the use of namespaces,
    similar to the use of colonized tokens in XML. There are a variety of problems with this, such as the incompatibility
    between various characters as delimiters and URLs, but even with a functional syntax the biggest deterrent is likely
    to be the additional complexity for the user.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e337 e337"><title class="po-block e338 e338"><textual class="po-textual">Faceted Classification</textual></title><para class="po-block e339 e339"><textual class="po-textual">
    Classification methodologies used in modern libraries have been profoundly influenced by S.R. Ranganathan's
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e340 e340" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Colon Classification</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> system </textual><xref class="po-milestone e341 e341" linkend="ISKOI"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">,
    developed in the 1930's. While Ranganathan's system</textual><footnote class="po-popup e342 e342" xml:id="fn07"><para class="po-block e343 e343"><textual class="po-textual">
      Ranganathan's scheme included five “fundamental” facets: Personality, Matter, Energy, Space
      and Time. Contemporary FC research tends to ignore this archaism but retains the methodology.
      </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
    did not itself survive, it was subsequently a profound influence on other classification schemes, including both
    Dewey Decimal and US Library of Congress (LoC), and led to the development of
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e344 e344" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Faceted Classification</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (FC), where the predominant terms of a given domain of
    knowledge are sorted into homogeneous, mutually exclusive conceptual categories or
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e345 e345" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">facets</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, each derived from the parent domain by a single characteristic. FC differs
    from a traditional enumerated scheme in that “it does not assign fixed slots to subjects in sequence, using
    instead clearly defined, mutually exclusive, and collectively exhaustive aspects, properties or characteristics of a
    class or given subject.” </textual><xref class="po-milestone e346 e346" linkend="Wynar"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e347 e347"><textual class="po-textual">
    As an example, Gregory Bateson's seminal work </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e348 e348" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Steps to an Ecology of Mind</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> contains
    the US Library of Congress Cataloging-in-Publication (CIP) data on its copyright page, used by libraries in cataloging
    the book. This includes:
    </textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e349 e349"><para class="po-block e350 e350"><textual class="po-textual">
    1. Anthropology, Cultural – Collected works. 2. Knowledge, Theory of – Collected works.
    3. Psychiatry – Collected works. 4. Evolution – Collected works. I. Title. II. Series.
    [DNLM: 1. Anthropology, Cultural – collected works. 2. Ecology – collected works.
    3. Evolution – collected works. 4. Schizophrenic Psychology – collected works.
    5. Thinking – collected works. GN 6 B329s 1972a].
    </textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e351 e351"><textual class="po-textual">
    Anyone interested in this book has a good chance of locating it by subject amongst the plenitude
    found in a library card catalog, even if they cannot remember the title or author. But it is
    rather unfortunate that the categories listed for </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e352 e352" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Steps to an Ecology of Mind</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    don't include cybernetics, cognitive science, and systems theory, though Bateson's ideas have been
    profoundly influential in the foundation of these sciences. We can perhaps forgive the librarians who classified
    a book that has broken so many boundaries. All classification schemes have their limitations and failings,
    including the very human problem of an inability to see into the future. The flexibility of allowing classifications
    to evolve without breaking is extremely important, especially during the early stages, where categories are still
    relatively unformed. Notably, this problem plagued expert systems implementations, where later changes to root level
    concepts were very difficult to accomplish (e.g., a change of logical foundations, such as from first order to modal
    logic).
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e353 e353"><textual class="po-textual">
    Many of the refinements in the system have been in the approach to defining the interrelationships between terms.
    There are two fundamental Faceted Classification relationship types: semantic and syntactic.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e354 e354"><textual class="po-textual">
    A </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e355 e355" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">semantic</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> relationship is independent of context and is by definition a permanent
    relationship, arising from the subjects involved. Semantic relationships are further divided into three types:
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e356 e356" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">equivalence</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> relationships, where terms are synonyms (and would be cross-referenced
    under the same category); two types of </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e357 e357" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">hierarchical</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> relationships,
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e358 e358" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">superclass-subclass</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e359 e359" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">mereological</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (whole-part);
    and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e360 e360" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">affinitive/associative</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> relationships, which are domain-specific relationships
    such as cause and effect, coordination, sequence, genetic, etc.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e361 e361"><textual class="po-textual">
    A </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e362 e362" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">syntactic</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> relationship is an </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e363 e363" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">ad hoc</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> relationship
    denoting otherwise unrelated concepts brought together as a composite subject in a specific context. This is the
    equivalent of how terms would appear together in a common sentence. It operates similarly to how we use keyword
    searches on the Web, such as “biblical archaeology”, “poetry by 12th century Japanese authors”,
    or “medieval weapon manufacture”. This approach is at the heart of the resource organization approach taken
    by most wikis in their use of camel-cased wiki page names. In the Assertion Framework we didn't set out to avoid
    the use of wiki page names as subject identifiers, but were looking to supplant the klunky use of category names by
    use of typed assertions between pages.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e364 e364"><textual class="po-textual">
    A highly recommended text on library classification schemes is </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e365 e365" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Essential Classification</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual><xref class="po-milestone e366 e366" linkend="Broughton"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, whose author is an active researcher in
    Faceted Classification.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e367 e367"><title class="po-block e368 e368"><textual class="po-textual">User Tagging or “Folksonomies”</textual></title><para class="po-block e369 e369"><textual class="po-textual">
    A </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e370 e370" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">user tag</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> permits the non-hierarchical assignment of a term or keyword to a
    resource. The syntax of user tagging in most social software sites (e.g., del.icio.us, Flickr) is a simple comma-
    or whitespace-delimited list of tokens. Whereas on these sites users are generally permitted to add tags to a
    resource at will (absent any validation or even spell-checking), in our case this would mean that many or most tags
    would remain undefined and outside the Assertion Framework.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e371 e371"><textual class="po-textual">
    Tags could be seen as keywords in a Dublin Core list of subjects and would in our implementation be therefore
    searchable, but we wanted tags to play a larger role than that of metadata given their current popularity.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e372 e372"><textual class="po-textual">
    While Faceted Classification permits synthetic classification, its facets are still usually derived from a controlled
    vocabulary. If each tag were represented by a wiki page, where each definition is discoverable, tags could then be seen
    as facets. The decision was therefore made to require each tag to be represented by a wiki page, even if this may be
    seen by some users as onerous. We don't yet have feedback that would permit us to evaluate how this may affect
    the willingness of people to tag resources.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e373 e373"><title class="po-block e374 e374"><textual class="po-textual">Assertions</textual></title><para class="po-block e375 e375"><textual class="po-textual">
    The basic graph design centers around a simple construct called an </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e376 e376" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Assertion</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, a
    form of simple declarative sentence using the Subject-Predicate-Object grammar common to natural
    language</textual><footnote class="po-popup e377 e377" xml:id="fn08"><para class="po-block e378 e378"><textual class="po-textual">This could also be localized for VSO or other grammars as necessary; the specific syntax is unimportant.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
    as well as other abstract syntaxes (e.g., RDF, where it is called a </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e379 e379" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">triple</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">).
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e380 e380"><textual class="po-textual">In this model each of the three components of the sentence is a Term:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e381 e381" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">Subject Predicate Object</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e382 e382"><textual class="po-textual">E.g., an Assertion stating that Gary Snyder is a poet might look like:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e383 e383" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">GarySnyder IsA Poet</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e384 e384"><textual class="po-textual">
    The Terms available for use in Assertions are not composed from a controlled vocabulary in the library sense, but
    given that the validation of a new Assertion uses the set of Terms dynamically derived from the extant wiki pages,
    the vocabulary may not be controlled but is at least nominally defined. Users may create new wiki pages as necessary
    to make available the Terms necessary to their Assertions.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e385 e385"><textual class="po-textual">
    The interpretation of an Assertion is similar (but not equivalent) to the definition in
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e386 e386" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">RDF Semantics</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">:
    </textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e387 e387"><para class="po-block e388 e388"><textual class="po-textual">The basic intuition of model-theoretic semantics is that asserting a sentence makes a claim
    about the world: it is another way of saying that the world is, in fact, so arranged as to be
    an interpretation which makes the sentence true. In other words, an assertion amounts to
    stating a constraint on the possible ways the world might be. (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e389 e389" linkend="RDFSemantics"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, §1.3)
    </textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e390 e390"><textual class="po-textual">
    Throwing out the assumption of a model theory and discarding any notion of a universal truth, we
    may more usefully consider an assertion in a socio-linguistic sense: a statement of belief made
    by a person about the world. Given that these Assertions are being made by many people in the
    collaborative environment of a wiki, this is quite a </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e391 e391" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">reasonable</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    stance. In other words, we may infer – based on the stated beliefs of the community –
    a statement of potentially equal believability.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e392 e392"><textual class="po-textual">
    The set of the wiki's extant Assertion triples forms a bipartite graph, where each pair of
    Subject and Object Terms are graph nodes linked by their respective Predicates. This bounded
    corpus of Assertions taken together is considered a form of </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e393 e393" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">informal
    ontology</textual></emphasis><footnote class="po-popup e394 e394" xml:id="fn09"><para class="po-block e395 e395"><textual class="po-textual">
      We will subsequently be using the term “ontology” in this context, i.e., without
      reference to any formalized model theory.
      </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e396 e396"><title class="po-block e397 e397"><textual class="po-textual">Core Predicates</textual></title><para class="po-block e398 e398"><textual class="po-textual">
    In simple terms, taxonomy is a restricted form of ontology, a hierarchy where all relations
    share a common ancestor type. Because our design uses hierarchical as well as other relation types
    it cannot be considered a proper taxonomy, but it does include a taxonomic “layer”.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e399 e399"><textual class="po-textual">
    Ontological hierarchies can be composed of a variety of formal relations, based on sets,
    classes, collections, etc. (depending on the underlying logic, derivation, and context of use).
    Because we are distinctly trying to avoid connoting formal (e.g., set theoretic) foundations as
    well as promote simple natural language terminology, the names of the predicates avoid formal titles
    but make reference to a formal, traditional relation type in their documentation.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e400 e400"><textual class="po-textual">
    There are three fundamental Predicates that compose the core of the ontology:
    </textual></para><variablelist class="po-table e401 e401"><varlistentry class="po-record e402 e402"><term class="po-block e403 e403"><textual class="po-textual">Kind Of</textual></term><listitem class="po-container e404 e404"><para class="po-block e405 e405"><textual class="po-textual">the superclass-subclass relation</textual></para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry class="po-record e406 e406"><term class="po-block e407 e407"><textual class="po-textual">Is A</textual></term><listitem class="po-container e408 e408"><para class="po-block e409 e409"><textual class="po-textual">the class-instance relation</textual></para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry class="po-record e410 e410"><term class="po-block e411 e411"><textual class="po-textual">Part Of</textual></term><listitem class="po-container e412 e412"><para class="po-block e413 e413"><textual class="po-textual">the mereological part-whole relation</textual></para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist><para class="po-block e414 e414"><textual class="po-textual">
    The "Kind Of" and "Part Of" assertions together form a hybrid hierarchy,
    with instances or individuals related via "Is A" Assertions</textual><footnote class="po-popup e415 e415" xml:id="fn10"><para class="po-block e416 e416"><textual class="po-textual">
      For brevity' sake, not all details are included here, e.g., the Terms defined for roles
      played in each relation type have not been included; other ontological structures have been
      simplified or omitted.
      </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e417 e417"><title class="po-block e418 e418"><textual class="po-textual">Upper Ontology</textual></title><figure class="po-container e419 e419" xml:id="fig03"><title class="po-block e420 e420"><textual class="po-textual">Core Ontology</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e421 e421"><imageobject class="po-container e422 e422"><imagedata class="po-meta e423 e423" fileref="../../../vol1/graphics/Altheim01/Altheim01-003.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e424 e424"><textual class="po-textual">
    As with many ontological models, all graph nodes are some descendant of a root Term
    called </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e425 e425" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Thing</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (“everything is a kind of thing”),
    such that the system is composed of a single connected graph. All Predicates are some
    descendant subclass of an </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e426 e426" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">ur</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">-Predicate called
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e427 e427" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Relation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. The core or base ontology is a very
    simple, as shown in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e428 e428" linkend="fig03"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e429 e429"><textual class="po-textual">
    Most Terms are related via a Kind Of (superclass-subclass) relation. The basic
    foundation of the ontology is primarily taxonomic, with some additions of mereological
    components.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e430 e430"><textual class="po-textual">Support for Faceted Classification is provided by the relation</textual></para><variablelist class="po-table e431 e431"><varlistentry class="po-record e432 e432"><term class="po-block e433 e433"><textual class="po-textual">Has Facet</textual></term><listitem class="po-container e434 e434"><para class="po-block e435 e435"><textual class="po-textual">the facet relation</textual></para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist><para class="po-block e436 e436"><textual class="po-textual">
    With the addition of various additional relations the “upper ontology”
    contains roughly 50 terms and 50 relations.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e437 e437"><title class="po-block e438 e438"><textual class="po-textual">Domain Ontology</textual></title><para class="po-block e439 e439"><textual class="po-textual">
    Domain ontologies using additional affinitive or associative relations are considered
    as “layers” on the Upper Ontology's taxonomical/mereological structure.
    Being domain-related, these are the most likely to be augmented and/or modified by
    users. Syntactic relationships are considered as the coming together of other relationship
    types, e.g., in constructing a character, a setting, an event, or a scene in a narrative
    ontology.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e440 e440"><textual class="po-textual">
    The project currently includes two domain ontologies:
    </textual></para><variablelist class="po-table e441 e441"><varlistentry class="po-record e442 e442"><term class="po-block e443 e443"><textual class="po-textual">Z39.19</textual></term><listitem class="po-container e444 e444"><para class="po-block e445 e445"><textual class="po-textual">
        includes the complete set of terms and relations as described by the Z39.19 standard.
        This includes complete role and relation templates for all Z39.19 predicates actually
        used by the system. All Z39.19 terms and relations are included as Terms even if
        currently unused.
        </textual></para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry class="po-record e446 e446"><term class="po-block e447 e447"><textual class="po-textual">Māori Subject Headings / Iwi Hapū Names List</textual></term><listitem class="po-container e448 e448"><para class="po-block e449 e449"><textual class="po-textual">
        this includes the set of terms and relations used in the Māori Subject Headings and
        Iwi Hapū List, with mappings to equivalent relations in Z39.19.
        </textual></para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist><para class="po-block e450 e450"><textual class="po-textual">
    Other domain ontologies developed for the Ceryle Project may be included as needed in the project.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e451 e451"><title class="po-block e452 e452"><textual class="po-textual">Relationship to Z39.19</textual></title><para class="po-block e453 e453"><textual class="po-textual">
    The ANSI/NISO standard Z39.19 </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e454 e454" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Guidelines for the Construction, Format, and
    Management of Monolingual Controlled Vocabularies (Z39.19 2005)</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> provides features for
    support of controlled vocabularies, thesaurus terminology and base relation types.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e455 e455"><textual class="po-textual">
    This is used in the context of the wiki using the following definitions (where Z39.19
    definitions are in </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e456 e456" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">bold</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">):
    </textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e457 e457"><listitem class="po-container e458 e458"><para class="po-block e459 e459"><textual class="po-textual">each wiki page is a precoordinated </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e460 e460" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">term</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> reifying a single </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e461 e461" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">concept</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> or subject</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e462 e462"><para class="po-block e463 e463"><textual class="po-textual">the wiki page name is considered the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e464 e464" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">subject heading</textual></emphasis></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e465 e465"><para class="po-block e466 e466"><textual class="po-textual">wiki Assertions are used rather than untyped links between pages to establish </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e467 e467" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">semantic relationships</textual></emphasis></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e468 e468"><para class="po-block e469 e469"><textual class="po-textual">the inherent predicate of each Z39.19 </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e470 e470" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">semantic relation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> is reified as a wiki page</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e471 e471"><para class="po-block e472 e472"><textual class="po-textual">the wiki is considered a </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e473 e473" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">controlled vocabulary</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> as dynamically bounded by gamut of wiki pages.
        </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e474 e474"><para class="po-block e475 e475"><textual class="po-textual">all domain-based predicates are likewise defined as wiki pages</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e476 e476"><textual class="po-textual">
    Z39.19 defines three types of semantic (as opposed to syntactic) relationships used in
    controlled vocabularies:  Equivalency (§8.2); Hierarchy (§8.3); and Association
    (§8.4).
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e477 e477"><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e478 e478" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Equivalency</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> relations include synonymy, near synonymy, and lexical variants. This is notably not
    an equivalency relation under any logic, i.e., it does not relate equivalent concepts or entities but
    equivalent </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e479 e479" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">terms</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Our ontology maps these to </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e480 e480" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Use</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e481 e481" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">UsedFor</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. (This does not map to the logical connective
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e482 e482" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Equivalent</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> relation found in our middle ontology, which is used only for
    logical relations.)</textual></para><para class="po-block e483 e483"><textual class="po-textual">
    Our project mirrors the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e484 e484" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Hierarchy</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> relations, though sadly the Z39.19 standard
    reflects a common error in knowledge representation texts of conflating IsA with a
    superclass-subclass relation. This results in Z39.19 using the same IsA name for
    the “Generic Relation” (ostensibly, superclass-subclass) and
    “Instance” (class-instance) relations. We provide the two Z39.19 generic
    relations as IsBroaderThan and IsNarrowerThan, with IsRelatedTo used when hierarchy
    is unknown or otherwise not implied.
    In our ontology we use </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e485 e485" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">IsA</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> for class-instance and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e486 e486" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">KindOf</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    for superclass-subclass, where the latter may be seen as a synonym for </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e487 e487" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">IsNarrowerThan</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.
    The mereological whole-part relation is in our ontology named </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e488 e488" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">PartOf</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.
    Note that we do not differentiate set theoretic from collection-based semantics;
    this is not a formal system.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e489 e489"><textual class="po-textual">
    Z39.19 defines eleven </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e490 e490" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Associative</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> relations (e.g., Cause / Effect, Process / Agent),
    and while they are included in the ontology and instantiated as wiki pages, they are
    not used in our source materials hence are not described here further, but again,
    these are considered as relations between vocabulary terms, not logical relations.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e491 e491"><title class="po-block e492 e492"><textual class="po-textual">Endorsement</textual></title><para class="po-block e493 e493"><textual class="po-textual">
    The concept of an </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e494 e494" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">endorsed set</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> means that some Terms and Predicates are
    protected from being removed or redefined by users, as they are considered part
    of the required semantics of the application. This was a requirement of the system,
    in that the set of terms and relations delivered to the public may be seen as a
    corporate endorsement of their definition or validity. Given that the public is to
    be permitted the ability to modify portions of this information there must be a
    way to either protect endorsed content or at least be able to differentiate the
    endorsed from unendorsed. This is done via </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e495 e495" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">scoping</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (in the Topic Map sense).
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e496 e496"><textual class="po-textual">
    User-created Assertions (i.e., those made via plugins on wiki pages) currently
    have no ability to express scope, so their scope in the resulting Topic Map is
    hardwired by the plugin itself.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e497 e497"><textual class="po-textual">
    If desired, administrators of the system may wish to develop a workflow-based
    endorsement process (policies and practices) whereby user-created terms and
    predicates can be migrated into the endorsed ontology.
    </textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e498 e498"><title class="po-block e499 e499"><textual class="po-textual">Implementation</textual></title><para class="po-block e500 e500"><textual class="po-textual">
    While the expression language and the functional implementation of the
    Assertion Framework is largely tied in this instance to its origins in the
    Ceryle Project and/or its current wiki implementation, in abstraction most
    elements of this design could be reused in non-wiki applications.
    </textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e501 e501"><title class="po-block e502 e502"><textual class="po-textual">A Software “Framework”</textual></title><para class="po-block e503 e503"><textual class="po-textual">
    One aspect of Ceryle that was clear early on was that in addition to supporting
    the stated functional requirements it also needed to serve as its own development
    laboratory. Over the years there have been a large number of experiments with
    features, software libraries, conversion tools, visualization capabilities, some
    of which have survived, though many only in backup archives. As a framework it has
    gradually matured and now includes user scripting and various extensibility features.
    The Assertion Framework described in this paper is a module added to the embedded
    wiki functioning within the Ceryle standalone application, but has also been installed
    as part of a generic JSPWiki distribution running on Apache Tomcat; in the latter case
    there are no dependencies on the standalone Ceryle application.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e504 e504"><title class="po-block e505 e505"><textual class="po-textual">Choice of Wiki Software</textual></title><para class="po-block e506 e506"><textual class="po-textual">
    There were two primary requirements that led to the addition of a wiki:  the ability
    to provide simple formatting markup in a non-WYSIWYG text editor; and to provide an online
    and/or collaborative editing environment that could function in either a standalone (local)
    or online environment.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e507 e507"><textual class="po-textual">
    The availability of software libraries, compatibility with the Ceryle application as a
    development environment, and my own previous experience made Java the programming language
    of choice.  An evaluation was made among the offerings of web servers and wiki software,
    based on features, ease of embedding, extensibility, stability, and the health of their
    respective communities and/or sponsors. Jetty</textual><footnote class="po-popup e508 e508" xml:id="fn11"><para class="po-block e509 e509"><textual class="po-textual">see </textual><link class="po-inline e510 e510" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.morgbay.org/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.mortbay.org/</textual></link></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
    was chosen as the embedded web server (there
    was little competition). No modifications to Jetty were needed apart from some configuration
    and embedding code. Following an evaluation of available open source wiki software applications,
    JSPWiki</textual><footnote class="po-popup e511 e511" xml:id="fn12"><para class="po-block e512 e512"><textual class="po-textual">see </textual><link class="po-inline e513 e513" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.jspwiki.org/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.jspwiki.org/</textual></link></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
    was chosen as the most versatile and extensible for our purposes. In the past year
    JSPWiki has been selected by the Apache Foundation as its wiki solution.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e514 e514"><title class="po-block e515 e515"><textual class="po-textual">Data Conversion</textual></title><para class="po-block e516 e516"><textual class="po-textual">
    The initial content for the present implementation was derived from the Māori Subject Headings
    and Iwi Hapū Names List thesaurus (Z39.19-compliant) databases and converted via Groovy scripts
    into interim XHTML documents, which were then converted into Linear Topic Map (LTM) source files
    to provide a backing structure for the wiki as well as generating an individual wiki page for
    each record.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e517 e517"><textual class="po-textual">
    Initially, the database export was only available as a plain text format. The MSH database software
    has been recently upgraded and now supports an XML export, so the Groovy script was updated to
    process the new format. This could have been accomplished via XSLT but the existing investment
    and rapid development of the scripting solution was considered important.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e518 e518"><title class="po-block e519 e519"><textual class="po-textual">WikiEvents and the WikiEventManager</textual></title><para class="po-block e520 e520"><textual class="po-textual">
    While JSPWiki was considered a good foundation, earlier versions of JSPWiki did not include any
    event handling code, so a general purpose WikiEvents API, a number of WikiEvent classes and a
    WikiEventManager (see Figure 4. WikiEventManager)
    were developed for this project. This permitted application-level events to be fired as wiki
    pages were created, edited, renamed, deleted, and displayed. This general purpose wiki events
    API and implementation are now part of the Apache JSPWiki distribution.
    </textual></para><figure class="po-container e521 e521"><title class="po-block e522 e522"><textual class="po-textual">WikiEventManager</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e523 e523"><imageobject class="po-container e524 e524"><imagedata class="po-meta e525 e525" fileref="../../../vol1/graphics/Altheim01/Altheim01-004.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e526 e526"><textual class="po-textual">
    Each wiki page editing session fires a number of associated WikiEvents. By filtering on event
    type we can capture specific life cycle events for a wiki page.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e527 e527"><title class="po-block e528 e528"><textual class="po-textual">Wiki Plugins</textual></title><para class="po-block e529 e529"><textual class="po-textual">
    Given that the basic idea was to permit users to make Assertions, we needed a means of
    expressing them using a simple wiki-like syntax. JSPWiki has a number of extensibility
    features, the WikiPlugin API being the most suitable for developing syntax-level functionality.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e530 e530"><textual class="po-textual">
    JSPWiki augments its formatting and linking syntax with a plugin syntax, where a reference
    to the plugin name is followed by a plugin body, which may contain one or more named parameters.
    For example, to transclude the wiki page “CopyrightStatement” using the InsertPage
    plugin one would include the following wiki text:
    </textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e531 e531" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">[{InsertPage page='CopyrightStatement'}]</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e532 e532"><textual class="po-textual">
    When the WikiEngine encounters this plugin syntax it instantiates a plugin object based on the plugin's name as mapped
    to a Java class name. The plugin object's  method is called and the plugin then performs its programmed tasks.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e533 e533"><textual class="po-textual">
    From the user's perspective, our entire system is implemented via a set of custom plugins, as described below. We've
    therefore augmented the default JSPWiki wiki text syntax with an additional assertion-related vocabulary, this vocabulary
    in keeping with the rest of JSPWiki's plugin syntax. Users already familiar with other JSPWiki plugins would find nothing
    unusual using the syntax of these new assertion features, and in fact, some of the plugins simplify the JSPWiki plugin
    syntax by not requiring use of explicit parameters.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e534 e534"><title class="po-block e535 e535"><textual class="po-textual">Assertion Plugins</textual></title><para class="po-block e536 e536"><textual class="po-textual">The implementation provides both assertion expression and query plugins, including:</textual></para><informaltable class="po-container e537 e537"><thead class="po-container e538 e538"><tr class="po-table e539 e539"><th class="po-field e540 e540"><textual class="po-textual">Plugin Name</textual></th><th class="po-field e541 e541"><textual class="po-textual">Alias</textual></th><th class="po-field e542 e542"><textual class="po-textual">Description</textual></th></tr></thead><tr class="po-table e543 e543"><th class="po-field e544 e544"><textual class="po-textual">AssertionPlugin</textual></th><td class="po-block e545 e545"><textual class="po-textual">Assert</textual></td><td class="po-block e546 e546"><textual class="po-textual">assert a single Subject-Predicate-Object sentence</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e547 e547"><th class="po-field e548 e548"><textual class="po-textual">AssertionFormPlugin</textual></th><td class="po-block e549 e549"><textual class="po-textual">AssertForm</textual></td><td class="po-block e550 e550"><textual class="po-textual">asserts properties based on a form template</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e551 e551"><th class="po-field e552 e552"><textual class="po-textual">AssertedPlugin</textual></th><td class="po-block e553 e553"><textual class="po-textual">Asserted</textual></td><td class="po-block e554 e554"><textual class="po-textual">query for Assertions matching a given pattern</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e555 e555"><th class="po-field e556 e556"><textual class="po-textual">AssertTagPlugin</textual></th><td class="po-block e557 e557"><textual class="po-textual">Tag</textual></td><td class="po-block e558 e558"><textual class="po-textual">assert one or more tags as properties of the Subject</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e559 e559"><th class="po-field e560 e560"><textual class="po-textual">HasAssertedTagOfPlugin</textual></th><td class="po-block e561 e561"><textual class="po-textual">HasTagOf</textual></td><td class="po-block e562 e562"><textual class="po-textual">query for wiki pages matching one or more tags</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e563 e563"><th class="po-field e564 e564"><textual class="po-textual">TopicMapPlugin</textual></th><td class="po-block e565 e565"><textual class="po-textual">TopicMap</textual></td><td class="po-block e566 e566"><textual class="po-textual">query the backing Topic Map (administrative use)</textual></td></tr></informaltable><para class="po-block e567 e567"><textual class="po-textual">The AssertionPlugin syntax is quite simple, just wrapping the abstract assertion syntax:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e568 e568" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">[{Assert [GarySnyder] IsA [Poet] }]</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e569 e569"><textual class="po-textual">
    Assertion Templates</textual><footnote class="po-popup e570 e570" xml:id="fn13"><para class="po-block e571 e571"><textual class="po-textual">i.e., a template for all Assertions using that Predicate.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
    use the same syntax but include a flag parameter, using the links to assert the roles
    played by the subject and object in Assertions of that type:
    </textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e572 e572" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">[{Assert template='true' [Instance] IsA [Class] }]</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e573 e573"><textual class="po-textual">Likewise, the query syntax is similar but uses parameters:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e574 e574" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">[{Asserted predicate='IsA' object='Poet' logic='and' }]</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e575 e575"><textual class="po-textual">
    This would return all Assertions having a Predicate “IsA” and an Object of “Poet”. Regular expressions
    are also supported. The current wiki page can be referenced in the syntax by “[.]”.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e576 e576"><textual class="po-textual">
    In practice almost all of the plugins developed for the project are domain-specific subclasses of either the
    AssertionPlugin or AssertedPlugin, developed to provide a specific feature based on a shorthand wiki text syntax.
    Some plugins are aliased to provide simpler or alternative names or to preset certain default values. For example,
    the Z39.19 predicates (e.g., “IsNarrowerThan”) were all included by presetting the current wiki page as
    the Subject and a fixed predicate name so that rather than
    </textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e577 e577" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">[{Assert [Whare] IsNarrowerThan [WhareT?puna] }]</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e578 e578"><textual class="po-textual">the user need only type</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e579 e579" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">[{IsNarrowerThan WhareT?puna }]</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e580 e580"><textual class="po-textual">
    It is hoped that these types of syntax simplifications will keep users from getting bogged down in the details of the
    syntax. Even the use of the word “assert” might be seen as overly technical by many. As the terminology
    used is easily changed we look forward to improving the system via user feedback.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e581 e581"><title class="po-block e582 e582"><textual class="po-textual">User Tagging</textual></title><para class="po-block e583 e583"><textual class="po-textual">
    A </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e584 e584" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">WikiTag</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> feature was developed to provide the ability to tag a wiki page,
    query pages matching one or more tags, or display a tag cloud. This again uses wiki plugins:
    </textual></para><informaltable class="po-container e585 e585"><thead class="po-container e586 e586"><tr class="po-table e587 e587"><th class="po-field e588 e588"><textual class="po-textual">Plugin Name</textual></th><th class="po-field e589 e589"><textual class="po-textual">Alias</textual></th><th class="po-field e590 e590"><textual class="po-textual">Description</textual></th></tr></thead><tr class="po-table e591 e591"><th class="po-field e592 e592"><textual class="po-textual">TagPlugin</textual></th><td class="po-block e593 e593"><textual class="po-textual">Tag</textual></td><td class="po-block e594 e594"><textual class="po-textual">assert one or more tags as properties of the Subject</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e595 e595"><th class="po-field e596 e596"><textual class="po-textual">HasTagOfPlugin</textual></th><td class="po-block e597 e597"><textual class="po-textual">HasTagOf</textual></td><td class="po-block e598 e598"><textual class="po-textual">query for wiki pages matching one or more tags</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e599 e599"><th class="po-field e600 e600"><textual class="po-textual">TagCloudPlugin</textual></th><td class="po-block e601 e601"><textual class="po-textual">TagCloud</textual></td><td class="po-block e602 e602"><textual class="po-textual">display a tag cloud based on a query</textual></td></tr></informaltable><para class="po-block e603 e603"><textual class="po-textual">Users can add tags to a page using a simplified plugin syntax:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e604 e604" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">[{Tag Person Actor Honcho }]</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e605 e605"><textual class="po-textual">
    This uses a TagManager that functions independently of the Assertion Framework, so that JSPWiki installations
    can be provided with a user tagging feature and augment the wiki at a later date with the Assertion Framework
    without any change in syntax. In this case, the only change necessary is the addition of the Assertion
    Framework library (jar file) and the re-aliasing of the plugins, e.g., changing the “Tag”
    alias from the TagPlugin to the AssertTagPlugin, the “HasTagOf” alias from the HasTagOfPlugin
    to the HasAssertedTagOfPlugin. JSPWiki provides this configuration feature via an XML file.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e606 e606"><textual class="po-textual">
    User tags are instantiated within the system as facets, such that the actual relationship between
    a page and one of its tags is a HasFacet relation. While this is a form of typed
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e607 e607" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">property assignment</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, the system does not currently support property
    typing of tags, though this can be done using via an assertion, eg.,
    </textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e608 e608" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">[{Assert [Habermas2006] DC_Title ="The Divided West" }]</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e609 e609"><textual class="po-textual">
    But this kind of thing might be seen as pushing the envelope on a wiki…
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e610 e610"><title class="po-block e611 e611"><textual class="po-textual">Assertion Framework</textual></title><para class="po-block e612 e612"><textual class="po-textual">
    When an instance of an AssertionPlugin is parsed on a wiki page it fires a subclass of
    WikiEvent called an AssertionEvent. An event listener filtering for AssertionEvents passes this on
    to a parser which generates an Assertion object corresponding to the parameters of the plugin
    syntax. In addition to Subject, Predicate, and Object we also capture the name of its origin wiki
    page and a creation timestamp</textual><footnote class="po-popup e613 e613" xml:id="fn14"><para class="po-block e614 e614"><textual class="po-textual">as described in the previous section, name-value property assertions are supported.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">.
    </textual></para><figure class="po-container e615 e615" xml:id="fig05"><title class="po-block e616 e616"><textual class="po-textual">Assertion Framework</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e617 e617"><imageobject class="po-container e618 e618"><imagedata class="po-meta e619 e619" fileref="../../../vol1/graphics/Altheim01/Altheim01-005.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e620 e620"><textual class="po-textual">
    The system supporting the expression, generation, caching and querying of Assertion objects
    is called an </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e621 e621" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Assertion Framework</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    (see </textual><xref class="po-milestone e622 e622" linkend="fig05"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">),
    which can be thought of in both static and dynamic terms:  static in the sense that at any point in
    time a snapshot of the system provides the set of extant Assertions; dynamic in the sense that the
    system is mutable, continually changing as people create and modify the wiki pages.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e623 e623"><textual class="po-textual">
    The workhorse of the system is the AssertionHandler, which handles all incoming Assertion objects,
    and managing a cache containing the set of all Assertions on the wiki. The initial set of Assertions
    is generated by an AssertionCrawler scan of all pages.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e624 e624"><textual class="po-textual">
    The AssertionHandler also provides methods to query the set of Assertions.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e625 e625"><title class="po-block e626 e626"><textual class="po-textual">WikiMapManager</textual></title><para class="po-block e627 e627"><textual class="po-textual">
    In the current implementation, the life of the AssertionHandler is very short. While the Assertion
    Framework using an AssertionHandler is a functional system, our requirements are better met by
    queries from a Topic Map.
    </textual></para><figure class="po-container e628 e628" xml:id="fig06"><title class="po-block e629 e629"><textual class="po-textual">WikiMapManager</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e630 e630"><imageobject class="po-container e631 e631"><imagedata class="po-meta e632 e632" fileref="../../../vol1/graphics/Altheim01/Altheim01-006.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e633 e633"><textual class="po-textual">
    Following initialization of the WikiEngine on startup, the AssertionCrawler crawls the wiki pages.
    Once this has finished it fires a completion event which triggers creation of a
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e634 e634" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">WikiMapManager</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    (see </textual><xref class="po-milestone e635 e635" linkend="fig06"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">),
    which also implements the AssertionHandler API.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e636 e636"><textual class="po-textual">
    The WikiMapManager obtains the set of Assertion objects from the existing AssertionHandler and
    converts them into Topics and Associations in an in-memory TopicMap object using the TM4J Topic Map engine.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e637 e637"><textual class="po-textual">
    Given our model of Assertions as simple binary relations, the translation to a Topic Map is straightforward.
    As described previously, the Assertion object contains references to the wiki page names for Subject,
    Predicate, and Object, the origin wiki page and a creation timestamp. Each wiki page name reference is
    converted to a Topic whose base name matches the wiki page name, with the page URL as a subject identifier.
    The Predicate is further typed as some descendant class of Relation within the Topic Map's subsumption
    hierarchy for relations. The Assertion itself is converted to a Topic Map Association, typed by the
    Predicate's Topic and also reified as a Topic. The timestamp is added as a property to this Association.
    If any of the wiki page name references match an existing Topic name the existing Topic is used. We are not
    currently scoping page names but will likely add scope to all names in the future given the current
    development project is multilingual.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e638 e638"><textual class="po-textual">
    Once this conversion is complete the WikiMapManager usurps the functioning of the existing AssertionHandler
    (which is then destroyed), so that incoming AssertionEvents are now processed as modifications and queries
    on the Topic Map.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e639 e639"><textual class="po-textual">
    The author of an Assertion relies upon the ability to read the respective wiki page documentation related
    to the sentence components at the moment of its expression. Since the system is mutable it must also be
    possible to view a snapshot of the system at the moment when the expression was made in order for others to
    interpret the Assertion correctly.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e640 e640"><title class="po-block e641 e641"><textual class="po-textual">Topic Map Interfaces</textual></title><para class="po-block e642 e642"><textual class="po-textual">
    The TopicMapPlugin is currently used to perform diagnostic queries on the Topic Map from a wiki page. The result
    of a query via a wiki plugin can return an XHTML fragment or content which could be processed via a Java Applet,
    so this usage is limited to direct display or visualization features.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e643 e643"><textual class="po-textual">
    There have been a few Web service experiments that return Topic Map (XTM) fragments, e.g., Topic and Association
    serializations corresponding to a set of Assertion objects. Though an interesting feature, there is no specific
    application requirement for inter-wiki sharing of structures that can't currently be accomplished via the
    existing XML-RPC features, so this remains as yet undeveloped.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e644 e644"><textual class="po-textual">
    Note that “Inferencer” is shown as a small box in the diagram. This is to indicate that this is
    not some big fancy inference engine, just a single Java class that performs simple queries on the Topic Map,
    such as returning simple transitive inferences upon relations whose predicates have been marked as transitive,
    such as ancestor and descendant tests, plus a few utility methods. Most return a boolean value so that they can
    be chained. As this functionality can easily be accommodated within the current use of wiki plugins no additional
    interfaces have been developed.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e645 e645"><title class="po-block e646 e646"><textual class="po-textual">Topic Map Modules</textual></title><para class="po-block e647 e647"><textual class="po-textual">
    One of the features of the system is the ability to provide run-time augmentation with the addition of drop-in
    LTM files as Topic Map modules. For example, if a user creates a wiki page called “Portugal” and
    asserts that Portugal IsA Country, we look up the
    page name in the ISO 3166 Country Codes for Topic Maps, as well as making any additional assertions about that
    Topic based on any Associations in the Topic Map.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e648 e648"><textual class="po-textual">
    Modules available, in development, or planned include ontologies for languages and countries, places, place
    names, events, geocode, measurement and datatypes, mappings to other library subject headings, and various other
    subject domains. One idea in the works incorporates a place names to latitude-longitude database to permit
    inclusion of Google Maps. For example, any wiki page asserted as a place would look up its wiki page name in
    the place names database, then use a wiki plugin to insert a Google Map for that location. This remains an area
    ripe for further exploration, and will likely be determined in part by user feedback.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e649 e649"><title class="po-block e650 e650"><textual class="po-textual">Endorsement</textual></title><para class="po-block e651 e651"><textual class="po-textual">
    Implementation-wise, all </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e652 e652" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">endorsed</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Topics and Associations within the backing
    Topic Map are scoped by an endorsing Topic. All user-created content within the Topic Map is either left unscoped,
    or scoped as "Unendorsed". In the case of the Māori Subject Headings and Iwi Hapū Names List,
    their Topics are scoped accordingly so that we may in the future extract Topic Maps corresponding to their
    respective domains.
    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e653 e653"><title class="po-block e654 e654"><textual class="po-textual">Wiki Features</textual></title><para class="po-block e655 e655"><textual class="po-textual">
    With all of this additional machinery behind the scenes, what effect does this have on the user experience?
    It must be said that, to reiterate one of the requirements, there is little desire to expose a great deal of
    complexity, particularly for readers. We likewise have on occasion decided not to implement a feature when it
    was seen to significantly add to the complexity of either the browsing or editing experience. Thus, most of
    the Assertion Framework features are experienced as links, structure displays or improved search or navigation.
    For example, the generated output from an AssertionPlugin shows the Subject, Predicate and Object as active
    wiki page links. A hideable navigational panel has been added to the page footer that displays any assertions
    or other information queried from the Topic Map for that wiki page.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e656 e656"><textual class="po-textual">
    We still have not investigated fully the use of many of these features and look forward to doing so following
    public release of the service.
    </textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e657 e657"><title class="po-block e658 e658"><textual class="po-textual">Next Steps</textual></title><para class="po-block e659 e659"><textual class="po-textual">
    Some future features are planned and/or partially implemented:
    </textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e660 e660"><listitem class="po-container e661 e661"><para class="po-block e662 e662"><textual class="po-textual">the project is currently being socialized amongst funding organizations</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e663 e663"><para class="po-block e664 e664"><textual class="po-textual">further develop query and inferencing functionality</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e665 e665"><para class="po-block e666 e666"><textual class="po-textual">provide term equivalence, related term, term aliasing, and term disambiguation features, both
                      manual (explicit) and automated (implicit) to deal with both homonyms and polysemes
                </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e667 e667"><para class="po-block e668 e668"><textual class="po-textual">provide enhanced search features based on assertions, tags, and collative terms</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e669 e669"><para class="po-block e670 e670"><textual class="po-textual">protect endorsed terms and relations using scope</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e671 e671"><para class="po-block e672 e672"><textual class="po-textual">permit scope-based filtering on queries</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e673 e673"><para class="po-block e674 e674"><textual class="po-textual">further develop basic ontologies and improve existing documentation</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e675 e675"><para class="po-block e676 e676"><textual class="po-textual">create forums for discussion of ontology development</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e677 e677"><para class="po-block e678 e678"><textual class="po-textual">with a current reliance on RecentChanges to manually discover errors, develop features for
                      structural analysis and validation</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e679 e679"><para class="po-block e680 e680"><textual class="po-textual">develop features to assist users in classifying new wiki pages (terms)</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e681 e681"><para class="po-block e682 e682"><textual class="po-textual">develop drop-in Topic Map-based ontologies</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e683 e683"><para class="po-block e684 e684"><textual class="po-textual">wiki hive functionality (sharing classifications across multiple wikis)</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e685 e685"><para class="po-block e686 e686"><textual class="po-textual">develop administrative features</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e687 e687"><para class="po-block e688 e688"><textual class="po-textual">develop (likely off-line) visualization features for analysis of the wiki structure
                </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e689 e689"><para class="po-block e690 e690"><textual class="po-textual">develop better internationalization/localization support</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e691 e691"><para class="po-block e692 e692"><textual class="po-textual">develop a RESTful web service providing queries on the Topic Map</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e693 e693"><para class="po-block e694 e694"><textual class="po-textual">performance improvement &amp; scalability testing</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></section><section class="po-hcontainer e695 e695"><title class="po-block e696 e696"><textual class="po-textual">Conclusion</textual></title><para class="po-block e697 e697"><textual class="po-textual">
    The Assertion Framework is still in a prototype state so there are many questions as to the viability of both
    the approach and implementation. An upcoming National Library of New Zealand project related to the Māori
    Subject Headings has been proposed that would use two wikis to perform a cross-dialect comparison of terms
    between the predominant te reo Māori language and a Taranaki dialect. We look forward to testing the
    system in a semi-controlled environment.
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e698 e698"><textual class="po-textual">
    This paper has put a substantial focus on epistemological and design issues rather than on implementation details.
    The reason for this is that the central innovation is not seen as the marrying of a Topic Map engine with a wiki
    – any programmer could accomplish that – but in the investigation into what the use of this
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e699 e699" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">means</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, i.e., does the expression of declarative statements incur an entailment
    or not? And if so, of what order? Surely there is no single answer to this question, but in the same way as people
    commonly anthropomorphize machines (hell, we anthropomorphize </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e700 e700" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">rocks</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">), this paper
    is, if anything, meant to inject a note of caution into inferring that the systems we develop do more than they do,
    that our claims notwithstanding we are in large part still playing with toys.
    </textual></para></section><bibliography class="po-hcontainer e701 e701"><title class="po-block e702 e702"><textual class="po-textual">Bibliography</textual><footnote class="po-popup e703 e703" xml:id="bibnote"><para class="po-block e704 e704"><textual class="po-textual">Note: all Web references accessed as of 18 April 2008.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
  </textual></title><bibliomixed class="po-block e705 e705" xml:id="Z3919"><textual class="po-textual">
    “ANSI/NISO Z39.19-2005: Guidelines for the Construction, Format, and Management of Monolingual Controlled Vocabularies.”
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e706 e706" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">U.S.A. National Information Standards Organization.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    25 July 2005.
    </textual><link class="po-inline e707 e707" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/resources/html/help/Z39-19-2005.pdf" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/resources/html/help/Z39-19-2005.pdf</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e708 e708" xml:id="BernersLee2001"><textual class="po-textual">
    Berners-Lee, Tim, James Hendler, and Ora Lassila. “The Semantic Web.”
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e709 e709" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Scientific American.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 2001.
    </textual><link class="po-inline e710 e710" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.sciam.com/article.cfm?id=the-semantic-web" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.sciam.com/article.cfm?id=the-semantic-web</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e711 e711" xml:id="Brandom"><textual class="po-textual">
    Brandom, Robert. “A Social Route from Reasoning to Representing.” In
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e712 e712" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Articulating Reasons</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, by Robert Brandom, 157-183.
    Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press, 2000.
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e713 e713" xml:id="Broughton"><textual class="po-textual">
    Broughton, Vanda. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e714 e714" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Essential Classification.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    London: Neal-Schuman Publishers, 2004.
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e715 e715" xml:id="ISKOI"><textual class="po-textual">
    “Colon classification.”
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e716 e716" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">International Society for Knowledge Organization.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual><link class="po-inline e717 e717" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.iskoi.org/doc/colon.htm" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.iskoi.org/doc/colon.htm</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e718 e718" xml:id="Context07"><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e719 e719" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">International and Interdisciplinary Conferences on Modeling and Using Context (CONTEXT).</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual><link class="po-inline e720 e720" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://mainesail.umcs.maine.edu/Context/context-conferences/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://mainesail.umcs.maine.edu/Context/context-conferences/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e721 e721" xml:id="DeLanda"><textual class="po-textual">
    “Virtuality and the Laws of Physics.” In
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e722 e722" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Intensive Science &amp; Virtual Philosophy</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">,
    by Manuel DeLanda, 117+. London: Continuum, 2002.
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e723 e723" xml:id="REST"><textual class="po-textual">
    Fielding, Roy T., and Richard N. Taylor. “Principled Design of the Modern Web Architecture.”
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e724 e724" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">ACM Transactions on Internet Technology (TOIT)</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    (Association for Computing Machinery) 2, no. 2 (2002-2005): 115-150.
    doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e725 doi e725"><textual class="po-textual">10.1145/514183.514185</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e726 e726" xml:id="RDFSemantics"><textual class="po-textual">
    Hayes, Pat. “RDF Semantics, W3C Recommendation.”
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e727 e727" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">W3C.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 10 February 2004.
    </textual><link class="po-inline e728 e728" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-mt/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-mt/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e729 e729" xml:id="Hayes2001"><textual class="po-textual">
    “Re: Why must the web be monotonic ?”
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e730 e730" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">www-rdf-logic mailing list archives.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> July 2001.
    </textual><link class="po-inline e731 e731" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/www-rdf-logic/2001Jul/0067.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/www-rdf-logic/2001Jul/0067.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e732 e732" xml:id="IRS"><textual class="po-textual">
    “Inferential Role Semantics.”
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e733 e733" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Wikipedia.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual><link class="po-inline e734 e734" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inferential_role_semantics" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inferential_role_semantics</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e735 e735" xml:id="McCHay69"><textual class="po-textual">
    McCarthy, John, and Pat Hayes. “Some philosophical problems from the Standpoint of Artificial Intelligence.”
    Edited by B. Meltzer and D. Michie.
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e736 e736" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Machine Intelligence</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    (Edinburgh University Press) 4 (1969).
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e737 e737" xml:id="Newell"><textual class="po-textual">
    Newell, Allen. “The Knowledge Level.”
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e738 e738" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Artificial Intelligence</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 18 (1982): 87-127.
    doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e739 doi e739"><textual class="po-textual">10.1016/0004-3702(82)90012-1</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e740 e740" xml:id="OpenCyc"><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e741 e741" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">OpenCyc.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual><link class="po-inline e742 e742" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.opencyc.org/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.opencyc.org/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e743 e743" xml:id="Reiter2001"><textual class="po-textual">
    Reiter, Raymond.
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e744 e744" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Knowledge in Action: Logical Foundations for Specifying and Implementing Dynamical Systems.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    Cambridge, Massachusetts; London, England: The MIT Press, 2001.
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e745 e745" xml:id="SWOver"><textual class="po-textual">
    “Semantic Web Overview.”
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e746 e746" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">semanticweb.org.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 2008.
    </textual><link class="po-inline e747 e747" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://semanticweb.org/wiki/Semantic_Web_overview" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://semanticweb.org/wiki/Semantic_Web_overview</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e748 e748" xml:id="SMW"><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e749 e749" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Semantic MediaWiki.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 2008.
    </textual><link class="po-inline e750 e750" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://semantic-mediawiki.org/wiki/Semantic_MediaWiki" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://semantic-mediawiki.org/wiki/Semantic_MediaWiki</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e751 e751" xml:id="Svenonius2000"><textual class="po-textual">
    Svenonius, Elaine.
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e752 e752" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">The Intellectual Foundation of Information Organization.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    Cambridge, Massachusetts: The MIT Press, 2000.
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e753 e753" xml:id="Turner"><textual class="po-textual">
    Turner, Christopher.
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e754 e754" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Organizing Information: principles and practice.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    London: Clive Bingley, 1987.
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e755 e755" xml:id="WikipediaSW"><textual class="po-textual">
    “Wikipedia:Semantic Web.”
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e756 e756" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Wikipedia.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 2008.
    </textual><link class="po-inline e757 e757" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semantic_web" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semantic_web</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e758 e758" xml:id="Wynar"><textual class="po-textual">
    Wynar, Bohdan S.
    </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e759 e759" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Introduction to Cataloguing and Classification.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    Boulder, Colorado: Libraries Unlimited, Inc., 1992.
    </textual></bibliomixed></bibliography></article></classedDocument>