<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2" xml:id="HR-23632987-8973"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">There are No Documents</textual></title><info class="po-record e2 e2"><confgroup class="po-record e3 e3"><conftitle class="po-field e4 e4"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2010</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">August 3 - 6, 2010</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e6 e6"><para class="po-block e7 e7"><textual class="po-textual">Last year at Balisage (2009) we considered the claim that documents cannot be modified. Our analysis took the form of identifying and evaluating possible responses to this inconsistent triad: 1) Documents are strings; 2) Strings cannot be modified; 3) Documents can be modified. Late this spring we were surprised to realize that our survey of possible responses to the document modifiability puzzle had overlooked one response: There are no documents. We turn to that neglected response now. </textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e8 e8"><personname class="po-record e9 e9"><firstname class="po-field e10 e10"><textual class="po-textual">Allen</textual></firstname><othername class="po-field e11 e11"><textual class="po-textual">H.</textual></othername><surname class="po-field e12 e12"><textual class="po-textual">Renear</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e13 e13"><para class="po-block e14 e14"><textual class="po-textual">Allen H. Renear is the Associate Dean for Research and an Associate Professor at the Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e15 e15"><jobtitle class="po-field e16 e16"><textual class="po-textual">Associate Dean for Research and Associate Professor</textual></jobtitle><orgname class="po-block e17 e17"><textual class="po-textual">Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e18 e18"><textual class="po-textual">renear@illinois.edu</textual></email></author><author class="po-record e19 e19"><personname class="po-record e20 e20"><firstname class="po-field e21 e21"><textual class="po-textual">Karen</textual></firstname><othername class="po-field e22 e22"><textual class="po-textual">M.</textual></othername><surname class="po-field e23 e23"><textual class="po-textual">Wickett</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e24 e24"><para class="po-block e25 e25"><textual class="po-textual">Karen M. Wickett is a doctoral student at the Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e26 e26"><jobtitle class="po-field e27 e27"><textual class="po-textual">Doctoral Student</textual></jobtitle><orgname class="po-block e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e29 e29"><textual class="po-textual">wickett2@illinois.edu</textual></email></author><legalnotice class="po-container e30 e30"><para class="po-block e31 e31"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright © 2010 by the authors.  Used by permission.</textual></para></legalnotice><keywordset class="po-table e32 e32" role="author"><keyword class="po-field e33 e33"><textual class="po-textual">document</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e34 e34"><textual class="po-textual">text</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e35 e35"><textual class="po-textual">XML</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e36 e36"><textual class="po-textual">ontology</textual></keyword></keywordset></info><section class="po-hcontainer e37 e37"><title class="po-block e38 e38"><textual class="po-textual">Introduction</textual></title><para class="po-block e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">Last year at Balisage (2009) we explored the claim that documents, in the sense of repeatable symbolic expressions, cannot undergo any genuine change or modification[</textual><xref class="po-milestone e40 e40" linkend="renear09"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. This is a claim obviously in direct contradiction to the common assumption that documents routinely undergo a wide variety of changes, such as revision, editing, and reformatting. The modification of documents is in fact an integral part of publishing workflows and so at the heart of many activities of professional interest to Balisage participants. Not surprisingly one comment on last year's presentation was: "You are telling me that my profession is impossible".</textual></para><para class="po-block e41 e41"><textual class="po-textual">Our analysis of the claim that documents cannot be modified took the form of identifying and evaluating possible responses to this inconsistent triad: 
    
    </textual><orderedlist class="po-table e42 e42"><listitem class="po-container e43 e43"><para class="po-block e44 e44"><textual class="po-textual">Documents are strings.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e45 e45"><para class="po-block e46 e46"><textual class="po-textual">Strings cannot be modified.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e47 e47"><para class="po-block e48 e48"><textual class="po-textual">Documents can be modified.</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist><textual class="po-textual">
</textual></para><para class="po-block e49 e49"><textual class="po-textual">Late this spring (2010) we were surprised to realize that our survey of possible responses to the document modifiability puzzle had overlooked one response: There are no documents. In the present paper we explore what might be said for this response as a solution to the modifiability puzzle. We also explain how this response escaped what we believed at the time to be a comprehensive survey of solutions.</textual></para><para class="po-block e50 e50"><textual class="po-textual">[This is the pre-conference version of a Balisage "late breaking" paper.  These are early provisional reflections, begun recently, and put in written form in order to elicit discussion at the 2010 conference.  We are looking forward to corrections, criticisms, and suggestions, which will inform the final version.]</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e51 e51"><title class="po-block e52 e52"><textual class="po-textual">The Arguments</textual></title><para class="po-block e53 e53"><textual class="po-textual">The word "document" has, of course, many senses. Our informal characterization of the sense intended in "Documents cannot be modified" is </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e54 e54" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">repeatable symbolic expression</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. This seems to be more or less the same sense implied in the XML specification, which defines "XML Document" as a string that matches certain formal constraints [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e55 e55" linkend="xml08"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. It also corresponds closely to the concept of an "expression" in the "Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records" (FRBR) [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e56 e56" linkend="frbr98"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] and to some uses of the word "text" in textual philology [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e57 e57" linkend="tanselle89"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. A document in this sense is not an individual physical object[</textual><xref class="po-milestone e58 e58" linkend="buckland97"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]  but the symbolic structure that can be found simultaneously instantiated in multiple physical objects [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e59 e59" linkend="derose90"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].</textual></para><para class="po-block e60 e60"><textual class="po-textual">We motivated the claim that documents cannot be modified in several ways: </textual><footnote class="po-popup e61 e61"><para class="po-block e62 e62"><textual class="po-textual">Please see the account presented last year for a more detailed presentation.[</textual><xref class="po-milestone e63 e63" linkend="renear09"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. See also  </textual><xref class="po-milestone e64 e64" linkend="renear08"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><xref class="po-milestone e65 e65" linkend="renear07"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">. </textual></para></footnote></para><para class="po-block e66 e66"><textual class="po-textual">First, we noted that digital documents, like all digital objects, are typically defined in terms of mathematical entities such as strings, tuples, relations, functions, and graphs. All of these entities are in turn defined as kinds of sets and, consequently, all are extensional: a set cannot, strictly speaking, lose or gain members, and therefore similar constraints will apply to those entities that are defined as kinds of sets, such as strings, tuples, relations, functions, and graphs. A string for instance cannot lose or gain a substring, a tuple cannot lose or gain an element, a relation cannot lose or gain a tuple, and so on. These constraints are consequences of all standard axiomatizations of mathematical set theory. Of course we can say that a string S was transformed into another string S', but this is an idiom -- there is no underlying thing that once was identical with S and now is identical with S', as genuine modification requires. Editing strings is mapping from one string to another, not modifying a persistent underlying entity. </textual></para><para class="po-block e67 e67"><textual class="po-textual">Second, we also observed more generally that abstract objects, and not just mathematical objects or digital objects, appear to have their non-relational properties essentially -- and so have no non-relational properties that they can lose. Since modification requires losing or gaining a non-relational property (ceasing to be thought about by John is not genuine modification) this means that abstract objects generally, and not just mathematical objects or digital objects, cannot undergo modification.</textual></para><para class="po-block e68 e68"><textual class="po-textual">Finally we observed that documents, in the sense intended, are in fact explicitly treated as immutable by communities with fairly practical non-philosophical objectives, such as catalogers [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e69 e69" linkend="frbr98"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], textual philologists [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e70 e70" linkend="tanselle89"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], and, in at least some contexts, XML specialists.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e71 e71"><title class="po-block e72 e72"><textual class="po-textual">The Document Modifiability Puzzle</textual></title><para class="po-block e73 e73"><textual class="po-textual">Because the claim that documents cannot be modified contradicts commonly held beliefs to the contrary the arguments just presented can be seen as presenting us with a puzzle, a conflict in our commonsense pre-theoretical beliefs. To systematically explore the various responses to this puzzle, we surveyed the alternative strategies for resolving the following "inconsistent triad":</textual></para><orderedlist class="po-table e74 e74"><listitem class="po-container e75 e75"><para class="po-block e76 e76"><textual class="po-textual">Documents are strings </textual><footnote class="po-popup e77 e77"><para class="po-block e78 e78"><textual class="po-textual">We say "strings" to allude to the definition of XML Document in the XML Specification, however we intend "strings" to stand in for a larger family of extensional entities, including graphs and relations.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e79 e79"><para class="po-block e80 e80"><textual class="po-textual">Strings cannot be modified.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e81 e81"><para class="po-block e82 e82"><textual class="po-textual">Documents can be modified.</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist><para class="po-block e83 e83"><textual class="po-textual">Responses to an inconsistent triad must reject one (at least) of the assertions in the triad and may be classified according to which assertion is rejected. Each class of responses has a distinctive burden. Responses rejecting the first assertion preserve our intuition that documents can be modified, but must provide an alternative account of what documents are, since they are not strings, graphs, or other immutable abstract entities. Responses rejecting the third assertion typically retain familiar definitions of document as immutable objects, but to be convincing they must provide a plausible account of what apparent document modification really is, since it cannot be genuine modification. Because there appeared to be very little that could be said in defense of rejecting the second assertion (extensional or abstract objects, such as strings, cannot undergo genuine modification) we focused primarily on responses that rejected the first or third assertions. </textual></para><para class="po-block e84 e84"><textual class="po-textual">We found responses that reject the first assertion to be fairly unpersuasive. They required admitting rather challenging ontological entities (e.g. "social objects") and relationships (e.g. "constitution"), and even given these entities and relationships it is not clear how a useful formal account of document change and identity could be developed [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e85 e85" linkend="cantwellsmith96"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">,  [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e86 e86" linkend="smith03"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. </textual></para><para class="po-block e87 e87"><textual class="po-textual">This seemed to tip the balance in favor of responses that reject the third assertion: documents can be modified. However a satisfying response here must avoid additional counterintuitive consequences, such as documents that exist before persons, or abstract objects that come into existence outside of the causal framework of natural science. We concluded, adapting the theory of social facts developed by John Searle [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e88 e88" linkend="searle95"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], that the least objectionable solution to the puzzle is that a document is indeed an unmodifiable string (or some other similarly extensional or abstract object) in a particular communicative role which it has in virtue of contingent social and linguistic circumstances.</textual></para><para class="po-block e89 e89"><textual class="po-textual">To meet the burden of providing an alternative account of modification we suggested that what is commonly referred to as the modification of a document might be understood as a person or persons coming to prefer one string to another for a particular communication task, and, typically, recording this intention in an information processing system or through some other physical medium. To the extent that our common discourse suggests that there is some thing, some real object, that is genuinely modified, this manner of speaking is not to be taken literally, but as some sort of idiom, metaphor, or "logical construction", perhaps similar to sentences such as "the sun rose in the east," or "the average plumber has 3.2 children". Such sentences can be true, but they cannot be literally true, in the sense of having a compositional semantics and directly (without rephrasing) supporting existential instantiation and valid inference. Of course this cannot be a complete account of apparent change, since it does not give explain "communicative role" in terms that would account for intuitions of apparent sameness in some circumstances of changing preferences, but it nevertheless seemed like a promising direction to explore.</textual></para><para class="po-block e90 e90"><textual class="po-textual">We were under no illusion as to whether we had succeeded in demonstrating that this particular resolution was decisively superior to the others, however we did believe that we had at least accomplished a breadth-first survey of the general kinds of responses that could be made to the triad. So it came as a surprise to realize that we had left one out.</textual></para><para class="po-block e91 e91"><textual class="po-textual">Before turning to a discussion of the missing response we make some brief remarks on the nature and significance of this sort of analysis.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e92 e92"><title class="po-block e93 e93"><textual class="po-textual">Aside: Why Should Anyone Care?</textual></title><para class="po-block e94 e94"><textual class="po-textual">Other then pure intellectual curiosity, why should anyone be interested in such a strange and abstruse meditation as we presented last year at Balisage, and now correct and extend this year?</textual></para><para class="po-block e95 e95"><textual class="po-textual">We believe that there is a case to be made that reflections of this sort are indeed relevant to the design of information management systems. Inferencing over formal ontologies is increasingly important in information processing, but systematically making information available in logic-based ontology languages requires that the assertions we wish to record be expressed in languages that allow only literal interpretation. Human beings may effectively communicate with natural language sentences such as "The sun rose in the east", "An fog of anxiety descended upon the congregation", "The average plumber has 3.2 children", or "The document was edited". But to support inferencing in the semantic web environment these idioms must be converted to assertions in languages that rely on compositional semantics, existential instantiation, and valid deductive consequences. The underlying ontology need not reflect the latest theories of modern physics, but it should nevertheless at least be internally consistent, and as much as possible avoid clashes with commonsense beliefs. A naive formalization of our familiar discourse about documents does not meet these requirements.</textual></para><para class="po-block e96 e96"><textual class="po-textual">That said, we realize that this sort of thing is not to everyone's taste. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e97 e97"><title class="po-block e98 e98"><textual class="po-textual">The Missed Possibility: There are No Documents</textual></title><para class="po-block e99 e99"><textual class="po-textual">This spring (2010) at the Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, we held a seminar titled "Identity and Change in Information Systems", focusing on issues related to formalizing our understanding of digital objects, particularly with respect to representing how they are created and reidentified, and what sort of changes they may undergo. In the course of reviewing prior relevant work on the topic of identity and change we considered a philosophical position, (physical object) eliminativism, which resolves traditional puzzles about change by arguing that ordinary physical objects do not really exist.</textual></para><para class="po-block e100 e100"><textual class="po-textual">Consider the staple problem of "material constitution". A statue S consists of a quantity of bronze B. In unguarded moments we are probably inclined to say that the statue and the quantity (mass, lump, etc.) of bronze are identical. After all they are in the same place at the same time and consist of the same stuff (and not just the same kind of stuff, but the very same stuff, the very same bits of bronze), and appear to have the same causal effects and powers. But problems with this identification ensue. </textual></para><para class="po-block e101 e101"><textual class="po-textual">For one thing if the statue was created this morning from an already existing lump of bronze then the statue has a property that the bronze does not have: </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e102 e102" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">being created this morning</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. And so the statue apparently can't be the very same thing as the lump of bronze. [On the general principle, sometimes known as Leibnit's Law, or the indiscerniblity of identicals, that if x and y are identical then x has all the properties y has.]</textual></para><para class="po-block e103 e103"><textual class="po-textual">Or imagine that our statue S (let's say it is a statue of a horse) is melted and reshaped into another statue, S' (a statue of a person). No bronze was lost so the lump of bronze, B, that was earlier identical with S continues to exist and is now identical with S'. But identity is transitive and so S, the statue of the horse, is identical with S', the statue of a person, -- which seems false.</textual></para><para class="po-block e104 e104"><textual class="po-textual">There are many more puzzles of this sort and many different approaches to resolving them. One rather extreme response is to deny that there are statues and instead to hold that there are just quantities of bronze which have particular properties that they can gain and lose. If the adjective were not already used with a different meaning we could say that some bronze can gain and lose the property of being "statuesque" [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e105 e105" linkend="chisholm76"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. Or alternatively one can say that the bronze can be "arranged statuewise" [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e106 e106" linkend="merricks01"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].</textual></para><para class="po-block e107 e107"><textual class="po-textual">The view that things of some familiar kind do not really exist is called "eliminativism" in philosophy. From the eliminativist's point some parts of our commonsense "folk ontology" are inconsistent, mistaken, or redundant, and need to be replaced with a more accurate conceptualization, one in which some of the familiar things in that ontology will have no role.  Sometimes the motivation for eliminativism is the view that contemporary science, typically physics, provides a much different and much better account of our world than our folk concepts do. Physicists for instance have routinely claimed that 20th century physics shows that our ordinary concepts of time, space, causality, and physical objects are flawed. One response to these new physical theories is to integrate the findings of physics into our commonsense ontology, which leads to assertions such as: tables are really wave functions.  This however is not eliminativism, but </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e108 e108" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">reductionism</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, as it reduces tables to other things but does not eliminate tables from the scientific view of the world -- on the contrary, the existence of the folk object is confirmed not denied in the reduction.</textual></para><para class="po-block e109 e109"><textual class="po-textual">The eliminativist on the other hand is not concerned to provide a more accurate and up-to-date understanding of what tables are, but rather to eliminate tables from our commonsense ontology altogether. The eliminativist claims that with respect to some fragment of our commonsense ontology (in this case medium-sized physical objects) it is not possible to map the concepts in that fragment, concept by concept, into the scientific alternative. Instead the scientific alternative must simply replace, entirely, the relevant portion of our folk ontology.  The eliminativist will hold that there is nothing in the real world, as revealed by modern physics, that corresponds closely enough to our concept of table to be appropriately considered a table, and that modern physics will allow us to say all there is to say about how things are in the kitchen without implying that there is a table in the room. Eliminativists argue that the objects of our commonsense notions are not just poorly understood, but that the concepts are too flawed to correspond to anything in the current scientific world view. 
    </textual><footnote class="po-popup e110 e110"><para class="po-block e111 e111"><textual class="po-textual">
        We note that both eliminativists and reductionists paraphrase ordinary sentences involving folk concepts into sentences without those concepts. However they often go about it differently. Eliminativists will typically need to provide a syntactically different replacement for an ordinary sentence they that they consider in its entirety to be an idiom.  Reductionists can sometimes expand a particular word or expression in place, leaving the rest of the sentence, seen as unobjectionable, intact.</textual></para></footnote></para><para class="po-block e112 e112"><textual class="po-textual">In philosophy contemporary eliminativism with respect to physical objects is sometimes a response to specific puzzles that reveal a conflict of commonsense intuitions. The problem of material constitution (the statue and the bronze) is an example. Other puzzles motivating recent eliminativism with respect to physical objects include those based on the vagueness of identity conditions for certain objects [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e113 e113" linkend="chisholm76"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e114 e114" linkend="unger79"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], the unclarity of when it is that two objects are parts of a third thing [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e115 e115" linkend="vaninwagen90"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], and the causal redundancy of composite wholes [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e116 e116" linkend="merricks01"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. The eliminativist claims that these puzzles demonstrate the deep incoherence of our ordinary (folk) views and argue that an eliminative resolution is the best recourse available: completely replace our ordinary notions with an alternative system of concepts. Eliminativist arguments are surveyed and criticised in Thomasson [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e117 e117" linkend="thomasson07"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]; see also Korman [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e118 e118" linkend="korman09"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].</textual></para><para class="po-block e119 e119"><textual class="po-textual">The reader will by now have guessed where this is going: one response to the problem of document modifiability is to simply maintain that there are no documents at all, this would allow us both to avoid accepting obscure social objects into our ontology and also to avoid endorsing the counterintuitive claim that documents cannot be modified. Needless to say these benefits would come at the cost of endorsing another counterintuitive claim: there are no documents. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e120 e120"><title class="po-block e121 e121"><textual class="po-textual">Why Was Eliminativism not Considered in 2009?</textual></title><para class="po-block e122 e122"><textual class="po-textual">However before going on to explore this alternative resolution we might wonder how it managed to escape the net of last year's systematic survey of possible responses to the inconsistent triad. Recall the triad:</textual></para><orderedlist class="po-table e123 e123"><listitem class="po-container e124 e124"><para class="po-block e125 e125"><textual class="po-textual">Documents are strings.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e126 e126"><para class="po-block e127 e127"><textual class="po-textual">Strings cannot be modified.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e128 e128"><para class="po-block e129 e129"><textual class="po-textual">Documents can be modified.</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist><para class="po-block e130 e130"><textual class="po-textual">Here is a natural formalization in first order logic:</textual></para><orderedlist class="po-table e131 e131"><listitem class="po-container e132 e132"><para class="po-block e133 e133"><textual class="po-textual">(x)[isaDocument(x) -&gt; isaString(x)]</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e134 e134"><para class="po-block e135 e135"><textual class="po-textual">(x)[isaString(x) -&gt; ~isModifiable(x)]</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e136 e136"><para class="po-block e137 e137"><textual class="po-textual">(x)[isaDocument(x) -&gt; isModifiable(x)]</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist><para class="po-block e138 e138"><textual class="po-textual">While the English version of the inconsistent triad may have appeared to be logically inconsistent, this set of first order logic formulas, is in fact </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e139 e139" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">not</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> logically inconsistent, at least according to the standard semantics of first order logic. In first order logic a universally quantified conditional "(x)[(isaDocument(x)-&gt;isModifiable(x)]" is logically equivalent to "(x)~[isaDocument(x) &amp; ~isModifiable(x)]" and so is true in an interpretation (an assignment of objects to predicates) if and only if nothing in that interpretatin both satisfies the antecedent and fails to satisfy the consequent. This entails that a universally quantified conditional will be true in all interpretations where nothing satisfies the antecedent -- regardless of what the consequent is. An odd and awkward result perhaps (it is one of the so-called "paradoxes" of material implication), but a common feature of first order logic nonetheless. As a consequence of this, in an interpretation where nothing is a document this set of assertions would be all satisfied; and so the set is consistent. 
</textual><footnote class="po-popup e140 e140"><para class="po-block e141 e141"><textual class="po-textual">However from the perspective of Aristotelian syllogistic rather than 20th century first order logic the natural language triad is indeed inconsistent (the form Calerent in the first figure is valid).</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> </textual></para><para class="po-block e142 e142"><textual class="po-textual">Did we actually commit a logical howler in last year's Balisage paper, allowing a class of resolutions strategies to escape our labored survey? Although we did neglect this possible resolution to the document modifiability paradox, we did not, fortunately, claim that a consistent triad was inconsistent.</textual></para><para class="po-block e143 e143"><textual class="po-textual">In our paper we formalized the triad not as in the preceding example, but like this:</textual></para><orderedlist class="po-table e144 e144"><listitem class="po-container e145 e145"><para class="po-block e146 e146"><textual class="po-textual">(x)[isaDocument(x) -&gt; isaString(x)]</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e147 e147"><para class="po-block e148 e148"><textual class="po-textual">(x)[isaString(x) -&gt; ~isModifiable(x)]</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e149 e149"><para class="po-block e150 e150"><textual class="po-textual">(Ex)[isaDocument(x) &amp; isModifiable(x)]</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist><para class="po-block e151 e151"><textual class="po-textual">And this is indeed an inconsistent set of assertions. The translation of the third assertion as an existentially quantified conjunction was made precisely to ensure that the intuitive inconsistency of the triad expressed in natural language would be present in the formalized version.  In the analysis presented last year we focused entirely on solution strategies that rejected the third assertion of this version of the triad </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e152 e152" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">only as a consequence of maintaining that its second conjunct could not be satisfied by any individual object that satisfied the first conjunct</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Accommodating the possibility that there are no documents was not on the agenda and so we did not consider the possibility that the third assertion is false simply because its first conjunct is not satisfied.</textual></para><para class="po-block e153 e153"><textual class="po-textual">Now that we have identified this overlooked class of solution strategies we propose to remedy the omission by giving this class of responses the same sympathetic consideration we gave the others. 

</textual><footnote class="po-popup e154 e154"><para class="po-block e155 e155"><textual class="po-textual"> Another strategy for representing the inconsistent triad is to modalize each univerally quantified assertion: 

</textual><orderedlist class="po-table e156 e156"><listitem class="po-container e157 e157"><para class="po-block e158 e158"><textual class="po-textual">L(x)[(isaDocument(x) -&gt; isaString(x)]</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e159 e159"><para class="po-block e160 e160"><textual class="po-textual">L(x)[(isaString(x) -&gt; ~isModifiable(x)]</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e161 e161"><para class="po-block e162 e162"><textual class="po-textual">L(x)[(isaDocument(x) -&gt; isModifiable(x)]</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist><textual class="po-textual">

</textual></para><para class="po-block e163 e163"><textual class="po-textual">Given the usual semantics of modal logic the fact that an interpretation has no documents does not itself entail that 1) and 3) are true in that interpretation, even though it does entail that the non-modal components of those formula (e.g., (x)[(isaDocument(x)-&gt;isModifiable(x)]) are true in that interpretation. The modalized formula is only true if there is no other interpretation where the non-modal portion of that assertion is true, that is to say, no interpretation that has a modifiable document. So with the modalization we do avoid consistency based on the trivial satisfaction of the conditional in an interpretation with no documents. </textual></para><para class="po-block e164 e164"><textual class="po-textual">However this does not materially change the problem. The modal triad is indeed inconsistent if there are interpretations where documents (and strings) exist, but the existence of such interpretations, or "possible worlds", is precisely what is in dispute. If we treat the predicates in our argument as logically opaque atoms that may be arbitrarily assigned to objects in an interpretation, then of course there will be interpretations where "isaDocument(x)" is assigned to an object, and which we might casually describe as interpretations where documents exist. But document eliminativism is not a view about the combinatoric possibilities for assigning objects to predicates; document eliminativism holds that there are no documents in any genuinely possible world. And if there are no documents in any possible world then the first and third modalized assertions are true in every possible world, for that reason alone the triad is consistent. </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">

</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e165 e165"><title class="po-block e166 e166"><textual class="po-textual">In Favor of Eliminativism</textual></title><para class="po-block e167 e167"><textual class="po-textual">If there are no documents our puzzle is resolved. And this is itself perhaps a reason to believe that there are no documents. But it is not much of a reason. To be preferred to other solutions to the document modifiability puzzle the position that there are no documents must have genuine advantages over those other approaches, and perhaps some independent positive rationale as well. Let's see what can be provided along those lines.</textual></para><para class="po-block e168 e168"><textual class="po-textual">We begin by realleging the results of last year's paper. Solutions to the modifiability puzzle that reject the first assertion (documents are strings) and redefine document as a social object, seem to us to be fairly unpromising, for the reasons given before. 

</textual><footnote class="po-popup e169 e169"><para class="po-block e170 e170"><textual class="po-textual">And redefining document in the relevant sense as a physical object, or set of physical objects, is both profoundly at odds with common discourse and unpromising as a solution to the puzzle in any event, as we argued in 2009.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> 

While not decisive, this might nevertheless be seen a providing at least some evidence in favor of the alternative, solutions that reject the third assertion -- though of course this prima facie warrant will be defeated if rejecting the third assertion turns out to have consequences even more obscure or counterintuitive than rejecting the first.</textual></para><para class="po-block e171 e171"><textual class="po-textual">In last year's paper we argued that although not every way of rejecting the third assertion was plausible, there was in fact a coherent position that rejected the third assertion and slightly qualified the first. This approach defined a document as a string in a contingent social role. Documents, being strings, are not modifiable on this account, but document modification discourse could be understood not as expressing literal truths, but rather consisting of harmless idioms and logical fictions that can be paraphrased into more precise representations.</textual></para><para class="po-block e172 e172"><textual class="po-textual">But we now know that there are two ways to reject the third assertion: (i) no modifiable documents, and (ii) no documents at all . So before preferring "no modifiable documents" to "no documents at all" we ought to see what there is to say in favor of "no documents".</textual></para><para class="po-block e173 e173"><textual class="po-textual">Obviously it is commonly believed that documents can be revised, edited, shortened, lengthened, and modified in other ways. This belief is widespread, and deeply rooted. It is perhaps so deeply rooted that it may be an integral part of our concept of what a document is, so intrinsic to the concept that perhaps that nothing can be document if it is not modifiable.</textual></para><para class="po-block e174 e174"><textual class="po-textual">Consider this example from the philosophical literature on the semantics of natural kind terms [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e175 e175" linkend="kripke81"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. We have beliefs about tigers. If some of these beliefs are wrong (say we believe tigers never have more than two kittens at a time, when in fact they often have more than two) then we are mistaken in believing such things about tigers -- but we are still believing something about tigers, even if it is something that isn't true. Now suppose we discover that tigers are not at all what we thought they were, that they aren't mammals for instance, or perhaps not even animals. Suppose they turn out to be robots. Should we really say "tigers are robots"? Intuitions here vary. Suppose it turns out that tiger experiences are being created by sophisticated multi-modal holograms. When we find this out would we say "we now know what tigers really are -- they are holograms"? Or would we say "Well, well, looks like there are no tigers after all, just holograms", or, in a similar vein, "what we thought were tigers are in fact holograms". Of course we might still open with "Tigers are holograms; who knew?", which suggests that there are tigers, and those tigers are holograms. But even if we said that casually, would it really be literally true? Wouldn't it be more accurate to say, after reflection, that </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e176 e176" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">there are no tigers, that what we thought were tigers are only holograms. </textual></emphasis></para><para class="po-block e177 e177"><textual class="po-textual">Perhaps being modifiable is to our concept of a document what being a living organism is to our concept of tiger. If so we could represent this conceptual fact, while maintaining neutrality on the question of whether there are documents, by the conditional: "if there are documents then they are modifiable" </textual><footnote class="po-popup e178 e178"><para class="po-block e179 e179"><textual class="po-textual">See Merricks [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e180 e180" linkend="merricks01"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. Thanks to Dan Korman for suggesting this approach. </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">. But in 2009 we presented arguments to the conclusion that documents are not modifiable.  From those two assertions, by </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e181 e181" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">modus tollens</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, the conclusion "There are no documents" follows. The argument, in short, is:</textual></para><orderedlist class="po-table e182 e182"><listitem class="po-container e183 e183"><para class="po-block e184 e184"><textual class="po-textual">There are no modifiable documents</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e185 e185"><para class="po-block e186 e186"><textual class="po-textual">If there are documents then they are modifiable</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e187 e187"><para class="po-block e188 e188"><textual class="po-textual">There are no documents</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist><para class="po-block e189 e189"><textual class="po-textual">This argument should be taken seriously even if one is skeptical of either (or both) of the two premises. This is because there is some supporting argumentation for each of those premises and, apparently, no decisive arguments against them. The support for the first premise is our argument last year that the unpromising nature of social objects as a way out of the modifiability puzzle provides at least some evidence, though not conclusive, for immutable documents.  Supporting the second premise is the widespread and deeply held belief that documents are modifiable.  The claim here is not that these considerations are sufficient to justify accepting the conclusion ("There are no documents"), but rather that they seem to shift the burden of proof to anyone who wishes to deny the conclusion and claim that there are documents.
        
        Spelled out step by step the reasoning goes:</textual></para><orderedlist class="po-table e190 e190"><listitem class="po-container e191 e191"><para class="po-block e192 e192"><textual class="po-textual"> isaDocument(x) -&gt; isaString(x)</textual></para><para class="po-block e193 e193"><textual class="po-textual">(argued in 2009)</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e194 e194"><para class="po-block e195 e195"><textual class="po-textual"> isaString(x) -&gt; ~isModifiable(x)</textual></para><para class="po-block e196 e196"><textual class="po-textual">(argued in 2009)</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e197 e197"><para class="po-block e198 e198"><textual class="po-textual"> isaDocument(x) -&gt; isModifiable(x)</textual></para><para class="po-block e199 e199"><textual class="po-textual">(argued in this section) </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e200 e200"><para class="po-block e201 e201"><textual class="po-textual"> isaDocument(x) -&gt; ~isModifiable(x)</textual></para><para class="po-block e202 e202"><textual class="po-textual">(from 1 and 2) </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e203 e203"><para class="po-block e204 e204"><textual class="po-textual"> ~(isaDocument(x) &amp; isModifiable(x))</textual></para><para class="po-block e205 e205"><textual class="po-textual">(from 5, Logical equivalence)
                </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e206 e206"><para class="po-block e207 e207"><textual class="po-textual"> isaDocument(x) -&gt; (isaDocument(x) &amp; isModifiable(x))</textual></para><para class="po-block e208 e208"><textual class="po-textual">(from 3, Logical
                    equivalence) </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e209 e209"><para class="po-block e210 e210"><textual class="po-textual"> ~(isaDocument(x))</textual></para><para class="po-block e211 e211"><textual class="po-textual">(6, 7, Modus Tollens) </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e212 e212"><para class="po-block e213 e213"><textual class="po-textual"> (x)~isaDocument(x)</textual></para><para class="po-block e214 e214"><textual class="po-textual">i.e. There are no documents. (8, Universal Generalization)</textual><footnote class="po-popup e215 e215"><para class="po-block e216 e216"><textual class="po-textual">Note that the premises of this argument do not, despite appearances perhaps, 
                        contain a contradiction; lines 3) and 5) are mutually consistent: they are both true 
                        if there are no documents.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
                </textual></para></listitem></orderedlist><para class="po-block e217 e217"><textual class="po-textual">The most likely response to this line of reasoning will be that the conclusion is on its face more implausible than denying one of the claims on which the argument depends (that modifiability is integral to the concept of a document for instance, or that the social object account of documents should be rejected in favor on immutability).  </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e218 e218"><title class="po-block e219 e219"><textual class="po-textual">Making Peace with Eliminativism</textual></title><para class="po-block e220 e220"><textual class="po-textual">The common response to eliminativist arguments against physical objects has been characterized as </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e221 e221" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">"Come on!"</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">[</textual><xref class="po-milestone e222 e222" linkend="wasserman09"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] Of course there are statues, tables, chairs, documents. What is more obvious? What advantage do we get by the strange tortured refusal to accept the existence ordinary things, especially if it is allowed that those things aren't at all what they seem to be?</textual></para><para class="po-block e223 e223"><textual class="po-textual">The answer to "what do we get?" is presumably: a simple consistent ontology that is free of both puzzles and obscure entities and preserves as many important commonsense intuitions as possible. And this is what we need for safe automatic inferencing in logic-based knowledge representation systems.</textual></para><para class="po-block e224 e224"><textual class="po-textual">But what remains most mystifying about eliminativism (to everyone except eliminativists) is that it will not be satisfied by reducing statues to other things (e.g., "stuff-arranged-statuewise"), but insists that we affirm that there are no statues at all. Why can't it be the case that stuff-arranged-statuewise is a statue? Isn't that what we mean by "statue"? Can't we simply affirm that statues are nothing more than stuff-arranged-statuewise without going on to deny the existence of statues?</textual></para><para class="po-block e225 e225"><textual class="po-textual">The eliminativist rejection of reductionist alternatives is uncompromising. The answer to "isn't stuff-arranged-statuewise a statue?" is: No, there are no statues; there is stuff-arranged-statuewise, but stuff-arranged-statuewise isn't a statue. Of course it is stuff-arranged-statuewise which is the result of sculpting, and stuff-arranged-statuewise which gives art historians statue experiences, but nevertheless: there are no statues. Statues, even reduced to stuff-arranged-statuewise, still create puzzles, and perhaps, in addition, are causally redundant, have inadequate identity conditions, and violate the principles of ontological parsimony... etc.  Reductionisms does not address any of these objections.</textual></para><para class="po-block e226 e226"><textual class="po-textual">The eliminativist answer to "but isn't stuff-arranged-statuewise what we mean by 'statue'?" is: maybe, but probably not. Most people seem to mean a thing, a statue, by "statue" and not stuff-arranged-statuewise [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e227 e227" linkend="merricks01"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. Though of course one </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e228 e228" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">could</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> mean stuff-arranged-statuewise by "statue"; just as one could mean biscuits-with-gravy by "statue". There should be no argument about that -- the meaning of words is a matter of convention. One's own idiolect can attach any meaning whatsoever to any word. And if "there are statues" </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e229 e229" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">is</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> understood to mean "there is stuff arranged statue-wise" then the eliminativist will grant that that sentence is true, and literally true -- but she will still not grant that a sentence understood this way implies that there are statues. This is because the eliminativist does not mean "stuff-arranged-statuewise" by statue when she says "there are no statues. By "statue" the eliminativist means statue, and by "there are no statues" the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e230 e230" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">eliminativist</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> means that there are no statues. 

</textual><footnote class="po-popup e231 e231"><para class="po-block e232 e232"><textual class="po-textual">Precisely how we are to understand ordinary beliefs and ordinary sentences about statues, from either the eliminativist or reductivist perspectives, is much debated.  The sentence "The TPS memo is now longer" is literally false according to both the document eliminativist and the string-in-a-role reductivist. For the eliminativist it is false because there is no TPS memo. For the reductivist it is false because the TPS memo cannot become longer. But what shall we say that the ordinary folk belief expressed by that sentence when it is uttered casually by an office worker? The reductivist may be comfortable saying that the ordinary belief expressed by the sentence is true even though the sentence is not literally true, just as "A dark fog of anxiety descended upon the congregation" might be true, even though it is not literally true. [Where literal truth would imply that </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e233 e233" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">there exists an object x such that x is an dark-fog-of-anxiety...etc.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">] This is perhaps because the reductivist may believe that the string-in-a-role view of documents is already implicit (even if hard to discern) in our commonsense beliefs. Eliminativists however will be more likely to insist that the sentence in question reveals that the office worker does have a false belief, namely that documents exist, and then offer an account of how such false beliefs can be "almost as good as true"[</textual><xref class="po-milestone e234 e234" linkend="merricks01"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> </textual></para><para class="po-block e235 e235"><textual class="po-textual">But these answers are frustrating if not inflammatory. To get a sense of how one might learn to live without documents, and like it, we begin by taking a closer look at the nature of predication.</textual></para><para class="po-block e236 e236"><textual class="po-textual">When social circumstances put a string in the distinctive communicative role described in last year's paper, why shouldn't one go on to say, as we said last year, that the string is then a document, that this in fact is what we mean by "document", just being a string in a particular kind of role? This is the reductivist complaint to the eliminativist. The eliminativist will answer: because this would have counterintuitive results (documents that are not modifiable), puzzles (things that are modifiable and not modifiable), and violate parsimony (if we can get along without positing documents, shouldn't we?), etc. But such arguments are not decisive when faced with competing claims on the same grounds (what is counterintuitive and what isn't) unless we have a better understanding of what it means to affirm the existence of stuff-arranged-statuewise while resisting statues. Or, in our case here, affirm the existence of strings in roles, but deny the existence of documents.</textual></para><para class="po-block e237 e237"><textual class="po-textual">One answer might go this way. It is often noted that there are many senses of the verb "to be". Identity (represented in symbolic logic as "x=y") is one; predication ("Fx") is another; constitution still another, and there are more. Our business here is with predication. Taking a closer look at predication we can see that it in turn might be divided into two sorts. There is exemplification ("Fido is brown"), and there is instantiation ("Fido is a mammal"). Both of these are represented with the same sort of formulas in symbolic logic (e.g., "Fx"), but arguably they are profoundly different in nature. 

</textual><footnote class="po-popup e238 e238"><para class="po-block e239 e239"><textual class="po-textual">The classical location for this distinction is in Aristotle's </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e240 e240" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Categories</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. An influential recent elaboration and be found in E.J. Lowe's work. For the most part we follow Lowe with respect to terminology. [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e241 e241" linkend="lowe06"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]</textual></para></footnote></para><para class="po-block e242 e242"><textual class="po-textual">Making peace with eliminativism might mean simply accepting that "is a document" is like "is brown", or "is a student", indicating that a particular thing exemplifies an attribute, rather than like "is a mammal", which indicates that a thing is an instance of a kind. From "Fido is a mammal" we can conclude that there are mammals, but from "Fido is brown" we do not conclude that there are "browns". Although we can, to be sure, conclude that there are brown things. Of course we can say that there is a document and simply mean by it that there is a thing which exemplifies a role, just like we could (but don't) say that there are "browns" and mean by it that there are things that are brown.</textual></para><para class="po-block e243 e243"><textual class="po-textual">This line of reasoning may seem independent of the preceding argument that there are no documents because if there were documents they would be both modifiable and not modifiable.  But there is perhaps a connection.  The attraction of the social object approach to documents is that it is consistent with our commonsense view that a document is a mutable instance of a particular kind of thing, a view that supports, psychologically, the development of useful idioms for expressing and recording changes of interest. When we recognize that this perspective is ultimately inconsistent with other things we believe about documents we are perhaps in effect recognizing that document is not a kind with instances; but only a role that immutable strings play in contingent social circumstances.</textual></para><para class="po-block e244 e244"><textual class="po-textual">It is hard to see how to weigh the competing considerations here. If one does proceed to affirm eliminativism on the grounds given then one can tidily resolve the entire document modifiability puzzle without positing counterintuitive unmodifiable documents. But at a cost, of course, of asserting a claim arguably every bit as counterintuitive: that there are no documents. The choice may seem imponderable, and it is not at all clear that restricting existence claims to instances of kinds tips the scale.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e245 e245"><title class="po-block e246 e246"><textual class="po-textual">Were we already there in 2009?</textual></title><para class="po-block e247 e247"><textual class="po-textual">Last year we observed that the "string-in-a-role" theory of what documents are has as a consequence that on one account of the requirements for being a "type" (or kind) of thing in a formal ontology, documents are not types of things, but rather roles that types of things (strings) have. Guarino and Welty [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e248 e248" linkend="guarino00"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] argue that one requirement for a property being a type is that it is "rigid": the things that have that property have it necessarily. The property of being a person, for instance, is a type and meets the rigidity requirement -- a thing which is a person could not have been anything other than a person, and cannot lose the property of being a person. But the property of being a student is not a type, because the things (persons) that are students might not have been students and may, and typically do at some point, cease to be students. </textual></para><para class="po-block e249 e249"><textual class="po-textual">Last year we already had arrived at a sympathetic consideration of the view a document is not a type of thing, but a role that some types of things (e.g. strings) have in particular circumstances. How far is this from eliminativism? One sort of eliminativist, the sort which bases their eliminativism on the kind/attribute distinction just elaborated, might say not far at all. The non-rigid nature of the property of being a document itself indicates that in a sound ontology </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e250 e250" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">document</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> is not a type/kind of thing but rather a way that things of a kind (strings) are related. The clash of string-in-role reductivism with our intuitive notion of modifiable documents reidentifiable over time might be taken to reveal that string-in-a-role reductivists have not fully internalized their own analysis, perhaps trying to use the hyphenated phrase "string-in-a-role" to have it both ways, inappropriately reifying a role.</textual></para><para class="po-block e251 e251"><textual class="po-textual">But the string-in-role reductivist will counter that the distinction between kinds and attributes is dubious, and even if real it does not obviously support kind/attribute-based eliminativism with respect to documents. After all, we don't say that there are no students just because we recognize that the property of being a student is not rigid -- being a person enrolled in an educational institution simply is what we mean by "student".   

    </textual><footnote class="po-popup e252 e252"><para class="po-block e253 e253"><textual class="po-textual">There is a difference between two sorts of eliminativist positions that is relevant here. Some eliminativists will allow that there is a thing (e.g., a lump of bronze) which has a property ("being statuesque" Chisholm suggests, though probably not seriously), even though there are no statues. Others do not admit the existence of a thing thing that has such a property, and instead make plural reference to other things (things that the non-eliminativist would say are constituents of the lump of bronze) asserting that it is those things arranged-statuewise that provide us with statue experiences, rather than any thing being statuesque. Document eliminativism, as presented here, seems to be an eliminativism of the former sort.  This constrains what sort traditional eliminativist arguments are likely to be supportive. The kind/attribute distinction for instance seems relevant to document elimination but not statue elimination.  Causal redundancy supports statue elimination but probably not document elimination. </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">

As to modifiability being integral to the concept of a document, the string-in-role reductivist can simply say we are often wrong about what is or is not an essential feature of a concept. We once thought that documents could be modified, we now know that they cannot be modified. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e254 e254"><title class="po-block e255 e255"><textual class="po-textual">Where are we now?</textual></title><para class="po-block e256 e256"><textual class="po-textual">Interesting arguments have emerged, and the burden of proof shifts now and then, but the main questions appear to be open still.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e257 e257"><title class="po-block e258 e258"><textual class="po-textual">Acknowledgements</textual></title><para class="po-block e259 e259"><textual class="po-textual"> We are grateful for conversations with many people, but are particularly indebted to David Dubin and Dan Korman. Thanks also to Simone Sacchi and Richard Urban and the other members of LIS590ICI: Identity and Change in Information Systems.</textual></para></section><bibliography class="po-hcontainer e260 e260"><title class="po-block e261 e261"><textual class="po-textual">Bibliography</textual></title><bibliomixed class="po-block e262 e262" xml:id="buckland97" xreflabel="buckland97"><textual class="po-textual"> Buckland, M. K. "What is a "Document"?" </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e263 e263" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Journal of the American Society for Information Science,</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 48 (1997),804-809. doi: </textual><biblioid class="po-atom e264 doi e264"><textual class="po-textual">10.1002/(SICI)1097-4571(199709)48:9%3C804::AID-ASI5%3E3.0.CO;2-V</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e265 e265" xml:id="cantwellsmith96" xreflabel="cantwellsmith96"><textual class="po-textual">Cantwell Smith, B.</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e266 e266" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">On the Origin of Objects</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Cambridge: MIT Press, 1996.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e267 e267" xml:id="derose90" xreflabel="derose90"><textual class="po-textual">DeRose, S. D., Durand D. G., Mylonas, E., Renear, A. H. "What is text really?" </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e268 e268" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Journal of Computing in Higher Education</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 1 (1990), 3-26. Reprinted in ACM/SIGDOC </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e269 e269" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Journal of Computer Documentation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 21 (1997). doi: </textual><biblioid class="po-atom e270 doi e270"><textual class="po-textual">10.1007/BF02941632</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e271 e271" xml:id="chisholm76" xreflabel="chisholm76"><textual class="po-textual">Chisholm, R. MB.</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e272 e272" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Person and Object</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Open Court, 1996.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e273 e273" xml:id="guarino00" xreflabel="guarino00"><textual class="po-textual">Guarino, N. and Welty, C. A. A Formal Ontology of Properties. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e274 e274" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of the 12th European Workshop on Knowledge Acquisition, Modeling and Management.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Lecture Notes In Computer Science. Springer-Verlag, (2000), 97-112.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e275 e275" xml:id="frbr98" xreflabel="frbr98"><textual class="po-textual">International Federation of Library Associations (IFLA). Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records: Final Report. UBCIM Publications-New Series. Vol. 19, München: K.G.Saur, 1998.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e276 e276" xml:id="korman09" xreflabel="korman09"><textual class="po-textual">Korman, D. Eliminativism and the Challenge from folk belief. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e277 e277" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Noûs 43</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">(2):242-264. 2009.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e278 e278" xml:id="kripke81" xreflabel="kripke81"><textual class="po-textual">Kripke, S. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e279 e279" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Naming and Necessity</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">Wiley-Blackwell, 1981.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e280 e280" xml:id="lowe06" xreflabel="lowe06"><textual class="po-textual">Lowe, E. J.</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e281 e281" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">The Four-Category Ontology: A Metaphysical Foundation for Natural Science, Oxford University Press, </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">Oxford, 2006.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e282 e282" xml:id="merricks01" xreflabel="merricks01"><textual class="po-textual">Merricks T. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e283 e283" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Objects and Persons</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Oxford: Clarendon, 2001.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e284 e284" xml:id="renear07" xreflabel="renear07"><textual class="po-textual">Renear, A. H., Dubin, D. "Three of the four FRBR group 1 entity types are roles not types." In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e285 e285" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings 70th Annual Meeting of the American Society for Information Science and Technology</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (Milwaukee, WI, October 2007).</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e286 e286" xml:id="renear08" xreflabel="renear08"><textual class="po-textual">Renear, A. H., Dubin, D., and Wickett, K. M. "When Digital Objects Change — Exactly What Changes?" In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e287 e287" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings 71st Annual Meeting of the American Society for Information Science and Technology</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (Columbus, OH, October 2008).</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e288 e288" xml:id="renear09" xreflabel="renear09"><textual class="po-textual">Renear, A. H., Wickett, K. M. "Documents Cannot Be Edited" </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e289 e289" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3, 2009. doi: </textual><biblioid class="po-atom e290 doi e290"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Renear01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e291 e291" xml:id="searle95" xreflabel="searle95"><textual class="po-textual">Searle, J. R. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e292 e292" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">The Construction of Social Reality</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. New York: The Free Press, 1995.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e293 e293" xml:id="smith03" xreflabel="smith03"><textual class="po-textual"> Smith, B. "John Searle: From Speech Acts to Social Reality", in </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e294 e294" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">John Searle</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, B. Smith (ed) Cambridge University Press 2003. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e295 e295" xml:id="tanselle89" xreflabel="tanselle89"><textual class="po-textual"> Tanselle, T. G. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e296 e296" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">A Rationale of Textual Criticism,</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Philadelphia: University ofPennsylvania Press, 1989 </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e297 e297" xml:id="thomasson07" xreflabel="thomasson07"><textual class="po-textual"> Thomasson, A. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e298 e298" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Ordinary Objects.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Oxford, 2007.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e299 e299" xml:id="unger79" xreflabel="unger79"><textual class="po-textual"> Unger, P. There are No Ordinary Things.</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e300 e300" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Synthese,</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 41, 1979.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e301 e301" xml:id="vaninwagen90" xreflabel="vaninwagen90"><textual class="po-textual"> van Inwagen, P. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e302 e302" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Material Beings.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Cornell, 1990.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e303 e303" xml:id="wasserman09" xreflabel="wasserman09"><textual class="po-textual"> Wasserman, R. Material Constitution (2009),</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e304 e304" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</textual></emphasis></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e305 e305" xml:id="xml08" xreflabel="xml08"><textual class="po-textual">Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0 (2008), Tim Bray, Jean Paoli, C. M. Sperberg-McQueen, Eve Maler, and François Yergeau, editors. W3C Recommendation 26 November 2008.</textual></bibliomixed></bibliography></article></classedDocument>