<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">Performance of XML-based applications: a case-study</textual></title><info class="po-record e2 e2"><confgroup class="po-record e3 e3"><conftitle class="po-field e4 e4"><textual class="po-textual">International Symposium on Processing XML Efficiently: Overcoming Limits on Space, Time, or Bandwidth</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">August 10, 2009</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e6 e6"><para class="po-block e7 e7"><textual class="po-textual">HighWire Press is the online publishing operation of the Stanford University Libraries,
        and currently hosts online journals for over 140 separate publishers. HighWire has developed
        and deployed a new XML-based publishing platform, codenamed H2O, and is in the process of
        migrating all of its publishers to this new platform.</textual></para><para class="po-block e8 e8"><textual class="po-textual">This paper describes four XML-based systems developed for our new H2O platform, and
        describes some of the performance characteristics of each. We describe some limitations
        encountered with these systems, and conclude with thoughts about our experience migrating to
        an XML-based platform.</textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e9 e9"><personname class="po-record e10 e10"><firstname class="po-field e11 e11"><textual class="po-textual">James</textual></firstname><othername class="po-field e12 e12"><textual class="po-textual">A.</textual></othername><surname class="po-field e13 e13"><textual class="po-textual">Robinson</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e14 e14"><para class="po-block e15 e15"><textual class="po-textual">Jim Robinson has been a systems developer at Stanford University HighWire Press for
          over ten years. He's been interested in XML-based technology since 2005.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e16 e16"><jobtitle class="po-field e17 e17"><textual class="po-textual">Information Systems Specialist</textual></jobtitle><orgname class="po-block e18 e18"><textual class="po-textual">Stanford University HighWire Press</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e19 e19"><textual class="po-textual">jim.robinson@stanford.edu</textual></email></author><legalnotice class="po-container e20 e20"><para class="po-block e21 e21"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright © 2009 by the Board of Trustees of the Leland Stanford Junior
        University. Used by permission.</textual></para></legalnotice><keywordset class="po-table e22 e22" role="author"><keyword class="po-field e23 e23"><textual class="po-textual">XML</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">XSLT</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e25 e25"><textual class="po-textual">XQuery</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e26 e26"><textual class="po-textual">Atom Publishing Protocol</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e27 e27"><textual class="po-textual">publishing platform</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">performance case-study</textual></keyword></keywordset></info><section class="po-hcontainer e29 e29"><title class="po-block e30 e30"><textual class="po-textual">Introduction</textual></title><para class="po-block e31 e31"><textual class="po-textual">In late 2006 HighWire had started internal discussions over whether or not we needed to
      implement a radical overhaul of our publishing, parsing and content delivery system. We wanted
      the system to be much more flexible when it came to incorporating new data, sharing data
      between systems, and delivering new features.</textual></para><para class="po-block e32 e32"><textual class="po-textual">At that time our system, which had been built up over the past decade, followed a fairly
      traditional model consisting of a display layer, a business logic layer, and a
      metadata/storage layer. Specifically, our original system could be described as a combination
      of:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e33 e33"><listitem class="po-container e34 e34"><para class="po-block e35 e35"><textual class="po-textual">Perl and Nsgmls based tools to process data supplied by file providers.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e36 e36"><para class="po-block e37 e37"><textual class="po-textual">NFS servers to hold derivatives (e.g., SHTML or similar files).</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e38 e38"><para class="po-block e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">Relational database servers, accessed via SQL, to hold metadata.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e40 e40"><para class="po-block e41 e41"><textual class="po-textual">Java Mediators talking to the NFS and database servers.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e42 e42"><para class="po-block e43 e43"><textual class="po-textual">Java Servlets with a custom templating language similar to JSP, named DTL, to build
          pages for the browser.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e44 e44"><textual class="po-textual">While this system has served us well, and continues to do so, there were some basic
      problems we were finding difficult to overcome:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e45 e45"><listitem class="po-container e46 e46"><para class="po-block e47 e47"><textual class="po-textual">The translation from the relational databases model into Java Objects, and then into
          DTL objects for use in the final display layer, often forced the writing of new
          application features to become a senior developer task. In order to handle new metadata,
          the developer had to determine whether or not the existing relational tables were flexible
          enough for the new data, or whether new tables were needed. Next would be the job of
          extending, or creating, appropriate stored procedures to access the new metadata. Finally,
          work would be needed in the Java layer to add object mapping support, including routines
          to map the metadata into DTL.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e48 e48"><para class="po-block e49 e49"><textual class="po-textual">Beyond the problem of mapping new metadata from the relational layer of the system to
          the DTL layer, the introduction of completely new models was daunting. The original
          database had been built to support journals whose primary components were modeled as
          issues with articles, and articles with figures and tables. The original design of the
          system had intended that we support new models by creating new relational tables, or
          entire databases, and then building new Java mediators to handle the translation from the
          database to the display layer. Unfortunately, the reality was that it was more difficult
          than we would have liked to support customers who wanted different, non-traditional (to
          us), models.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e50 e50"><para class="po-block e51 e51"><textual class="po-textual">The original system hadn't been built with either XML or Unicode in mind. Much of the
          core system had been developed in the late 1990s, around the same time XML 1.0 was
          published, and before it was widely adopted. By the same token, the DTL system was
          developed before Unicode was supported in mainstream browsers. These shortcomings meant it
          was very difficult for us to properly ingest XML and produce valid XHTML with Unicode
          support on the display side. Attempting to add Unicode support alone was a daunting task,
          as it required careful vetting of all code which worked at the character level, beginning
          with the Perl system, moving through to the database systems and filesystems, and ending
          in the Java layers.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e52 e52"><textual class="po-textual">What we decided to build:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e53 e53"><listitem class="po-container e54 e54"><para class="po-block e55 e55"><textual class="po-textual">An end-to-end XML-based system. We would accept incoming XML, transform it into
          different XML representations, store it as XML, query it as XML, and generate XML for the
          end user.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e56 e56"><para class="po-block e57 e57"><textual class="po-textual">We would encode certain types of oft-used relationship data up front, trying as much
          as possible to compute it only once.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e58 e58"><para class="po-block e59 e59"><textual class="po-textual">We decided to build everything following a RESTful [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e60 e60" linkend="fielding"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] model,
          with the idea that using a simple set of operators (GET/HEAD, POST, PUT, and DELETE),
          using unique URIs (vs. SOAP documents submitted to a single URI shared by all resources),
          and embedding hyperlink metadata into our documents would make it easier to spin off new
          services.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e61 e61"><textual class="po-textual">After about six months of discussions and prototyping, we had an outline of what we would
      be building and which new software technologies we would be using. By January of 2007 we had
      built a demonstration system which made use of XSLT and XQuery to transform incoming XML into
      metadata and XHTML, and to deliver dynamically built XHTML pages.</textual></para><para class="po-block e62 e62"><textual class="po-textual">After about fifteen months of work following this prototyping, HighWire had a beta site
      operating, and was ready to announce its new platform, dubbed H2O. In the first week of July
      of 2008 we launched our first migrated site, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
      of the United States of America (PNAS). Since that time we've launched 57 additional sites,
      consisting of a mixture of new launches and migrations.</textual></para><para class="po-block e63 e63"><textual class="po-textual">There are three primary tiers of XML-based technology in the H2O system:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e64 e64"><listitem class="po-container e65 e65"><para class="po-block e66 e66"><textual class="po-textual">Firenze, a HighWire-developed XSLT 2.0 pipeline execution system used to build both
          front-end sites and back-end data services.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e67 e67"><para class="po-block e68 e68"><textual class="po-textual">Schema, Addressing, and Storage System (SASS), a data store implementing an internally
          developed protocol, the HighWire Publishing Protocol (HPP) built on top of the Atom
          Publishing Protocol (APP) [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e69 e69" linkend="atompub"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] and Atom Syndication Format (ASF)
            [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e70 e70" linkend="atom"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. SASS is used to manage and serve content, implemented in two
          different technologies: XSLT 2.0 using Saxon-SA (read-only) and XQuery using MarkLogic
          Server 3.x (read/write).</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e71 e71"><para class="po-block e72 e72"><textual class="po-textual">Babel XSLT, a HighWire-developed vector processing engine which we use to drive XSLT
          2.0 transformations.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e73 e73"><textual class="po-textual">In this paper we'll discuss how these systems work, and will examine their different
      performance characteristics.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e74 e74"><title class="po-block e75 e75"><textual class="po-textual">Firenze</textual></title><para class="po-block e76 e76"><textual class="po-textual">The first layer of the H2O system we'll describe is the Firenze application framework. The
      Firenze framework, written in 87,000 lines of code across 526 Java classes, is the core piece
      of technology we run that services all dynamic page generation requests in our public-facing
      H2O web servers. All of the dynamically generated content served by the public-facing sites
      flows through this framework.</textual></para><para class="po-block e77 e77"><textual class="po-textual">The bulk of Firenze is a vendor-agnostic set of classes which rely on various public
      standard APIs, e.g., the Java Servlet API, JAXP, and HTTP handlers. An additional set of
      classes are then needed to provide a vendor-specific service-provider to execute XSLT
      Transformations, and to provide custom URI Resolver implementations. We've written about 30
      additional Java classes which use Saxon-SA 9.x to implement this service-provider
      functionality. The original implementation of Firenze used Saxon-SA 8.x APIs directly, but in
      a subsequent rewrite we decided that we would benefit from abstracting the smaller
      vendor-specific parts away from the larger, more general, framework.</textual></para><para class="po-block e78 e78"><textual class="po-textual">A Firenze application pushes an incoming request through four basic stages to produce an
      outgoing response:</textual><orderedlist class="po-table e79 e79"><listitem class="po-container e80 e80"><para class="po-block e81 e81"><textual class="po-textual">It transforms an incoming HTTP request from the Java Servlet API into an XML
            representation, </textual><code class="po-atom e82 e82"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, based on an internal schema.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e83 e83"><para class="po-block e84 e84"><textual class="po-textual">Firenze pushes the </textual><code class="po-atom e85 e85"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> through zero or more Filters which may
            amend the </textual><code class="po-atom e86 e86"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> document, adding or removing data from the
            body.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e87 e87"><para class="po-block e88 e88"><textual class="po-textual">Next, Firenze pushes the amended </textual><code class="po-atom e89 e89"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> through a chain of one or
            more XSLT Templates to produce an XML response representation,
            </textual><code class="po-atom e90 e90"><textual class="po-textual">rsp:response</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, which is also based on an internal schema.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e91 e91"><para class="po-block e92 e92"><textual class="po-textual">Finally, Firenze transforms the </textual><code class="po-atom e93 e93"><textual class="po-textual">rsp:response</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> into appropriate calls
            against the Java Servlet API to output an HTTP response to the client</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist></para><para class="po-block e94 e94"><textual class="po-textual">The process of pushing these documents through the pipeline is handled via SAX2 events,
      implemented by various event-handlers. As each event-handler is invoked it has a chance to
      operate on parts of the </textual><code class="po-atom e95 e95"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><code class="po-atom e96 e96"><textual class="po-textual">rsp:response</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> as the documents
      flow through the pipeline. Once each handler completes its area of responsibility it is
      removed from the execution stack, thereby reducing the number of SAX2 events fired across the
      length of the pipeline. </textual><figure class="po-container e97 e97" floatstyle="1" xml:id="firenze-pipeline-1" xreflabel="Firenze Application Pipeline"><mediaobject class="po-container e98 e98"><imageobject class="po-container e99 e99"><imagedata class="po-meta e100 e100" fileref="../../../vol4/graphics/Robinson01/Robinson01-001.png" format="png" width="90%"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><note class="po-container e101 e101"><para class="po-block e102 e102"><textual class="po-textual">From Time 1 through Time 5, various handlers for Filters and Transforms complete
            their tasks and are removed from the pipeline, reducing the number of SAX2 events which
            have to be fired.</textual></para></note></figure></para><para class="po-block e103 e103"><textual class="po-textual">The demarcation of responsibilities between Filters and Templates is fuzzy: both may amend
        </textual><code class="po-atom e104 e104"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> documents in any fashion, and the decision whether to make the
      process a specific Filter or part of the Template chain is up to the author. The Template
      pipeline is then responsible for transforming the </textual><code class="po-atom e105 e105"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> into a final
        </textual><code class="po-atom e106 e106"><textual class="po-textual">rsp:response</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> document. It may be interesting to note that almost all of the
      Filters we've implemented are XSLT stylesheets. Only a few of the Filters have been
      implemented directly in Java.</textual></para><para class="po-block e107 e107"><textual class="po-textual">As an example of a pipeline operation, a request flowing through the pipeline might start
      its life as a </textual><code class="po-atom e108 e108"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> document as built via the Java Servlet API: </textual><programlisting class="po-block e109 e109" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
&lt;req:request
  xmlns:req="http://schema.highwire.org/Service/Request"
  xmlns:ctx="http://schema.highwire.org/Service/Context"
  xmlns:msg="http://schema.highwire.org/Service/Message"
 id="SltVIKtCeVIAAFFBoFQAAAT@"
 protocol="HTTP/1.1"
 client-host="171.66.232.30"
 server-host="www.pnas.org"
 server-port="80"
 method="GET"
 secure="false"
 path="/content/106/27/10877.full"
 service-path="/content"
 extra-path="/106/27/10877.full"
 xml:base="http://www.pnas.org/content/106/27/10877.full"&gt;
  &lt;ctx:context server-info="Apache Tomcat/5.5.23" resource-root="jndi:/localhost/pnas/"&gt;
     &lt;ctx:attribute
       name="org.highwire.firenze.pipeline.cache"&gt;org.highwire.firenze.resolver.CachingOutputURIResolver@43861b3&lt;/ctx:attribute&gt;
     &lt;ctx:attribute
       name="org.apache.catalina.WELCOME_FILES"&gt;index.html, index.htm, index.jsp&lt;/ctx:attribute&gt;
     &lt;ctx:attribute
       name="org.apache.catalina.jsp_classpath"&gt;...&lt;/ctx:attribute&gt;
      ...
  &lt;/ctx:context&gt;
  &lt;msg:header
    name="host"&gt;www.pnas.org&lt;/msg:header&gt;
  &lt;msg:header
    name="user-agent"&gt;Mozilla/5.0 (Macintosh; U; Intel Mac OS X 10.5; en-US; rv:1.9.0.11) Gecko/2009060214 Firefox/3.0.11&lt;/msg:header&gt;
  &lt;msg:header
    name="accept"&gt;text/html,application/xhtml+xml,application/xml;q=0.9,*/*;q=0.8&lt;/msg:header&gt;
  &lt;msg:header
    name="accept-language"&gt;en-us,en;q=0.5&lt;/msg:header&gt;
  &lt;msg:header
    name="accept-encoding"&gt;gzip,deflate&lt;/msg:header&gt;
  &lt;msg:header
    name="accept-charset"&gt;ISO-8859-1,utf-8;q=0.7,*;q=0.7&lt;/msg:header&gt;
  &lt;msg:header
    name="keep-alive"&gt;300&lt;/msg:header&gt;
  &lt;msg:header
    name="connection"&gt;keep-alive&lt;/msg:header&gt;
&lt;/req:request&gt;
</textual></programlisting></para><para class="po-block e110 e110"><textual class="po-textual">The initial </textual><code class="po-atom e111 e111"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> document describe the HTTP request in its entirety.
      The first Filter handler which processes this </textual><code class="po-atom e112 e112"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> may then, for example,
      add additional information about the resource being requested, shown here as an additional
        </textual><code class="po-atom e113 e113"><textual class="po-textual">msg:attribute</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> element added to the end of the </textual><code class="po-atom e114 e114"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
      document: </textual><programlisting class="po-block e115 e115" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
&lt;req:request
  xmlns:req="http://schema.highwire.org/Service/Request"
  xmlns:ctx="http://schema.highwire.org/Service/Context"
  xmlns:msg="http://schema.highwire.org/Service/Message" ...&gt;
  ...
  &lt;msg:header name="keep-alive"&gt;300&lt;/msg:header&gt;
  &lt;msg:header name="connection"&gt;keep-alive&lt;/msg:header&gt;
  &lt;msg:attribute xmlns:msg="http://schema.highwire.org/Service/Message" name="content-peek"&gt;
   &lt;content-response xmlns=""&gt;
     &lt;content-request&gt;
        &lt;corpus code="pnas"&gt;&lt;/corpus&gt;
        &lt;content collection="/"&gt;
           &lt;resource id="106/27/10877" specifiers="full" /&gt;
        &lt;/content&gt;
     &lt;/content-request&gt;
     &lt;sdp:variant-info xmlns:sdp="http://xslt.highwire.org/Service/SASS/DataProvisioning"
                       xmlns:c="http://schema.highwire.org/Compound"
                       href="http://sass.highwire.org/pnas/106/27/10877.full"
                       c:role="http://schema.highwire.org/variant/full-text"&gt;
        &lt;sdp:role-selector&gt;full&lt;/sdp:role-selector&gt;
        &lt;view xmlns="http://schema.highwire.org/Site" name="full-text" alias="full"
              legacy-name="full"
              display-name="Full Text"
              variant-role="full-text"
              variant-short-role="full"
              type="application/xhtml+xml" /&gt;
        &lt;sdp:entry&gt;http://sass.highwire.org/pnas/106/27/10877.atom&lt;/sdp:entry&gt;
     &lt;/sdp:variant-info&gt;
     &lt;content-ref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="atom:entry" xlink:type="simple"
                  xlink:href="http://sass.highwire.org/pnas/106/27/10877.atom?with-ancestors=yes" /&gt;
   &lt;/content-response&gt;
  &lt;/msg:attribute&gt;
&lt;/req:request&gt;
</textual></programlisting></para><para class="po-block e116 e116"><textual class="po-textual">The </textual><code class="po-atom e117 e117"><textual class="po-textual">msg:attribute</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> element in this case, given a name
        </textual><code class="po-atom e118 e118"><textual class="po-textual">content-peek</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, provides detailed information about how to retrieve the requested
      resource from the central data store, in this case via the URL
        </textual><code class="po-atom e119 e119"><textual class="po-textual">http://sass.highwire.org/pnas/106/27/10877.atom?with-ancestors=yes</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">. A second
      Filter may then consume this msg:attribute and use it to fill in the contents of that URL, in
      this case a full text article with metadata about its ancestry (the issue it is in, its
      volume, etc.) expanded in-line, by adding another msg:attribute to the end of the
        </textual><code class="po-atom e120 e120"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> document: </textual><programlisting class="po-block e121 e121" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
  &lt;req:request
    xmlns:req="http://schema.highwire.org/Service/Request"
    xmlns:ctx="http://schema.highwire.org/Service/Context"
    xmlns:msg="http://schema.highwire.org/Service/Message" ...&gt;
    ...
            &lt;content-ref
               xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
               type="atom:entry" xlink:type="simple"
               xlink:href="http://sass.highwire.org/pnas/106/27/10877.atom?with-ancestors=yes" /&gt;
         &lt;/content-response&gt;
      &lt;/msg:attribute&gt;
      &lt;msg:attribute xmlns:msg="http://schema.highwire.org/Service/Message" name="contents"&gt;
         &lt;atom:entry xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
                     xmlns:nlm="http://schema.highwire.org/NLM/Journal"
                     xml:base="http://sass.highwire.org/pnas/106/27/10877.atom?with-ancestors=yes"
                     nlm:article-type="article-commentary"&gt;
            &lt;c:parent xmlns:c="http://schema.highwire.org/Compound" xml:base="/pnas/106/27.atom"&gt;
               &lt;c:parent xml:base="/pnas/106.atom"&gt;
                  &lt;c:parent xml:base="/pnas.atom"&gt;
                     &lt;c:parent xml:base="/svc.atom"&gt;
                        &lt;atom:category
                          scheme="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing#role"
                            term="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing/Service" /&gt;
                        &lt;atom:id&gt;http://atom.highwire.org/&lt;/atom:id&gt;
                        &lt;atom:title&gt;HighWire Atom Store&lt;/atom:title&gt;
                        &lt;atom:author&gt;
              ...
            &lt;/c:parent&gt;
            &lt;atom:category
              scheme="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing#role"
                term="http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Article" /&gt;
            &lt;atom:category
              scheme="http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Article#has-earlier-version"
                term="yes" /&gt;
            &lt;atom:id&gt;tag:pnas@highwire.org,2009-07-02:0905722106&lt;/atom:id&gt;
            &lt;atom:title&gt;Should Social Security numbers be replaced by modern,
              more secure identifiers?&lt;/atom:title&gt;
            ...
       &lt;/atom:entry&gt;
    &lt;/msg:attribute&gt;
  &lt;/req:request&gt;
</textual></programlisting></para><para class="po-block e122 e122"><textual class="po-textual">In this fashion, Filters and Templates aggregate data from multiple sources until enough
      information has been accumulated to produce the final response. It is probably obvious that
      the amount of data produced within the pipeline over the lifetime of a request may greatly
      exceed the final size of the response document sent to the client. For the example above, the
      final </textual><code class="po-atom e123 e123"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> document produced by the pipeline exceeds 375 kilobytes of
      serialized XML, while the final XHTML document sent to the user is a mere 60 kilobytes.</textual></para><para class="po-block e124 e124"><textual class="po-textual">The public-facing H2O sites run almost entirely off of Firenze, executing a codebase
      consisting of a little under 50,000 lines of XSLT 2.0 code (including comments and
      whitespace), spread across a set of 160 stylesheets. This codebase is maintained under a
      shared repository, with each site then applying overriding stylesheets for any site-specific
      functionality. Currently each site has between 10 and 23 site-specific stylesheets, though
      some of these only consist of a single include statement referencing a shared stylesheet. When
      a context is deployed, a copy of the shared and local stylesheets are pushed out to its Tomcat
      server, and the context compiles and caches a private set of Templates objects for execution.
      This means that the shared development model for stylesheets doesn't get carried all the way
      through to the runtime, and each site must allocate memory to compile and store a private copy
      of all the stylesheets.</textual></para><para class="po-block e125 e125"><textual class="po-textual">Firenze implements two levels of caching. The first is context-wide caching. Each
      context-wide cache records all retrieved documents, e.g., JAXP Source and Templates objects,
      as well as any documents generated and cached on-the-fly by the pipeline. These cached items
      are available for any subsequent requests that execute in the context. Each context-wide cache
      may have a specific cache-retention policy and algorithm associated with it, as well as its
      own implementation of a backing store. Currently a memory-based store is used, but we are in
      the processing of implementing a disk-based store as well (our intent is to create a two-tier
      memory and disk cache).</textual></para><para class="po-block e126 e126"><textual class="po-textual">Each context-wide cache then serves as a provider for request-specific caches. These
      request-specific caches store items in memory for the duration of a given request. The
      request-specific caches were originally developed to fulfill a contract implied by the XSLT
      specification, which requires that a document, once read via functions like </textual><code class="po-atom e127 e127"><textual class="po-textual">doc</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
      or </textual><code class="po-atom e128 e128"><textual class="po-textual">doc-available</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, remain immutable for the duration of the transformation. We've
      extended this policy to require that any document read during the execution of a pipeline
      remain unchanged for the duration of that request.</textual></para><para class="po-block e129 e129"><textual class="po-textual">Currently the sites implement a very straightforward context-wide caching policy. Any
      Templates object survives for the lifetime of the context, while most Source objects will
      survive for a lifetime of 30 minutes, or until the cache size has reached a 1,000 item size
      limit. Once the cache has reached its size limit, the addition of any new entries force the
      oldest Source objects to be evicted. In some cases we fine-tune the policy for Source objects,
      ensuring they will survive for the lifetime of the context, or by increasing or decreasing the
      size of the cache. This level of caching has proved to be sufficient, if not ideal, for our
      current level of traffic. The default cache policy is most effective for the scenario of a
      user who is looking at an abstract and then the full text of the article, or the scenario of a
      user scanning the abstracts of an Issue in sequential order, clicking from one abstract to the
      next within a fairly short period of time.</textual></para><para class="po-block e130 e130"><textual class="po-textual">To determine the response times for requests handled by Firenze, we examined 78 days'
      worth of Apache access logs, consisting of 727 million requests. These requests cover all
      types of requests, meaning it includes static file requests as well as dynamic page requests.
      We found that 214 million requests were dynamic, meaning that Firenze would have handled them.
      Examining the response times for those Firenze requests, we found the following response
      times: </textual><table class="po-container e131 e131"><caption class="po-container e132 e132"><para class="po-block e133 e133"><textual class="po-textual">Response Times for Firenze requests</textual></para></caption><thead class="po-container e134 e134"><tr class="po-table e135 e135"><th class="po-field e136 e136"><textual class="po-textual">Seconds</textual></th><th class="po-field e137 e137"><textual class="po-textual">Percent</textual></th></tr></thead><tbody class="po-table e138 e138"><tr class="po-table e139 e139"><td align="right" class="po-block e140 e140"><textual class="po-textual">&lt; 1</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e141 e141"><textual class="po-textual">84%</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e142 e142"><td align="right" class="po-block e143 e143"><textual class="po-textual">1 - 2</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e144 e144"><textual class="po-textual">8%</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e145 e145"><td align="right" class="po-block e146 e146"><textual class="po-textual">2 - 3</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e147 e147"><textual class="po-textual">3%</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e148 e148"><td align="right" class="po-block e149 e149"><textual class="po-textual">3 - 4</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e150 e150"><textual class="po-textual">2%</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e151 e151"><td align="right" class="po-block e152 e152"><textual class="po-textual">&gt; 4</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e153 e153"><textual class="po-textual">3%</textual></td></tr></tbody></table></para><para class="po-block e154 e154"><textual class="po-textual">This means that 92% of Firenze requests took less than 2 seconds to complete, 5% took from
      2 to 4 seconds to complete, and 3% took more than 4 seconds to complete. Our performance goal
      is to be able to serve all dynamic page requests, and any associated static content, within
      1.5 seconds, so we have not yet met our performance goals.</textual></para><para class="po-block e155 e155"><textual class="po-textual">We've been hosting sets of 15 to 20 sites per load-balanced cluster, with each cluster
      consisting of either two or five servers. Each server has 32 gigabytes of memory and between
      four and eight CPU cores operating between 2.3 and 2.5 GHz. CPU on the clusters is not heavily
      taxed; we routinely record only 15% to 25% CPU usage per server, even during peak traffic
      periods.</textual></para><para class="po-block e156 e156"><textual class="po-textual">By far the least efficient part of the Firenze system we've seen is its memory footprint.
      What we've seen is that each 32-gigabyte server may use 9 gigabytes of memory during the
      lowest traffic periods, up to 15 gigabytes of memory in normal traffic periods, and 30
      gigabytes during very high traffic periods. During normal traffic periods, memory use can
      cycle between 9 and 15 gigabytes within the space of a minute, with all the activity occurring
      in the Eden and Survivor spaces of the JVM. The need to allocate between one and two gigabytes
      of memory per site is a serious impediment to packing enough sites onto a machine to fully
      utilize the CPUs.</textual></para><para class="po-block e157 e157"><textual class="po-textual">In order to improve the response time of the Firenze layer, we are currently building
      Cache-Channel [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e158 e158" linkend="cc"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] support into Firenze, and are building a disk-based cache
      implementation. The disk-based cache will allow us to store dynamically generated components
      of pages for a longer period of time, and will be paired with the in-memory caches to take
      advantage of optimized Source representations.</textual></para><para class="po-block e159 e159"><textual class="po-textual">We also plan to implement an Adaptive Replacement Cache (ARC) [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e160 e160" linkend="arc"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]
      algorithm to replace the Least Recently Used (LRU) algorithm currently used by the in-memory
      cache. The HighWire sites receive a steady stream of traffic from indexing web-crawlers, and
      we've found that these crawlers tend to push highly-used resources out of cache when they
      start crawling large amounts of archival content.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e161 e161"><title class="po-block e162 e162"><textual class="po-textual">SASS</textual></title><para class="po-block e163 e163"><textual class="po-textual">Firenze can be thought of as a framework designed to aggregate data from multiple sources,
      and then to manipulate that aggregate data into a final form. We currently aggregate data from
      many different services, gathering information for access control, running search requests,
      gathering reference data, etc. One of the primary services that the sites use is the Schema,
      Addressing, and Storage System (SASS). A SASS service is a data store that provides a unified
      view of metadata and content for publications we host.</textual></para><para class="po-block e164 e164"><textual class="po-textual">One of the first decisions we needed to make when we were building the replacement system
      was how we would store metadata and related resources. Early on we mocked up a file-system
      based set of XML files along with an XQuery prototype that combined these files dynamically,
      feeding the combined resources to an XSLT-based display layer. These experiments proved to us
      that the fairly simple concept of using a hierarchy of XML files could actually provide enough
      flexibility and functionality for our needs. We decided we could replace some of the
      relational databases of our original system with a hierarchy of XML files. Our implementation
      of this, SASS, is the result of that decision.</textual></para><para class="po-block e165 e165"><textual class="po-textual">A SASS service uses an HTTP-based protocol we've defined, named HighWire Publishing
      Protocol (HPP), to handle requests. HPP is built on top of the Atom Publishing Protocol (APP),
      which specifies much of the basic functionality we needed for a database system:</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e166 e166"><listitem class="po-container e167 e167"><para class="po-block e168 e168"><textual class="po-textual">It specifies how resources are created, retrieved, updated, and deleted.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e169 e169"><para class="po-block e170 e170"><textual class="po-textual">It specifies the format of introspection documents, which provide configuration
            information.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e171 e171"><para class="po-block e172 e172"><textual class="po-textual">It specifies the output format for an aggregation of resources, using feeds of
            entries.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e173 e173"><para class="po-block e174 e174"><textual class="po-textual">It offers a flexible data model, allowing foreign namespaced elements and
            attributes.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para class="po-block e175 e175"><textual class="po-textual">After examining APP in detail, we decided we needed a little more functionality, and we
      concluded that we would adopt APP and then extend it in three ways. Our extensions give us the
      ability to:</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e176 e176"><listitem class="po-container e177 e177"><para class="po-block e178 e178"><textual class="po-textual">Add Atom entries with hierarchical parent/child relationships.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e179 e179"><para class="po-block e180 e180"><textual class="po-textual">Create multiple alternative representations of an Atom entry, called variants.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e181 e181"><para class="po-block e182 e182"><textual class="po-textual">Create relationship links between Atom entries.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para class="po-block e183 e183"><textual class="po-textual">As with APP, we have defined a form of XML-based introspection document, similar to an APP
      Service Document. These introspection documents define which collections exist and the types
      of resources the collections will accept. Because our HPP system allows every single Atom
      entry to potentially act as a service point to which new resources may be attached, every Atom
      entry references a unique introspection document. Each introspection document describes which
      content types and roles may be used for variant representations of the entry, and defines zero
      or more collections for sub-entries, with constraints regarding the types and roles of
      resources that may be added to each collection.</textual></para><para class="po-block e184 e184"><textual class="po-textual">Both client and server examine the introspection document, the client being responsible
      for evaluating which collection should best be used for a new resource it wishes to create,
      and the server to evaluate whether or not to allow a particular operation. Once the server has
      decided that a client's request to create a new resource is allowed, it further examines the
      introspection document to:</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e185 e185"><listitem class="po-container e186 e186"><para class="po-block e187 e187"><textual class="po-textual">Determine how to name the new resource.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e188 e188"><para class="po-block e189 e189"><textual class="po-textual">Determine what, if any, modifications need to be made to the new resource, e.g.,
            creating server-managed hyperlinks to its parent.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e190 e190"><para class="po-block e191 e191"><textual class="po-textual">Determine what other resources might need to be created or modified, e.g., creating
            reciprocal hyperlinks between resources or creating a new Atom sub-entry for a media
            resource.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para class="po-block e192 e192"><textual class="po-textual">An example slice of resource paths in our data store shows a top level entry, a journal
      entry (pnas), a volume (number 106) entry, an issue (number 27) entry and an article (page
      10879) entry, and a child (Figure 1) of the article.
      </textual><programlisting class="po-block e193 e193" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
/svc.atom
  /pnas.atom
    /pnas/106.atom
      /pnas/106/27.atom
      /pnas/106/27.cover-expansion.html
      /pnas/106/27.cover.gif
      /pnas/106/27/local/ed-board.atom
      /pnas/106/27/local/ed-board.pdf
      /pnas/106/27/local/masthead.atom
      /pnas/106/27/local/masthead.pdf
      /pnas/106/27/focus/e3fd854717680e79.atom
      /pnas/106/27/focus/528ef4747e7bd83a.atom
      /pnas/106/27/focus/a596193d15fdf2f0.atom
      /pnas/106/27/focus/05aacbb50196a10f.atom
      /pnas/106/27/focus/c1e857a34ad4b0f3.atom
        /pnas/106/27/10879.atom
        /pnas/106/27/10879.full.pdf
        /pnas/106/27/10879.full.html
        /pnas/106/27/10879.source.xml
        /pnas/106/27/10879.figures-only.html
          /pnas/106/27/10879/F1.atom
          /pnas/106/27/10879/F1.expansion.html
          /pnas/106/27/10879/F1.small.gif
          /pnas/106/27/10879/F1.medium.gif
          /pnas/106/27/10879/F1.large.jpg          
</textual></programlisting></para><para class="po-block e194 e194"><textual class="po-textual">Examining the extensions of the paths above, you will see a number of media types
      represented. The </textual><code class="po-atom e195 e195"><textual class="po-textual">.atom</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> files are metadata resources, while the </textual><code class="po-atom e196 e196"><textual class="po-textual">.xml</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">,
        </textual><code class="po-atom e197 e197"><textual class="po-textual">.html</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><code class="po-atom e198 e198"><textual class="po-textual">.gif</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><code class="po-atom e199 e199"><textual class="po-textual">.jpg</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, and </textual><code class="po-atom e200 e200"><textual class="po-textual">.pdf</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> files allow
      us to serve alternative representations (variants) of those resources. SASS therefore provides a
      unified system for serving metadata paired with an array of alternative
      representations.</textual></para><para class="po-block e201 e201"><textual class="po-textual">The system is intended to be flexible enough that we can model new relationships
      relatively quickly, and once those relationships are defined we can immediately start creating
      and serving the new resources and relationships. As an example, the hierarchy of relationships
      we originally designed was, in part:</textual><figure class="po-container e202 e202" floatstyle="1" xml:id="sass-model-1" xreflabel="Initial SASS Journal Model"><mediaobject class="po-container e203 e203"><imageobject class="po-container e204 e204"><imagedata class="po-meta e205 e205" fileref="../../../vol4/graphics/Robinson01/Robinson01-002.png" format="png" width="25%"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></para><para class="po-block e206 e206"><textual class="po-textual">This model allows one or more Journals, each Journal may have one or more Volumes, each
      Volume may have one or more Issues, etc. When we encountered a journal whose hierarchy didn't
      match this model, we simply edited the templates for the introspection documents. In this
      case, we edited it to allow for an Issue to be attached directly to a Journal:</textual><figure class="po-container e207 e207" floatstyle="1" xml:id="sass-model-2" xreflabel="Updated SASS Journal Model"><mediaobject class="po-container e208 e208"><imageobject class="po-container e209 e209"><imagedata class="po-meta e210 e210" fileref="../../../vol4/graphics/Robinson01/Robinson01-003.png" format="png" width="50%"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></para><para class="po-block e211 e211"><textual class="po-textual">When deciding how to implement SASS, we concluded early-on that we needed to provide both
      a read-only and a read/write service. The read-only SASS services would be used by the
      public-facing sites, and the read/write service would be used by our back-end publishing
      system. Splitting the services this way would allow us to optimize each service for its
      primary use-case: transactions and complicated searching would be needed in the read/write
      SASS service, but would not be needed in the read-only SASS service.</textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e212 e212"><title class="po-block e213 e213"><textual class="po-textual">Read-Only SASS</textual></title><para class="po-block e214 e214"><textual class="po-textual">Based on our early prototyping work, we were confident that we could develop a
        filesystem-based read-only implementation of the HPP protocol that would serve the needs of
        the public-facing sites. Currently we've implemented a read-only version of SASS using
        Firenze.</textual></para><para class="po-block e215 e215"><textual class="po-textual">The description of SASS to this point has only described the basic hierarchical layout
        of resources. To take advantage of this hierarchy, HPP defines ways to request an aggregated
        view of the metadata and content representations for a resource. Specifically, a set of
        parameters may be provided when requesting an Atom entry:</textual><table class="po-container e216 e216"><caption class="po-container e217 e217"><para class="po-block e218 e218"><textual class="po-textual">HPP Expansion Parameters</textual></para></caption><thead class="po-container e219 e219"><tr class="po-table e220 e220"><th class="po-field e221 e221"><textual class="po-textual">Parameter</textual></th><th class="po-field e222 e222"><textual class="po-textual">Example values</textual></th></tr></thead><tbody class="po-table e223 e223"><tr class="po-table e224 e224"><td class="po-block e225 e225"><textual class="po-textual">with-variant</textual></td><td class="po-block e226 e226"><textual class="po-textual">no, yes, 1</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e227 e227"><td class="po-block e228 e228"><textual class="po-textual">variant-role</textual></td><td class="po-block e229 e229"><textual class="po-textual">http://schema.highwire.org/variant/abstract,
                http://schema.highwire.org/variant/full-text, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e230 e230"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis></td></tr><tr class="po-table e231 e231"><td class="po-block e232 e232"><textual class="po-textual">variant-type</textual></td><td class="po-block e233 e233"><textual class="po-textual">application/xhtml+xml, application/pdf, application/*, video/*,
                  </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e234 e234"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis></td></tr><tr class="po-table e235 e235"><td class="po-block e236 e236"><textual class="po-textual">variant-lang</textual></td><td class="po-block e237 e237"><textual class="po-textual">en, fr, de, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e238 e238"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis></td></tr><tr class="po-table e239 e239"><td class="po-block e240 e240"><textual class="po-textual">with-ancestors</textual></td><td class="po-block e241 e241"><textual class="po-textual">no, yes, 1, 2, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e242 e242"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e243 e243"><textual class="po-textual">N</textual></emphasis></td></tr><tr class="po-table e244 e244"><td class="po-block e245 e245"><textual class="po-textual">with-ancestors-role</textual></td><td class="po-block e246 e246"><textual class="po-textual">http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Issue,
                http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Volume, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e247 e247"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis></td></tr><tr class="po-table e248 e248"><td class="po-block e249 e249"><textual class="po-textual">with-ancestors-content</textual></td><td class="po-block e250 e250"><textual class="po-textual">alternate, inline, out-of-line</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e251 e251"><td class="po-block e252 e252"><textual class="po-textual">with-ancestors-variant</textual></td><td class="po-block e253 e253"><textual class="po-textual">no, yes, 1, 2, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e254 e254"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e255 e255"><textual class="po-textual">N</textual></emphasis></td></tr><tr class="po-table e256 e256"><td class="po-block e257 e257"><textual class="po-textual">with-ancestors-variant-role</textual></td><td class="po-block e258 e258"><textual class="po-textual">http://schema.highwire.org/variant/cover,
                http://schema.highwire.org/variant/manifest, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e259 e259"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis></td></tr><tr class="po-table e260 e260"><td class="po-block e261 e261"><textual class="po-textual">with-ancestors-type</textual></td><td class="po-block e262 e262"><textual class="po-textual">image/gif, image/*, application/xml, text/* </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e263 e263"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis></td></tr><tr class="po-table e264 e264"><td class="po-block e265 e265"><textual class="po-textual">with-ancestors-lang</textual></td><td class="po-block e266 e266"><textual class="po-textual">en, fr, de, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e267 e267"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis></td></tr><tr class="po-table e268 e268"><td class="po-block e269 e269"><textual class="po-textual">with-descendants</textual></td><td class="po-block e270 e270"><textual class="po-textual">no, yes, 1, 2, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e271 e271"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e272 e272"><textual class="po-textual">N</textual></emphasis></td></tr><tr class="po-table e273 e273"><td class="po-block e274 e274"><textual class="po-textual">with-descendants-role</textual></td><td class="po-block e275 e275"><textual class="po-textual">http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Article,
                http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Fragment, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e276 e276"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis></td></tr><tr class="po-table e277 e277"><td class="po-block e278 e278"><textual class="po-textual">with-descendants-content</textual></td><td class="po-block e279 e279"><textual class="po-textual">alternate, inline, out-of-line</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e280 e280"><td class="po-block e281 e281"><textual class="po-textual">with-descendants-variant</textual></td><td class="po-block e282 e282"><textual class="po-textual">no, yes, 1, 2, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e283 e283"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e284 e284"><textual class="po-textual">N</textual></emphasis></td></tr><tr class="po-table e285 e285"><td class="po-block e286 e286"><textual class="po-textual">with-descendants-variant-role</textual></td><td class="po-block e287 e287"><textual class="po-textual">http://schema.highwire.org/variant/abstract,
                http://schema.highwire.org/variant/full-text</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e288 e288"><td class="po-block e289 e289"><textual class="po-textual">with-descendants-type</textual></td><td class="po-block e290 e290"><textual class="po-textual">application/xhtml+xml, application/pdf, application/*, video/*,
                  </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e291 e291"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis></td></tr><tr class="po-table e292 e292"><td class="po-block e293 e293"><textual class="po-textual">with-descendants-lang</textual></td><td class="po-block e294 e294"><textual class="po-textual">en, fr, de, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e295 e295"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></emphasis></td></tr></tbody></table></para><para class="po-block e296 e296"><textual class="po-textual">These parameters may be combined in variations and some may be repeated. Taken together,
        the parameters serve as a way to drive the expansion of a resource along its parent, child,
        and variant axes, returning a compound document consisting of an appropriate slice of the
        hierarchy. As an example, requesting
          </textual><code class="po-atom e297 e297"><textual class="po-textual">http://sass.highwire.org/pnas/106/27/10877.atom</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> will retrieve the Atom entry
        associated with PNAS Volume 106, Issue 27, Page 10877:</textual><programlisting class="po-block e298 e298" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">

  &lt;atom:entry xml:base="http://sass.highwire.org/pnas/106/27/10877.atom"
    nlm:article-type="article-commentary"  ...&gt;
     &lt;atom:link rel="http://schema.highwire.org/Compound#parent"
      href="/pnas/106/27.atom"
      c:role="http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Issue"/&gt;
     &lt;atom:category
       scheme="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing#role"
         term="http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Article"/&gt;
     &lt;atom:category
       scheme="http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Article#has-earlier-version"
         term="yes"/&gt;
     &lt;atom:id&gt;tag:pnas@highwire.org,2009-07-02:0905722106&lt;/atom:id&gt;
     &lt;atom:title&gt;Should Social Security numbers be replaced by modern, more secure identifiers?&lt;/atom:title&gt;
     &lt;atom:author nlm:contrib-type="author"&gt;
       &lt;atom:name&gt;William E. Winkler&lt;/atom:name&gt;
       &lt;atom:email&gt;william.e.winkler@census.gov&lt;/atom:email&gt;
       &lt;nlm:name name-style="western" hwp:sortable="Winkler William E."&gt;
         &lt;nlm:surname&gt;Winkler&lt;/nlm:surname&gt;
         &lt;nlm:given-names&gt;William E.&lt;/nlm:given-names&gt;
       &lt;/nlm:name&gt;
     &lt;/atom:author&gt;
     ...
     &lt;atom:link rel="alternate"
       href="/pnas/106/27/10877.full.pdf"
       c:role="http://schema.highwire.org/variant/full-text"  type="application/pdf"/&gt;
     &lt;atom:link rel="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing#edit-variant"
       href="/pnas/106/27/10877.full.pdf"
       c:role="http://schema.highwire.org/variant/full-text"    type="application/pdf"/&gt;
     &lt;atom:link rel="alternate"
       href="/pnas/106/27/10877.full.html"
       c:role="http://schema.highwire.org/variant/full-text" type="application/xhtml+xml"/&gt;
     &lt;atom:link rel="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing#edit-variant"
       href="/pnas/106/27/10877.full.html"
       c:role="http://schema.highwire.org/variant/full-text"    type="application/xhtml+xml"/&gt;
     ...
   &lt;/atom:entry&gt;
   </textual></programlisting><textual class="po-textual"> while adding the parameter to expand its ancestry axis in full,
          </textual><code class="po-atom e299 e299"><textual class="po-textual">http://sass.highwire.org/pnas/106/27/10877.atom?with-ancestors=yes</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">,
        additionally expands the Atom entries for the article's Issue, its Volume, etc:</textual><programlisting class="po-block e300 e300" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
   &lt;atom:entry xml:base="http://sass.highwire.org/pnas/106/27/10877.atom?with-ancestors=yes"
     nlm:article-type="article-commentary" ...&gt;
     &lt;c:parent xml:base="/pnas/106/27.atom"&gt;
       &lt;c:parent xml:base="/pnas/106.atom"&gt;
         &lt;c:parent xml:base="/pnas.atom"&gt;
           &lt;c:parent xml:base="/svc.atom"&gt;
             &lt;atom:category
              scheme="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing#role"
                term="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing/Service"/&gt;
             &lt;atom:id&gt;http://atom.highwire.org/&lt;/atom:id&gt;
             &lt;atom:title&gt;HighWire Atom Store&lt;/atom:title&gt;
             ...
            &lt;/c:parent&gt;
           &lt;atom:category
            scheme="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing#role"
              term="http://schema.highwire.org/Journal"/&gt;
           &lt;atom:id&gt;doi:10.1073/pnas&lt;/atom:id&gt;
           &lt;atom:title&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/atom:title&gt;
           &lt;atom:author&gt;
             &lt;atom:name&gt;National Academy of Sciences&lt;/atom:name&gt;
           &lt;/atom:author&gt;
           ...
         &lt;/c:parent&gt;
         &lt;atom:category
          scheme="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing#role"
            term="http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Volume"/&gt;
         &lt;atom:id&gt;tag:pnas@highwire.org,2009-01-06:106&lt;/atom:id&gt;
         &lt;atom:title&gt;106&lt;/atom:title&gt;
         &lt;atom:author nlm:contrib-type="publisher"&gt;
           &lt;atom:name&gt;National Academy of Sciences&lt;/atom:name&gt;
         &lt;/atom:author&gt;
         ...
       &lt;/c:parent&gt;
       &lt;atom:category
        scheme="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing#role"
          term="http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Issue"/&gt;
       &lt;atom:id&gt;tag:pnas@highwire.org,2009-06-11:106/27&lt;/atom:id&gt;
       &lt;atom:title&gt;106 (27)&lt;/atom:title&gt;
       &lt;atom:author nlm:contrib-type="publisher"&gt;
         &lt;atom:name&gt;National Academy of Sciences&lt;/atom:name&gt;
       &lt;/atom:author&gt;
       ...
     &lt;/c:parent&gt;
     &lt;atom:category
      scheme="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing#role"
        term="http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Article"/&gt;
     &lt;atom:category
      scheme="http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Article#has-earlier-version"
        term="yes"/&gt;
     &lt;atom:id&gt;tag:pnas@highwire.org,2009-07-02:0905722106&lt;/atom:id&gt;
     &lt;atom:title&gt;Should Social Security numbers be replaced by modern, more secure identifiers?&lt;/atom:title&gt;
     &lt;atom:author nlm:contrib-type="author"&gt;
       &lt;atom:name&gt;William E. Winkler&lt;/atom:name&gt;
       &lt;atom:email&gt;william.e.winkler@census.gov&lt;/atom:email&gt;
       &lt;nlm:name name-style="western" hwp:sortable="Winkler William E."&gt;
         &lt;nlm:surname&gt;Winkler&lt;/nlm:surname&gt;
         &lt;nlm:given-names&gt;William E.&lt;/nlm:given-names&gt;
       &lt;/nlm:name&gt;
     &lt;/atom:author&gt;
    ...
    &lt;atom:link rel="alternate"
      href="/pnas/106/27/10877.full.pdf" type="application/pdf"
      c:role="http://schema.highwire.org/variant/full-text"/&gt;
    &lt;atom:link rel="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing#edit-variant"
      href="/pnas/106/27/10877.full.pdf"
      c:role="http://schema.highwire.org/variant/full-text"   type="application/pdf"/&gt;
    &lt;atom:link rel="alternate"
      href="/pnas/106/27/10877.full.html"
      c:role="http://schema.highwire.org/variant/full-text" type="application/xhtml+xml"/&gt;
    &lt;atom:link rel="http://schema.highwire.org/Publishing#edit-variant"
      href="/pnas/106/27/10877.full.html"
      c:role="http://schema.highwire.org/variant/full-text" type="application/xhtml+xml"/&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/atom:entry&gt;  
</textual></programlisting></para><para class="po-block e301 e301"><textual class="po-textual">The difference between the two documents is that the parent link in the entry:</textual><programlisting class="po-block e302 e302" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">

     &lt;atom:link rel="http://schema.highwire.org/Compound#parent"
       href="/pnas/106/27.atom" c:role="http://schema.highwire.org/Journal/Issue"/&gt;
</textual></programlisting><textual class="po-textual"> has been expanded into an element </textual><programlisting class="po-block e303 e303" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
     &lt;c:parent xml:base="/pnas/106/27.atom"&gt;...&lt;/c:parent&gt;
</textual></programlisting></para><para class="po-block e304 e304"><textual class="po-textual">Because the with-ancestors value was </textual><code class="po-atom e305 e305"><textual class="po-textual">yes</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, each entry has had its parent
        link expanded into a </textual><code class="po-atom e306 e306"><textual class="po-textual">c:parent</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> element, pulling in metadata all the way up to
        the root of the hierarchy.</textual></para><para class="po-block e307 e307"><textual class="po-textual">Likewise, a client may also request </textual><code class="po-atom e308 e308"><textual class="po-textual">with-descendants</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, and a common request
        sent by the sites is for a Journal Issue with its ancestors expanded completely, and its
        descendants expanded to a depth of one. This in effect gives them the metadata for the Issue
        and its Article children, from which they may do things like build a Table of Contents
        page.</textual></para><para class="po-block e309 e309"><textual class="po-textual">In effect, these parameters allow us to perform operations somewhat like a join
        operation in a relational database. If you think of the Atom entries as relational tables,
        and atom:link elements as foreign keys, we have a limited ability to join documents
        together on those keys.</textual></para><para class="po-block e310 e310"><textual class="po-textual">The read-only SASS service hosts an Apache front-end, load-balancing requests to a set
        of four Tomcat servers. Each Tomcat server uses two AMD 1210 cores, 8 gigabytes of memory,
        and two local SATA disks. Each Tomcat server runs Firenze to execute the read-only SASS
        service stylesheets. The stylesheets in turn pull data from a service named SASSFS, running
        on an Apache-only server using four AMD 2218 CPU cores, 32 gigabytes of memory, and 3.7
        terabytes of FC attached SATA storage. The SASSFS service holds a synchronized clone of the
        read/write SASS service. The SASSFS system is, in effect, a network-based storage system for
        SASS, accessed over HTTP instead of a more traditional NFS protocol.</textual></para><para class="po-block e311 e311"><textual class="po-textual">The XSLT implementation of read-only SASS consists just under 5,000 lines of XSLT 2.0
        code (including whitespace and comments), spread across a set of 13 stylesheets. About 2,000
        of those lines of code are an interim prototype for disk-based caching.</textual></para><para class="po-block e312 e312"><textual class="po-textual">Our initial version of the read-only SASS service used the default in-memory caching
        available in Firenze. This default would store the most recent 1,000 resources requested
        from SASSFS in memory as Source document (the underlying representation being a Saxon
        TinyTree). This caching proved to be effective, and the service performed very well under
        high load. While we were satisfied with the performance, we knew that we wanted to implement
        a more effective caching algorithm for Firenze as a whole, and we decided to use the
        read-only SASS service as a test-bed for prototyping part of this work.</textual></para><para class="po-block e313 e313"><textual class="po-textual">Because HighWire hosts a great deal of material that does not change very often, we
        wanted to implement a caching system that could take advantage of the fact that most of our
        material is for all intents and purposes written once and then read many times. Our research
        turned up the Cache-Channel specification, describing a method where clients could poll an
        efficient service to detect when cached items were stale. If we implemented this system, we
        could cache responses built by the SASS service and, for the most part, never have to update
        them again. Thus, we could trade disk space for time, allowing us to short circuit almost
        all processing within the Firenze system when we had a cached response available</textual></para><para class="po-block e314 e314"><textual class="po-textual">To prototype this work, we implemented a set of extensions for Saxon that allowed us to
        write serialized XML to a local disk partition. When an incoming request could be fulfilled
        by the cache, we could simply stream the data from disk, bypassing the bulk of the XSLT
        processing we would otherwise have to perform.</textual></para><para class="po-block e315 e315"><textual class="po-textual">In the XSLT prototype, the </textual><code class="po-atom e316 e316"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> representation of the HTTP request
        is processed via the following steps:</textual><orderedlist class="po-table e317 e317"><listitem class="po-container e318 e318"><para class="po-block e319 e319"><textual class="po-textual">Examine the HTTP PATH of the </textual><code class="po-atom e320 e320"><textual class="po-textual">req:request</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and check that the resource
              is available on SASSFS; if it is not, return a not-found error code.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e321 e321"><para class="po-block e322 e322"><textual class="po-textual">If the media type of the requested resource is not XML, stream the resource from
              SASSFS to the client.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e323 e323"><para class="po-block e324 e324"><textual class="po-textual">If the resource is not in cache, build the response. SASS reads resources from
              SASSFS, storing the resources in local cache. Using the resources fetched from SASSFS,
              the SASS service builds an XML </textual><code class="po-atom e325 e325"><textual class="po-textual">rsp:response</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, and stores that response in
              cache. Each resource written to the cache is accompanied by a corresponding XML
              metadata file.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e326 e326"><para class="po-block e327 e327"><textual class="po-textual">If the resource was in cache, check the metadata and perform HTTP HEAD requests
              against SASSFS to see whether or not the item needs to be rebuilt. The rebuild would
              be needed if any one of the constituent resources on SASSFS have changed. If nothing
              has changed, stream the response from disk to the client. Otherwise a
                </textual><code class="po-atom e328 e328"><textual class="po-textual">rsp:response</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> is built as in step #3.</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist></para><para class="po-block e329 e329"><textual class="po-textual">For the XSLT-based prototype work, we decided not to implement the actual Cache-Channel
        client or to hook into the in-memory cache of frequently used Source objects. We would
        tackle these items later, when we implemented the caching logic in Java.</textual></para><para class="po-block e330 e330"><textual class="po-textual">We expected this prototype to be slower than the original implementation, both because
        Firenze would now need to be parsing XML from disk for every request, instead of simply
        reusing cached Source objects, and because we would be polling SASSFS to see if a resource
        had changed.</textual></para><para class="po-block e331 e331"><textual class="po-textual">Our initial analysis of the prototype's performance simply examined the average response
        time across all requests.  We were very unpleasantly surprised to find that for single Atom
        entries the average response time jumped from 0.031 seconds to 0.21 seconds. The average
        response times for compound entries jumped from 0.05 seconds to 0.26 seconds. Looking at
        those averages, we decided we needed to know whether or not the slowdown was across the
        board, or whether the averages reflected large outliers.</textual></para><para class="po-block e332 e332"><textual class="po-textual">We examined response times for a day's worth of requests using each of the two caching
        implementations, and sorted the requests into two categories. One category was for requests
        that would return a single resource, effectively a transfer of a file from SASSFS to the
        client via SASS, with some cleanup processing applied. The second category was for requests
        that returned compound resources. These were resources built by SASS, using component
        resources fetched from SASSFS. We examined the response time for these requests, and sorted
        them into percentiles:</textual><table class="po-container e333 e333"><caption class="po-container e334 e334"><para class="po-block e335 e335"><textual class="po-textual">SASS Response Times in Seconds per Cache implementation</textual></para></caption><thead class="po-container e336 e336"><tr class="po-table e337 e337"><th class="po-field e338 e338"><textual class="po-textual"> </textual></th><th class="po-field e339 e339" colspan="2"><textual class="po-textual">Native Firenze Cache</textual></th><th class="po-field e340 e340" colspan="2"><textual class="po-textual">XSLT Prototype Disk Cache</textual></th></tr><tr class="po-table e341 e341"><th class="po-field e342 e342"><textual class="po-textual">Percentile</textual></th><th class="po-field e343 e343"><textual class="po-textual">Single</textual></th><th class="po-field e344 e344"><textual class="po-textual">Compound</textual></th><th class="po-field e345 e345"><textual class="po-textual">Single</textual></th><th class="po-field e346 e346"><textual class="po-textual">Compound</textual></th></tr></thead><tbody class="po-table e347 e347"><tr class="po-table e348 e348"><td align="right" class="po-block e349 e349"><textual class="po-textual">25%</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e350 e350"><textual class="po-textual">0.0181</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e351 e351"><textual class="po-textual">0.0212</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e352 e352"><textual class="po-textual">0.0262</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e353 e353"><textual class="po-textual">0.0266</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e354 e354"><td align="right" class="po-block e355 e355"><textual class="po-textual">50%</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e356 e356"><textual class="po-textual">0.0228</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e357 e357"><textual class="po-textual">0.0346</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e358 e358"><textual class="po-textual">0.0385</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e359 e359"><textual class="po-textual">0.0616</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e360 e360"><td align="right" class="po-block e361 e361"><textual class="po-textual">75%</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e362 e362"><textual class="po-textual">0.0299</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e363 e363"><textual class="po-textual">0.0609</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e364 e364"><textual class="po-textual">0.0785</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e365 e365"><textual class="po-textual">0.1121</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e366 e366"><td align="right" class="po-block e367 e367"><textual class="po-textual">95%</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e368 e368"><textual class="po-textual">0.0562</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e369 e369"><textual class="po-textual">0.0956</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e370 e370"><textual class="po-textual">0.7691</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e371 e371"><textual class="po-textual">1.0838</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e372 e372"><td align="right" class="po-block e373 e373"><textual class="po-textual">99%</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e374 e374"><textual class="po-textual">0.1434</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e375 e375"><textual class="po-textual">0.2134</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e376 e376"><textual class="po-textual">4.3750</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e377 e377"><textual class="po-textual">4.7483</textual></td></tr></tbody></table></para><para class="po-block e378 e378"><textual class="po-textual">This analysis shows that the disk-caching prototype was 1-2.5 times slower than the
        memory-based cache for about 75% of the requests, but that performance was significantly
        worse for the remaining 25% of the requests.</textual></para><para class="po-block e379 e379"><textual class="po-textual">What we discovered were two bottlenecks occurring with the prototype. The first, and
        most significant, bottleneck was the IO subsystem. The hardware on our machines couldn't
        keep up with the level of read/write activity being asked of them. When measuring the disk
        activity, we found it was operating at around 700 block writes per second and around 100
        block reads per second. This level of activity was overwhelming the 7,200 rpm SATA disks
        used by the servers, causing high IO wait times.</textual></para><para class="po-block e380 e380"><textual class="po-textual">The second bottleneck turned out to be the portion of XSLT code responsible for
        executing HTTP HEAD requests to determine whether or not a resource had changed. When we
        profiled the application on a stand-alone machine (eliminating disk contention), we found
        that the following snippet of code was responsible for 30% of the execution time:</textual><programlisting class="po-block e381 e381" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
    &lt;xsl:sequence select="
      some $m in $cache:metadata
      satisfies cache:is-stale($m)" /&gt;
</textual></programlisting></para><para class="po-block e382 e382"><textual class="po-textual">The </textual><code class="po-atom e383 e383"><textual class="po-textual">cache:is-stale</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> function takes as an argument a small XML metadata
        element storing a URL, a timestamp, and an HTTP ETag value. The function executes an HTTP
        HEAD request against the URL to determine whether or not the resource has been modified.
        As Saxon does not take heavy advantage of multi-threading, this XPath expression
        ends up running serially. Because underlying resources don't change very often, the
        algorithm usually ends up running through every metadata element only to find nothing has
        changed.</textual></para><para class="po-block e384 e384"><textual class="po-textual">These discoveries were actually good news to us, as we knew that we could both reduce
        disk contention and parallelize the check for stale resources when we implemented the code
        in Java as a native Firenze service. We're in the process of completing this work, and in
        the meantime we have rolled the XSLT prototype code into active service.</textual></para><para class="po-block e385 e385"><textual class="po-textual">Performance of the prototype has proven to be adequate. Examining 12 days of access logs
        from read-only SASS, the service is handling an average of 5.9 million requests per day,
        ranging from a low of 3.3 million requests to a high of 7.8 million requests. On average the
        service is processing 70 requests per second, writing 3.5 megabytes per second to its
        clients.</textual></para><para class="po-block e386 e386"><textual class="po-textual">Overall the read-only SASS service is serving an average of 266 gigabytes per day.
        Because SASS serves both XML markup and binary data, and because binary data may be streamed
        directly from the SASSFS system without any intermediate processing by SASS, only a subset
        of those 266 gigabytes is XML processed via Firenze. A breakdown of the two types of content
        shows we serve an average of 166 gigabytes of XML data per day, and an average of 100
        gigabytes of binary data:</textual><table class="po-container e387 e387"><caption class="po-container e388 e388"><para class="po-block e389 e389"><textual class="po-textual">Gigabytes served per day by read-only SASS</textual></para></caption><thead class="po-container e390 e390"><tr class="po-table e391 e391"><th class="po-field e392 e392"><textual class="po-textual">Date</textual></th><th class="po-field e393 e393"><textual class="po-textual">XML</textual></th><th class="po-field e394 e394"><textual class="po-textual">Binary</textual></th><th class="po-field e395 e395"><textual class="po-textual">Total</textual></th></tr></thead><tbody class="po-table e396 e396"><tr class="po-table e397 e397"><td align="right" class="po-block e398 e398"><textual class="po-textual">2009-07-01</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e399 e399"><textual class="po-textual">193.05</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e400 e400"><textual class="po-textual">122.33</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e401 e401"><textual class="po-textual">315.38</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e402 e402"><td align="right" class="po-block e403 e403"><textual class="po-textual">2009-07-02</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e404 e404"><textual class="po-textual">179.54</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e405 e405"><textual class="po-textual">114.36</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e406 e406"><textual class="po-textual">293.90</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e407 e407"><td align="right" class="po-block e408 e408"><textual class="po-textual">2009-07-03</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e409 e409"><textual class="po-textual">132.53</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e410 e410"><textual class="po-textual">87.73</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e411 e411"><textual class="po-textual">220.26</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e412 e412"><td align="right" class="po-block e413 e413"><textual class="po-textual">2009-07-04</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e414 e414"><textual class="po-textual">88.69</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e415 e415"><textual class="po-textual">60.18</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e416 e416"><textual class="po-textual">148.87</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e417 e417"><td align="right" class="po-block e418 e418"><textual class="po-textual">2009-07-05</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e419 e419"><textual class="po-textual">111.07</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e420 e420"><textual class="po-textual">69.61</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e421 e421"><textual class="po-textual">180.68</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e422 e422"><td align="right" class="po-block e423 e423"><textual class="po-textual">2009-07-06</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e424 e424"><textual class="po-textual">197.56</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e425 e425"><textual class="po-textual">124.15</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e426 e426"><textual class="po-textual">321.71</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e427 e427"><td align="right" class="po-block e428 e428"><textual class="po-textual">2009-07-07</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e429 e429"><textual class="po-textual">221.43</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e430 e430"><textual class="po-textual">141.19</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e431 e431"><textual class="po-textual">362.61</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e432 e432"><td align="right" class="po-block e433 e433"><textual class="po-textual">2009-07-08</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e434 e434"><textual class="po-textual">228.73</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e435 e435"><textual class="po-textual">142.96</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e436 e436"><textual class="po-textual">371.69</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e437 e437"><td align="right" class="po-block e438 e438"><textual class="po-textual">2009-07-09</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e439 e439"><textual class="po-textual">215.75</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e440 e440"><textual class="po-textual">123.90</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e441 e441"><textual class="po-textual">339.65</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e442 e442"><td align="right" class="po-block e443 e443"><textual class="po-textual">2009-07-10</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e444 e444"><textual class="po-textual">178.74</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e445 e445"><textual class="po-textual">97.77</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e446 e446"><textual class="po-textual">276.51</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e447 e447"><td align="right" class="po-block e448 e448"><textual class="po-textual">2009-07-11</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e449 e449"><textual class="po-textual">115.11</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e450 e450"><textual class="po-textual">48.31</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e451 e451"><textual class="po-textual">163.42</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e452 e452"><td align="right" class="po-block e453 e453"><textual class="po-textual">2009-07-12</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e454 e454"><textual class="po-textual">134.76</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e455 e455"><textual class="po-textual">67.93</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e456 e456"><textual class="po-textual">202.68</textual></td></tr></tbody></table></para><para class="po-block e457 e457"><textual class="po-textual">It has proven difficult to compare these numbers against our older system because the
        SASS service combines services that are spread out across multiple database and NFS servers
        in the older system.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e458 e458"><title class="po-block e459 e459"><textual class="po-textual">Read/Write SASS</textual></title><para class="po-block e460 e460"><textual class="po-textual">In order to implement the read/write SASS service, we knew we needed to build a
        transactional system. We had to be able to know that we could roll back any operation that
        met with an error condition. In addition, we wanted a system that would allow us to search
        the XML documents without needing to write custom code or build new indexes for every new
        query we might come up with.</textual></para><para class="po-block e461 e461"><textual class="po-textual">After exploring the available systems, we decided to license the XML server provided by
        Mark Logic Corporation. In addition, since both the MarkLogic Server and its underlying
        XQuery technology were new to us, we contracted with Mark Logic for consultants to work with
        us to build an implementation of our HPP specification. HighWire staff provided details
        regarding the specification and Mark Logic consultants wrote an implementation in XQuery.
        The implementation was written in just under 7,600 lines of XQuery code, spread across 24
        modules.</textual></para><para class="po-block e462 e462"><textual class="po-textual">We're currently running MarkLogic Server version 3.2, which is a few years old, and
        which uses a draft version of XQuery. Newer releases of MarkLogic implement the XQuery 1.0
        specification, and we plan to eventually modify the XQuery implementation to take advantage
        of the newer releases.</textual></para><para class="po-block e463 e463"><textual class="po-textual">We are currently running the MarkLogic implementation on one dedicated production server
        using four AMD 2218 CPU cores, 32 gigabytes of memory, and 3.7 terabytes of FC attached SATA
        storage. This server is currently handling between 7 to 8 million requests per month, and is
        used as the system of record for our production processing system. The break-down of those
        requests for the months of April, May, and Jun in 2009 were:</textual><table class="po-container e464 e464"><caption class="po-container e465 e465"><para class="po-block e466 e466"><textual class="po-textual">Number of requests to SASS read/write service</textual></para></caption><thead class="po-container e467 e467"><tr class="po-table e468 e468"><th class="po-field e469 e469"><textual class="po-textual">Type</textual></th><th class="po-field e470 e470"><textual class="po-textual">April</textual></th><th class="po-field e471 e471"><textual class="po-textual">May</textual></th><th class="po-field e472 e472"><textual class="po-textual">Jun</textual></th></tr></thead><tbody class="po-table e473 e473"><tr class="po-table e474 e474"><td class="po-block e475 e475"><textual class="po-textual">GET (non-search)</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e476 e476"><textual class="po-textual">7,199,235</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e477 e477"><textual class="po-textual">5,852,764</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e478 e478"><textual class="po-textual">5,900,093</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e479 e479"><td class="po-block e480 e480"><textual class="po-textual">GET (search)</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e481 e481"><textual class="po-textual">642,681</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e482 e482"><textual class="po-textual">521,106</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e483 e483"><textual class="po-textual">751,463</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e484 e484"><td class="po-block e485 e485"><textual class="po-textual">GET (report)</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e486 e486"><textual class="po-textual">23,308</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e487 e487"><textual class="po-textual">10,461</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e488 e488"><textual class="po-textual">16,919</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e489 e489"><td class="po-block e490 e490"><textual class="po-textual">POST </textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e491 e491"><textual class="po-textual">1,097,209</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e492 e492"><textual class="po-textual">730,489</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e493 e493"><textual class="po-textual">913,385</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e494 e494"><td class="po-block e495 e495"><textual class="po-textual">PUT </textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e496 e496"><textual class="po-textual">21,214</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e497 e497"><textual class="po-textual">10,284</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e498 e498"><textual class="po-textual">26,905</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e499 e499"><td class="po-block e500 e500"><textual class="po-textual">DELETE </textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e501 e501"><textual class="po-textual">9,989</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e502 e502"><textual class="po-textual">4,652</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e503 e503"><textual class="po-textual">35,143</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e504 e504"><th class="po-field e505 e505"><textual class="po-textual">Total Requests</textual></th><td align="right" class="po-block e506 e506"><textual class="po-textual">8,993,636</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e507 e507"><textual class="po-textual">7,129,756</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e508 e508"><textual class="po-textual">7,643,908</textual></td></tr></tbody></table><orderedlist class="po-table e509 e509"><listitem class="po-container e510 e510"><para class="po-block e511 e511"><textual class="po-textual">GET (non-search) reflects the retrieval of a single Atom entry or variant</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e512 e512"><para class="po-block e513 e513"><textual class="po-textual">GET (search) reflects the execution of a search</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e514 e514"><para class="po-block e515 e515"><textual class="po-textual">GET (report) reflects the execution of custom reporting modules we've
              written</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist></para><para class="po-block e516 e516"><textual class="po-textual">What these numbers translate to is the loading of between 40,000 to 50,000 articles per
        month, though in our first month of operations, when we were migrating PNAS, we loaded
        93,829 articles that month alone.</textual></para><para class="po-block e517 e517"><textual class="po-textual">As of Jun 18th 2009, the read/write SASS service held the following counts of resource
        types (there are others, but these are the ones whose counts may be of general interest):</textual><table class="po-container e518 e518"><caption class="po-container e519 e519"><para class="po-block e520 e520"><textual class="po-textual">read/write SASS service resource counts</textual></para></caption><thead class="po-container e521 e521"><tr class="po-table e522 e522"><th class="po-field e523 e523"><textual class="po-textual">Resource Type</textual></th><th class="po-field e524 e524"><textual class="po-textual">Count</textual></th></tr></thead><tbody class="po-table e525 e525"><tr class="po-table e526 e526"><td class="po-block e527 e527"><textual class="po-textual">Journal/Volume</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e528 e528"><textual class="po-textual">2,735</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e529 e529"><td class="po-block e530 e530"><textual class="po-textual">Journal/Issue</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e531 e531"><textual class="po-textual">17,734</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e532 e532"><td class="po-block e533 e533"><textual class="po-textual">Journal/Article</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e534 e534"><textual class="po-textual">421,375</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e535 e535"><td class="po-block e536 e536"><textual class="po-textual">Journal/Fragment</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e537 e537"><textual class="po-textual">485,792</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e538 e538"><td class="po-block e539 e539"><textual class="po-textual">Adjunct</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e540 e540"><textual class="po-textual">99,121</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e541 e541"><td class="po-block e542 e542"><textual class="po-textual">All variants</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e543 e543"><textual class="po-textual">3,511,002</textual></td></tr></tbody></table></para><para class="po-block e544 e544"><textual class="po-textual">In the table above, Journal/Volume, Journal/Issue, and Journal/Article resources
        correspond to the obvious parts of a journal. Journal/Fragment resources indicate resources
        extracted from an article to create a sub-resource, in this case they are representations of
        figures and tables. Adjuncts are media resources that provide supplemental data to article
        (e.g., raw data sets submitted along with an article). All variants consist of alternative
        representations, including XHTML files, PDFs, images, etc.</textual></para><para class="po-block e545 e545"><textual class="po-textual">In general we've found the performance of MarkLogic to be very good, and have not yet
        reached the level of use that would require us to add additional servers. When we do reach
        that point, an important advantage we see in MarkLogic was that we ought be able to increase
        capacity by simply creating a MarkLogic cluster of multiple servers.</textual></para><para class="po-block e546 e546"><textual class="po-textual">There are two areas where MarkLogic has had some trouble with our particular application:</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e547 e547"><listitem class="po-container e548 e548"><para class="po-block e549 e549"><textual class="po-textual">Complex DELETE operations are slow</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e550 e550"><para class="po-block e551 e551"><textual class="po-textual">Some ad-hoc XQuery reporting may be resource intensive depending on the
              expressions used.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para class="po-block e552 e552"><textual class="po-textual">In MarkLogic, individual delete transactions are very efficient, but to properly
        implement a DELETE operation in SASS the application executes an expensive traversal
        algorithm, building a list of resources, including:</textual><orderedlist class="po-table e553 e553"><listitem class="po-container e554 e554"><para class="po-block e555 e555"><textual class="po-textual">Resources that are children of the targeted resource. </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e556 e556"><para class="po-block e557 e557"><textual class="po-textual">Resources that refer to the resource targeted for deletion or to any of its child
              resources.</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist><textual class="po-textual">The application then needs to delete all the descendant resources and remove
        all references to those deleted resources. Deleting a single article could require that the
        application perform a dozen searches, delete fifty resources, and then update all Atom
        entries that refer to those deleted resources. This algorithm is costly to execute, and it
        makes DELETE far slower than the other operations.</textual></para><para class="po-block e558 e558"><textual class="po-textual">For each type of HTTP operation a selection for 5,000 log entries were examined for
        their execution times:</textual><table class="po-container e559 e559"><caption class="po-container e560 e560"><para class="po-block e561 e561"><textual class="po-textual">Seconds to complete a request</textual></para></caption><thead class="po-container e562 e562"><tr class="po-table e563 e563"><th class="po-field e564 e564" colspan="4"><textual class="po-textual"> </textual></th><th align="center" class="po-field e565 e565" colspan="3"><textual class="po-textual">Percentiles</textual></th></tr><tr class="po-table e566 e566"><th class="po-field e567 e567"><textual class="po-textual">Type</textual></th><th class="po-field e568 e568"><textual class="po-textual">Mean</textual></th><th class="po-field e569 e569"><textual class="po-textual">Minimum</textual></th><th class="po-field e570 e570"><textual class="po-textual">Maximum</textual></th><th class="po-field e571 e571"><textual class="po-textual">50%</textual></th><th class="po-field e572 e572"><textual class="po-textual">75%</textual></th><th class="po-field e573 e573"><textual class="po-textual">99%</textual></th></tr></thead><tbody class="po-table e574 e574"><tr class="po-table e575 e575"><td class="po-block e576 e576"><textual class="po-textual">GET (non-search)</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e577 e577"><textual class="po-textual">0.0397</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e578 e578"><textual class="po-textual">0.0073</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e579 e579"><textual class="po-textual">3.6032</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e580 e580"><textual class="po-textual">0.0133</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e581 e581"><textual class="po-textual">0.0328</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e582 e582"><textual class="po-textual">0.2670</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e583 e583"><td class="po-block e584 e584"><textual class="po-textual">GET (search)</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e585 e585"><textual class="po-textual">0.4611</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e586 e586"><textual class="po-textual">0.0098</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e587 e587"><textual class="po-textual">23.9744</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e588 e588"><textual class="po-textual">0.2342</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e589 e589"><textual class="po-textual">0.3818</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e590 e590"><textual class="po-textual">3.9794</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e591 e591"><td class="po-block e592 e592"><textual class="po-textual">POST</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e593 e593"><textual class="po-textual">0.0775</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e594 e594"><textual class="po-textual">0.0259</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e595 e595"><textual class="po-textual">0.5822</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e596 e596"><textual class="po-textual">0.0592</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e597 e597"><textual class="po-textual">0.0977</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e598 e598"><textual class="po-textual">0.1750</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e599 e599"><td class="po-block e600 e600"><textual class="po-textual">PUT</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e601 e601"><textual class="po-textual">0.1304</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e602 e602"><textual class="po-textual">0.0159</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e603 e603"><textual class="po-textual">4.3666</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e604 e604"><textual class="po-textual">0.0897</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e605 e605"><textual class="po-textual">0.1487</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e606 e606"><textual class="po-textual">0.6931</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e607 e607"><td class="po-block e608 e608"><textual class="po-textual">DELETE</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e609 e609"><textual class="po-textual">6.1802</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e610 e610"><textual class="po-textual">0.0084</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e611 e611"><textual class="po-textual">628.9670</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e612 e612"><textual class="po-textual">3.4020</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e613 e613"><textual class="po-textual">4.1776</textual></td><td align="right" class="po-block e614 e614"><textual class="po-textual">33.2024</textual></td></tr></tbody></table><orderedlist class="po-table e615 e615"><listitem class="po-container e616 e616"><para class="po-block e617 e617"><textual class="po-textual">GET (non-search) reflects the retrieval of a single Atom entry or a variant</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e618 e618"><para class="po-block e619 e619"><textual class="po-textual">GET (search) reflects the execution of a search</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist></para><para class="po-block e620 e620"><textual class="po-textual">Performance is excellent for the GET (non-search), POST, and PUT operations, and fairly
        good for GET (search), but DELETE operations are far slower than any other operation. The
        intrinsic problem with handling a DELETE is the complexity of the algorithm and the number
        of documents that need to be searched and modified. In theory we ought to be able to
        optimize how the searches are performed, implementing a more efficient algorithm, thereby
        speeding up the execution. Because DELETE operations make up such a small number of the
        requests we execute, we have not yet seriously investigated implementing such an
        optimization.</textual></para><para class="po-block e621 e621"><textual class="po-textual">The other problem area we've had with MarkLogic is constructing efficient ad-hoc
        queries. MarkLogic automatically creates indexes for any XML that it stores, and while these
        indexes cover many types of possible queries, it is possible to construct queries that do
        not take advantage of these indexes. At various times we want to run ad-hoc reports against
        the database, and we've found that some of these queries can time out if they are written
        without applying some knowledge of how the server's query optimizer work. Given the
        structure of our XML, for some of our ad-hoc queries, a challenge has been that our version
        of MarkLogic Server will not use an index if the expression is within nested predicates. As
        an example, if we have an index built on the two attributes </textual><code class="po-atom e622 e622"><textual class="po-textual">@scheme</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and
          </textual><code class="po-atom e623 e623"><textual class="po-textual">@term</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> for </textual><code class="po-atom e624 e624"><textual class="po-textual">atom:category</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> in an Atom entry, which together
        function as a key/value pair:</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e625 e625"><listitem class="po-container e626 e626"><para class="po-block e627 e627"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><code class="po-atom e628 e628"><textual class="po-textual">/atom:entry/atom:category/@scheme</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e629 e629"><para class="po-block e630 e630"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><code class="po-atom e631 e631"><textual class="po-textual">/atom:entry/atom:category/@term</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><textual class="po-textual"> as well as on the element:</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e632 e632"><listitem class="po-container e633 e633"><para class="po-block e634 e634"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><code class="po-atom e635 e635"><textual class="po-textual">/atom:entry/nlm:issue-id</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><textual class="po-textual"> then if we wanted to find those entries with the values represented by the
        variables </textual><code class="po-atom e636 e636"><textual class="po-textual">$scheme</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><code class="po-atom e637 e637"><textual class="po-textual">$term</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, and </textual><code class="po-atom e638 e638"><textual class="po-textual">$issue-id</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, the XPath
        expression must be written along the lines of
        </textual><programlisting class="po-block e639 e639" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
  for $cat in /atom:entry[nlm:issue-id = $issue-id]/atom:category[@scheme eq $scheme and @term eq $term]
  return $cat/parent::atom:entry
</textual></programlisting></para><para class="po-block e640 e640"><textual class="po-textual">Writing it in an alternative way, using nested predicates,
        </textual><programlisting class="po-block e641 e641" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
  /atom:entry[atom:category[@scheme eq $scheme and @term eq $term] and nlm:issue-id = $issue-id]
</textual></programlisting><textual class="po-textual">
        results in the server's not using the </textual><code class="po-atom e642 e642"><textual class="po-textual">@scheme</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><code class="po-atom e643 e643"><textual class="po-textual">@term</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> indexes,
        resulting in longer execution times. As more predicates are added to a query, it can become
        very difficult to figure out how best to structure the query to take full advantage of the
        indexes.</textual></para><para class="po-block e644 e644"><textual class="po-textual">As an example, the following XQuery expression searches for Atom entries under a
        specified $journal-root location, and identifies those Atom entries that match particular
        atom:link and atom:category criteria. The nested predicates listed are required to ensure no
        false positives are returned:
        </textual><programlisting class="po-block e645 e645" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
  xdmp:directory($journal-root, "infinity")/hw:doc
    /atom:entry
      [atom:link[@rel eq $hpp:rel.parent and @c:role = $hpp:model.journal]]
      [atom:category[@scheme eq $hpp:role.scheme and @term eq $hpp:model.adjunct]]
      [not(atom:link[@rel eq 'related' and @c:role = $hpp:model.adjunct.related])]
</textual></programlisting></para><para class="po-block e646 e646"><textual class="po-textual">This query takes some 472 seconds to run against a </textual><code class="po-atom e647 e647"><textual class="po-textual">$journal-root</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> which
        contains a little over 1.8 million resources. Rewriting the query to first look for one half
        of the criteria for each nested predicate listed above, thereby allowing the server to use
        more indexes, reduces the execution time to around 4.6 seconds:
        </textual><programlisting class="po-block e648 e648" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
  for $entry in
    xdmp:directory($journal-root, "infinity")/hw:doc
      /atom:entry
        [atom:link/@c:role = $hpp:model.journal]
        [atom:category/@term = $hpp:model.adjunct]
        [not(atom:link/@c:role = $hpp:model.adjunct.related)]
  where
    $entry/atom:category[@scheme eq $hpp:role.scheme and @term eq $hpp:model.adjunct]
    and $entry/atom:link[@rel eq $hpp:rel.parent and @c:role = $hpp:model.journal]
    and not($entry/atom:link[@rel eq 'related' and @c:role = $hpp:model.adjunct.related])
  return
    $entry
</textual></programlisting><textual class="po-textual">Both
        queries produce the correct results; it's just a matter of how quickly those results are
        computed. Another way we could improve the performance of this query is to change the
        structure of our XML to be better aligned with MarkLogic's indexes. For this application,
        that was not an option.</textual></para><para class="po-block e649 e649"><textual class="po-textual">MarkLogic Server is able to provide detailed information about which parts of a query
        are using an index, and is able to provide very detailed statistics regarding cache hit
        rates for a query. Many queries in MarkLogic can be fully evaluated out of the indexes, and
        these queries are very efficient, usually returning in sub-second time. However, as queries
        become more complex, the developer needs to understand the impact of the query's conditions
        and the way they interact with the indexes. MarkLogic provides accurate responses to
        queries, and as the query is made to make more use of the indexes, response times are
        typically reduced.</textual></para><para class="po-block e650 e650"><textual class="po-textual">As an example, the following query makes full uses of the indexes to identify those
        resources that contain a given DOI value $doi, and MarkLogic can return results for this
        type of query in less than 0.1
        seconds:</textual><programlisting class="po-block e651 e651" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
       for $doc in
         xdmp:directory("/pnas/", "infinity")/hw:doc/
           atom:entry/nlm:article-id[@pub-id-type eq "doi"][. eq $doi]
       return
         base-uri($doc)
     </textual></programlisting></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e652 e652"><title class="po-block e653 e653"><textual class="po-textual">Babel XSLT</textual></title><para class="po-block e654 e654"><textual class="po-textual">The final component of the XML-based systems used in H2O is the Babel XSLT processing
      engine. Babel XSLT is a batch processing engine that we use to transform incoming source XML
      into resources for loading into the read/write SASS service. We've implemented an HPP aware
      client in XSLT 2.0 (using Java extensions to allow XSLT programs to act as an HTTP client),
      and we perform the bulk of our content loading using the Babel XSLT engine to POST the content
      into the read/write SASS service.</textual></para><para class="po-block e655 e655"><textual class="po-textual">Babel XSLT is an HTTP service that accepts XML documents describing a batch operation to
      perform. A batch consists of an XSLT stylesheet to run, an optional set of XSLT parameters
      (these parameters may be complex content, meaning they may contain document fragments or node
      sequences), and one or more input sources to process, along with corresponding output targets.
      When a batch is submitted, it is queued for processing until the server has free
      capacity.</textual></para><para class="po-block e656 e656"><textual class="po-textual">Once the server begins processing a batch, it draws from a pool of threads to apply the
      specified stylesheet to each specified input source in parallel. Upon completion, a batch log
      report is produced that indicates the start and stop time of each transformation, as well as
      any </textual><code class="po-atom e657 e657"><textual class="po-textual">xsl:message</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> log events captured during the execution of the individual
      transformations. As with the input parameters, the </textual><code class="po-atom e658 e658"><textual class="po-textual">xsl:message</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> log events may be
      complex content.</textual></para><para class="po-block e659 e659"><textual class="po-textual">An example batch input </textual><programlisting class="po-block e660 e660" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
&lt;babel-xsl:batch xmlns:babel-xsl="http://schema.highwire.org/Babel/XSLT/Batch"
  name="HWX.jmicro_iss_58_4.intake.StyleCheckPMC.runPMCArticleValidator"  
  stylesheet="stylesheets/third-party/pmc-nlm-style/default/nlm-stylechecker.xsl"&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp013.xml" 
    result="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp013.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp010.xml" 
    result="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp010.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp018.xml" 
    result="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp018.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp002.xml" 
    result="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp002.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp017.xml" 
    result="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp017.xml" /&gt;
&lt;/babel-xsl:batch&gt;
</textual></programlisting><textual class="po-textual"> would apply the specified stylesheet in to all five
        </textual><code class="po-atom e661 e661"><textual class="po-textual">babel-xsl:transform/@source</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> inputs in parallel, producing five result files and
      a batch log:</textual><programlisting class="po-block e662 e662" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
&lt;babel-xsl:log xmlns:babel-xsl="http://schema.highwire.org/Babel/XSLT/Batch"
  name="2009/07/15/09/HWX.jmicro_iss_58_4.intake.StyleCheckPMC.runPMCArticleValidator" 
  stylesheet="jndi:/localhost/babel-xslt-01/stylesheets/third-party/pmc-nlm-style/default/nlm-stylechecker.xsl"&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:start time="2009-07-15T09:16:23.652-07:00" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform-start time="2009-07-15T09:16:23.667-07:00" 
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp013.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform-start time="2009-07-15T09:16:23.667-07:00" 
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp010.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform-start time="2009-07-15T09:16:23.667-07:00" 
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp018.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform-start time="2009-07-15T09:16:23.667-07:00" 
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp017.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform-start time="2009-07-15T09:16:23.668-07:00" 
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp002.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform-success time="2009-07-15T09:16:24.406-07:00" 
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp018.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform-success time="2009-07-15T09:16:24.647-07:00" 
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp002.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform-success time="2009-07-15T09:16:24.756-07:00" 
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp010.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform-success time="2009-07-15T09:16:24.769-07:00" 
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp013.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:transform-success time="2009-07-15T09:16:24.795-07:00" 
    source="file:/HWE1/process/intake/jmicro/jmicro_iss_58_4/TagTextFiles/StyleCheckPMC/dfp017.xml" /&gt;
  &lt;babel-xsl:success time="2009-07-15T09:16:24.795-07:00" /&gt;
&lt;/babel-xsl:log&gt;
</textual></programlisting></para><para class="po-block e663 e663"><textual class="po-textual">The Babel XSLT service keeps a permanent cache of compiled Templates for the stylesheets
      it is asked to execute. Because a batch requires the uniform application of any XSLT
      parameters to every input source in a batch, the server is then able to set up its processing
      workflow once and then apply that workflow en masse to all the inputs listed in the
      batch.</textual></para><para class="po-block e664 e664"><textual class="po-textual">We currently use Babel XSLT to produce and, via its HTTP and HPP client extensions, to
      load and update almost all H2O content. The production process includes tasks such as applying
      Schematron assertions to produce reports on the content, applying normalization routines to
      the article source XML, enriching the article source XML to include extra metadata, and
      converting those article source files into Atom entries and variant representations (e.g.,
      XHTML). HighWire has written about 48,000 lines of XSLT 2.0 code (including comments and
      whitespace), spread across 318 stylesheets, to perform this work.</textual></para><para class="po-block e665 e665"><textual class="po-textual">We are currently running Babel XSLT on two servers. Each server uses two AMD 1210 cores, 8
      gigabytes of memory, and various NFS mounted storage arrays. Across both servers we are
      executing an average of 3,839 transformations per hour. At peak times we've run anywhere from
      23,000 to 57,000 transformations in an hour. Transformation execution times range from a low
      0.20 seconds to a high of 20.0 seconds, with 95% of transformations taking less than 7.0
      seconds to complete.</textual></para><para class="po-block e666 e666"><textual class="po-textual">The biggest efficiency headache we've encountered with the Babel XSLT service has been
      related to its memory requirements. A large enough batch job can run into memory limits as it
      converts the incoming batch into a JDOM object, runs its XSLT transformations, and uses JDOM
      to produce the batch log report. The Babel XSLT servers have a minimum memory footprint
      ranging from 200 to 300 megabytes, but can easily use up to 5 gigabytes of memory to process
      their workloads. In the space of one minute, a server might jump from needing 500 megabytes to
      needing 2.5 gigabytes of memory.</textual></para><para class="po-block e667 e667"><textual class="po-textual">Currently HighWire uses a Perl-based framework to submit Babel XSLT jobs. The Perl code is
      responsible for identifying which stylesheet and which input and output files need to be
      submitted for a given batch, based on the phase of processing in a workflow. The Perl code is
      responsible for producing a batch, submitting it to the Babel XSLT system, and then examining
      the batch log report to determine whether or not the job was completed successfully, and to
      report any messages emitted by the stylesheet.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e668 e668"><title class="po-block e669 e669"><textual class="po-textual">Conclusion</textual></title><para class="po-block e670 e670"><textual class="po-textual">By far our most challenging experience has been that of educating everyone within our
      organization. Our developers are faced with new systems that make use of a bewildering array
      of specifications and standards, and it has not been easy for everyone involved to come up to
      speed on everything; our developers have demanded better documentation and clearer
      explanations of how the new systems work.</textual></para><para class="po-block e671 e671"><textual class="po-textual">In terms of performance, we've found the XML-based technologies to be adequate, if not
      stellar. When we've needed to improve performance we've applied traditional techniques:</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e672 e672"><listitem class="po-container e673 e673"><para class="po-block e674 e674"><textual class="po-textual">Don't perform work if you don't need to (e.g., Firenze's ability to remove handlers
            from the stack when the handler has completed its task).</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e675 e675"><para class="po-block e676 e676"><textual class="po-textual">Take advantage of optimized representations of your data, if available (e.g., using
            compiled Templates, making use of optimized Source implementations).</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e677 e677"><para class="po-block e678 e678"><textual class="po-textual">Develop caching techniques at multiple layers, trading space for time.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e679 e679"><para class="po-block e680 e680"><textual class="po-textual">Examine your algorithms to determine if they are the best fit for the
            application.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para class="po-block e681 e681"><textual class="po-textual">Applying these techniques, the XML-based technologies we've discussed here can be made
        </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e682 e682"><textual class="po-textual">fast enough</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> for most of our needs.</textual></para><para class="po-block e683 e683"><textual class="po-textual">The advantages we see to using a unified, RESTful, XML data store paired with high-level
      declarative programming languages like XSLT and XQuery are:</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e684 e684"><listitem class="po-container e685 e685"><para class="po-block e686 e686"><textual class="po-textual">It is easier to introduce changes to our data models.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e687 e687"><para class="po-block e688 e688"><textual class="po-textual">There's no need to spend time writing code that converts data from one data model
            into another (e.g., from relational form to an object-oriented form and back).</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e689 e689"><title class="po-block e690 e690"><textual class="po-textual">Acknowledgements</textual></title><para class="po-block e691 e691"><textual class="po-textual">I would like to thank Craig Jurney </textual><email class="po-field e692 e692"><textual class="po-textual">cjurney@stanford.edu</textual></email><textual class="po-textual">, the architect and
      developer of the Firenze system, and Jules Milner-Brage </textual><email class="po-field e693 e693"><textual class="po-textual">jules@adakara.com</textual></email><textual class="po-textual">, the
      primary architect of the SASS specification and the architect and developer of the Babel XSLT
      system, for their comments and advice during the preparation of this paper.</textual></para></section><bibliography class="po-hcontainer e694 e694"><title class="po-block e695 e695"><textual class="po-textual">References</textual></title><bibliomixed class="po-block e696 e696" xml:id="fielding" xreflabel="Fielding2000"><textual class="po-textual">Roy Thomas Fielding,
        </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e697 e697"><textual class="po-textual">Architectural Styles and the Design of Network-based Software
        Architectures,</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Ph.D. Thesis, University of California, Irvine, Irvine,
      California, 2000. [online]. [cited July 2009].
        </textual><link class="po-inline e698 e698" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.ics.uci.edu/~fielding/pubs/dissertation/top.htm</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e699 e699" xml:id="atompub" xreflabel="AtomPub2007"><textual class="po-textual">Joe Gregorio, ed. and Bill de
      Hóra, ed. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e700 e700"><textual class="po-textual">The Atom Publishing Protocol,</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Internet RFC 2053,
      October 2007. [online]. [cited July 2009].
      </textual><link class="po-inline e701 e701" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5023</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e702 e702" xml:id="atom" xreflabel="Atom2005"><textual class="po-textual">M. Nottingham, ed. and R. Sayre, ed.
        </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e703 e703"><textual class="po-textual">The Atom Syndication Format,</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Internet RFC 4287, December 2005 [online].
      [cited July 2009]. </textual><link class="po-inline e704 e704" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4287</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e705 e705" xml:id="cc" xreflabel="Nottingham2007"><textual class="po-textual">M. Nottingham, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e706 e706"><textual class="po-textual">HTTP Cache
        Channels,</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> October 2007. [online]. [cited July 2009].
        </textual><link class="po-inline e707 e707" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://ietfreport.isoc.org/idref/draft-nottingham-http-cache-channels/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e708 e708" xml:id="arc" xreflabel="Megiddo2003"><textual class="po-textual">Nimrod Megiddo and Dharmendra S. Modha,
        </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e709 e709"><textual class="po-textual">ARC: A Self-Tuning, Low Overhead Replacement Cache</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, USENIX File and
      Storage Technologies (FAST), March 31, 2003, San Francisco, CA. [online]. [cited July 2009].
        </textual><link class="po-inline e710 e710" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.almaden.ibm.com/StorageSystems/projects/arc/arcfast.pdf</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed></bibliography></article></classedDocument>