<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">Moving sands: Adventures in XML e-book-land</textual></title><subtitle class="po-block e2 e2"><textual class="po-textual">From XML to XML. Is that enough?</textual></subtitle><info class="po-record e3 e3"><confgroup class="po-record e4 e4"><conftitle class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e6 e6"><textual class="po-textual">August 7 - 10, 2012</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e7 e7"><para class="po-block e8 e8"><textual class="po-textual">Converting XML to e-books supported by multiple devices is a significant task. Deficiencies
				in the EPUB standard, undocumented bugs in some devices, and issues such as fixed
				layout vs. flowable content add complexity. Fortunately, the first experts to
				experience weird effects are sharing their findings. This paper continues this flow
				of information by describing experience in a US IRS project. The first step is
				scheduled for completion in July 2012. When fully deployed, this project will target
				multiple devices, some announced but not yet available, which differ in size,
				features, the formats they can read, and how much of the EPUB standard they
				implement, if any. This paper analyzes issues that have been encountered while
				working on automatic production of e-books using XML technologies and also suggests
				a new vision to ensure a sustainable, minimally intrusive, long term solution for
				producing e-books on various devices. Relying on standards is necessary but not
				sufficient and some issues that are at the core of structured markup are coming
				back.: the difference between structure and presentation has never been so acute.
				This project reminds us that there is no short circuit to a sound approach of
				analysis not only of how information looks, but also of what it means. </textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e9 e9"><personname class="po-record e10 e10"><firstname class="po-field e11 e11"><textual class="po-textual">Michel</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e12 e12"><textual class="po-textual">Biezunski</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e13 e13"><para class="po-block e14 e14"><textual class="po-textual">Consultant in Information Technology, Specialized in Publishing Applications,
					Creator of the Topic Maps standard.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e15 e15"><jobtitle class="po-field e16 e16"><textual class="po-textual">Consultant</textual></jobtitle><orgname class="po-block e17 e17"><textual class="po-textual">Infoloom</textual></orgname></affiliation></author><legalnotice class="po-container e18 e18"><para class="po-block e19 e19"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright © 2012 Michel Biezunski</textual></para></legalnotice><keywordset class="po-table e20 e20" role="author"><keyword class="po-field e21 e21"><textual class="po-textual">e-book</textual></keyword></keywordset></info><note class="po-container e22 e22"><para class="po-block e23 e23"><textual class="po-textual">
				</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e24 e24" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Note. In this article, the word “e-reader” is used to
					designate a reading device, for example a tablet, while the word “reader”
					(except in the phrase “e-ink reader”) is used to designate a human being
					performing the action of reading.</textual></emphasis></para></note><section class="po-hcontainer e25 e25" xml:id="section1"><title class="po-block e26 e26"><textual class="po-textual">Introduction — E-books go mainstream</textual></title><para class="po-block e27 e27"><textual class="po-textual">Contemporary publishers of books, journals, and magazines are moving away from a publishing
			model based on printed pages. Printed books are industrial products that, once written,
			edited and formatted, undergo several steps: printing, binding, storing, distributing,
			displaying, selling. The process of selling e-books is much simpler: once composed, an
			e-book can be put on a server in an online store, where customers can buy it
			instantaneously. e-books will never be “out-of-print”, nor will e-books need to be
			destroyed because they don’t sell enough. The term “e-book” encompasses content beyond
			text and graphics. Audio and video can be included, as well as software components using
			scripts. </textual></para><para class="po-block e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">There are many devices that let us read e-books, including e-ink readers, tablets, smart
			phones, and computers. E-ink readers are best fit for reading plain books, tablets for
			magazines and audio/video content. Smart phones, even though they don’t offer the same
			reading “real estate”, can be used to read the same material. And computers can do all,
			but they don’t necessarily offer the comfortable experience that users want for
			leisurely reading. e-books can be downloaded in their entirety and therefore can be read
			off-line.</textual></para><para class="po-block e29 e29"><textual class="po-textual">The e-book business has become big business. In addition to traditional booksellers such as
			Barnes &amp; Noble, most book publishers, and, increasingly, news-“papers”, key players
			now include Apple, Google, Microsoft, Adobe, Samsung, and Amazon. Actors in the sector
			are both information technology companies and content owners. </textual></para><para class="po-block e30 e30"><textual class="po-textual">E-book formats are basically a set of compressed XML documents, where the main content
			is stored in XHTML. The EPUB delivery standard has become the prevalent means of
			document delivery. Amazon is an exception and has adopted its own formats —
			MOBI/AZW and now KF8. Use of XML in e-books is more tightly controlled than it is in web
			browsers. In particular, web browsers tolerate XML-like HTML in which validity to a DTD
			or a schema is almost irrelevant. In contrast, e-books must be entirely conformant to
			XML schemas, including XHTML for the main content. One would think that this rigor would
			guarantee that e-books will properly display on most e-readers and eliminate tweaking of
			content according to the e-reader the way web pages must be tweaked according to the
			browser. Unfortunately, this is not the case. The primary goal if this article is to
			show that XML is insufficient to guarantee smooth interoperability for rendering. A
			secondary goal is to remind us not to underestimate the distinction between a logical
			structure and its presentation, a distinction that is at the core of structured
			markup.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e31 e31"><title class="po-block e32 e32"><textual class="po-textual">XML-based standards</textual></title><section class="po-hcontainer e33 e33"><title class="po-block e34 e34"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB</textual></title><para class="po-block e35 e35"><textual class="po-textual">Why is this paragraph a comment?  </textual></para><para class="po-block e36 e36"><textual class="po-textual">The EPUB standards are a set of XML vocabularies including the document content (XHTML),
				the “manifest”, declaring the document entities present in one e-book, the “table of
				contents” for navigating, the front cover page, and a mimetype declaration. Fine
				tuning the formatting is achieved through the use of cascading style sheets (CSS).
				The XML documents are compressed together with the style sheets, the images, any
				videos, and when applicable, Javascript programs. A compressed package is called an
				“EPUB” document. </textual></para><para class="po-block e37 e37"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB is created by an industry consortium named IDPF, the International Digital Publishing Forum. The two versions in use of EPUB are 2.0.1 and 3.0. EPUB 2.0.1 was approved in May, 2010, and EPUB 3.0 in October, 2011. In practice, they are augmented with proprietary features that are only available on one particular device; the most famous is the Apple extension to CSS for iPads. The conformance level to a given version of a standard also varies. </textual></para><para class="po-block e38 e38"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB 2.0.1 comprises three specifications: the Open Publication Structure (OPS), the Open Packaging Format (OPF), and the Open Container Format (OCF). The OPS is based on XHTML 1.1 and DTBook (DAISY Digital Talking Book). The style language is a required subset of CSS 2. It allows the inclusion of so-called “XML Islands” which are any complete XML document with a structure different from DTBook or XHTML. This feature was not widely implemented and “out-of-line XML islands” have been dropped in EPUB 3.0. </textual></para><para class="po-block e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB 3.0 contains the following specifications: Publications 3.0, Content Documents 3.0,
				Open Container Format 3.0, Media Overlays 3.0, and EPUB Canonical Fragment
				Identifiers. The main difference between EPUB 2.0.1 and EPUB 3.0 is that the latter
				contains more provisions for incorporating diverse media, such as audio and video,
				and parallels the evolution of HTML towards XHTML 5. EPUB3 was first implemented in
				Apple’s iBooks, Readium, and Azari. Recent progress has been reported for other
				devices. EPUB 3 is gaining a lot of momentum. Its adoption is accelerating
				noticeably in Japan due to its enhanced capabilities for global language support,
				particularly handling writing directions including vertical writing. Furthermore,
				EPUB 3 books can be read on an EPUB 2 reader, providing an EPUB 2.0.1 table of
				contents is provided.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e40 e40"><para class="po-block e41 e41"><textual class="po-textual">Liz Castro: “What I learned in Japan about EPUB 3”, July 9, 2012. </textual><link class="po-inline e42 e42" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.pigsgourdsandwikis.com/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.pigsgourdsandwikis.com/</textual></link></para></footnote></para><para class="po-block e43 e43"><textual class="po-textual">Support for other EPUB 3 features varies. There are only a few signs of implementation of
				video and audio support and pragmatists in the industry prefer to “wait and see”
				before guaranteeing that it actually delivers on its promises. Although Javascript
				is enabled, its support is being largely discarded because of potential security
				breaches. It may be possible to move forward by restricting Javascript to a set of
				industry-supported scripts that could be implemented in most e-readers. However, SVG
				and MathML are now incorporated, and there seems to be more traction on that front.
				Specific extensions to CSS3 for e-books are also defined in the
				specification.</textual></para><para class="po-block e44 e44"><textual class="po-textual">In addition to the general framework the EPUB 3 specification provides, satellite
				specifications are now being defined to offer support for multimedia and indexes. An
				important one will support fixed layout. Fixed layout contrasts to the flowable
				content addressed by the base EPUB standard but is needed for documents such as
				comic books, illustrated books, children books, knitting patterns, textbooks, and
				magazines. A single publication should include both flowable content and fixed
				layout, but this requirement seems to be unavailable at this point. Fixed layout
				must support multiple columns, and a fixed height to width ratio in different page
				sizes. Rendering fixed layout on a variety of e-readers is a challenging
				task.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e45 e45"><title class="po-block e46 e46"><textual class="po-textual">Amazon</textual></title><para class="po-block e47 e47"><textual class="po-textual">Amazon e-book formats differ from the EPUB standards and are optimized for rendering on
				Kindle devices. They also contain provisions for support of audio and video directly
				inspired by HTML 5. The main Amazon formats used today are MOBI/AZW and KF8. MOBI is
				an open standard that was bought by Amazon. AZW was developed by Amazon specifically
				for the Kinder e=ink reader and is DRM (Digital Rights Management)- restricted and
				is locked to a specific device</textual><footnote class="po-popup e48 e48"><para class="po-block e49 e49"><link class="po-inline e50 e50" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.guidingtech.com/9661/difference-between-epub-mobi-azw-pdf-ebook-formats/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.guidingtech.com/9661/difference-between-epub-mobi-azw-pdf-ebook-formats/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> 
				KF8 uses a subset of HTML5 and CSS3, and is designed to be backward-compatible with
				MOBI.</textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e51 e51"><title class="po-block e52 e52"><textual class="po-textual">Rendering remains a challenge</textual></title><para class="po-block e53 e53"><textual class="po-textual">There are two kinds of e-books: flowable content and fixed layout e-books. Flowable content
			can be reformatted on the fly, depending on the device and the user configuration.
			Furthermore, some devices automatically redisplay the content depending on the
			orientation in which they are held. Under these conditions, the traditional notion of a
			page no longer holds. This obvious difference from the world of published documents
			consisting of the well-defined pages of paper or PDF, also distinguishes e-books from
			web pages. Even if browser windows can be reformatted using user-defined local settings,
			the notion of a web page is pervasive. And fragment identifiers help locate the exact
			location of any information on a page, regardless of rendering. This location addressing
			facility is not currently available on an e=book. Technically, flowable content in an
			e-book is displayed by pages, which depend on the local conditions, and is divided into
			units which correspond more or less to the chapters of a traditional printed book. Each
			of these units may correspond to a different physical XHTML file, although the
			page-break property of a CSS may separate one file into multiple pages. However, an
			actual page of flowable content on an e-reader is rendered purely dynamically and
			depends on the conditions set for it. Some e-readers assign page numbers, but these are
			modified each time there is a change in the display style. Thus, e-books have no notion
			of an absolute page number nor of a specific URL for a chapter. (While the file
			structure within the e-book could be used to locate a particular page, the file
			structure is only visible when the e-book is decompressed, information that e-book
			developers but not readers are expected to see.)</textual></para><para class="po-block e54 e54"><textual class="po-textual">The second category of e-books are those for which the layout is partially if not strictly
			fixed. The contents of each page is well defined, and can not be reflowed without
			constraints. For example, magazines, comic books, children books, art books, and text
			books often need to link tightly illustrations, audio, or video content to surrounding
			text. Many pages must be presented in a way that does not dramatically alter the
			aesthetics of the publication and the meaning of the content. Some e-books also contain
			software which provide a more interactive experience to the reader, with supplementary
			constraints about what needs to be displayed under various conditions.</textual></para><para class="po-block e55 e55"><textual class="po-textual">A mechanism called media queries allows an e-book to contain conditional statements, but is
			insufficient to guarantee that the resulting EPUB will be usable on a variety of
			e-readers. Thus, the diversity of e-readers, as well as the existence of multiple
			standards, producing several output versions of many e-books is practically impossible
			to avoid.</textual></para><para class="po-block e56 e56"><textual class="po-textual">Professionals also advice of not trusting the result displayed when the rendering of
			one e-reader is emulated on another one. For example, a Kindle application on an iPad,
			Android tablet, or on a smart phone doesn't reflect in all details the rendering
			obtained on an actual Kindle device.</textual></para><para class="po-block e57 e57"><textual class="po-textual">Implementation of software for rendering EPUB has specific issues on each e-reader. For example, there is an e-reader-specific limit on the size of acceptable files. As a result, a Kindle 3 may freeze while trying to display a document which an iPad can absorb without difficulty.</textual></para><para class="po-block e58 e58"><textual class="po-textual">The physical characteristics of e-readers vary greatly and have an effect on the way they
			are handling documents. For example, e-ink Kindles and Nooks truncate tables that don’t
			fit their screens. The rightmost part of a wide table is simply not displayed, typically
			after the fourth column. In landscape mode the device may display more than in portrait
			mode, but there still may not be sufficient space to render the full table even when the
			font is set to is minimal size. Readers may well be surprised by this loss of
			information, especially since it contrasts to their experience with the web pages and
			PDF documents they are accustomed to magnifying or reducing as desired.</textual></para><para class="po-block e59 e59"><textual class="po-textual">Should rumors that Apple is preparing a 7-inch iPad prove true, one would expect that it will
			render the same information that can be displayed on the current versions. But so far,
			that remains wishful thinking, because the actual size is often used as a guide for an
			optimized rendition. </textual></para><para class="po-block e60 e60"><textual class="po-textual">As far as flowable content is concerned, the font size and margins can be customized
			by every user. If the layout of the page is not fluid enough, some unpredictable things
			may occur, making the text meaningless. This is for example the case with presentation
			in which horizontal layout is critical. If a line wraps where it was not designed to do,
			then the content becomes unreadable. Some e-readers dynamically calculate the page
			numbers, and those numbers will change dynamically, according to the font size or to
			whether the device is hold vertically or horizontally. Others only assign “location
			values”. Some users want to be able to read the documents on their smart phones, which
			offer a much smaller space than the tablets or e-ink readers. </textual></para><para class="po-block e61 e61"><textual class="po-textual">Another problem is the nature of the documents accepted in an EPUB. Text and images must be treated differently. The rendition of graphics may vary according to the e-reader. For example, some e-readers, such as the iPad, enable full-screen display of graphics, and allow the reader to enlarge even a full-screen image by pinching. Other e-readers, for example the Kindle 3, do not offer this possibility. Some graphics may therefore be unreadable on some e-readers. The new iPad, with the Retina display, has a much higher resolution than the other models, and therefore demands images with greater resolution. These images will not fit on many other e-readers, and may slow them to a halt.</textual></para><para class="po-block e62 e62"><textual class="po-textual">So far, there is no universal way of guaranteeing accessibility and each e-reader handles
			accessibility requirements (such as Section 508 compliance) differently. Some e-readers
			include software that enables text to be read aloud. Others do not. EPUB3 provides
			guidelines for accessible documents, but it has not been implemented yet, and it is too
			early to say which features are going to be actually used.</textual></para><para class="po-block e63 e63"><textual class="po-textual">By definition, footnotes are displayed in books at the bottom of a page. Since e-books have
			no notion of a fixed page in flowable content, they have no analogous location. Each
			e-book or e-book series could specify a location for displaying footnotes (such as the
			end of a chapter or of the entire book). Such conventions blur any logical distinction
			between footnotes and endnotes. Another possibility is for footnotes to pop up when the
			reader moves the cursor over a reference to a footnote. </textual></para><para class="po-block e64 e64"><textual class="po-textual">Bugs in some e-reader software causes improper rendering of some HTML code. For example, a notorious iPad bug, known as the “span bug”, ignores any font change on the HTML &lt;span&gt; element. If several fonts are needed within one iPad document the HTML &lt;span&gt; element should not be used to specify fonts. Apple may well solve this bug in a future release of iBooks software and when that occurs this restriction will not be needed. On other platforms, this bug does not occur, and the &lt;span&gt; element can reliably used for font changes.</textual></para><para class="po-block e65 e65"><textual class="po-textual">Another category of problems results from initial settings that vary among devices. Relying
			on the default values can therefore produce undesirable differences that would be
			eliminated if all formatting requirements were explicitly stated. For example, the Kobo
			e-reader centers some headings that other e-readers left align. Amazon uses different
			default values in MOBI than in KF8. Using Amazon’s conversion tool to upgrade can
			therefore break the alignment, indentation, and other formatting features. These issues
			can be solved if all formatting requirements are explicitly stated.</textual></para><para class="po-block e66 e66"><textual class="po-textual">The tables of contents are encoded according to a given structure, which differs between EPUB2 and EPUB3. The EPUB3 format uses more XHTML tags. Multi-level tables of contents can be created, but it is not always possible to render them as folded. For example, on the iPad, the tables of contents are displayed, with all levels, each sublevel being indented appropriately. On e-readers software such as Sigil, by Google, the tables of contents are “folded”. At first, one sees only the first level elements, and they can be unfolded to reveal the next level headers, etc. </textual></para><para class="po-block e67 e67"><textual class="po-textual">In general, the information on these details is scarce, and much trial and error is required to obtain satisfactory results. Fortunately, the most prominent consultants in the field share information about their successes and failures through web pages and blogs; such resources also provide a forum for exchanging pertinent questions and answers. One such blog, maintained by Liz Castro, is called “Pigs, Gourds and Wikis” (http://www.pigsgourdsandwikis.com/) and includes tweets posted at #eprdctn.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e68 e68"><title class="po-block e69 e69"><textual class="po-textual">IRS</textual></title><para class="po-block e70 e70"><textual class="po-textual">The US Internal Revenue Service publishes documents that help taxpayers compute their taxes.
			These include Taxpayer Information Publications (TIP) as well as instructions for forms
			and the associated schedules. These documents are updated each year; they are available
			in print and on the Web (in PDF, HTML, and also as a topic map called “Tax Map”). </textual></para><para class="po-block e71 e71"><textual class="po-textual">For decades, the IRS has served as a laboratory of innovation for testing new
			technology in information delivery. It is now launching its first e-books. The IRS is as
			agnostic as possible in hardware choice and gives preference to formal and de facto
			standards over proprietary formats. As a result, the IRS plans to make its e-books
			available on most e-readers currently on the market. However, it has encountered the
			same issues as those faced by other publishes of e-books for multiple platforms. As a
			starting point, the work has therefore focused on a single platform, the iPad.
			Extensions to other platforms are planned to follow quickly.</textual></para><para class="po-block e72 e72"><textual class="po-textual">Seen from the perspective of XML application development, the e-book project seems
			straightforward. XML source files conforming to a limited number of schemas must be
			transformed into another XML structure (namely, XHTML and the other EPUB structures).
			XSLT is a natural method for transforming this material. The XSLT process includes
			slicing the sources into chapter-like divisions that are small enough to prevent
			e-readers from crashing, converting static text to cross-references and links to the
			Web, tagging footnotes and graphics, building the table of contents, and (in a later
			stage of the project) creating an index.</textual></para><para class="po-block e73 e73"><textual class="po-textual">The road has been bumpier than expected. Limiting initial output to a single e-reader reduced the number of e-reader-dependent quirks that had to be addressed for a proof-of-concept project, but there was no way to plan for undocumented idiosyncrasies. An easy workaround to the &lt;span&gt; bug mentioned above is to use HTML elements such as &lt;cite&gt;, or the rarely-used &lt;samp&gt; element instead of &lt;span&gt;.</textual></para><para class="po-block e74 e74"><textual class="po-textual">The problem with this kind of bug is that it may just be temporary. Perhaps Apple will issue a software upgrade that will solve it. Or not. Or perhaps the upgrade will introduce a new side effect that didn’t exist before. And there is no way to know, the documentation is almost non-existent, and the only source of information is the community of practitioners that exchange this kind of information on specialized forums. And of course, the problem highlighted here is just one of them, and it’s only for the iPad. Other e-readers have their own issues, and these issues are only known at the time of testing.</textual></para><para class="po-block e75 e75"><textual class="po-textual">To provide products that work reliably on a variety of environments, a project must
			establish the least common denominator among the formatting requirements, and minimize
			use of platform-specific features. This recommendation is easier to follow for flowable
			content than for fixed layout, where interoperability between e-readers is even more
			challenging. Apple, for example, has released software that allows an author to create
			an e-book that may contain text, images, video, etc., and may be beautifully laid out.
			However, the result is only usable on Apple platforms. Apple’s commercial motivation for
			this product is obvious. Until vendors have greater motivation to support
			platform-independent standards, the technical features that would ensure good quality
			rendering on various devices are pretty daunting, and we are clearly not there
			yet.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e76 e76"><title class="po-block e77 e77"><textual class="po-textual">Moving Forward</textual></title><para class="po-block e78 e78"><textual class="po-textual">Publishing high quality e-books on multiple e-readers requires quality assurance on every
			platform. The scope of this tedious process is open-ended, since new e-readers appear
			regularly, although others are discarded. The work area where testing is performed can
			resemble a toy store with shelves containing numerous devices. Media queries and similar
			mechanisms for anticipating how e-books will appear on various devices can bring
			interesting issues to light, but do not substitute for real tests on real devices.
			Testing is a learning process for accumulating the experience for tracking,
			categorizing, and fixing in the most possible generic way any detected problems.</textual></para><para class="po-block e79 e79"><textual class="po-textual">Long term solutions require conceptual, abstract thinking about the e-book environment and
			nature of the issues involve.</textual></para><para class="po-block e80 e80"><textual class="po-textual">There are several kinds of traditional books, not all consisting of flowable content or
			fixed layout. Flowable content includes novels, essays, academic books, textbooks,
			reference books, technical manuals, etc. Most books have tables of contents, some have
			indexes, cross-references and references to parts of other books. Some are illustrated,
			others are not. In addition to the graphics and photographs, there can be structures
			with complex layout, such as tables. Tables are sometimes automatically composed from a
			source in XML (for example, the content may be provided in DocBook). In addition,
			e-books can be interactive and can contain audio and video clips. Almost every item
			listed here poses a challenge to e-book publishing.</textual></para><para class="po-block e81 e81"><textual class="po-textual">A novel is typically easy to publish as an e-book. Most e-reader devices support tables of
			contents. In principle, such mechanisms could work well as well for essays and academic
			books, but there is a supplementary problem here. How should academic citations to part
			of an e-book be made? Literate references to books typically identify the cited book and
			the relevant pages. Since e-books have no fixed page numbers, new conventions for
			academic citations must be developed. Publishers advise authors of academic material to
			use numbered sections, and create references by section number. If sections are
			automatically numbered, however, section numbers can easily become obsolete in a later
			edition of a work. Perhaps the URI reference system that is pervasive on the Web can be
			used for citations to content within an e-book. Such conventions will only be useful if
			widely adopted.</textual></para><para class="po-block e82 e82"><textual class="po-textual">Few current e-books include an index because little e-book publishing software makes it easy
			to build an index. While the XML community is experienced in building indexes from
			“invisible tags” stored within an XML source document, knowledge of XSLT in the
			publishing industry is quite limited. Publishers are much more likely to tweak a CSS
			stylesheet to create desired formatting than to consider the design of XML source
			material.</textual></para><para class="po-block e83 e83"><textual class="po-textual">Some presentational effects, such as multi-column layout, are dropped in flowable content
			within the e-book edition of a book. Such degradation of original formatting may be an
			aesthetic loss mourned by purists, but is usually not a tremendous loss of information
			content.</textual></para><para class="po-block e84 e84"><textual class="po-textual">It is a completely different story with tables. As previously noted, tables as represented
			in printed documents or web pages do not display well in the restricted real estate of
			an e-reader screen. Even when manufacturers offer the ability to zoom in and out, it is
			not convenient to view tabular information in limited space. Worse, as previously
			discussed, e-readers merely crop the tables to fit the maximum width of the device. The
			amount of information available is proportional to the font size, and depends on whether
			the device is held in portrait or landscape mode. This problem is much more acute with
			e-books than traditional publishing because paper-based publishing relied on an implicit
			notion of using paper of a reasonable width for the content. As more and more material
			has moved to computer screens, readers change font size or scroll to view tabular
			material successfully in the vast majority of cases. Now that we are reading on smaller
			devices, including smart phones, the situation has changed, and the notion of adjustment
			in the width becomes crucial.</textual></para><para class="po-block e85 e85"><textual class="po-textual">These issues take us back to the early days of logical markup, and the difference between semantic and presentational structures. Practitioners in the XML community, and earlier, in the SGML community, have been aware of these issues from the beginning of generic markup. Tables survive because they are a compact and visually compelling presentation for some kind of information. They will continue to be used as long as there are methods for fitting them on a display of “reasonable width”. </textual></para><para class="po-block e86 e86"><textual class="po-textual">Alternatively, some tables could be presented as lists. For example, a customer list in
			which the first column contains the first name, the second column the last name, and the
			third column an email address, could very well be represented as an indented list that
			can be more easily rendered in an e-book. The same information could still be rendered
			as a table for print, PDF, or web pages.</textual></para><para class="po-block e87 e87"><textual class="po-textual">We also know that tables—and this is especially visible when managed within spreadsheet software—are views into a database. This model considers each row to be a record and each cell a field. A header row expresses the database schema. A cell therefore is the response to a query about a specific property. In database terminology, the word “table” is actually used interchangeably for “relation”. This database model suggests the possibility of software that offers a form-like user interface for searching for information within a table. </textual></para><para class="po-block e88 e88"><textual class="po-textual">List and database solutions for rendering tabular material require document sources that use semantic markup rather than visual markup to store this type of information.</textual></para><para class="po-block e89 e89"><textual class="po-textual">Other navigational devices need to be adjusted for e-book publishing: footnotes, running
			headers, indexes, can be rendered a number of ways, and there are provisions in the EPUB
			3.0 specification (or in one of its satellites currently under development) to handle
			these features in interoperable ways. Such features will remain a factor of
			differentiation among e-reader device manufacturers, because supporting these features
			are not required. </textual></para><para class="po-block e90 e90"><textual class="po-textual">As we still are in the infancy of the e-book industry, we are in the period of the “Whoa!”
			effect. It’s great to be able to carry thousands of books on a device for which the
			battery life can span over a month or to exchange bookmarks with “friends” on a social
			network. We still accept that e-books do not yet have all the features we have in
			printed books. As readers become more familiar with e-books, they will demand more of
			the sophistication and quality they deserve. Serious readers will require the
			nitty-gritty details that have evolved over centuries of book publishing to become
			standard in print. How quickly this demand will develop is still difficult to predict.
			The XML community, especially publishers within the XML community, clearly will have a
			big part in the future of e-books. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e91 e91"><title class="po-block e92 e92"><textual class="po-textual">References</textual></title><itemizedlist class="po-table e93 e93"><listitem class="po-container e94 e94"><para class="po-block e95 e95"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB Standard: </textual><link class="po-inline e96 e96" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://idpf.org/epub" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://idpf.org/epub</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">. This is the
					main resource for the reference documents on EPUB 3.0, EPUB 2.0.1 and the
					differences between the two versions.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e97 e97"><para class="po-block e98 e98"><textual class="po-textual">Liz Castro's Blog: </textual><link class="po-inline e99 e99" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.pigsgourdsandwikis.com/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.pigsgourdsandwikis.com/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">. </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e100 e100"><para class="po-block e101 e101"><textual class="po-textual">Liz Castro has written several books on ebook publishing, including:
						</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e102 e102"><textual class="po-textual">HTML, XHTML, and CSS: Visual Starting Guide, 6th
						Edition</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">(</textual><link class="po-inline e103 e103" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.elizabethcastro.com/html/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.elizabethcastro.com/html/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">) </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e104 e104"><textual class="po-textual">epub straight to the
						point</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (</textual><link class="po-inline e105 e105" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.elizabethcastro.com/epub/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.elizabethcastro.com/epub/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">), and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e106 e106"><textual class="po-textual">From InDesign
						CS 5.5. to EPUB and Kindle (</textual></emphasis><link class="po-inline e107 e107" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://store.kagi.com/cgi-bin/store.cgi?storeID=6FHNX_LIVE&amp;page=IDCS55EPUBK〈=en" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://store.kagi.com/cgi-bin/store.cgi?storeID=6FHNX_LIVE&amp;page=IDCS55EPUBK&amp;lang=en</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">).</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e108 e108"><para class="po-block e109 e109"><textual class="po-textual">Twitter Feed: #eprdctn</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e110 e110"><para class="po-block e111 e111"><textual class="po-textual">Joshua Tallent (eBooks Architects): About Kindle Formatting, See </textual><link class="po-inline e112 e112" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://kindleformatting.com/index.php" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://kindleformatting.com/index.php</textual></link></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e113 e113"><para class="po-block e114 e114"><textual class="po-textual">Validation tool for EPUB by Google: "epubcheck". See </textual><link class="po-inline e115 e115" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://code.google.com/p/epubcheck/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://code.google.com/p/epubcheck/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></section></article></classedDocument>