<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2" xml:id="Bal2010bara0723"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">Managing semantics in XML vocabularies: an experience in the legal and legislative domain</textual></title><info class="po-record e2 e2"><confgroup class="po-record e3 e3"><conftitle class="po-field e4 e4"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2010</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">August 3 - 6, 2010</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e6 e6"><para class="po-block e7 e7"><textual class="po-textual">Akoma Ntoso is an XML vocabulary for legal and legislative documents sponsored by the United Nations, initially for African Countries and subsequently for use in other world countries. The XML documents that represent legal and legislative resources in Akoma Ntoso contain a large quantity of elements and sections with concrete semantic information about the correct description and identification of the resource itself and the legal knowledge it contains. Such information is organized in many distinct conceptual layers, allowing for the contribution of different semantic information according to competencies and role in the workflow of the contributor.</textual></para><para class="po-block e8 e8"><textual class="po-textual">This paper shows how the Akoma Ntoso standard expresses the independent conceptual layers of semantic information, and provides ontological structures on top of them. We also discuss how current Semantic Web technologies could be used on these layers to reason on the underlying legal texts.</textual></para><para class="po-block e9 e9"><textual class="po-textual">As one of the main funding principles of Akoma Ntoso is the long-term preservation of legal documents and of their intended meaning, this paper also shows and justifies some design decisions that have been made in order allow future toolmakers to access the enclosed legal information without having to rely on current technology that may be long forgotten in the future decades.</textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e10 e10"><personname class="po-record e11 e11"><firstname class="po-field e12 e12"><textual class="po-textual">Gioele</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e13 e13"><textual class="po-textual">Barabucci</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e14 e14"><para class="po-block e15 e15"><textual class="po-textual">Gioele Barabucci holds a degree in Computer Science at the Univeristy of Bologna. The main research interests in his current Ph.D. Carerr include Web technologies, content formatting and XML schema languages.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e16 e16"><orgname class="po-block e17 e17"><textual class="po-textual">Department of Computer Science, University of Bologna, Bologna, Italy</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e18 e18"><textual class="po-textual">barabucc@cs.unibo.it</textual></email></author><author class="po-record e19 e19"><personname class="po-record e20 e20"><firstname class="po-field e21 e21"><textual class="po-textual">Luca</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e22 e22"><textual class="po-textual">Cervone</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e23 e23"><para class="po-block e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">Luca Cervone is a Master student in Computer Science and he hold a grant with CIRSFID.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e25 e25"><orgname class="po-block e26 e26"><textual class="po-textual">CIRSFID, University of Bologna</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e27 e27"><textual class="po-textual">luca.cervone@unibo.it</textual></email></author><author class="po-record e28 e28"><personname class="po-record e29 e29"><firstname class="po-field e30 e30"><textual class="po-textual">Angelo</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e31 e31"><textual class="po-textual">Di Iorio</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e32 e32"><para class="po-block e33 e33"><textual class="po-textual">Angelo Di Iorio holds a Ph.D. in Computer Science, from the University of Bologna. His thesis is positioned over markup languages and document engineering areas, being focused on design patterns for digital documents and automatic processes of analysis and segmentation. During his PhD he has also worked on collaborative authoring, document versioning, content formatting, and semantic web technologies. His research interests have recently extended towards layout languages and algorithms. He is a member of the W3C XSL-FO working group, and author of several conference and journal papers on markup languages, digital publishing and Web technologies.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e34 e34"><orgname class="po-block e35 e35"><textual class="po-textual">Department of Computer Science, University of Bologna, Bologna, Italy</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e36 e36"><textual class="po-textual">diiorio@cs.unibo.it</textual></email></author><author class="po-record e37 e37"><personname class="po-record e38 e38"><firstname class="po-field e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">Monica</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e40 e40"><textual class="po-textual">Palmirani</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e41 e41"><para class="po-block e42 e42"><textual class="po-textual">Monica Palmirani is associate professor in Law and Computer Science Department (CIRSFID) at the University of Bologna, where she teaches Cyberlaw.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e43 e43"><orgname class="po-block e44 e44"><textual class="po-textual">CIRSFID, University of Bologna, Bologna, Italy</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e45 e45"><textual class="po-textual">monica.palmirani@unibo.it</textual></email></author><author class="po-record e46 e46"><personname class="po-record e47 e47"><firstname class="po-field e48 e48"><textual class="po-textual">Silvio</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e49 e49"><textual class="po-textual">Peroni</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e50 e50"><para class="po-block e51 e51"><textual class="po-textual">Silvio Peroni holds a degree in Computer Science at the University of Bologna. The main research interests in his current Ph.D. career include Semantic Web technologies, markup languages for complex documents, design patterns for digital documents and automatic processes of analysis and segmentation. He has published 9 scientific papers about these subjects.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e52 e52"><orgname class="po-block e53 e53"><textual class="po-textual">Department of Computer Science, University of Bologna, Bologna, Italy</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e54 e54"><textual class="po-textual">speroni@cs.unibo.it</textual></email></author><author class="po-record e55 e55"><personname class="po-record e56 e56"><firstname class="po-field e57 e57"><textual class="po-textual">Fabio</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e58 e58"><textual class="po-textual">Vitali</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e59 e59"><para class="po-block e60 e60"><textual class="po-textual">Fabio Vitali is associate professor in Computer Science at the University of Bologna, where he teaches Web Technologies and Human-Computer Interaction. His interests lie in models and languages for document management and hypertext support, and has published more than 60 papers in national and international venues. He is member of the W3C Working Group on XML Schema, and member of the scientific committee of several conferences and journals in Web engineering and technologies. He is author of important standards in the legislative XML Domain, and work on issues related to digital publishing, Web technologies and Semantic Web technologies.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e61 e61"><orgname class="po-block e62 e62"><textual class="po-textual">Department of Computer Science, University of Bologna, Bologna, Italy</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e63 e63"><textual class="po-textual">fabio@cs.unibo.it</textual></email></author><legalnotice class="po-container e64 e64"><para class="po-block e65 e65"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright © 2010 by the authors.  Used with
permission.</textual></para></legalnotice><keywordset class="po-table e66 e66" role="author"><keyword class="po-field e67 e67"><textual class="po-textual">XML vocabulary</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e68 e68"><textual class="po-textual">Parliamentary documents</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e69 e69"><textual class="po-textual">Legal reasoning</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e70 e70"><textual class="po-textual">GRDDL</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e71 e71"><textual class="po-textual">Legal and legislative resource</textual></keyword></keywordset></info><section class="po-hcontainer e72 e72"><title class="po-block e73 e73"><textual class="po-textual">Introduction</textual></title><para class="po-block e74 e74"><textual class="po-textual">Akoma Ntoso is an XML vocabulary for legal and legislative documents whose primary objective is to provide semantic information on top of a received legal text. There are three key aspects of legal documents on which Akoma Ntoso focuses: identification of structures, references to other legal documents and storage of non-authoritative annotations. Structures are identified and marked up according to an XML vocabulary based on common patterns found in legal documents. References to legal documents across countries are made using a common naming convention based on URIs. Third-party annotations and interpretations (broadly called </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e75 e75" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">metadata</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">) are stored using and ontologically sound approach compatible with Topic Maps [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e76 e76" linkend="TopicMaps"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], OWL [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e77 e77" linkend="OWL"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] and GRDDL [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e78 e78" linkend="GRDDL"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].</textual></para><para class="po-block e79 e79"><textual class="po-textual">The XML documents created according to the Akoma Ntoso specifications use a layered structure where each layer addresses a single problem: the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e80 e80" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">text </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">layer provides a faithful representation of the original content of the legal text, the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e81 e81" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">structure</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> layer provides a hierarchical organization of the parts present in the text layers, the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e82 e82" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">metadata</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> layer associate information from the underlying layers with ontological information. Whenever this semantic information is the result of a subjective interpretation, Akoma Ntoso allows multiple and independent opinions to be stored in a formal way within the document, and used alternatively, cumulatively or compared to each other.</textual></para><para class="po-block e83 e83"><textual class="po-textual">The layered structure of Akoma Ntoso is an attempt at balancing extensibility, needed to accommodate the specific needs of individual countries, with clarity and self-explanatoriness, both needed for the preservation of legal digital resources over time (even long spans of time, measured in decades or centuries). Both these aspect have been evaluated taking into account the fact that long preservation of Akoma Ntoso documents must be possible even without access to the extensive original documentation.</textual></para><para class="po-block e84 e84"><textual class="po-textual">The same layered structure creates a strict separation between the content that has been approved by the body empowered by law to endorse it (data) and what has been added by other parties (metadata). This separation significantly helps the development of tools able to preserve and guarantee the authenticity of the processed legal document, favouring trust towards e-government initiatives. In fact, Akoma Ntoso XML documents can be managed in any step of the legislative or judiciary life cycle (for instance, in the publishing phase) without any modification to the received text.</textual></para><para class="po-block e85 e85"><textual class="po-textual">While Akoma Ntoso imposes an (extensible) XML vocabulary, it does not prescribe the use of a particular ontology. Actually Akoma Ntoso defines a minimal and loose ontology based on few </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e86 e86" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Top Level Classes</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (TLCs) e.g., Person, Role, Concept, etc. These classes are only generic groupings of instances: no particular property is defined for any of them. Inside an Akoma Ntoso document, a section of the metadata links pieces of text with the appropriate TLC instances, another section of the metadata combines these instances to create complex relations.</textual></para><para class="po-block e87 e87"><textual class="po-textual">To perform elaborated computations on a document or on a collection of documents, more precise ontologies have to be used and linked with the provided metadata. For example, we may be interested in using the FRBR (Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records) ontology to associate some of the document metadata describing legislative documents to FRBR concepts like Work or Expression of a Work. Another example is the representation of individual persons: instances of the TLC Person class may be associated to instances of the Person class of the FOAF (Friend of a Friend) ontology or to instances of the Creator class of the Dublin Core ontology. Akoma Ntoso allows the use of these and of future ontologies.</textual></para><para class="po-block e88 e88"><textual class="po-textual">Even if one relies only on the bare knowledge provided by the Akoma Ntoso minimal ontology and by its document markup, there are many interesting queries that can be carried out using only the original document. Some of these queries can be expressed through XPath expressions [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e89 e89" linkend="XPath"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], even though it is syntactically and semantically better to query documents metadata (extracted and stored in RDF statements) through SPARQL [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e90 e90" linkend="SPARQL"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. Another way to use the same semantic information (accompanied or not accompanied by an external ontology) it to use it as a knowledge base on top of which systems based on LKIF (Legal Knowledge Interchange Format) [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e91 e91" linkend="LKIF"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] or RuleML [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e92 e92" linkend="RuleML"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] can operate.</textual></para><para class="po-block e93 e93"><textual class="po-textual">This paper is organized as follows. </textual><xref class="po-milestone e94 e94" linkend="SectionANArchitecture"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> illustrates the layered architecture of the Akoma Ntoso vocabulary. </textual><xref class="po-milestone e95 e95" linkend="SectionDataLayers"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> describes the lower layers of the Akoma Ntoso document architecture where the legal text is described and the hooks used by upper layers are added. </textual><xref class="po-milestone e96 e96" linkend="SectionMetadataLayer"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> shows how authoritative and non-authoritative legal knowledge (metadata) can be codified in an Akoma Ntoso document. Finally, </textual><xref class="po-milestone e97 e97" linkend="SectionSemanticTechnologies"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> illustrates how current semantic tools can use the generic Akoma Ntoso ontology system to reason over legal documents.</textual></para><para class="po-block e98 e98"><textual class="po-textual">Note: throughout this paper we will use the terms </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e99 e99" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">legal text</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e100 e100" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">legal resource</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> for legal texts as endorsed by an official authority; we will use the term </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e101 e101" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">legal document</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> for their computer representation; we will use the terms </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e102 e102" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">legal content</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e103 e103" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">normative content</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> for pointing out the normative meaning of the text.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e104 e104" xml:id="SectionANArchitecture"><title class="po-block e105 e105"><textual class="po-textual">The Akoma Ntoso document architecture</textual></title><para class="po-block e106 e106"><textual class="po-textual">The role of Akoma Ntoso is to mark up legal and legislative texts so that the legal knowledge and the legal structure of the text can be understood by current and future computer applications. This means that legal texts form the basis on which Akoma Ntoso documents exist. Akoma Ntoso documents add information on top of the actual text. The added information can itself be seen as composed of different stratified layers (text, structure, metadata, etc.) [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e107 e107" linkend="FillTheGap"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. Akoma Ntoso clearly separates the legal text from these different levels of information but still allows higher layers to reference the underlying layers, thus building knowledge on top of other knowledge, with the content of the legal text acting as the base knowledge.</textual></para><para class="po-block e108 e108"><textual class="po-textual">As with any technology that deals with legal resources, Akoma Ntoso has been designed to work on the original text without changing to it. Words and punctuation marks, but also other typographical symbols, are left untouched by the mark up process that transforms a plain-text legal document into an Akoma Ntoso-compliant XML document.</textual></para><para class="po-block e109 e109"><textual class="po-textual">Additionally, Akoma Ntoso maintains a strict separation between data and metadata and provides an unambiguous definition of them as well as an operational distinction in authoriality: as such, data is any information that has been created or at least approved by the relevant legal author (for example the whole of the text of an act), while metadata is any information that was not present in the original version of the document as it was approved by the relevant legal author but was added editorially in a later moment of the production process (e.g., the issue number of the official gazette or, even, the page numbers in the printed version of the same act).</textual></para><para class="po-block e110 e110"><textual class="po-textual">The distinction between data and metadata is not only a theoretical distinction, since the actual layers of markup in Akoma Ntoso, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e111 e111" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">text</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e112 e112" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">structure</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e113 e113" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">metadata</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, are based on it.</textual></para><para class="po-block e114 e114"><textual class="po-textual">Textual markup identifies, within the content of the legal documents, fragments that have a precise legal or referential meaning, e.g., concepts such as “this piece of text is a date”, “this piece of text is a legal reference” or “this piece of text contains the name of a party of the trial”. Structural markup identifies and organize the parts of the content that divide it into containers, and especially hierarchical containers: “this piece of text is an article” or “this piece of text is the title of an act”, “this piece of text is the background section of a judgement”, etc. Metadata markup adds knowledge generated by an interpretation of the legal text performed by an human or mechanical agent: “the phrase the pre-existing Acts refers to Act 32 of 1989 and Act 2 of 1990”, or “the person cited in the minutes as Mr. Gidisu is really Mr. Joe Kwashie Gisidu, the only member of the current Ghanaian parliament with that name and elected to a seat in it since 2000”.</textual></para><para class="po-block e115 e115"><textual class="po-textual">The analysis of the textual and structural information is quite straightforward and its results are rarely disputed. On the contrary, the analysis of more advanced concepts found in the legal text requires some experience and it is easy for different sources to disagree on the generated interpretation. For this reason Akoma Ntoso documents have exactly one textual and one structural layer in each documents while interpretation of the advanced concepts is stored as metadata, and Akoma Ntoso allows multiple metadata layers in the same document, each providing an interpretation by a different source.</textual></para><para class="po-block e116 e116"><textual class="po-textual">Finally, each interpretation added by a specific actor can be linked to ontologies of legal concepts (e.g. date of enter into force as modelled by the LKIF-core ontology or the concept of the High Court of South Africa as modelled in an ontology about the judiciary system in Africa) by associating ABox assertions, described in the XML document and extractable in a more proper data model using GRDDL [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e117 e117" linkend="GRDDL"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], to the general TBox properties, axioms and relationships defined into the core or domain ontology.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e118 e118" xml:id="SectionDataLayers"><title class="po-block e119 e119"><textual class="po-textual">The authorial layers</textual></title><para class="po-block e120 e120"><textual class="po-textual">Any Akoma Ntoso document is based on a legal resource that has been endorsed by an authority empowered by law: an act approved by a parliament, a decree issued by a ministry, a judgement entered by a court. Fidelity to the approved text is, thus, of primary importance; the data layers of Akoma Ntoso have been designed so that it is possible to markup a received legal text while preserving all the information contained in it and changing its content in no way.</textual></para><para class="po-block e121 e121"><textual class="po-textual">The documents that Akoma Ntoso deals with are legal resources whose significance is given by the fact that they have the power to influence citizens' life. Legal texts must, thus, be handled with extreme care and all the measures should be taken to make sure that the technological tools employed to manipulate the texts do not change or interfere with their intended meaning.</textual></para><para class="po-block e122 e122"><textual class="po-textual">In Akoma Ntoso, legal documents are created by enclosing parts of the legal text in XML tags (mixed content model). No pieces of the legal text are discarded, even those that could be generated by an application (e.g. the article numbers in an act). The resulting documents are thus augmented versions of the authentic text; the approved text can be retrieved by simply removing all the XML tags.</textual></para><para class="po-block e123 e123"><textual class="po-textual">The Akoma Ntoso markup process strives to preserve the legal validity of the text as endorsed by the official authority, without adding any additional content to the text. Obviously, the mere act of marking up a sentence involves an act of interpretation or annotation and thus cannot be considered perfectly neutral. However, the kind of markup done at the Akoma Ntoso data layers is almost objective, to the point that some automatic parsers have been developed [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e124 e124" linkend="Norma"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], and is rarely subject to disputes. For this reason Akoma Ntoso documents are designed to contain only one interpretation of the text and structure layers.</textual></para><para class="po-block e125 e125"><textual class="po-textual">In addition to the importance of associating content fragments to their structural roles, the markup in the text and structure layers also provide anchors that the upper layers can use to give meaning to pieces of text. For instance, to describe that a certain paragraph states a textual modification to a certain act, the relevant text would be marked up with a </textual><code class="po-atom e126 e126"><textual class="po-textual">mod</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> element and given an identifier via its </textual><code class="po-atom e127 e127"><textual class="po-textual">id</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> attribute. At the same time, in the metadata section, there will be one (or more) </textual><code class="po-atom e128 e128"><textual class="po-textual">textualMod</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> elements referring to the URI of the </textual><code class="po-atom e129 e129"><textual class="po-textual">mod</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> element that will link that piece of text to its semantic description. The following sections contains examples of how </textual><code class="po-atom e130 e130"><textual class="po-textual">textualMod</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and other legal analysis are connected to the authorial layer.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e131 e131" xml:id="SectionMetadataLayer"><title class="po-block e132 e132"><textual class="po-textual">The editorial layer</textual></title><para class="po-block e133 e133"><textual class="po-textual">The Akoma Ntoso metadata layer is a collection of pieces of legal knowledge that can be added onto a legal text by an editorial team as its personal interpretation of the written text, for example the analysis of the reasoning being performed by the judge while writing a judgement or the explicit consequences of the text of an amendment over an act. These pieces of legal knowledge are often subjective may vary across experts. Instead of forcing a single interpretation, Akoma Ntoso allows multiple, and even contrasting, interpretations to be put in the same document. These interpretations of the underlying text form the foundation upon which semantic technologies can make inferences (as discussed in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e134 e134" linkend="SectionSemanticTechnologies"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">).</textual></para><para class="po-block e135 e135"><textual class="po-textual">The metadata layer allows agents to provide different kinds of information. The following are examples of the information that can be added with Akoma Ntoso.</textual></para><para class="po-block e136 e136"><emphasis class="po-inline e137 e137" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Reference disambiguation.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> The </textual><code class="po-atom e138 e138"><textual class="po-textual">references</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> section links pieces of text to ontological entities. The usefulness of this information is twofold. First, conflicts between ambiguous phrases are resolved: for instance, in a sentence of a speech the text “Speaker” may be related to the role called “Speaker” (for example in the sentence “the Speaker must be at least of age 30”) while in another sentence the same text “Speaker” may refer to a specific person that is in charge as speaker at the very time the debate was held. In such a scenario, the </textual><code class="po-atom e139 e139"><textual class="po-textual">references</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> section will contain these two elements (the </textual><code class="po-atom e140 e140"><textual class="po-textual">href</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> attributes point to a URI defined by the Akoma Ntoso naming convention that will be explained in the next section):</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e141 e141" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;TLCRole id="speaker" showAs="Speaker" 
  href="/ontology/Role/gha/speaker"/&gt;
&lt;TLCPerson id="speaker_20090218" showAs="Speaker" 
  href="/ontology/Person/gha/parliament/JohnSmith.1948"/&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e142 e142"><textual class="po-textual">Inside the document, occurrences of the word “Speaker” with the former meaning will be linked to </textual><code class="po-atom e143 e143"><textual class="po-textual">#speaker</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, occurrences of the word “Speaker” with the latter meaning will be linked to </textual><code class="po-atom e144 e144"><textual class="po-textual"># speaker_20090218</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para><para class="po-block e145 e145"><textual class="po-textual">In addition to disambiguation, references are used also to consolidate different spellings found in the text to a single entity; in a court judgement, phrases like “Ms. Poliey”, “Judge Poliey” and “Her Honour” can all be linked to the same person identified by the TLC Person instance </textual><code class="po-atom e146 e146"><textual class="po-textual">/ontology/Person/Poliey.1954</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para><para class="po-block e147 e147"><emphasis class="po-inline e148 e148" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Legal analysis.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> The </textual><code class="po-atom e149 e149"><textual class="po-textual">analysis</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> section provides information about many legal aspects that can be inferred by a legal expert when interpreting the text. An example is the interpretation of the effects of an amendment in an amendment act. The following example states that, when the act will enter into force, part of the text of the document identified by </textual><code class="po-atom e150 e150"><textual class="po-textual">/ke/act/1997-08-22/3/main</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> will be changed: inside the section </textual><code class="po-atom e151 e151"><textual class="po-textual">#sec34-sub2-itma</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> of </textual><code class="po-atom e152 e152"><textual class="po-textual">/ke/act/1997-08-22/3/main</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, the text that matches the content of </textual><code class="po-atom e153 e153"><textual class="po-textual">#mod10-qtd1</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> (relative to the current document) will be substituted with the content of </textual><code class="po-atom e154 e154"><textual class="po-textual">#mod10-qtd2</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> (again, relative to the current document).</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e155 e155" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;textualMod type="substitution" id="am5"&gt;
    &lt;source href="#sec4-sub1-itma"/&gt;
    &lt;destination href="/ke/act/1997-08-22/3/main#sec34-sub2-itma"/&gt;
    &lt;old href="#mod10-qtd1"/&gt;
    &lt;new href="#mod10-qtd2"/&gt;
&lt;/textualMod&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e156 e156"><textual class="po-textual">Another example is the identification of the role played by citations of precedents in the judgement argumentation of a judge (e.g., the application of a rule of law of a precedent, the override of a previous ruling, etc.). In the following excerpt it is pointed out that the sentence </textual><code class="po-atom e157 e157"><textual class="po-textual">#ref01</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> (a reference to the judgement identified by the URI </textual><code class="po-atom e158 e158"><textual class="po-textual">/gb/judgement/1829/QB273/eng@/main.xml</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">) is used to supports the court's decision to deny the request of statutory damages.</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e159 e159" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;judicial&gt;
    &lt;result type="deny"/&gt; 
    &lt;supports id="jdc01"&gt; 
        &lt;source href="#ref01"/&gt; 
        &lt;destination href="/gb/judgement/1829/QB273/eng@/main.xml"/&gt; 
    &lt;/supports&gt; 
&lt;/judicial&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e160 e160"><emphasis class="po-inline e161 e161" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Work identification.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> The identification section classifies the document using a conceptual model drawn from FRBR (Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records) [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e162 e162" linkend="FRBR"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. This classification is used to inform the semantic tools that the document is the XML rendering (a </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e163 e163" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">manifestation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> in the FRBR model) of a certain version (an </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e164 e164" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">expression</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> in FRBR) of a document (a </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e165 e165" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">work</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">), so that we can formally distinguish between different aspects of the idea of document. A detailed account of FRBR in Akoma Ntoso can be found in [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e166 e166" linkend="AkomaFRBR"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].</textual></para><para class="po-block e167 e167"><textual class="po-textual">In addition to these kinds of metadata, there are other types of metadata currently defined (e.g., </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e168 e168" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">lifecycle</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e169 e169" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">workflow</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> elements for tracking the events affecting the document) and other are being added as Akoma Ntoso extends to its reach to more and more types of analysis of the legal text.</textual></para><para class="po-block e170 e170"><textual class="po-textual">All the information gathered in the metadata layer is derived from the legal text (using the data layers) though subjective reasoning. Many different interpretation can arise over the same legal text from different legal experts. Take, for instance, the following sentence: “the subsection 3 of the section 42 states a modification of the section 44 of the same act”. Two different actors may disagree on the interpretation of that sentence: one sees it as an </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e171 e171" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">authentic interpretation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, another as a </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e172 e172" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">derogation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. From a the legal point of view, the two types of modification produce different effects: the authentic interpretation is applied </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e173 e173" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">ex-tunc</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (since the beginning), while the derogation is an exception under some condition. Akoma Ntoso allows both interpretations to coexists in the same document, even if they are in contrast.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e174 e174" xml:id="SectionSemanticTechnologies"><title class="po-block e175 e175"><textual class="po-textual">Semantic technologies and reasoning on Akoma Ntoso documents</textual></title><para class="po-block e176 e176"><textual class="po-textual">Currently, there are interesting developments in the area of legal knowledge representation and manipulation. Akoma Ntoso documents, with their rich metadata layer, can serve as the basis upon which various tools can work on. For example representations expressed at the metadata layer can be used to generate a legal ontology to be used by legal rule modelling technologies like RuleML [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e177 e177" linkend="RuleML"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] or the more specialized LKIF [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e178 e178" linkend="LKIF"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].</textual></para><para class="po-block e179 e179"><textual class="po-textual">Akoma Ntoso documents are not tied to a particular semantic technology or to particular ontology. The current format is very loose and permits the conversion of information into more specific data models (like RDF [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e180 e180" linkend="RDF"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], OWL [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e181 e181" linkend="OWL"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] or Topic Maps [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e182 e182" linkend="TopicMaps"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]). This strategy warrants that semantic technologies of the future decades will be able to convert Akoma Ntoso documents into their own format without going through what, by then, may be seen as ancient formats or data models.</textual></para><para class="po-block e183 e183"><textual class="po-textual">Even if Akoma Ntoso does not impose which ontology to use to represent legal and legislative concepts, it relies on the FRBR [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e184 e184" linkend="FRBR"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] concepts of Work, Manifestation, Expression and Item to describe the relation of a certain document to other documents – for example to distinguish references to the generic Wildlife Act (Work) from references to the Wildlife Act valid in 2008 (Manifestation) and to references to a document that contains the said Wildlife Act valid in 2008 (Expression).</textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e185 e185" xml:id="ottupla"><title class="po-block e186 e186"><textual class="po-textual">Representation of facts in Akoma Ntoso</textual></title><para class="po-block e187 e187"><textual class="po-textual">Akoma Ntoso documents can be seen as containers of statements written in some legal human language. The formalization of these statements must take into account many subtle distinctions in order to carry all the meaning that the legal systems pose on these statements.</textual></para><para class="po-block e188 e188"><textual class="po-textual">All statements in an Akoma Ntoso documents follow this schema:</textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e189 e189"><para class="po-block e190 e190"><textual class="po-textual">the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e191 e191" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">author of a manifestation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (XML rendering) asserts on the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e192 e192" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">manifestation date</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> that </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e193 e193" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">the author of the corresponding expression</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (version with a specific content) asserts on the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e194 e194" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">expression date</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> in a particular </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e195 e195" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">context</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> that </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e196 e196" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">subject</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> does </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e197 e197" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">predicate</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> on </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e198 e198" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">object</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e199 e199"><textual class="po-textual">We can formalize this schema with an octuple:</textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e200 e200"><para class="po-block e201 e201"><textual class="po-textual">(manifestation_author, manifestation_time, expression_author, expression_time, context, subject, predicate, object)</textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e202 e202"><textual class="po-textual">Consider for instance the example already illustrated in the previous sections:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e203 e203" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;analysis source="#cirsfid"&gt;
    &lt;textualMod type="substitution" id="am5"&gt;
        &lt;source href="#sec4-sub1-itma"/&gt;
        &lt;destination href="/ke/act/1997-08-22/3/main#sec34-sub2-itma"/&gt;
        &lt;old href="#mod10-qtd1"/&gt;
        &lt;new href="#mod10-qtd2"/&gt;
    &lt;/textualMod&gt;
&lt;/analysis&gt;
&lt;identification source="#cirsfid"&gt;
    &lt;FRBRExpression&gt;
        &lt;FRBRthis value="/ke/act/2003-12-10/8/eng@"/&gt;
        &lt;FRBRdate date="2003-12-10" name="Generation"/&gt;
        &lt;FRBRauthor href="#parliament" as="#author"/&gt;
    &lt;/FRBRExpression&gt;
    &lt;FRBRManifestation&gt;
        &lt;FRBRthis value="/ke/act/2003-12-10/8/eng.akn"/&gt;
        &lt;FRBRdate date="2007-07-27" name="Generation"/&gt;
        &lt;FRBRauthor href="#cirsfid" as="#editor"/&gt;
    &lt;/FRBRManifestation&gt;
&lt;/identification&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e204 e204"><textual class="po-textual">One of the assertions contained in the above extract is that </textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e205 e205"><para class="po-block e206 e206"><emphasis class="po-inline e207 e207" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">#cirsfid</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (editor of the manifestation) asserts on 27th July, 2007 (date of the manifestation) that the #parliament (author of the expression) asserts on 10th December, 2003 (date of the expression) that in the context of the fragment with id </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e208 e208" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">#art4-cla1-itma</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> the text modification </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e209 e209" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">am5</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> has been performed which is of type substitution</textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e210 e210"><textual class="po-textual">or, using an octuple</textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e211 e211"><para class="po-block e212 e212"><textual class="po-textual">(#cirsfid, “2007-07-27”, #parliament, “2003-12-10”, #art4-cla1-itma, #am5, isOfType, “substitution”)</textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e213 e213"><textual class="po-textual">It must be pointed out that not all the parts of these assertions lay at the same FRBR level: some are inherently properties of the FRBR manifestation (the date when </textual><code class="po-atom e214 e214"><textual class="po-textual">#cirsfid</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> did add its own metadata to the Akoma Ntoso file containing the act) while other are properties of the connected FRBR expression (the date when </textual><code class="po-atom e215 e215"><textual class="po-textual">#parliament</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> did approve the act). For this reason, every Akoma Ntoso document explicitly states what are the FRBR manifestation and expression that it is modelling inside the </textual><code class="po-atom e216 e216"><textual class="po-textual">FRBRthis</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> element. The </textual><code class="po-atom e217 e217"><textual class="po-textual">value</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> attribute of </textual><code class="po-atom e218 e218"><textual class="po-textual">FRBRthis</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> specifies the URI of the document on which all the assertions are made.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e219 e219" xml:id="SectionSemanticallyAnonymous"><title class="po-block e220 e220"><textual class="po-textual">Everything is semantically generic</textual></title><para class="po-block e221 e221"><textual class="po-textual">Akoma Ntoso defines an ontological structure for metadata that is grounded on what we call the</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e222 e222" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual"> Top Level Classes</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e223 e223" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">TLC</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">). They do not define a real ontology: on purpose, none of the TLCs has a precise meaning nor a well-defined set of properties. The only constraint imposed on them is that all the instances of a certain TLC must follow the Akoma Ntoso naming guideline in the definition of their URI [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e224 e224" linkend="NamingConvention"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. This choice is driven by a precise design intent: the ontology used to manage the concepts expressed in Akoma Ntoso documents is not hard coded in the document, but can be decided at will by individual users and applications, according to their particular needs.</textual></para><para class="po-block e225 e225"><textual class="po-textual">Furthermore, TLCs, even if represented by a clear label and a specific URI, have neither formal (logically defined) nor informal (written in natural language) semantics. Akoma Ntoso does not define the classes of a particular ontology but only the URIs and labels that should be used for the classes defined in all ontologies.</textual></para><para class="po-block e226 e226"><textual class="po-textual">This assumption is needed to allow a great degree of flexibility in what can be expressed in the metadata layer of Akoma Ntoso documents, in order to adapt any legal document to any ontological representation of concepts. It is the duty of a third party, possibly the document editor, possibly its users, to associate a clear and formal semantics to each class using a specific formalism (e.g. OWL). This semantic genericness, coupled with XML elements whose names resemble familiar concepts, is an important feature that allows Akoma Ntoso to maintain documents understandable and consumable independently from the passing of time: future toolmakers (“The 'future toolmaker' is 10 years old now.” [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e227 e227" linkend="PotentialUsers"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]) will have clues about the intended meaning of a marker even in the unfortunate case the formal ontology is no longer available.</textual></para><para class="po-block e228 e228"><textual class="po-textual">Akoma Ntoso makes ten different and disjoint TLCs available to document creators in order to identify individual entities present in the document: Person, Organization, Concept, Object, Event, Place, Process, Role, Term, Reference (all identified by the URIs </textual><code class="po-atom e229 e229"><textual class="po-textual">/ontology/[</textual></code><code class="po-atom e230 e230"><textual class="po-textual">TLC</textual></code><code class="po-atom e231 e231"><textual class="po-textual">]</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">).</textual></para><para class="po-block e232 e232"><textual class="po-textual">Using these TLCs and the canonical FRBR classes Work, Expression, Manifestation and Item, it is possible to make quite complex assertions on Akoma Ntoso documents. Akoma Ntoso does not aim at describing neither objective facts nor personal opinions about such classes according to the author of the document: rather it allows to express an interpretation that is due, in a precise moment, to a particular actor working on the statements that can be found in the published legal text (e.g., the interpretation of </textual><code class="po-atom e233 e233"><textual class="po-textual">#cirsfid</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> of the correct interpretation of the nature of the textual modification </textual><code class="po-atom e234 e234"><textual class="po-textual">am5</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">).</textual></para><para class="po-block e235 e235"><textual class="po-textual">By defining a mechanism for describing items (actors, legal documents, properties, concepts, etc.) that are involved in the assertions (both making assertions and being the subject of an assertion), and by relating them to some TLC, we are able to assert facts about an Akoma Ntoso document, implicitly producing a data model for its semantic data.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e236 e236" xml:id="SectionURINaming"><title class="po-block e237 e237"><textual class="po-textual">Ontology URI naming conversion</textual></title><para class="po-block e238 e238"><textual class="po-textual">All the items in an Akoma Ntoso document can belong to a particular TLC simply by specifying an URI that follows a naming convention [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e239 e239" linkend="NamingConvention"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. The following example shows a list of URIs pointing to the same entity.</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e240 e240" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">/ontology/Person/lewanika.1961
/ontology/Person/judges/lewanika.1961
/ontology/Person/za/judges/lewanika.1961</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e241 e241"><textual class="po-textual">Even if a human can interpret them in some ways depending on the particular interpretation used, from an ontological point of view all these three URIs say the same thing: they identify an instance of the top level class Person and they identify exactly the same instance in any ontology (regardless of the ontology).</textual></para><para class="po-block e242 e242"><textual class="po-textual">The Akoma Ntoso naming convention contains few precise rules:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e243 e243"><listitem class="po-container e244 e244"><para class="po-block e245 e245"><textual class="po-textual">the first two fragments of the URI (</textual><code class="po-atom e246 e246"><textual class="po-textual">/ontology/Person</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">) specify the TLC the instance belongs to;</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e247 e247"><para class="po-block e248 e248"><textual class="po-textual">the last fragment of the URI (</textual><code class="po-atom e249 e249"><textual class="po-textual">lewanika.1961</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> in the above example) is the identifier of the instance we are referring to (a South African judge called Lewanika and born in 1961);</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e250 e250"><para class="po-block e251 e251"><textual class="po-textual">the middle URI fragments (</textual><code class="po-atom e252 e252"><textual class="po-textual">za/judges/</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">), when they are present, provide evocative information for the human reader and for the systems that cannot use any more detailed ontology for the document. They suggest, in fact, a clear interpretation from a human perspective, e.g., that Lewanika is a South African person holding the role of judge. Since Akoma Ntoso does not force any given set of properties for the top level classes, the responsibility to choose which, and whether, additional fragments should be added lies with the author of the manifestation.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e253 e253"><textual class="po-textual">Taking into account the implicit semantics given to each URI by the Akoma Ntoso naming convention, it is possible to query an Akoma Ntoso-compliant legal XML document using XPath [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e254 e254" linkend="XPath"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], without relying on external ontologies. The following excerpt shows some references to various resource.</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e255 e255" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;akomaNtoso xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/1.0"&gt; 
    &lt;references source="#cirsfid"&gt; 
        &lt;TLCOrganization id="parliament" 
            showAs="Parliament of Kenya" 
            href="/ontology/Organization/ke/parliament" /&gt; 
        &lt;TLCOrganization id="cirsfid" showAs="CIRSFID" 
            href="/ontology/Organization/cirsfid" /&gt; 
        &lt;TLCPerson id="fv" showAs="Fabio Vitali" 
            href="/ontology/Person/fv" /&gt; 
        &lt;TLCRole id="author" showAs="Author" 
            href="/ontology/Roles/author" /&gt; 
        &lt;TLCRole id="jurist" showAs="Jurist" 
            href="/ontology/Roles/jurist" /&gt; 
        &lt;TLCRole id="editor" showAs="Editor" 
            href="/ontology/Roles/editor" /&gt; 
    &lt;/references&gt;
    [...]</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e256 e256"><textual class="po-textual">Through XPath, it is possible to perform queries based on the semantic data that is present in the document. For example, the following queries could be performed on the data shown in the above excerpt:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e257 e257"><listitem class="po-container e258 e258"><para class="po-block e259 e259"><textual class="po-textual">what roles have been involved in the generation of the legal document: </textual><code class="po-atom e260 e260"><textual class="po-textual">//references/element()[matches(@href,'/Roles/')]</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">;</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e261 e261"><para class="po-block e262 e262"><textual class="po-textual">which Kenyan organizations are referred to in the legal document: </textual><code class="po-atom e263 e263"><textual class="po-textual">//references/element()[matches(@href,'/Organization/.*/ke/')]</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e264 e264"><textual class="po-textual">The naming convention used by Akoma Ntoso, together with the presence of additional middle URI fragments, allows the semantic data available in the document to be queried, even in sophisticated ways, without requiring access to any ontology. When the underlying ontology is available, the additional information provided by the middle URI fragments can be discarded and more complex queries, based on deductive elements such as those gathered through the use of reasoners, can be performed. The optional middle URI fragments fulfil, thus, two different tasks: on the one hand they provide clues to the human readers who do not have access to the underlying ontologies, on the other hand they allow semantic data about the referenced entities to be carried also in the document itself and not only in external knowledge bases.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e265 e265" xml:id="SectionGRDDL"><title class="po-block e266 e266"><textual class="po-textual">Transformation into a proper semantic data model format</textual></title><para class="po-block e267 e267"><textual class="po-textual">In order to be able to carry out more complex queries on the facts expressed in Akoma Ntoso documents, it is necessary to bind the abstract Akoma Ntoso classes and instances to external ontological models. This also require to translate the same facts to a more concrete representations that the current semantic tools can work with (e.g., RDF and Topic Maps). This happens without specifying a particular format, but allowing users to choose their favourite formats and tools, a choice that the users will take on the base of current languages, their knowledge and other technical constraints.</textual></para><para class="po-block e268 e268"><textual class="po-textual">An example of a concrete data model format that today fits the current technology scenario is RDF [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e269 e269" linkend="RDF"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. Although the following example, covering the extraction of metadata from Akoma Ntoso documents, is completely based on RDF, it is also possible to use different end-format for expressing these semantic data, such as Topic Maps [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e270 e270" linkend="TopicMaps"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. In any case, if we wanted to convert an XML document into a set of RDF/Topic Maps assertions, we could use a GRDDL transformation. GRDDL (Gleaning Resource Descriptions from Dialects of Languages) [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e271 e271" linkend="GRDDL"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] is a W3C Recommendation that standardize the extraction of semantic data from XML documents using one or more XSLT stylesheets [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e272 e272" linkend="XSLT"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], obtaining, in the particular example presented, an RDF document. Note that this particular mechanism it is also suggested in the current CEN Metalex proposal [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e273 e273" linkend="CENMetalex"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] of which Akoma Ntoso is a compliant instance:</textual></para><blockquote class="po-container e274 e274"><para class="po-block e275 e275"><textual class="po-textual">If metadata is not available as RDFa, it must be systematically translatable from the custom format to RDF. The translation from a proprietary metadata format to RDF must be publicly available following the Gleaning Resource Descriptions from Dialects of Languages (GRDDL) specification.</textual></para></blockquote><para class="po-block e276 e276"><textual class="po-textual">It is easy to convert an Akoma Ntoso document in one of the semantic formats currently available. For example, if we consider the FRBR class implicitly defined within the Akoma Ntoso schema, we could generate assertions that link FRBR instances gleaned from a document to the OWL-specified FRBR ontology, simply through GRDDL. Given the following fragment:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e277 e277" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;identification source="#cirsfid"&gt;
    &lt;FRBRExpression&gt;
        &lt;FRBRthis value="/ke/act/2003-12-10/8/eng@"/&gt;
        &lt;FRBRdate date="2003-12-10" name="Generation"/&gt;
        &lt;FRBRauthor href="#parliament" as="#author"/&gt;
    &lt;/FRBRExpression&gt;
    &lt;FRBRManifestation&gt;
        &lt;FRBRthis value="/ke/act/2003-12-10/8/eng.akn"/&gt;
        &lt;FRBRdate date="2007-07-27" name="Generation" /&gt;
        &lt;FRBRauthor href="#cirsfid" as="#editor" /&gt;
    &lt;/FRBRManifestation&gt;
&lt;/identification&gt;

&lt;references source="#cirsfid"&gt;
    &lt;TLCOrganization id="parliament" showAs="Parliament of Kenya"
     href="/ontology/Organization/ke/parliament"/&gt;
    &lt;TLCRole id="author" showAs="Author" href="/ontology/Role/author"/&gt;
&lt;/references&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e278 e278"><textual class="po-textual">we can use GRDDL to obtain assertions such as the following:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e279 e279" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">@prefix ke: &lt;http://www.akomantoso.org/ke&gt; .
@prefix an: &lt;http://www.akomantoso.org/ontology/&gt; .

ke:/act/2003-12-10/8/eng@ a an:FRBRExpression ; 
    an:hasDate "2003-12-10" ;
    an:hasAuthor an:Organization/ke/parliament .
an:Organization/ke/parliament an:hasRole an:Role/author .</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e280 e280"><textual class="po-textual">These are just plain RDF statements unrelated to any logical structure. To address particular demands (such as reasoning, data sharing and so on) we need to associate those instances, classes and properties to well-defined ontologies. Though an additional XSLT stylesheet in the GRDDL process we can add new ontological data about FRBR:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e281 e281" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">@prefix frbr: &lt;http://purl.org/vocab/frbr/core#&gt; .
@prefix dc: &lt;http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/&gt; .
@prefix owl: &lt;http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#&gt; .

an:FRBRExpression owl:sameAs frbr:Expression .
ke:/act/2003-12-10/8/eng@ frbr:realizer an:person/Organization/ke/parliament .
an:hasDate owl:sameAs dc:date .</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e282 e282"><textual class="po-textual">Unfortunately, even if we can define semantics in order to infer automatically new data, OWL does not have a native or standard way to model reified statements. To represent in OWL the Akoma Ntoso octuple statement illustrated previously, we have to resort to peculiar approaches. The NeOn project [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e283 e283" linkend="NeOn"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] has developed many elegant and logically-sound techniques to overcome the limitations of OWL; they have been collected under the name of Ontology Design Pattern [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e284 e284" linkend="Pattern"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. The Ontology Design Patterns are a set of guidelines that help the design process of ontologies; each pattern codifies one or more best practices of the ontology-design realm. The following examples will use and briefly introduce some of those patterns; a proper description of each used pattern is out of the scope of our paper.</textual></para><para class="po-block e285 e285"><textual class="po-textual">The most straightforward way to handle complex assertions, such as the octuples used by Akoma Ntoso, in OWL is to use the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e286 e286" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">n-ary participation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> pattern. The n-ary participation pattern is used to describe events happening in a certain moment and that involve one or more entities. This pattern can also be used to simulate RDF reifications in OWL. </textual><xref class="po-milestone e287 e287" linkend="OWLFigure"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> shows a graphical representation of the previously shown octuple expressed in OWL using the n-ary participation pattern.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e288 e288" xml:id="OWLFigure" xreflabel="Figure 1"><title class="po-block e289 e289"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e290 e290"><imageobject class="po-container e291 e291"><imagedata class="po-meta e292 e292" fileref="../../../vol5/graphics/Barabucci01/Barabucci01-001.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject><caption class="po-container e293 e293"><para class="po-block e294 e294"><textual class="po-textual">A possible Akoma Ntoso data extraction into a OWL pattern-based format of the octuple introduced in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e295 e295" linkend="SectionGRDDL"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></caption></mediaobject></figure></section><section class="po-hcontainer e296 e296"><title class="po-block e297 e297"><textual class="po-textual">Querying Akoma Ntoso documents</textual></title><para class="po-block e298 e298"><textual class="po-textual">Having an RDF/OWL or a Topic Maps representation of Akoma Ntoso data could be very useful in querying metadata of a legislative document using different and much more proper tools than XPath to query data models, such as SPARQL [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e299 e299" linkend="SPARQL"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] and TMQL [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e300 e300" linkend="TMQL"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] according to the format we use to express Akoma Ntoso metadata. Let us take into consideration the following excerpt from an Akoma Ntoso document:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e301 e301" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;identification source="#cirsfid"&gt;
    &lt;FRBRWork&gt;
        &lt;FRBRthis value="/ke/act/2003-12-10/8"/&gt;
        &lt;FRBRauthor href="#parliament" as="#author"/&gt;
    &lt;/FRBRWork&gt;
    &lt;FRBRExpression&gt;
        &lt;FRBRthis value="/ke/act/2003-12-10/8/eng@"/&gt;
        &lt;FRBRauthor href="#parliament" as="#author"/&gt;
    &lt;/FRBRExpression&gt;
    &lt;FRBRManifestation&gt;
        &lt;FRBRauthor href="#cirsfid" as="#editor"/&gt;
        &lt;FRBRauthor href="#fv" as="#editor"/&gt;
    &lt;/FRBRManifestation&gt;
&lt;/identification&gt;

&lt;references source="#cirsfid"&gt;
    &lt;TLCOrganization id="cirsfid" href="/ontology/Organization/cirsfid"/&gt;
    &lt;TLCPerson id="fv" href="/ontology/Person/fv" /&gt;
&lt;/references&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e302 e302"><textual class="po-textual">Suppose we want to query it looking for whether the document is a candidate to be an authoritative Expression of a given Work (i.e., the author of the Expression is the same of the Work).</textual></para><para class="po-block e303 e303"><textual class="po-textual">We can describe this request in a query comparing two different XPath expressions:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e304 e304" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">//FRBRExpression/FRBRauthor/@href = //FRBRWork/FRBRauthor/@href</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e305 e305"><textual class="po-textual">Obviously, querying the Akoma Ntoso metadata through XPath is possible, but it can be also intricate: XPath was developed to browse easily XML hierarchies, that are trees, not to query much more complicate data structures (i.e., a graph) such as the one implicitly defined through Akoma Ntoso metadata. The previous XPath expressions give the correct answers for the respective queries but the way in which a user query the document is not so natural.</textual></para><para class="po-block e306 e306"><textual class="po-textual">Converting the Akoma Ntoso metadata into a data model format, such as RDF or Topic Maps, can help to build queries in a much easier way, using specific languages (e.g., SPARQL or TMQL) expressly developed to handle these scenarios. Let us take into consideration an OWL ontology</textual><footnote class="po-popup e307 e307" xml:id="ftn7"><para class="po-block e308 e308"><link class="po-inline e309 e309" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://purl.org/vocab/frbr/core" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://purl.org/vocab/frbr/core</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> describing the FRBR data shown in the previous excerpt. Then, we can query the ontology using a SPARQL representation of the previous XPath expressions:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e310 e310" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">ASK {
    ?e frbr:realizer ?a .
    ?w frbr:creator ?a .
    ?e akomantoso:frbrthis "/ke/act/2003-12-10/8/eng@" .
    ?e frbr:realizes ?w .
}</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e311 e311"><textual class="po-textual">The conversion from an Akoma Ntoso document into an OWL document can be done in an automatic way using GRDDL [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e312 e312" linkend="GRDDL"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. Moreover, this transformation is completely free of constraints: we can use whatever ontologies we prefer to represent those data according to some particular model-representation needs.</textual></para><para class="po-block e313 e313"><textual class="po-textual">In order to demonstrate the feasibility of the GRDDL approach, we developed an XSLT that extracts metadata from an Akoma Ntoso document according to three different ontologies – the FRBR OWL ontology, the n-ary participation pattern ontology, and an ontology for handling other data concerning textual modifications.</textual></para><para class="po-block e314 e314"><textual class="po-textual">Let us give an example: the XSLT template to transform the FRBR manifestation of an Akoma Ntoso document into RDF statements:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e315 e315" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;xsl:template match="an:FRBRManifestation"&gt;
    &lt;frbr:Manifestation 
        rdf:about="{//an:FRBRManifestation/an:FRBRthis/@value}"&gt;
        &lt;xsl:for-each select="an:FRBRauthor"&gt;
            &lt;frbr:producer rdf:resource="{$uri}
                {//an:references/element()
                    [@id = substring-after(@href,'#')]/@href}" /&gt;
        &lt;/xsl:for-each&gt;
        &lt;dc:date&gt;&lt;xsl:value-of select="an:FRBRdate/@date" /&gt;&lt;/dc:date&gt;
    &lt;/frbr:Manifestation&gt;
&lt;/xsl:template&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e316 e316"><textual class="po-textual">Using this template, we are able to map any element and attribute involved in the description of an FRBR manifestation of any Akoma Ntoso document onto proper classes and individuals, in particular:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e317 e317"><listitem class="po-container e318 e318"><para class="po-block e319 e319"><textual class="po-textual">Akoma Ntoso </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e320 e320" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">FRBRManifestation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> elements are represented by the class </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e321 e321" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Manifestation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> of the FRBR ontology;</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e322 e322"><para class="po-block e323 e323"><textual class="po-textual">all the URIs contained in the attribute </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e324 e324" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">value</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> of the element </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e325 e325" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">FRBRthis</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> of any </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e326 e326" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">FRBRManifestation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> become proper individuals belonging to the class </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e327 e327" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Manifestation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">;</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e328 e328"><para class="po-block e329 e329"><textual class="po-textual">each </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e330 e330" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">FRBRauthor</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> contained in a particular </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e331 e331" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">FRBRManifestation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> is mapped adding an RDF statement having as subject the particular ontological individual of that manifestation, as object the resource identified by the URI specified as value of the attribute </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e332 e332" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">id </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">of a TLC, obtained by dereferencing the attribute </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e333 e333" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">href</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> of the element </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e334 e334" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">FRBRauthor</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, and, as predicate, the object property </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e335 e335" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">producer</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> of the FRBR ontology;</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e336 e336"><para class="po-block e337 e337"><textual class="po-textual">the value of the attribute </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e338 e338" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">date</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> of the element </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e339 e339" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">FRBRdate</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> contained in </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e340 e340" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">FRBRManifestation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> becomes the object literal of the RDF statement obtained using, as subject, the ontological individual refers to the manifestation we are processing, and, as predicate, the Dublin Core [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e341 e341" linkend="DublinCore"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] property </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e342 e342" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">date</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e343 e343"><textual class="po-textual">Applying this template on an Akoma Ntoso document, we obtain the following RDF statements:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e344 e344" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">@prefix m: &lt;http://www.akomantoso.org/&gt; .

m:ke/act/2003-12-10/8/eng.akn a frbr:Manifestation ; 
    dc:date "2007-07-27" ;
    frbr:producer m:ontology/Person/fv , m:ontology/Organization/cirsfid .</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e345 e345"><textual class="po-textual">Similarly, we wrote a template based on the n-ary participation pattern and our textual modifications model that, for instance, allows us to export the relative Akoma Ntoso metadata of the excerpt shown in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e346 e346" linkend="ottupla"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> in the following statements:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e347 e347" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">m:manifestation_time a ti:TimeInterval ; 
    ti:hasIntervalDate "2007-07-27" .

m:ontology/Organization/ke/parliament a part:Object .

m:author_tuple_5 a nary:NaryParticipation ;
    nary:participationIncludes m:ontology/Organization/ke/parliament , 
        m:author_tuple_5_tmod , m:expression_time .

m:author_tuple_5_tmod a m:substitution ;
    part:hasParticipant m:ke/act/2003-12-10/8/eng.akn#am5 .

m:marker_tuple_5 a nary:NaryParticipation ;
    nary:participationIncludes m:manifestation_time , 
        m:author_tuple_5 , m:ontology/Person/fv ,
        m:ontology/Organization/cirsfid .

m:substitution a owl:Class ; rdfs:subClassOf part:Event .

m:ontology/Person/fv a part:Object .

m:ke/act/2003-12-10/8/eng.akn#am5 a tm:TextualModification ;
    tm:hasDestination m:ke/act/1997-08-22/3/eng/main#art34-cla2-itma ;
tm:hasNewText "statement of assets and liabilities" ;
tm:hasOldText "balance sheet" ;
tm:hasSource m:ke/act/1997-08-22/3/eng/main#art34-cla2-itma , 
        m:ke/act/2003-12-10/8/eng.akn#art4-cla1-itma .

m:expression_time a ti:TimeInterval ; ti:hasIntervalDate "2003-12-10" .

m:ontology/Organization/cirsfid a part:Object .</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e348 e348"><textual class="po-textual">These pieces of code show that the creation of a GRDDL process to extract metadata from an Akoma Ntoso document is quite feasible and moreover is also very flexible and adaptable according to particular needs. Apart from being able to query data through SPARQL or TMQL, modelling Akoma Ntoso metadata by OWL or Topic Maps it is possible to use reasoners to infer new assertions on the basis of all the extracted data from Akoma Ntoso documents available.</textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e349 e349"><title class="po-block e350 e350"><textual class="po-textual">Conclusions</textual></title><para class="po-block e351 e351"><textual class="po-textual">Akoma Ntoso has been designed as a format for legal documents that must be read and understood for decades and at the same time be useful to computer applications, including semantic reasoners. In order to balance clearness, fidelity to the authentic legal text, interoperability and usability with semantic tools, Akoma Ntoso made some clear design choices. In this paper we showed how these choices fit the stated goals: using XML as the underlying mark-up format and having clearly separated layers allow documents to be preserved for long periods of time and without modifications to the endorsed texts. Additionally, multiple agents can provide their own interpretation of certain legal aspects of the given legal text. Moreover, computer reasoners can extract semantic information from Akoma Ntoso documents and reason over them both with or without user-supplied ontologies.</textual></para><para class="po-block e352 e352"><textual class="po-textual">The approach used by Akoma Ntoso allows the development of systems that use more sophisticated formal logic modelling framework, like non-monotonic or non-deductive logics in order to apply sophisticated legal reasoning theories, more suitable for the complex legal domain, filling the gap between all the semantic web layers while preserving interdependency and expressiveness.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e353 e353" xml:id="Ack"><title class="po-block e354 e354"><textual class="po-textual">Acknowledgments</textual></title><para class="po-block e355 e355"><textual class="po-textual">The authors would like to thank Flavio Zeni (Kenya Unit of UN/DESA) and all of his team, for supporting the Akoma Ntoso project and for permitting this research project. We would also like to thank Alexander Boer and Enrico Francesconi for their precious contributions on the definition of the URI syntax.</textual></para></section><bibliography class="po-hcontainer e356 e356"><title class="po-block e357 e357"><textual class="po-textual">Bibliography</textual></title><bibliomixed class="po-block e358 e358" xml:id="SPARQL" xreflabel="1"><textual class="po-textual">Beckett D., Broekstra J. (2008). SPARQL Query Language for RDF. W3C Recommendation. World Wide Web Consortium. http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-sparql-query/.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e359 e359" xml:id="XPath" xreflabel="2"><textual class="po-textual">Berglund, A., Boag, S., Chamberlin, D., Fernández, M. F., Kay, M., Robie, J., Siméon, J. (2007). XML Path Language (XPath) 2.0. W3C Recommendation. World Wide Web Consortium. http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath20/.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e360 e360" xml:id="CENMetalex" xreflabel="3"><textual class="po-textual">Boer, A., Vitali, F., Palmirani, M., Retai, B. (2009). CEN Metalex workshop agreement. http://www.metalex.eu/WA/proposal.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e361 e361" xml:id="GRDDL" xreflabel="4"><textual class="po-textual">Connolly, D. (2007). Gleaning Resource Descriptions from Dialects of Languages (GRDDL). W3C Recommendation. World Wide Web Consortium. http://www.w3.org/TR/grddl/</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e362 e362" xml:id="LKIF" xreflabel="5"><textual class="po-textual">Gordon, T.F. (2008. Constructing Legal Arguments with Rules in the Legal Knowledge Interchange Format (LKIF). In Computable Models of the Law: Languages, Dialogues, Games, Ontologies, pp. 162-184.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e363 e363" xml:id="RuleML" xreflabel="6"><textual class="po-textual">Hirtle, D., Boley, H., Grosof, B., Kifer, M., Sintek, M., Tabet, S., Wagner, G. (2006). Schema Specification of RuleML 0.91. http://ruleml.org/0.91/.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e364 e364" xml:id="FRBR" xreflabel="7"><textual class="po-textual">IFLA Study Group on the Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records. (1998). Functional requirements for bibliographic records: final report. K. G. Saur.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e365 e365" xml:id="XSLT" xreflabel="8"><textual class="po-textual">Kay, M (2007). XSL Transformations (XSLT) Version 2.0. W3C Recommendation. World Wide Web Consortium. http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e366 e366" xml:id="RDF" xreflabel="9"><textual class="po-textual">Manola, F., Miller, E. (2004). RDF Primer. W3C Recommendation. World Wide Web Consortium. http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-primer/.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e367 e367" xml:id="DublinCore" xreflabel="10"><textual class="po-textual">Nilsson, M., Powell, A., Johnston, P., Naeve, A. (2007). Expressing Dublin Core metadata using the Resource Description Framework (RDF). http://dublincore.org//documents/2007/06/04/dc-rdf.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e368 e368" xml:id="Norma" xreflabel="11"><textual class="po-textual">Palmirani, M., Benigni, F. (2007). Norma-System: A Legal Information System for Managing Time. In V Legislative XML Workshop, pp. 205-224.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e369 e369" xml:id="FillTheGap" xreflabel="12"><textual class="po-textual">Palmirani, M., Contissa, G., Rubino, R. (2009). Fill the gap in the legal knowledge modelling. In the Proceeding of RuleML 2009, pp. 305-314.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e370 e370" xml:id="Pattern" xreflabel="13"><textual class="po-textual">Presutti, V., Gangemi, A. (2008). Content ontology design patterns as practical building blocks for web ontologies. In the Proceedings of 27th International Conference on Conceptual Modeling (ER2008). Barcelona, Spain.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e371 e371" xml:id="NeOn" xreflabel="14"><textual class="po-textual">Presutti, V., Gangemi, A., David, S., Aguado de Cea, G., Suárez-Figueroa, M. C., Montiel-Ponsoda, E., Poveda, M. (2008). A Library of Ontology Design Patterns. NeOn project deliverable D2.5.1.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e372 e372" xml:id="TopicMaps" xreflabel="15"><textual class="po-textual">SC34/WG3. (2003). Topic Maps. ISO 13250. International Organization for Standardization. Geneva, Switzerland.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e373 e373" xml:id="TMQL" xreflabel="16"><textual class="po-textual">SC34/WG3. (2008). Topic Maps Query Language (TMQL). ISO 18048. International Organization for Standardization. Geneva, Switzerland.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e374 e374" xml:id="NamingConvention" xreflabel="17"><textual class="po-textual">United Nations. (2009). Akoma Ntoso: Naming Conventions. http://www.akomantoso.org/release-notes/akoma-ntoso-1.0-schema/naming-conventions-1.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e375 e375" xml:id="PotentialUsers" xreflabel="18"><textual class="po-textual">United Nations. (2009). Akoma Ntoso: Potential users, http://www.akomantoso.org/akoma-ntoso-in-detail/users.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e376 e376" xml:id="OWL" xreflabel="19"><textual class="po-textual">W3C OWL Working Group (2009). OWL 2 Web Ontology Language Document Overview. W3C Recommendation. World Wide Web Consortium. http://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-overview/.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e377 e377" xml:id="AkomaFRBR" xreflabel="20"><textual class="po-textual">de Oliveira Lima, A., Palmirani, M., Vitali, F. (2008). Moving in the Time: An Ontology for Identifying Legal Resources. In Computable Models of the Law, Languages, Dialogues, Games, Ontologies pp. 71-85.</textual></bibliomixed></bibliography></article></classedDocument>