<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">Report from the Front: EPUB3</textual></title><info class="po-record e2 e2"><confgroup class="po-record e3 e3"><conftitle class="po-field e4 e4"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">August 2 - 5, 2011</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e6 e6"><para class="po-block e7 e7"><textual class="po-textual">In 2010, the IDPF chartered a working group to update the EPUB specification to more
            accurately reflect the demands and expectations of a quickly growing marketplace. The
            specific items to be addressed included: </textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e8 e8"><listitem class="po-container e9 e9"><para class="po-block e10 e10"><textual class="po-textual">Greater rich media (audio and video) and interactivity support
                        (programmatic content, such as would be needed to implement a quiz or
                        crossword puzzle).</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e11 e11"><para class="po-block e12 e12"><textual class="po-textual">Enhanced global language support for the character sets, Ruby markup, and
                        typographic rules needed for reading systems in CJK geographies (including
                        but not limited to special line-breaking rules and vertical writing
                        direction). </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e13 e13"><para class="po-block e14 e14"><textual class="po-textual">Enhanced article support in order to support magazines and
                        newspapers.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e15 e15"><para class="po-block e16 e16"><textual class="po-textual">Enhanced metadata support beyond embedded publication metadata. </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e17 e17"><para class="po-block e18 e18"><textual class="po-textual">Ability to convey page-level layouts and target multiple display surface
                        sizes in a single publication.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e19 e19"><para class="po-block e20 e20"><textual class="po-textual">Enhanced navigation support.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e21 e21"><para class="po-block e22 e22"><textual class="po-textual">Alignment with broadly-adopted Web standards as implemented by modern
                        browsers. </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e23 e23"><para class="po-block e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">Support for annotation. </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e25 e25"><para class="po-block e26 e26"><textual class="po-textual">Native support for mathematics. </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e27 e27"><para class="po-block e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">Support for book-specific structures, such as glossaries, note reference
                        systems and advanced cross-reference systems. </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e29 e29"><para class="po-block e30 e30"><textual class="po-textual">Improved accessibility support.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e31 e31"><para class="po-block e32 e32"><textual class="po-textual">Mechanism for adding industry specific extensions in an interoperable
                        manner.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e33 e33"><para class="po-block e34 e34"><textual class="po-textual">Define relationships to approved national and international
                        standards.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e35 e35"><para class="po-block e36 e36"><textual class="po-textual">Define mechanism for including advertising.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><textual class="po-textual">This paper will discuss those changes and present the author's view on
            whether the goals set forth by the IDPF were met. The potential impacts on the market
            from both the publisher and consumer view will also be considered.</textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e37 e37"><personname class="po-record e38 e38"><firstname class="po-field e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">Eric</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e40 e40"><textual class="po-textual">Freese</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e41 e41"><para class="po-block e42 e42"><textual class="po-textual">Eric Freese is a veteran of publishing production
                        optimization. From the early days of SGML, he has worked in roles as varied
                        as consultant, software developer, content architect and semantic web
                        technologist in industries including defense, technical publishing,
                        commercial software and legal publishing. In his role as Director/Solutions
                        Architect, Eric helps Aptara customers efficiently transition to cost-saving
                        digital publishing models that simultaneously support eBook and other
                        electronic delivery platforms, as well as traditional print
                        production.</textual></para></personblurb><email class="po-field e43 e43"><textual class="po-textual">eric.freese@aptaracorp.com</textual></email><affiliation class="po-record e44 e44"><jobtitle class="po-field e45 e45"><textual class="po-textual">Director - Solutions Architect</textual></jobtitle><orgname class="po-block e46 e46"><textual class="po-textual">Aptara</textual></orgname></affiliation></author><legalnotice class="po-container e47 e47"><para class="po-block e48 e48"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright © 2011 by the author. Used with permission.</textual></para></legalnotice><keywordset class="po-table e49 e49" role="author"><keyword class="po-field e50 e50"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e51 e51"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB3</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e52 e52"><textual class="po-textual">ebook</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e53 e53"><textual class="po-textual">specification</textual></keyword></keywordset></info><section class="po-hcontainer e54 e54"><title class="po-block e55 e55"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB3 Overview</textual></title><para class="po-block e56 e56"><itemizedlist class="po-table e57 e57"><listitem class="po-container e58 e58"><para class="po-block e59 e59"><textual class="po-textual">Multimedia &amp; Media Overlays</textual></para><para class="po-block e60 e60"><textual class="po-textual">While audio and video had been incorporated into EPUB files previously,
                        this version of the spec codified their use by incorporating the HTML5 audio
                        and video markup. This markup provides a standard way in which to include
                        multimedia within the EPUB files. In addition, a mechanism for adding media
                        overlays within books enables new functionality, including text highlighting
                        for read along books. This is done using the SMIL language.</textual></para><para class="po-block e61 e61"><textual class="po-textual">The adoption of the HTML5 audio and video markup is probably the most
                        familiar addition in this area. While there was little discussion around the
                        audio formats to be used (MP3 required and MP4 AAC LC suggested), there was
                        a great deal of discussion surrounding the video formats to be supported.
                        The main contenders were MPEG4 H.264 and VP8. The main point of dissention
                        was the level of support for each. Originally all reading systems were going
                        to be required to support both. However, various reading system developers
                        expressed concerns about being required to support 2 formats. There were
                        also concerns about the copyright on the H.264 format and how licensing
                        might affect reading systems. After a great deal of discussion and threats
                        of non-support if both formats where mandated, it was decided that there
                        would not be a requirement that reading systems support either format.
                        Instead, an informational paragraph was included recommending the use of one
                        of the formats, but not precluding the use of another format. In essence,
                        this will require publishers to create videos in both formats in order to
                        support the widest range of reading systems -- and hopefully no reading
                        system decides to use an alternative format.</textual></para><para class="po-block e62 e62"><textual class="po-textual">The epub:trigger element was created in order to support markup that
                        defines user interfaces for controlling multimedia objects when they are
                        encountered, without requiring scripting. Using this element, it is now
                        possible to activate media files based on the content.</textual></para><para class="po-block e63 e63"><textual class="po-textual">The ability to hear the content is a vital accessibility concern and is
                        desirable for many other users as well. Media overlays provide a mechanism
                        that allows the synchronization of text and audio content within a
                        publication. There are many possible use cases for this functionality beyond
                        that of accessibility, including learning to read. Within the spec there are
                        options for computer-based text-to-speech reading as well as synchronized
                        audio files to the text.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e64 e64"><para class="po-block e65 e65"><textual class="po-textual">MathML</textual></para><para class="po-block e66 e66"><textual class="po-textual">MathML became a first class citizen within EPUB3. The spec requires
                        support for embedded Presentation MathML and allows for processing of
                        Content MathML based on MathML 3.0. In the prior versions of the spec,
                        mathematical formulas were usually converted to images. The inclusion of
                        MathML allows formulas to be marked semantically and displayed. This also
                        allows the formulas to reflow along with the rest of the text rather than
                        remain as a static image. The markup also can be used as input to
                        mathematical engines like Wolfram Alpha, allowing formulas to become
                        interactive.</textual></para><para class="po-block e67 e67"><textual class="po-textual">While MathML is supported in the spec, it would still be prudent for
                        publishers to provide the image renditions of symbols and formulas as
                        fallbacks for older reading systems.  Publishers should also provide
                        alternative text content for accessibility purposes including
                        text-to-speech.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e68 e68"><para class="po-block e69 e69"><textual class="po-textual">Scripting &amp; Interactivity</textual></para><para class="po-block e70 e70"><textual class="po-textual">Javascript was also added to EPUB3 to allow some levels of interactivity
                        similar to what is available in modern browsers. There was a great deal of
                        discussion about the level of support to be included, due mostly to security
                        concerns. Most reading system that are attached to online vendors have
                        access to personal financial information which must be protected. The final
                        decision was that reading systems must provide appropriate levels of
                        security in order to safeguard sensitive data.</textual></para><para class="po-block e71 e71"><textual class="po-textual">The addition of JavaScript to the specification provides the ability to
                        create interactivity within EPUBs. This support is optional and operates
                        under several restrictions and limitations. Due to this, it is not clear to
                        what level reading systems will support this new functionality. Reading
                        systems that are based on browser engines, such as Webkit, will likely
                        provide support, but other non-browser based systems may not be able to
                        provide an equal level of support. Also, due to security concerns, many
                        people disable Javascript within their browsers and likely will within
                        readings systems as well. Publishers that opt to incorporate scripting
                        should ensure that the user experience is acceptable whether Javascript is
                        enabled or not. </textual></para><para class="po-block e72 e72"><textual class="po-textual">Also new to the spec is the epubReadingSystem Javascript object which
                        provides a means for querying a reading system to determine its capabilites.
                        This will allow scripts to be developed which can provide their own levels
                        of fallback capabilities.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e73 e73"><para class="po-block e74 e74"><textual class="po-textual">Speech &amp; Accessibility</textual></para><para class="po-block e75 e75"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB has always been about supporting adaptive layouts and accessibility.
                        Most of the enhancements made in EPUB3 had to pass an accessibility litmus
                        test to ensure that new enhancements would still be accessible.  Anything
                        done through JavaScript must have an accessibility component associated with
                        it.  The same applies for MathML and SVG content.</textual></para><para class="po-block e76 e76"><textual class="po-textual">With the removal of the DTBook schema, text-to-speech became more
                        important within EPUB3 to support accessibility. Portions of the W3C PLS and
                        SSML specifications are included in EPUB3 to allow publishers to provide
                        information to TTS engines, including pronunciation guides for terms which
                        might not be in a standard dictionary. In addition, features found within
                        the CSS3 Speech Module allow publishers to control speech synthesis options,
                        such as voice pitch and rate.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e77 e77"><para class="po-block e78 e78"><textual class="po-textual">Metadata &amp; Semantic Inflection</textual></para><para class="po-block e79 e79"><textual class="po-textual">The metadata capabilities have been greatly expanded to include more
                        information about a publication as well as attaching complete bibliographic
                        records.  Also, a unique identifier attribute was created which allows a way
                        in which to identify a specific manifestation of a publication.  Finally a
                        mechanism was created allowing for annotating document markup with more
                        semantically meaningful information.</textual></para><para class="po-block e80 e80"><textual class="po-textual">Within EPUB3, metadata can be expressed using any combination of
                        EPUB-specific metadata, DCMES, DCTERMS, as well as other profiles including
                        PRISM and FOAF. Multiple identifiers can be defined, but none are mandated.
                        This allows publishers to select how they want to manage identifiers.
                        However, the unique identifier selected by the publisher to represent the
                        package is expected to be persistent, in order to support linking and other
                        applications. Packages must also include a decterms:modified property as a
                        timestamp. The package identifier is then made up of a combination of the
                        unique identifier and the modification date.</textual></para><para class="po-block e81 e81"><textual class="po-textual">Within each package, a publication can have multiple titles.  The
                        alternate titles may include short titles, subtitles, series information,
                        display sequences, sortable titles and non-Latin versions of the
                        title.</textual></para><para class="po-block e82 e82"><textual class="po-textual">Semantic inflection is used to attach additional meaning about the
                        specific purpose or nature of an element within the content. The spec
                        defines the epub:type attribute to express domain-specific semantics. This
                        metadata is not intended for human use, but rather, to assist reading
                        systems in enhancing the reading experience for users. The spec defines a
                        Structural Semantics Vocabulary which is the default vocabulary for all EPUB
                        documents. Within the vocabulary, there are structures including document
                        partitions (e.g. cover, back matter, etc.), document divisions (e.g. volume,
                        part, etc.), document sections and components (e.g. epigraph, conclusion,
                        preamble, etc.), document reference sections (e.g. index, colophon,
                        glossaries, appendices, bibliographies, etc.), preliminary sections and
                        components (e.g. errata, copyright page, etc.), complementary content (e.g.
                        sidebar, marginalia, etc.), notes (e.g. notes, footnotes, etc.), headings
                        (e.g. bridgehead), titles (e.g. subtitle, covertitle, etc.), document text
                        (e.g. keyword, topic sentence, etc.), references, pagination, tables, and
                        lists. In the cases of tables and lists, the semantic inflection is often
                        used to indicate to media overlays whether that content is escapable or
                        skippable.</textual></para><para class="po-block e83 e83"><textual class="po-textual">Support for a standard dictionary markup scheme was discussed and it was
                        decided that a companion specification would be developed specifically for
                        this type of content.</textual></para><para class="po-block e84 e84"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB3 also provides a mechanism that can be used to identify and embed
                        semantic information within the content of a publication. There was a great
                        deal of discussion about the use of RDFa within EPUB3 and it was decided
                        that the complexity of implementing a full RDFa engine within a reading
                        system was too burdensome. However, there is a method through which RDF or
                        OWL can be inserted into an EPUB files. This can be done using the
                        epub:switch element as shown below:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e85 e85" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;epub:switch id=”giraffeOwlSwitch"&gt; 
&lt;epub:case required-namespace="http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#"&gt; 
&lt;Class rdf:about”#giraffe”&gt; 
&lt;rdfs:label&gt;giraffe&lt;/rdfs:label&gt;
&lt;rdfs:subClassOf&gt; 
&lt;Class rdf:about=“#animal”/&gt;
&lt;/rdfs:subClassOf&gt; &lt;!-- other restrictions could be added here --&gt;
&lt;/Class&gt; 
&lt;/epub:case&gt; 
&lt;epub:default&gt; giraffe &lt;/epub:default&gt;
&lt;/epub:switch&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e86 e86"><textual class="po-textual">The epub:switch element allows XML fragments to be conditionally inserted
                        into the content of an EPUB document. Reading systems must process each
                        epub:switch element to determine whether they can render any of the
                        epub:case elements. The fallback is the epub:default element.  In theory,
                        and RDF/OWL capable reading system could use the information defined above
                        to build a taxonomy within the publication, that then could be used to aid
                        in searching for information within the publication based on the taxonomy.
                        This method can also be used to insert other markup schemes such as ChemML.
                        At this point in time, it is not known whether any reading system plans to
                        support the use of RDF in this manner.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e87 e87"><para class="po-block e88 e88"><textual class="po-textual">SVG</textual></para><para class="po-block e89 e89"><textual class="po-textual">Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) also became a first class citizen with the
                        adoption of a subset of SVG1.1. While it had previously been listed as a
                        supported graphic format, it is now recognized as a suitable method for
                        inclusion of content, fonts and images within the spine and table of
                        contents in addition to the main content. SVG fonts provide the ability to
                        create more complex typography that can be scaled when the readers reflow
                        the content. SVG content can be inserted by reference or by
                        inclusion.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e90 e90"><para class="po-block e91 e91"><textual class="po-textual">Navigation</textual></para><para class="po-block e92 e92"><textual class="po-textual">Publications in EPUB3 can now have orders other than sequential from
                        beginning to end. In addition there is new functionality to enhance
                        accessibility and navigation, including allowing i18n and embedded grammars
                        (MathML, SVG) within the navigation documents. In addition, CSS can be used
                        to tailor the display of navigation information.</textual></para><para class="po-block e93 e93"><textual class="po-textual">NCX documents are deprecated in favor of the EPUB Navigation Document
                        which uses the HTML5 nav element to define navigation information.  The NCX
                        document can still be included to allow EPUB2 reading systems to attempt to
                        process an EPUB3 document.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e94 e94"><para class="po-block e95 e95"><textual class="po-textual">Linking</textual></para><para class="po-block e96 e96"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB3 defines a new EPUB Canonical Fragment Identifier (CFI) specification
                        that defines a standardized method for linking into a publication.  This
                        specification enables EPUB reading systems to have an interoperable linking
                        mechanism, which can, for example, facilitate the sharing of bookmarks and
                        reading locations across devices.</textual></para><para class="po-block e97 e97"><textual class="po-textual">The CFI is a combination of IRI and URI, HTML ids and named anchors, and
                        shorthand Xpointer.  At this time, linking via the CFI is only supported
                        within an EPUB publication.  Another companion specification is planned that
                        will address linking between EPUB documents.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e98 e98"><para class="po-block e99 e99"><textual class="po-textual">Styling &amp; Layout</textual></para><para class="po-block e100 e100"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB3 sets CSS 2.1 as its baseline, but incorporates some CSS3 modules
                        (speech, fonts, text, writing mode, media queries, multi-column, ruby
                        positioning) to provide advanced layout and styling beyond what was
                        previously available. The spec also introduces some EPUB-specific CSS
                        constructs.</textual></para><para class="po-block e101 e101"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB3 also supports the ability to include multiple style sheets within a
                        publication.  This functionality can be used to change between day and night
                        reading modes or change the rendering direction.  Initially, there were
                        plans to incorporate page-level layouts (similar to Apple's fixed layout
                        format) and the ability to target multiple display sizes, all within a
                        single publication.  However, this functionality got pushed out to a
                        separate accompanying specification to be defined at a later time.</textual></para><para class="po-block e102 e102"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB3 now requires that reading systems support OpenType and WOFF font
                        formats for embedded fonts. In addition, there are now normative sections
                        dealing with font obfuscation.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e103 e103"><para class="po-block e104 e104"><textual class="po-textual">Global Language Support</textual></para><para class="po-block e105 e105"><textual class="po-textual">A specific working group was formed to address the issues surrounding
                        character sets, writing direction, etc. The work done by the group is viewed
                        as one of the major improvements to the EPUB specification, allowing it to
                        be adopted in a much wider range of markets.</textual></para><para class="po-block e106 e106"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB3 uses Pronunciation Lexicon Specification (PLS) documents and Speech
                        Synthesis Markup Language (SSML) attributes to increase pronunciation
                        control for rendering natural language in text-to-speech enabled reading
                        systems. It is also possible to combine CSS Speech and inline SSML phonemes
                        to provide fine control over ruby.</textual></para><para class="po-block e107 e107"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB3's CSS support enables horizontal and vertical writing as well as
                        left-to-right and right-to-left writing.  In addition, there is better
                        control over line breaking so that breaks can occur at the character level
                        for languages that do not use spaces to delimit words. However, reading
                        systems are not required to support all these capabilities.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e108 e108"><para class="po-block e109 e109"><textual class="po-textual">Removal of DTBook and XML Islands</textual></para><para class="po-block e110 e110"><textual class="po-textual">While most publishers delivered content in accordance with the EPUB
                        schema, far fewer used the DTBook syntax, which is targeted to systems
                        supporting accessibility to print-impaired users. It was decided fairly
                        early in the process that the 2 schemas would be unified in order to
                        increase accessibility to digital content. This was enabled by HTML5's
                        intrinsic semantic markup capabilities that were similar to those found in
                        DTBook. In essence, all EPUB3 content is accessible by nature. That being
                        said, there are still steps that should be taken to make content even more
                        accessible, including alternate text on images and formulas.</textual></para><para class="po-block e111 e111"><textual class="po-textual">XML islands were also a feature that was little used and caused
                        interchange issues between reading systems. A survey of publishers and
                        conversion service providers revealed very little use of this
                        feature.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><textual class="po-textual">
        </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e112 e112"><title class="po-block e113 e113"><textual class="po-textual">What is still missing?</textual></title><section class="po-hcontainer e114 e114"><title class="po-block e115 e115"><textual class="po-textual">Inter-document linking</textual></title><para class="po-block e116 e116"><textual class="po-textual">Although the CFI spec provides mechanisms for addressing locations within an EPUB
                file, inter-document linking functionality will not be included at this time.
                Inter-document linking was proposed to allow EPUB files to reference other EPUB
                files. The difficulty was in designing a linking mechanism that supported all the
                following use cases:</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e117 e117"><listitem class="po-container e118 e118"><para class="po-block e119 e119"><textual class="po-textual">linking to a specific place within a specific EPUB file (e.g. a
                            reference to a particular passage within a particular version of Tom
                            Sawyer) from another EPUB file</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e120 e120"><para class="po-block e121 e121"><textual class="po-textual">linking to a specific place within a non-specific EPUB file (e.g. a
                            reference to a particular passage within whatever version of Tom Sawyer
                            is available to the device) from another EPUB file</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e122 e122"><para class="po-block e123 e123"><textual class="po-textual">appropriate actions in cases where the target location is not
                            available on the device (e.g. dead link, access a store, etc.) </textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><textual class="po-textual">The difficulty in developing a complete and thorough specification
                was deemed too much to accomplish within the timeframe for developing the EPUB3
                specs. It is anticipated that work will begin on a new companion spec after the
                EPUB3 specs have been finally approved.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e124 e124"><title class="po-block e125 e125"><textual class="po-textual">Annotations</textual></title><para class="po-block e126 e126"><textual class="po-textual">Another class of functionality that is dependent on the CFI is the definition of
                an interchangeable method for defining annotations on an EPUB. There is a
                requirement to be able to move annotations between reading devices in much the same
                manner as the publications themselves can be interchanged. As with the
                inter-document linking work, this work was postponed until after the final approval
                of the EPUB3 specs in order to meet deadlines and to allow the CFI to become final
                before designing something that was dependent on it.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e127 e127"><title class="po-block e128 e128"><textual class="po-textual">Dictionary Interchange</textual></title><para class="po-block e129 e129"><textual class="po-textual">During the discussions about glossaries and indexes, it was determined that there
                is a need to include dictionary interchange support. Most reading systems provide
                dictionary lookup capabilities, but there is not a standardized or extensible method
                for doing so. The goal of this companion specification will be to define an
                interchangeable dictionary scheme. In addition, it will provide a method for an EPUB
                to insert publication specific terms into the dictionary mechanism in order to
                create a consistent user experience for looking up terms within a publication, no
                matter what reading system is being used.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e130 e130"><title class="po-block e131 e131"><textual class="po-textual">Enhanced article support and support for ads</textual></title><para class="po-block e132 e132"><textual class="po-textual">The stated goals of the IDPF board for EPUB3 included the definition of a
                mechanism for including advertising and enhanced article support. When it was time
                to create working groups for the different work items, there was lukewarm support
                for this within the working group. In conjunction with these was a suggestion to
                define functionality to support hotspots on graphics. Within IDEAlliance, a working
                group consisting mostly of magazine and periodical publishers, known as nextPUB has
                begun work on creating a layer based on EPUB3 that will work well within the
                magazine industry. The aforementioned goals have essentially been passed to the
                nextPUB working group for resolution.</textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e133 e133"><title class="po-block e134 e134"><textual class="po-textual">Adoption and Market Impact</textual></title><para class="po-block e135 e135"><textual class="po-textual">Whenever a new version of a specification is released, there is inevitable upheaval
            within the marketplace. This specification will be no different. Publishers will need to
            revise their production process to support the new format. In addition, they will need
            to determine how best to take advantage of the new functionality provided within the
            spec. This must be tempered with knowledge of what is supported across reading systems.
            Many of the new features within the specification are optional, meaning that device
            capabilities might be even broader than they are now.</textual></para><para class="po-block e136 e136"><textual class="po-textual">One of the things the working group did well was the mandate that all EPUB3 reading
            systems are required to support pre-EPUB3 files. This guarantees that current customer
            libraries will be able to be read on devices supporting EPUB3. However, there is no
            mandate for forward compatibility from current EPUB reading systems, meaning that some
            dedicated devices may begin a path to obsolescence. While it is possible that many can
            be updated via software upgrades, there are still device limitations that must be
            considered. E-Ink based displays cannot refresh quickly enough to support video, meaning
            that publishers should provide fallbacks any time they incorporate video within an
            Ebook. The video format compromise will also force publishers to create fallbacks to
            support different formats on different reading systems.</textual></para><para class="po-block e137 e137"><textual class="po-textual">At this point in time it is difficult to predict the level of support for EPUB3 from
            reading system developers. Several high profile reading system vendors were part of the
            working group, but none have made any formal announcement concerning schedules for
            releasing EPUB3 capable reading systems and apps. It seems logical that non-dedicated
            reading system vendors (such as the iPad or android tablets) might be able to be more
            agile in releasing the updates, especially the functionality around embedded audio and
            video and JavaScript. Dedicated reading systems, such as the Kindle, Nook or Kobo, do
            not have the hardware capability to support video, meaning new models of the devices
            will be required. Barnes &amp; Noble has been proactive in releasing the nookColor,
            which is capable of supporting the new multimedia capabilities.</textual></para><para class="po-block e138 e138"><textual class="po-textual">Publishers, on the other hand, will be caught between a rock and hard place, yet
            again. Conversion vendors are already receiving requests for EPUB3 support, even before
            reading systems are available. Validation software is also not available yet, making it
            very difficult to test EPUB3 files.  The timing of the final spec release (July 2011)
            will also compound problems as publisher begin to gear up for the upcoming holiday
            season, without a clear understanding of what capabilities will be available in the
            different reading systems. It would be prudent for publishers to continue to support the
            current EPUB standard in order to support the current customer base. However, there will
            also be pressure on them to begin creating EPUB3 files to take advantage of the new
            functionality and capabilities. This will result in additional cost burdens for
            publishers.</textual></para><para class="po-block e139 e139"><textual class="po-textual">At this point, it is unknown how the public will react to the release of EPUB3-based
            books. For some time, there will likely be additional confusion about which formats are
            supported on which devices. There is also some interest in how the various online
            sources will market the new files. It is anticipated that multiple choices will be
            available for the foreseeable future. How long the stores identify the different
            versions remains to be seen.</textual></para></section><bibliography class="po-hcontainer e140 e140"><title class="po-block e141 e141"><textual class="po-textual">Bibliography</textual></title><bibliomixed class="po-block e142 e142"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB Canonical Fragment Identifier (epubcfi) Specification - 23 May 2011 -
            http://www.idpf.org/epub/linking/cfi/epub-cfi.html</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e143 e143"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB 3 Changes from EPUB 2.0.1 - 23 May 2011 -
            http://www.idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-changes.html</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e144 e144"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB 3 Content Documents 3.0 - 23 May 2011 -
            http://www.idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-contentdocs.html</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e145 e145"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB 3 Media Overlays 3.0 - 23 May 2011 -
            http://www.idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-mediaoverlays.html</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e146 e146"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB 3 Overview - 23 May 2011 -
            http://www.idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-overview.html</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e147 e147"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB 3 Publications 3.0 - 23 May 2011 -
            http://www.idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-publications.html</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e148 e148"><textual class="po-textual">EPUB 3 Structural Semantics Vocabulary -
            http://www.idpf.org/epub/vocab/structure/#</textual></bibliomixed></bibliography></article></classedDocument>