<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">Things change, or, the “real meaning” of technical terms</textual></title><info class="po-record e2 e2"><confgroup class="po-record e3 e3"><conftitle class="po-field e4 e4"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">August 7 - 10, 2012</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e6 e6"><para class="po-block e7 e7"><textual class="po-textual">Vocabulary is slippery, especially the sorts of technical jargon we are immersed in at events like Balisage. When we want to talk about a new idea, process, specification, or procedure we have two choices: make up a new word or use a word that is already in use to mean something else. New words may be difficult to remember and awkward to use. Re-purposing an existing word may cause confusion between the </textual><quote class="po-inline e8 e8"><textual class="po-textual">old</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> and your </textual><quote class="po-inline e9 e9"><textual class="po-textual">new</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> meaning. In either case, usage of terms changes. The usage of a technical term may mutate over time and may evolve differently in different communities. At times it is useful for a community to pressure users to use terms to mean what they meant when coined, but more often it is simple pedantry to insist that any usage other than that of the person who first introduced the term is incorrect. Our challenge is in finding that balance.</textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e10 e10"><personname class="po-record e11 e11"><firstname class="po-field e12 e12"><textual class="po-textual">B. Tommie</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e13 e13"><textual class="po-textual">Usdin</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e14 e14"><para class="po-block e15 e15"><textual class="po-textual">B. Tommie Usdin is President of Mulberry Technologies, Inc., a consultancy specializing in XML and SGML. Ms. Usdin has
been  working with SGML since 1985 and has been a supporter of XML since 1996. She chairs the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e16 e16" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> conference.
  Ms. Usdin has
    developed DTDs, Schemas, and XML/SGML application frameworks for applications in government and industry. Projects
    include reference  materials in medicine, science, engineering, and law; semiconductor documentation; historical and
    archival materials. Distribution formats have included print books, magazines, and journals, and both web- and
    media-based electronic publications. She is co-chair of the NISO Z39-96, JATS:
    Journal Article Tag Suite Working Group. You can read more about her at
    </textual><link class="po-inline e17 e17" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.mulberrytech.com/people/usdin/index.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.mulberrytech.com/people/usdin/index.html</textual></link></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e18 e18"><orgname class="po-block e19 e19"><textual class="po-textual">Mulberry Technologies, Inc.</textual></orgname></affiliation></author><legalnotice class="po-container e20 e20"><para class="po-block e21 e21"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright © 2012 by the author. Used with permission.</textual></para></legalnotice></info><para class="po-block e22 e22"><textual class="po-textual">Good morning.  I want to do two things.  I want to introduce a piece of technology that I am about to use.  I want to introduce it primarily for the sake of the speakers, but I’ll show it to the rest of you as well.  This is our </textual><link class="po-inline e23 e23" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.timetimer.com/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">timer</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.  Set it to however much time you have to speak, and watch your time disappear!  I am going to give myself twenty-five minutes.  I don’t think I actually need all of it.</textual></para><para class="po-block e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">As several people have already said, we are absolutely delighted to see you.  I see old friends, I see new faces, I see some people I have only communicated with in the past by email — maybe those are my favorite because it’s nice to actually get to know the people in person that you’ve been talking to by email.</textual></para><para class="po-block e25 e25"><textual class="po-textual">This is a remarkable group of people.  This is a group of people where when somebody says, </textual><quote class="po-inline e26 e26"><textual class="po-textual">You know, that’s not actually how it works.  I wrote that, and what really happens under the covers is …,</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> don’t laugh; they probably did write it.  Maybe make a mental note to ask some more questions about it over coffee.</textual></para><para class="po-block e27 e27"><textual class="po-textual">As a general rule, in this crowd, when someone makes a preposterous claim — maybe especially when they make a preposterous claim — it is probably true.  It may not be sensible, but except when they’re playing </textual><quote class="po-inline e28 e28"><emphasis class="po-inline e29 e29" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Bluff,</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  it’s probably true.</textual></para><para class="po-block e30 e30"><textual class="po-textual">You’re also a funny group.  You probably noticed — I know a lot of you noticed — that on the registration form one of the things we ask for is </textual><quote class="po-inline e31 e31"><textual class="po-textual">Special Requirements such as dietary requirements.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  And as I was looking through the registration forms, I was reminded of a very, very rainy Sunday afternoon at the end of a very, very long rainy week when my little brother was perhaps seven-years-old, and he said to my mother </textual><quote class="po-inline e32 e32"><textual class="po-textual">What can I do?</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  And she proposed something, perhaps, </textual><quote class="po-inline e33 e33"><textual class="po-textual">Get out your crayons and draw.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  </textual><quote class="po-inline e34 e34"><textual class="po-textual">I did that yesterday.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  </textual><quote class="po-inline e35 e35"><textual class="po-textual">Okay.  Well, why don’t you play with something-or-other?</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  </textual><quote class="po-inline e36 e36"><textual class="po-textual">I don’t wanna.  What can I do?</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  She said, </textual><quote class="po-inline e37 e37"><textual class="po-textual">I already proposed two things.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  He said, </textual><quote class="po-inline e38 e38"><textual class="po-textual">What can I do that’s fun and I wanna do, and I didn’t do yesterday?</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  And she said, </textual><quote class="po-inline e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">You’re going to have to solve that problem yourself.</textual></quote></para><para class="po-block e40 e40"><textual class="po-textual">Well, looking at your special requirements — you as a group — I have a feeling that what you’ve been saying to us is </textual><quote class="po-inline e41 e41"><textual class="po-textual">What can I do that’s fun and I wanna do, and that isn’t folding towels, and that I didn’t do yesterday?</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  I’m going to suggest to you that if you, for example, look at the options at lunch and say, </textual><quote class="po-inline e42 e42"><textual class="po-textual">There are two things there I’m allergic to and one I hate, therefore this lunch is awful,</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> you’re going to be very unhappy.  If you look at the options and say, </textual><quote class="po-inline e43 e43"><textual class="po-textual">There are two things I like and one that is what I probably ought to be eating,</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> you will be very happy.  It’s up to you, and you’re going to have to solve that problem yourself.  What we have planned for lunch every day is:  a fish-based option, a meat-based option, a vegetarian option, and a gluten-free option.  Now I don’t know why the gluten-free option isn’t simultaneous with one of the others — and perhaps it will be — but if you have sensitivities or issues, ask.  (We have also asked them to label the various options.)  But we have a fair amount of variety.</textual></para><para class="po-block e44 e44"><textual class="po-textual">So as with lunch, also the conference as a whole.  I had a conversation — oh, now several months ago — with, as it happens, an attendee at this conference who had registered because </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e45 e45" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> seemed like a cool conference, and he wanted to come, so he got his institution to pay for it and registered.  Then the preliminary program came out, and I got email saying </textual><quote class="po-inline e46 e46"><textual class="po-textual">How do I cancel my registration?</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  I wrote back and said, </textual><quote class="po-inline e47 e47"><textual class="po-textual">Well, if you really want to cancel your registration, tell us and we’ll credit your credit card.  Why do you want to cancel your registration?</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  </textual><quote class="po-inline e48 e48"><textual class="po-textual">Well, there isn’t very much on that program that is directly related to my job, and I don’t have the background for some of it.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  I said, </textual><quote class="po-inline e49 e49"><textual class="po-textual">Please wait for the final program.  We’ve got a bunch of late-breaking slots.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  And then the late-breaking talks were posted, and I wrote back and said, </textual><quote class="po-inline e50 e50"><textual class="po-textual">Okay, the complete program is up.  Take a look at it.  If you really want to cancel, you can cancel, but let me tell you that as far as I’m concerned, the fact that all of the conference doesn’t appeal to you is sort of par for the course.  There are going to be several sessions at this conference that I will find totally bewildering; people are going to talk about things that are just so far outside my area of expertise I have no idea what they’re talking about.  There are also several papers on this program where I can’t imagine why anybody cares; I’m going to be polite and not tell you which.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  My guess is that each of you agrees with me that there are several papers on the program for which you can’t imagine why anybody cares, but if the conference committee has done it right, we don’t agree on which ones those are.  So, if you approach this conference — by the way, that person is here, and I hope enjoys the conference — as </textual><quote class="po-inline e51 e51"><textual class="po-textual">If every paper isn’t spot on for me at all times, this is a waste of time,</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> then I can tell you right now, this is a waste of time.  If you approach it as a place to learn some things, think about some new ideas, and maybe be exposed to some things that matter to other people but not to you (or at least not to you right now), you’re going to have a great time this week.</textual></para><para class="po-block e52 e52"><textual class="po-textual">I would like to talk to some of the speakers at this conference for a moment.  You’re going to have a platform; you’re going to be allowed to say pretty much what you want to say.  But I would like you not to sound like the teenage child of a good friend that I spent some time with not so long ago.  I spent a week with a teenager who taught me that I don’t know anything about music.  Well, that didn’t surprise me.  I learned that I don’t anything about fashion.  In fact, I don’t even know how to wear a scarf.  I learned that I don’t know anything about technology, or at least about technology that matters, such as, for example, how to get the most out of a cell phone or even what phone to buy.  I learned that I don’t read the right books or watch the right television.  I learned that my job is easy.  And I learned that there are simple answers to all questions:  technological, financial, political, and ethical.  I would like to think that most of us have matured just a little bit beyond this particular child who knows everything.  The experience sensitized me to easy answers through simplification — something that many of us in this room do tend toward.  This process does seem to underline many of the pronouncements that I have heard at other conferences and suspect we will hear a little too much of this week.</textual></para><para class="po-block e53 e53"><textual class="po-textual">While most of my colleagues are a little more circumspect in the way they phrase it, I nonetheless would like to warn you not to say </textual><quote class="po-inline e54 e54"><textual class="po-textual">My problem area is very complicated, and your problem area is not; there is a simple answer to the thing you are working on — let’s focus on the thing I care about.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  Now I don’t mind you focusing </textual><quote class="po-inline e55 e55"><textual class="po-textual">on the thing that I care about,</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> but you know, the things other people are working on, maybe those are hard too.  Let’s assume this week that if someone is struggling with a problem you’ve just learned about for the first time that the obvious solution that pops into your mind just might not take all the subtleties into account.</textual></para><para class="po-block e56 e56"><textual class="po-textual">Let’s be careful with our terminology.  We all deal with significant complexity:  complex issues, complex technologies.  And the way we communicate is through the use of technical terminology — jargon.  The use of jargon is important.  It makes our meanings clear; it demonstrates that we know what we’re talking about.  It establishes credibility.  I have a client who knows a lot about her documents and her document systems and the ways documents are created and produced, and I fairly regularly have to remind myself of this because as we’re talking about document models, she not only talks about modifying the DDT — I know what she means, I really do know what she means, but I alo heard what she said, and it’s a problem.  Worse than that, when what she means is </textual><quote class="po-inline e57 e57"><textual class="po-textual">Let’s make that attribute have a set of defined values,</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> what she says is </textual><quote class="po-inline e58 e58"><textual class="po-textual">Make that a pick-list.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  Now, in fact in one of the tools — not even all of the tools she’s going to use — in one of the tools she is going to use, that’s the way that will be visualized.  But that’s what she says, and what it does is erode her credibility.  I’m warning you here that this audience is even fussier than I am about correct use of terminology, and if you use a technical term incorrectly, there will be a line at the microphone, and somebody will very politely say </textual><quote class="po-inline e59 e59"><textual class="po-textual">That is correctly called a zagorgaflesh, you know.</textual></quote></para><para class="po-block e60 e60"><textual class="po-textual">I was recently confused by someone else who sent me email complaining about the </textual><quote class="po-inline e61 e61"><textual class="po-textual">pointy-bracket-date-close-pointy-bracket</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> thing in a tag set.  Date element?  I don’t believe this tag set has a date element.  And I did a lot of digging around and searching until I figured out that the thing in email that was spelled </textual><quote class="po-inline e62 e62"><textual class="po-textual">pointy-bracket-d-a-t-e-close-pointy-bracket</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> was an attribute.  Because I didn’t look for it there!!  Surrounding things with pointy-brackets in our world has a well-established meaning.  The guy in email lost a lot of credibility because he spelled the name of an attribute with pointy-brackets around it.</textual></para><para class="po-block e63 e63"><textual class="po-textual">Now, these are terms with well-established meanings.  What about when you’re working in the world where most of us are going to be talking at </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e64 e64" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> — a world where we don’t quite have well-established meanings?  Where the meanings drift over time?  Meanings of words change all the time.  I don’t mean necessarily technical terms or jargon, but in the real world.  For example, I’m old enough and picky enough to find it really irritating when people use the word </textual><quote class="po-inline e65 e65"><textual class="po-textual">decimate</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> to mean </textual><quote class="po-inline e66 e66"><textual class="po-textual">to do serious damage to</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><quote class="po-inline e67 e67"><textual class="po-textual">totally destroy.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  That’s not what that word used to mean, and I’m enough of a curmudgeon to think it’s not what the word should mean.  But nonetheless when I listen to somebody giving a speech at a political rally and they say that something or other will decimate the economy, I know that they don’t really mean </textual><quote class="po-inline e68 e68"><textual class="po-textual">remove 10%</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> of it; they really mean it’s just awful.</textual></para><para class="po-block e69 e69"><textual class="po-textual">Our technical terms do the same thing, and while I’m telling you to use technical terms correctly, I’m also warning you that that may not actually be possible.  What is the real meaning of a technical term?  The meaning of the first person who used it?  The popular meaning?  The current meaning?  The meaning in Wikipedia?  We’re going to encounter that issue a lot during this conference.  Imagine, if you will, a situation that several of you in this room who are speaking are going to encounter in the next few days:  You invented something.  You thought of something really clever.  You coined a term for it — either you made up a new word or you borrowed a word somebody else was using.  (You can’t win; if you coin a new word — if you make up a new word — you’ll confuse people.  If you use a word that means something else in some other context for your new thing, you’ll confuse people, so, you know, there’s no winning.)  But you came up with this new thing, you gave a couple conference talks about it, you published a couple of papers about it — it’s clever, it’s new, it’s yours — and now somebody else is talking about this same idea.  Do you get bent out of shape if they don’t use your word?  Or do you get bent out of shape if they do use your word?  What if what they’re talking about isn’t exactly what you were talking about; it’s sorta similar.  Do you want them to use your word for something sorta similar?  Or do you want them not to use your word because it isn’t your thing?  What if their work was based on your work?  You want them to cite your paper — do you want them to use your terminology?  They’re not using it </textual><quote class="po-inline e70 e70"><textual class="po-textual">right</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> because they’ve moved in some direction that probably isn’t the direction you were going to move.  What if they invented the same thing at the same time more-or-less-approximately, but they’re not crediting you because they figured it out too?  Is there such a thing as simultaneous invention?  Yes.  Would it be polite if they cited your paper too?  Yes.  Do they have to use your vocabulary?  Think about it.  I don’t know.  What if they’re using your term just plain incorrectly?  Is this a good thing because people are going to call attention to your work too?  Is this a bad thing because they’re doing it wrong?  I’m not sure what the answer is, but I do think you want to think about it.  And it’s the kind of thing we’re going to be seeing at </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e71 e71" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para><para class="po-block e72 e72"><textual class="po-textual">There are few other things I would like to say about </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e73 e73" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.  As far as I’m concerned, you’re my guest.  You’re here — you’re my guest.  And so is everybody else in this room.  And what that means is:  You must treat everyone else who is here as one of my guests.  I do not want anybody being negative at anybody.  I said that a couple of years ago at this conference and thought, </textual><quote class="po-inline e74 e74"><textual class="po-textual">That’s kinda preachy and prissy, and why on earth do I need to say that?</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  And then the next year I didn’t say it, and several people said, </textual><quote class="po-inline e75 e75"><textual class="po-textual">We really need to be reminded of that.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  I thought about it, and somebody said, </textual><quote class="po-inline e76 e76"><textual class="po-textual">Did you hear that guy at the microphone who said to a speaker, `That’s the stupidest idea I’ve ever heard!’?</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  I said, </textual><quote class="po-inline e77 e77"><textual class="po-textual">Oh.  Yeah.  I did hear that.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  Let’s not do that.  No personal attacks.  By the way, </textual><quote class="po-inline e78 e78"><textual class="po-textual">that’s the stupidest idea I’ve ever heard</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> is not about the idea — that’s a personal attack.  And don’t </textual><quote class="po-inline e79 e79"><textual class="po-textual">language</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> lawyer at me and say, </textual><quote class="po-inline e80 e80"><textual class="po-textual">No, no, it’s about the idea, not the person.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  It’s a personal attack, folks.  We don’t do that here.  </textual><quote class="po-inline e81 e81"><textual class="po-textual">That idea won’t work because …</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> </textual><quote class="po-inline e82 e82"><textual class="po-textual">Have you thought of this?</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  That’s talking about the idea.  </textual><quote class="po-inline e83 e83"><textual class="po-textual">That’s the worst paper I’ve ever heard.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  If you have to say that, say it on the critique forms.  You know why it’s safe to say that on the critique forms?  They’re going to be edited before they go to the speakers.  Because some of you use very colorful language, and we’ll tone if down before passing it on.</textual></para><para class="po-block e84 e84"><textual class="po-textual">Now, that doesn’t mean that I want you to sit carefully in your seats with your hands folded and behave like — I don’t know — some notion of how school children behave.  I’ve never actually seen school children behave like that.  This is a lively environment.  This is an environment in which, in my opinion, the more successful a talk is, the longer the line will be at the microphone of people who want either to ask the speaker a question or disagree with something the speaker said.  There will also be people who are inspired during talks to say either </textual><quote class="po-inline e85 e85"><textual class="po-textual">Yes!!</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><quote class="po-inline e86 e86"><textual class="po-textual">Ooh!</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  And if you have either of those sort of mono-syllabic comments to make where the point of it is the tone of voice and not the content, just shout.  However, if you really have something to say that involves words, use the microphone.  Even if you are sitting in one of the first two or three rows and the speaker will be able to hear you if you speak from your seat, the people behind you will not.</textual></para><para class="po-block e87 e87"><textual class="po-textual">There are a few notions that we saw and that peer reviewers called out in some of the papers that were submitted to this conference.  They were rarely this bald, but there were some people who said, for example:  </textual><quote class="po-inline e88 e88"><textual class="po-textual">If I don’t need it, you can’t have it.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  </textual><quote class="po-inline e89 e89"><textual class="po-textual">There is this big complicated specification, three-quarters of which I don’t need in my environment, and therefore the way to make all of our lives easier is to eliminate the stuff I don’t need.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  Be careful when you’re saying, </textual><quote class="po-inline e90 e90"><textual class="po-textual">Nobody needs something because I don’t need it.</textual></quote></para><para class="po-block e91 e91"><textual class="po-textual">We had several draft papers that included statements on the general order of </textual><quote class="po-inline e92 e92"><textual class="po-textual">Everybody doing XML does this</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><quote class="po-inline e93 e93"><textual class="po-textual">Nobody in the XML world does that.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  If you say, </textual><quote class="po-inline e94 e94"><textual class="po-textual">Everybody I know in the XML world does this</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><quote class="po-inline e95 e95"><textual class="po-textual">Everybody in my industry …</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> although you might want to make that </textual><quote class="po-inline e96 e96"><textual class="po-textual">Everybody in my industry that I know does this,</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> you’re on solid ground.  </textual><quote class="po-inline e97 e97"><textual class="po-textual">I am not aware of anyone who needs something or other</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> — you’re fine.  But </textual><quote class="po-inline e98 e98"><textual class="po-textual">Everybody in the XML world does their analysis this way</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> or </textual><quote class="po-inline e99 e99"><textual class="po-textual">Nobody uses that specification</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> — it’s a good bet, you’re wrong.  (Well, with the possible exception of XLink.  Oh, you mean that somebody does use it?  Hmmmm.  Maybe there are no possible exceptions.)</textual></para><para class="po-block e100 e100"><textual class="po-textual">A few other things that I want us to think about.  </textual><quote class="po-inline e101 e101"><textual class="po-textual">If you have more data, you’re more important.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  </textual><quote class="po-inline e102 e102"><textual class="po-textual">If you have more data, your problems are harder.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  </textual><quote class="po-inline e103 e103"><textual class="po-textual">Any solution that works for people who have the maximum amount of data and resources is the right answer.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  Or conversely, </textual><quote class="po-inline e104 e104"><textual class="po-textual">Any solution that cannot be implemented by a person with good intentions but no programming background and no budget at all doesn’t work.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  </textual><quote class="po-inline e105 e105"><textual class="po-textual">If I can’t do it with what I know for free, it can’t be done.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  Let’s not go there either.</textual></para><para class="po-block e106 e106"><textual class="po-textual">And one of the ones that I think we’re likely to spend a lot of energy on:  </textual><quote class="po-inline e107 e107"><textual class="po-textual">If some people who used to use XML stop using XML and do something else, then they must be stopped, or XML will be a failure.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  That’s almost as sensible as </textual><quote class="po-inline e108 e108"><textual class="po-textual">If everybody on the planet doesn’t use XML and know that they are using XML, then XML is a failure.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">  You’ve got some funny notions, folks.  If something works for some users for some applications, it is valuable and useful and interesting to talk about at </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e109 e109" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.  If something is important to some users and it is something that you don’t need now, that doesn’t mean you won’t need it in the future.  For example, we have, to me, a surprising number of papers that will talk about JSON this week.  The big threat to XML, right???  Woooooo!  But then again I remember when XML was the big threat to Java, which never made any sense to me; sliced bread is not a threat to toasters.  JSON is not a threat to XML, and the fact that there are environments in which some technology other than XML might meet some people’s needs does not make XML obsolete or useless or necessarily in need of changing so those people will use it.  Nor do those people need to be bullied into using XML because XML is better than anything else.</textual></para><para class="po-block e110 e110"><textual class="po-textual">We’ll also hear people saying that about </textual><quote class="po-inline e111 e111"><textual class="po-textual">overlap</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">.  Everbody knows that in XML, structures don’t overlap, and therefore you don’t need </textual><quote class="po-inline e112 e112"><textual class="po-textual">overlap</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> and therefore we should not talk about it at conferences.  Right?  Except sometimes those rules get a little tight, and sometimes there are things that don’t quite work in that world.  That dirty little secret is something we’re allowed to talk about here.</textual></para><para class="po-block e113 e113"><textual class="po-textual">We’re also allowed to talk about other things that don’t quite work and don’t quite fit and haven’t been quite solved.  That’s what we do here.  And that is what I think it’s time for us to start talking about.  Welcome to </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e114 e114" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">!</textual></para></article></classedDocument>