<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">Platform Independence 2010 - Helping Documents Fly Well in Emerging Architectures</textual></title><info class="po-record e2 e2"><confgroup class="po-record e3 e3"><conftitle class="po-field e4 e4"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2010</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">August 3 - 6, 2010</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e6 e6"><para class="po-block e7 e7"><textual class="po-textual">Parallel processing and memory bottlenecks dominate current platform architecture
                conversations. After many years on the sidelines, parallel architectures are rapidly
                becoming mainstream, with more parallelism the obvious way to gain yet more
                performance. Feeding data to and from all these parallel cycles is also becoming
                more challenging. </textual></para><para class="po-block e8 e8"><textual class="po-textual">What does this have to do with XML? Surely all this is under the hood, something
                for compiler designers, software architects and other non-content people to worry
                about? The answer is that these issues can't be totally hidden under the hood.
                Balisageurs as content-folks and interoperability-folks need to pay attention now to
                the high level information design heuristics that will prevent our data structures
                being the ones that happen to run like treacle (or molasses) on the coming
                generations of faster, larger and neater systems.</textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e9 e9"><personname class="po-record e10 e10"><firstname class="po-field e11 e11"><textual class="po-textual">Ann</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e12 e12"><textual class="po-textual">Wrightson</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e13 e13"><para class="po-block e14 e14"><textual class="po-textual">Ann Wrightson has been working with markup since 1978, from typesetting
                    languages &amp; fielded records through generic coding to SGML &amp; XML. She
                    has experience of using markup for interoperability and platform-independence
                    across a wide range of content including published reference works, technical
                    publications, e-learning, legal codes &amp; materials, and semantic
                    interoperability standards for information systems in healthcare. </textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e15 e15"><jobtitle class="po-field e16 e16"><textual class="po-textual">IT Consultant - Technical Architecture</textual></jobtitle><orgname class="po-block e17 e17"><textual class="po-textual">Informing Healthcare (NHS Wales)</textual></orgname></affiliation></author><legalnotice class="po-container e18 e18"><para class="po-block e19 e19"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright © 2010 Ann Wrightson</textual></para></legalnotice><keywordset class="po-table e20 e20" role="author"><keyword class="po-field e21 e21"><textual class="po-textual">XML processing performance</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e22 e22"><textual class="po-textual">Parallel processing</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e23 e23"><textual class="po-textual">Memory hierarchy</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">Cache-oblivious data structure</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e25 e25"><textual class="po-textual">XML instance design</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e26 e26"><textual class="po-textual">Data exchange</textual></keyword></keywordset></info><section class="po-hcontainer e27 e27"><title class="po-block e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">Introduction</textual></title><para class="po-block e29 e29"><textual class="po-textual">Ever faster sequential computations in single ever-larger memory spaces has been
            "just how it is" in mainstream computing for about a generation - long enough
            for design considerations that are actually dependent on this environment to become
            invisible, unthought assumptions. After many years on the sidelines, parallel
            architectures are becoming mainstream, with more parallelism now the obvious way to gain
            more performance. Memory performance has been growing more slowly, so feeding data to
            and from all these parallel cycles is also a major challenge, with platform architecture
            solutions generally focussing on efficient ways to move data through deep hierarchies
            spanning the range from distant network resources to on-chip caches. Large and
            distributed data in particular needs to move efficiently through many layers of memory
            hierarchy, with each layer behaving as a cache with respect to the previous layer, that
            is, being significantly smaller and faster, and with a different block or page size. </textual></para><para class="po-block e30 e30"><textual class="po-textual"> What does this have to do with XML? Surely all this is under the hood or behind the
            scenes, something for compiler designers, software architects and other non-content
            people to worry about? After all, a platform is a just a platform, and XML and many XML
            tools are platform-independent. </textual></para><para class="po-block e31 e31"><textual class="po-textual">To an extent this is true. Compiler designers, software architects and especially
            database vendors are busy worrying right now, and much thought from the Balisage
            community and others will also undoubtedly go into making basic XML tools work well on
            the new platforms. However, notwithstanding these efforts, data designed with due
            attention to the fundamental characteristics of emerging platform architectures are
            likely to fare better, especially in speed of processing, than data designed for the
            "old world".</textual></para><para class="po-block e32 e32"><textual class="po-textual">Against this background, the premise underlying this paper is that since parallel
            processing and managing data flows within memory hierarchies are increasingly prominent
            in mainstream platform architecture, any large data structure, or collection of data
            that is usually processed together, now needs to be more or less parallel-friendly,
            cache-oblivious, and distribution-tolerant, to be really platform-independent - and this
            includes XML instances. This paper is about the attention we need to pay now as
            designers of XML content to the structural design patterns that will promote or prevent
            our data structures being the ones that happen to start running unexpectedly slowly next
            year or the year after.</textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e33 e33"><title class="po-block e34 e34"><textual class="po-textual">Note on language</textual></title><para class="po-block e35 e35"><textual class="po-textual">In this paper, the common parlance "XML vocabularies" is deprecated in
                favour of discussing XML data structures and design features of instances of XML
                content. This is partly from personal preference, but also from a suspicion that
                thinking about XML in terms of vocabularies may inhibit the kind of thinking that
                this paper is intended to encourage. Markup that contains terms reflecting natural
                language does function like language vocabulary in some ways (see </textual><xref class="po-milestone e36 e36" linkend="Wrightson05"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">) however XML instances are also structured data, and
                the latter is the aspect that predominates in the issues discussed in this paper.
            </textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e37 e37"><title class="po-block e38 e38"><textual class="po-textual">What are these emerging architectures?</textual></title><para class="po-block e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">This section provides a concise account of emerging processor architectures and the
            state of the art in data access. Implications for platform-independent XML content
            design are discussed in the following section.</textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e40 e40"><title class="po-block e41 e41"><textual class="po-textual">Single processor architecture becoming multi-, then many-core</textual></title><para class="po-block e42 e42"><textual class="po-textual">About 2003-4, performance improvement in sequential processors slowed down very
                significantly. Power density was a major factor, but so was the growing difficulty
                of getting even cleverer about executing single sequences of instructions really
                fast. With a way still to go in raw chip capacity, a consensus rapidly emerged
                amongst the majority of processing-chip designers that the only way forward was to
                put multiple processing "cores" on a chip, first two or four, then twelve,
                sixty-four, eighty... The latest edition of Patterson &amp; Hennesey's classic
                textbook on processor architecture provides a fuller account of this phenomenon (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e43 e43" linkend="PatHen09"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, Chapter 7).</textual></para><para class="po-block e44 e44"><textual class="po-textual">Graphics processors and some other niche processing applications had already made
                some progress into gaining performance through large-scale parallel processing, but
                for the rest of the industry there was a fairly sudden realization a few years ago
                that all that weird parallel stuff from the 1980s onward that no-one except the
                high-performance crowd had been taking seriously was on its way back in with a
                vengeance. Following this realization, and taking into account the head start
                achieved by graphics applications, graphics processors and general purpose
                processors are on an interesting journey of combination and convergence, for example
                in Intel's "Larrabee" architecture (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e45 e45" linkend="Seiler08"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">).</textual></para><para class="po-block e46 e46"><textual class="po-textual">While various parallel computation models have been proposed and investigated, two
                of the most durable have been BSP (bulk-synchronous-parallelism) and nested
                parallelism. BSP (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e47 e47" linkend="BSP90"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><xref class="po-milestone e48 e48" linkend="BSP96"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">) formalizes the notion of performing a bunch of parallel
                computations then collating the results before setting up and performing another
                bunch of parallel computations, in a regular cycle of
                compute-communicate/collate-compute. Nested parallelism (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e49 e49" linkend="NESL"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">,</textual><xref class="po-milestone e50 e50" linkend="PJ08"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">) is more of a language model, enabling a programmer to
                describe a large computation as a recursively nested structure of parallel
                parts.</textual></para><para class="po-block e51 e51"><textual class="po-textual">The main point for our purposes is that in order to work well in a parallel world,
                computation (and its requisite data) needs to come apart into independent pieces, at
                least for long enough to be useful in getting some work done. Two interesting
                special cases are where many computations run in parallel on the same data, and
                where a single computation runs the same instruction stream to process many
                different, similar items of data. The latter is the basis of graphics processing
                units. Both put a disproportionate cost on variation, in data content and processing
                respectively, compared to sequential processing, so that replication of common parts
                and separating rather than combining similar cases becomes more efficient. </textual></para><para class="po-block e52 e52"><textual class="po-textual">This is very counterintuitive to those engineers and information designers,
                including many who have come into markup since XML emerged as a mainstream force in
                1998-2000, whose intuitions have been formed in situations that take for granted
                single (increasingly fast) computation and single (increasingly fast and capacious)
                memory. Based on personal conversations and anecdotal evidence, there is a mixed
                reaction from the older hands who did not play in the parallel pond, and remember
                what it took to keep computations and working memory compact on smaller machines or
                in the small job partitions in early multitasking architectures. To caricature
                somewhat, some feel that after a period of deep illusion, computing has finally
                woken up once more to some essential design disciplines - and some feel this is
                separating the engineer even further from the real machine, which is becoming ever
                more deeply incomprehensible.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e53 e53"><title class="po-block e54 e54"><textual class="po-textual">Memory and storage hierarchy</textual></title><para class="po-block e55 e55"><textual class="po-textual">Memory performance has been growing continually alongside processor performance,
                over decades. In recent years it has become a commonplace to say that the rate of
                growth in memory performance is markedly slower than for processing, leading to a
                large and increasing performance gap. This is broadly true, but stated simply
                obscures a more interesting detailed picture of evolving patterns of memory and
                storage access over a range of hardware, media and networks (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e56 e56" linkend="PatHen09"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, 5.13). </textual></para><para class="po-block e57 e57"><textual class="po-textual"> Multiple cache levels within processors, deep memory hierarchies using different
                types of hardware, delegating disk access management to on-board processors within
                disk drives, and introducing specialized storage network managers, have between them
                taken the strain to a large extent. However, the very intensity and diversity of
                this effort means that different platforms are more likely than before to have
                different memory hierarchies and storage characteristics.A practical consequence is
                that fine tuning of memory hierarchy assumptions and data design to make data fast
                on one platform can very easily slow it down on another.</textual></para><para class="po-block e58 e58"><textual class="po-textual">This is an area where a good theory has turned out to be very practical as a tool
                for thinking. Cache-obliviousness (better named hierarchy-obliviousness, but as
                usual the initial name has stuck) is the core concept of an area of research on data
                structures that are not only fast to process in principle, but remain fast however
                the memory hierarchy (and storage network, at larger scale) is structured.
                Cache-oblivious data structures have high locality with respect to whatever the
                usual operations are on the data.That is, if an instance of a cache-oblivious data
                structure is broken arbitrarily into pieces </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e59 e59" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual"> of any size </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (for example, loaded a page at a time into
                a cache, hence the name) the common operations on the data structure are, on
                average, highly likely to need data that is within the same piece. The value of this
                area of work for our purposes is not so much in the detail as in the overall
                concept. Data structures that follow this design pattern are likely to "fly
                well" in a wide range of memory hierarchies, since at any scale, the usual
                kinds of processing are less likely to walk or reference out of the piece that is
                already in fast(er) memory.</textual></para><para class="po-block e60 e60"><textual class="po-textual">For readers interested in following up the detail of the theory, there is a
                thorough introduction to cache-obliviousness by Erik Demaine (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e61 e61" linkend="Dem02"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">) in the papers from a European summer school on large data
                structures in 2002 (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e62 e62" linkend="BRICS02"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">).</textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e63 e63"><title class="po-block e64 e64"><textual class="po-textual">Platform Independence 2010++? </textual></title><para class="po-block e65 e65"><textual class="po-textual">So what is it to be platform independent in 2010 and beyond? What do we need to be
            independent of, specifically? In simple terms, the key platform features are:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e66 e66"><listitem class="po-container e67 e67"><para class="po-block e68 e68"><textual class="po-textual"> A processing model that uses many processing units, breaking large computations
                    into many independent, different tasks that run simultaneously. This happens
                    within a many-core chip, and also happens when computations are deployed across
                    several processors with different data processing characteristics (one example
                    that is already mainstream is a desktop computer with a separate graphics
                    processor that is highly data-parallel);</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e69 e69"><para class="po-block e70 e70"><textual class="po-textual">A memory hierarchy of arbitrary depth and width, with considerable variation
                    in the detail of how data is moved up and down the hierarchy; and</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e71 e71"><para class="po-block e72 e72"><textual class="po-textual">Greater variation in platform architectures as architecture concepts developed
                    in niche areas (especially high performance scientific computing and graphics
                    processing) are brought to bear in mainstream computing platforms.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e73 e73"><textual class="po-textual">Any one platform can be assumed to have clever low-level software that is designed to
            hide its complexity and weirdness, so that everything still works correctly. Preserving
            correct processing is a high priority in designing new processor architectures with
            forward compatibility from older ones - however it turns out that data designed for the
            "old world" , although not broken, can be unexpectedly slow in emerging
            architectures. This can also lead indirectly to faults, for example when timing
            assumptions are broken. </textual></para><para class="po-block e74 e74"><textual class="po-textual">The main evidence I have for this is anecdotal - side-remarks in talks and
            water-cooler chat with infrastructure-specialist colleagues who are managing a range of
            data-intensive applications in a growing data centre. Suffice it to say that there are
            people who earn a living advising how to get this right, and that my colleagues tell me
            that more than one well-established product has needed updates to resolve performance
            problems in a more distributed, parallel environment. </textual></para><para class="po-block e75 e75"><textual class="po-textual"> Abstracting away from platform features into data processing, the key features are as
            follows.</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e76 e76"><listitem class="po-container e77 e77"><para class="po-block e78 e78"><textual class="po-textual">Significant performance speed-up by separating large computations into smaller
                    pieces of computation that can run independently long enough to get some useful
                    work done (task parallelism).</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e79 e79"><para class="po-block e80 e80"><textual class="po-textual">Significant performance speed-up by executing exactly the same process
                    simultaneously and independently across numbers (8, 16, 32...) of data items
                    (data parallelism);</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e81 e81"><para class="po-block e82 e82"><textual class="po-textual">Separating large data structures into smaller pieces that are usable in
                    isolation long enough to get some useful work done (required in both task
                    parallelism and data parallelism).</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e83 e83"><para class="po-block e84 e84"><textual class="po-textual">Moving data up (read) and down (write) a deep memory hierarchy. At each level
                    some size of data will need to be broken into parts (in a very simple manner, eg
                    pages), and there is significant performance benefit if, on average, such parts
                    of data (at any level) are usable in isolation long enough to get some useful
                    work done.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e85 e85"><para class="po-block e86 e86"><textual class="po-textual">Moving data between the pieces of a parallel computation so that each piece
                    has the data it needs, respecting dependencies regarding data integrity (eg read
                    vs write) and the intended overall flow of computation. </textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e87 e87"><textual class="po-textual">The balance of emphasis between these features varies across the different
            architectures involved, for example scheduling dependencies and data exchange (rather
            than just data partitioning) become more prominent the more communication is needed
            between pieces of computation. Data exchange operates at different scales such as a
            multicore chip passing data between independently processing cores that have separate
            caches, and a multi-processor architecture passing data between processors (such as the
            common example of a desktop computer with a separate graphics processor).</textual></para><para class="po-block e88 e88"><textual class="po-textual">A fundamental research result regarding data exchange is that, in the general case
            where the structures at each end are different, and a computation is needed to map data
            from one to the other, the computational complexity of a data exchange is exponentially
            related to the complexity of the data schemas at each end. The complexity of a data
            schema is a combination of complexity measures on the actual data structure and how it
            is described (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e89 e89" linkend="Kol06"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">). </textual></para><para class="po-block e90 e90"><textual class="po-textual">This result is no great surprise, since data exchange feels like a hard problem in
            practice. However, when data exchange becomes a larger proportionate part of general
            computation, its exponential general complexity properties suggest that there are
            significant benefits to be gained from keeping data structures and the ways they are
            described as simple as possible.</textual></para><para class="po-block e91 e91"><textual class="po-textual">Partitioning data and computation is a more familiar problem, though one effect of a
            generation of ever-more-capable sequential processing environments with ever-larger
            memory spaces has been a tendency to regard such concerns as rather old-fashioned. High
            performance computing for scientific data analysis has kept this area of work alive,
            especially in relation to arrays of data and matrix computations (for example </textual><xref class="po-milestone e92 e92" linkend="LeeZedem02"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">) and automatic data partitioning on this kind of data in XML
            has also been investigated (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e93 e93" linkend="HG09"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">). </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e94 e94"><title class="po-block e95 e95"><textual class="po-textual">Design Principles for Platform-Independence</textual></title><para class="po-block e96 e96"><textual class="po-textual">This section suggests a few rules of thumb that are likely to make larger documents,
            and smaller documents (such as messages) that turn up in large numbers, more truly
            platform independent over these changes in processing architecture. Some of the rules
            come naturally when writing or designing documents by hand, but are pretty easy to break
            or ignore when marked-up data is generated by a program. Others may look like obvious
            bad practice from the point of view of writing and maintaining documents by hand, but
            look more like candidates for sensible design trade-offs when marked-up data is being
            generated by a program. (Note that "generated by a program" includes using one
            of the many authoring tools that provide an illusion of manual editing. If you are not
            seeing all the grim details of the pointy brackets as you type, then your data is being
            generated by a program.)</textual></para><para class="po-block e97 e97"><textual class="po-textual">Note that it is specifically NOT assumed here that the current usual-suspect XML
            processing tools will be used to process or pre-process the document instances
            concerned. These tools may or may not be able to overcome fundamental problems in data
            characterstics " under the hood ", even if rewritten, and new tools will come.
            The only assumptions made below are the structural properties of XML instances.</textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e98 e98"><title class="po-block e99 e99"><textual class="po-textual">Minimize action at a distance</textual></title><itemizedlist class="po-table e100 e100"><listitem class="po-container e101 e101"><para class="po-block e102 e102"><textual class="po-textual">Ensure that the intended scope of influence of any data value that
                        represents a parameter for processing data in the document propagates in a
                        direction from root to leaf along the tree structure of the document.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e103 e103"><para class="po-block e104 e104"><textual class="po-textual"> Minimize cross-references in the data (in particular when purely implicit
                        in the data and not made evident in the raw XML structure) that mean that a
                        computation on the data finds out in flight that it needs to look at a
                        distant part of the tree.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></section><section class="po-hcontainer e105 e105"><title class="po-block e106 e106"><textual class="po-textual">Help processing to "shop local"</textual></title><itemizedlist class="po-table e107 e107"><listitem class="po-container e108 e108"><para class="po-block e109 e109"><textual class="po-textual">Put things that are relevant to each other for processing, close to each
                        other in the document, that is, few steps apart in the document tree. Expect
                        the document tree to be cut into branches, twig-bunches or even small twigs
                        for processing, and think about what computations can be completed in-twig
                        with larger and smaller twig-sizes.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e110 e110"><para class="po-block e111 e111"><textual class="po-textual">Keep document structure aligned with probable processing structures. Think
                        about the flow of information through expected computations on the document,
                        and see if it follows a natural decompositon of the document structure. A
                        simple positive example is hyphenation a paragraph at a time over many
                        paragraphs making up a chapter of a novel.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></section><section class="po-hcontainer e112 e112"><title class="po-block e113 e113"><textual class="po-textual">Replication may be your friend</textual></title><itemizedlist class="po-table e114 e114"><listitem class="po-container e115 e115"><para class="po-block e116 e116"><textual class="po-textual">Repeating pieces of data in different places seems wasteful, yet it may be
                        a really good idea. If a document is generated by a program, so that the
                        conceptual burden of repetition and likelihood of error are small, then
                        there is no reason not to replicate data items it if it helps to reduce
                        action at a distance.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></section><section class="po-hcontainer e117 e117"><title class="po-block e118 e118"><textual class="po-textual">Detailed differences across lots of sort-of-similar things may be costly</textual></title><itemizedlist class="po-table e119 e119"><listitem class="po-container e120 e120"><para class="po-block e121 e121"><textual class="po-textual"> If a processor with data-parallel capabilities thinks that some bunch of
                        things are all the same, then it may decide to process them in a
                        data-parallel way, that is, assume that their processing is identical. A
                        consequence of this is that, from the point of view of any arbitrary one of
                        the parallel processing threads, it has to wait idly through the work needed
                        to cope with all the detailed optional differences that apply to any of the
                        others. If this really is efficient for your data, fine, however it may be
                        better have more different kinds of things, and less optionality within the
                        same kind of thing, so that the under-the-hood gnomes can make more
                        efficient choices more easily for parallel processing.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></section><section class="po-hcontainer e122 e122"><title class="po-block e123 e123"><textual class="po-textual">Examples</textual></title><para class="po-block e124 e124"><textual class="po-textual">The performance penalties discussed above would be expected to be felt mainly at
                large scale, that is, on large documents or high volume processing of smaller
                documents. However, the structural patterns in the rules of thumb can be illustrated
                using small examples, and that is the purpose of this section. </textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e125 e125"><title class="po-block e126 e126"><textual class="po-textual">Action at a distance, "shopping local", and replication</textual></title><para class="po-block e127 e127"><textual class="po-textual">These patterns are illustrated in this section using two contrasting examples.
                    Each example is based on the structural characteristics of a (different) real
                    data format designed for exchanging information extracted from patient records. </textual></para><para class="po-block e128 e128"><textual class="po-textual">The first example has instances divided into in two main parts. First, a list
                    of entities (people, roles and locations), and second, a list of recorded events
                    involving these entitites. Entities are included in events by reference to a
                    unique identifier for each entity. </textual></para><para class="po-block e129 e129"><textual class="po-textual">As the number of events grows, then because a patient will tend to interact
                    with the same people and be treated in the same places, the proportion of
                    entities compared to events will decrease.</textual></para><para class="po-block e130 e130"><textual class="po-textual">There are two motivating ideas underlying these design features. One is to
                    minimize repetition of data, and the other is to facilitate data transfer
                    between instances of software applications having similar (relational) database
                    structures that are closely aligned with the structure of the data. These aims
                    lead to a structure that explicitly avoids replication and has a strong tendency
                    not to &amp;quot;shop local&amp;quot;. In addition, the references to
                    identifiers are well hidden in the data from the point of view of XML parsing,
                    and the majority of references are between two subtrees that diverge near the
                    root of the document (" action at a distance").</textual></para><figure class="po-container e131 e131"><title class="po-block e132 e132"><textual class="po-textual">Example 1</textual></title><programlisting class="po-block e133 e133" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;record&gt;
    &lt;entities&gt;
        &lt;person&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;FF138AF1-F3BC-4BF7-B45C-427E012BA3F4&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;dateOfBirth&gt;1987-11-20&lt;/dateOfBirth&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;...&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;address&gt;...&lt;/address&gt;
        &lt;/person&gt;
        &lt;person&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;BBBBE23A-A9D1-A411-F824-9F7A00A33757&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;dateOfBirth&gt;1987-11-20&lt;/dateOfBirth&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;...&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;address&gt;...&lt;/address&gt;
        &lt;/person&gt;
        &lt;location&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;4B98A89C-41AD-4425-B6CF-17DE8C779FC7&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;...&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;address&gt;...&lt;/address&gt;
        &lt;/location&gt;
        &lt;role&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;8533C566-74FB-4176-8EFE-13E3FCE5B3A6&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;General Practitioner&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;moreAboutRole&gt;...&lt;/moreAboutRole&gt;
        &lt;/role&gt;
        &lt;practitioner&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;3CBA0926-1E25-4B0E-AAFC-F9CF02F8596B&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;person&gt;BBBBE23A-A9D1-A411-F824-9F7A00A33757&lt;/person&gt;
            &lt;role&gt;8533C566-74FB-4176-8EFE-13E3FCE5B3A6&lt;/role&gt;
        &lt;/practitioner&gt;
        &lt;patient&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;A17B8BFA-3A2B-4796-87ED-F9A4D7375C3D&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;pasNumber&gt;39752746&lt;/pasNumber&gt;
            &lt;patientPerson&gt;FF138AF1-F3BC-4BF7-B45C-427E012BA3F4&lt;/patientPerson&gt;
        &lt;/patient&gt;
    &lt;/entities&gt;
    &lt;events&gt;
        &lt;encounter&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;97E037BE-4CBE-46BA-98F8-3BA6B4DA3D1C&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;date&gt;2010-04-01&lt;/date&gt;
            &lt;patient&gt;A17B8BFA-3A2B-4796-87ED-F9A4D7375C3D&lt;/patient&gt;
            &lt;practitioner&gt;3CBA0926-1E25-4B0E-AAFC-F9CF02F8596B&lt;/practitioner&gt;
            &lt;location&gt;4B98A89C-41AD-4425-B6CF-17DE8C779FC7&lt;/location&gt;
        &lt;/encounter&gt;
    &lt;/events&gt;
    &lt;/record&gt;
</textual></programlisting></figure><para class="po-block e134 e134"><textual class="po-textual">In the second example, data about the people and places involved in a care
                    event are given directly in each event subtree of the record extract. This data
                    format was designed to convey information from a number of different software
                    applications into a common store, from which it is then retrieved on a per-event
                    basis. An explicit design criterion was to make no assumptions about the
                    internal structure of the data store, and in the real situation this is based
                    on, there are several such stores with different internal database structures. </textual></para><para class="po-block e135 e135"><textual class="po-textual">This example also illustrates the role of replicating subtrees of data. A
                    location address may appear many times, however the benefits of replication were
                    judged to outweigh the costs, and the sending system is unlikely to make errors
                    putting the same data into a number of events in a transferred record.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e136 e136"><title class="po-block e137 e137"><textual class="po-textual">Example 2</textual></title><programlisting class="po-block e138 e138" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;Record&gt;
&lt;Event&gt;
    &lt;EffectiveTime&gt;2008-04-23T15:10:00.0Z&lt;/EffectiveTime&gt;
    &lt;EventType&gt;
        &lt;IdValue&gt;[Identifier for this event type]&lt;/IdValue&gt;
    &lt;/EventType&gt;
    &lt;PatientDetails&gt;
        &lt;NHSnumber&gt;
            &lt;IdValue&gt;1234567890&lt;/IdValue&gt;
        &lt;/NHSnumber&gt;
        &lt;Name&gt;...&lt;/Name&gt;
        &lt;Address&gt;...&lt;/Address&gt;
    &lt;/PatientDetails&gt;
    &lt;ResponsiblePerson&gt;
        &lt;StructuredName&gt;
            &lt;Title&gt;Dr&lt;/Title&gt;
            &lt;GivenName&gt;Local&lt;/GivenName&gt;
            &lt;FamilyName&gt;Doctor&lt;/FamilyName&gt;
        &lt;/StructuredName&gt;
    &lt;/ResponsiblePerson&gt;
    &lt;Role&gt;
        &lt;IdValue&gt;[role of responsible person]&lt;/IdValue&gt;
    &lt;/Role&gt;
    &lt;Location&gt;
        &lt;StructuredAddress&gt;
            &lt;PropertyNumber&gt;65&lt;/PropertyNumber&gt;
            &lt;AddressLine&gt;Festaville Way&lt;/AddressLine&gt;
            &lt;AddressLine&gt;Limnoleon&lt;/AddressLine&gt;
            &lt;AddressLine&gt;Cranmore Regis&lt;/AddressLine&gt;
        &lt;/StructuredAddress&gt;
        &lt;PostCode&gt;LL99 3BB&lt;/PostCode&gt;
    &lt;/Location&gt;
    &lt;LocationType&gt;
        &lt;IdValue&gt;[Identifier for location type]&lt;/IdValue&gt;
    &lt;/LocationType&gt;
&lt;/Event&gt;
&lt;/Record&gt;
                </textual></programlisting></figure></section><section class="po-hcontainer e139 e139"><title class="po-block e140 e140"><textual class="po-textual">Variation in content between apparently similar things </textual></title><para class="po-block e141 e141"><textual class="po-textual">The next example illustrates in principle how parallel processing of instances
                    of the same element is slowed down by optionality in the data, in a processor
                    that runs the same instruction stream in parallel on many data instances (SIMD).
                    Each picture in the series shows the effect of progressively more variation
                    between instances. Coloured cells indicate steps where no progress is made in
                    processing that element.</textual></para><para class="po-block e142 e142"><textual class="po-textual">The first picture below shows element instances with no variation at all, and
                    there is no loss of performance. In the next, some items are optional. Any
                    instance that lacks an optional item will be waiting while the other instances
                    use that part of the instruction stream. The next one after shows what happens
                    when a content model has a choice of sequences of elements. Finally, the fourth
                    picture shows the result of having many possible options (for example, a rich XML vocabulary) with only a few used in
                    any one data instance. </textual></para><figure class="po-container e143 e143"><title class="po-block e144 e144"><textual class="po-textual">No optionality</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e145 e145"><imageobject class="po-container e146 e146"><imagedata class="po-meta e147 e147" fileref="../../../vol5/graphics/Wrightson01/Wrightson01-001.JPG" format="jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><figure class="po-container e148 e148"><title class="po-block e149 e149"><textual class="po-textual">Sparse optionality</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e150 e150"><imageobject class="po-container e151 e151"><imagedata class="po-meta e152 e152" fileref="../../../vol5/graphics/Wrightson01/Wrightson01-002.JPG" format="jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><figure class="po-container e153 e153"><title class="po-block e154 e154"><textual class="po-textual">Alternative substructures</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e155 e155"><imageobject class="po-container e156 e156"><imagedata class="po-meta e157 e157" fileref="../../../vol5/graphics/Wrightson01/Wrightson01-003.JPG" format="jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><figure class="po-container e158 e158"><title class="po-block e159 e159"><textual class="po-textual">Selective use of a large vocabulary</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e160 e160"><imageobject class="po-container e161 e161"><imagedata class="po-meta e162 e162" fileref="../../../vol5/graphics/Wrightson01/Wrightson01-004.JPG" format="jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e163 e163"><textual class="po-textual">A simple count provides a rough indication of the magnitude of the effect.
                    Taking the content of the </textual><code class="po-atom e164 e164"><textual class="po-textual">example</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> element only, in the first case,
                    all steps are active. In the second, there are 5 idle steps out of 40, giving a
                    crude efficiency measure of 87.5%. In the third case, 24 steps out of 40 are
                    idle, i.e. 45% are active. In the final case, the majority of the steps relate
                    to options not represented in the data, and only 4 steps out of 40 are active,
                    i.e. 10%. </textual></para><para class="po-block e165 e165"><textual class="po-textual">It must be emphasized that this is only a rough indication in principle; real
                    effects will depend on a combination of data structures, application-level
                    algorithms, programming language implementations, and operating system and
                    processor strategies. However, even this crude analysis indicates the potential
                    value of, for example, reconfiguring messages that have repetitive internal
                    structure to use different element names in preference to naming elements by
                    role and varying their internal structure, in order to provide easy
                    opportunities for efficient data-parallel processing.</textual></para></section></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e166 e166"><title class="po-block e167 e167"><textual class="po-textual">Conclusion</textual></title><para class="po-block e168 e168"><textual class="po-textual">Only experience will show conclusively what effect emerging architectures may have on
            processing XML and other markup language instances. It just might turn out that the
            under-the-hood gnomes in the new architectures are so clever that most document and data
            designers can safely ignore these issues. However, the factors discussed above suggest
            that developers and owners of XML vocabularies, document types and data architectures
            should give some thought to the effect of emerging architectures on the realities of
            platform-independence.</textual></para><para class="po-block e169 e169"><textual class="po-textual">This paper has focussed strongly on XML instances, independent from schemas, data
            models and processing models. Thorough consideration of these from the perspective of
            platform independence on emerging archtitectures may well either show some of the
            concerns in the paper to be groundless, or (more likely) yield more refined guidance on
            design principles. In particular, it is worth noting that the functional style of XSLT,
            and the explicitly context-limited formal semantics of XQuery, are both favourable
            characteristics (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e170 e170" linkend="XQsem"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><xref class="po-milestone e171 e171" linkend="XDM"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><xref class="po-milestone e172 e172" linkend="XSLT2"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">) .</textual></para><para class="po-block e173 e173"><textual class="po-textual">Another possible area of further work would be to analyse data exchange complexity
            specifically for XML to XML data exchanges. Theoretical work on data exchange complexity
            mostly uses relational database schemas as a reference model of data structure, and the
            work on XML-to-XML data exchange that came to light in researching this paper (though
            well short of a thorough literature review on the topic) indicated a tendency to work
            from oversimplified models of XML without apparent knowledge of foundational XML-related
            work such as the XPath/XQuery data model and formal semantics.</textual></para></section><bibliography class="po-hcontainer e174 e174"><title class="po-block e175 e175"><textual class="po-textual">References</textual></title><bibliomixed class="po-block e176 e176" xml:id="LeeZedem02" xreflabel="Lee &amp; Zedem 2002"><textual class="po-textual">P Lee, Z Kedem </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e177 e177"><textual class="po-textual">Automatic Data and Computation
                Decomposition on Distributed Memory Parallel Computers </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> ACM Transactions
            on Programming Languages and Systems, Vol. 24, No. 1, January 2002, Pages 1–50. doi: </textual><biblioid class="po-atom e178 doi e178"><textual class="po-textual">10.1145/509705.509706</textual></biblioid></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e179 e179" xml:id="ParLab09" xreflabel="Par Lab 09"><textual class="po-textual">Asanovic, Bodik et al </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e180 e180"><textual class="po-textual">A view of the parallel computing
                landscape. </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">Commun. ACM 52, 10 (Oct. 2009), 56-67. 
          doi: </textual><biblioid class="po-atom e181 doi e181"><textual class="po-textual">10.1145/1562764.1562783</textual></biblioid></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e182 e182" xml:id="ParLab06" xreflabel="Par Lab 06"><textual class="po-textual">Asanovic, Bodik et al </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e183 e183"><textual class="po-textual">The Landscape of Parallel
                Computing Research: A View from Berkeley</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Technical Report No.
            UCB/EECS-2006-183 2006 </textual><link class="po-inline e184 e184" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">
                http://www.eecs.berkeley.edu/Pubs/TechRpts/2006/EECS-2006-183.pdf</textual></link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e185 e185" xml:id="Seiler08" xreflabel="Seiler et al 08"><textual class="po-textual">L Seiler et al </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e186 e186"><textual class="po-textual"> Larrabee: A Many-Core x86
                Architecture for Visual Computing </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> ACM Transactions on Graphics, Vol. 27,
            No. 3, Article 18 August 2008. doi: </textual><biblioid class="po-atom e187 doi e187"><textual class="po-textual">10.1145/1360612.1360617</textual></biblioid></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e188 e188" xml:id="BSP90" xreflabel="Valliant 90"><textual class="po-textual">L Valliant </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e189 e189"><textual class="po-textual">A Bridging Model for Parallel Computation
            </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Communications of the ACM Vol.33, No.8 August 1990. doi: </textual><biblioid class="po-atom e190 doi e190"><textual class="po-textual">10.1145/79173.79181</textual></biblioid></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e191 e191" xml:id="BSP96" xreflabel="Skillicorn et al 96"><textual class="po-textual">D Skillicorn, J Hill and W McColl </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e192 e192"><textual class="po-textual">Questions
                and Answers about BSP </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Oxford University Computing Laboratory
            PRG-TR-15-96 November 1996</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e193 e193" xml:id="PJ08" xreflabel="Peyton Jones et al 08"><textual class="po-textual">S Peyton Jones et al </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e194 e194"><textual class="po-textual"> Harnessing the Multicores: Nested Data
                Parallelism in Haskell </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Foundations of Software Technology and
            Theoretical Computer Science (Bangalore) 2008.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e195 e195" xml:id="Kol06" xreflabel="Kolaitis et al 06"><textual class="po-textual">P Kolaitis, J Panttaja, W Tan </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e196 e196"><textual class="po-textual">The Complexity of Data Exchange
            </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> ACM SIGMOD-SIGACT-SIGART symposium on Principles of database systems (PODS)
            2006. doi: </textual><biblioid class="po-atom e197 doi e197"><textual class="po-textual">10.1145/1142351.1142357</textual></biblioid></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e198 e198" xml:id="XQsem" xreflabel="XPath/XQuery formal semantics"><emphasis class="po-inline e199 e199"><textual class="po-textual">XQuery 1.0 and XPath 2.0 Formal
                Semantics </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> W3C Recommendation 23 January 2007 </textual><link class="po-inline e200 e200" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">
                http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery-semantics/</textual></link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e201 e201" xml:id="XDM" xreflabel="XPath/XQuery data model"><emphasis class="po-inline e202 e202"><textual class="po-textual">XQuery 1.0 and XPath 2.0 Data Model (XDM) </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> W3C
            Recommendation 23 January 2007 </textual><link class="po-inline e203 e203" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">
            http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath-datamodel/</textual></link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e204 e204" xml:id="XSLT2" xreflabel="XSLT 2.0"><emphasis class="po-inline e205 e205"><textual class="po-textual">XSL Transformations (XSLT) Version 2.0,</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> W3C
            Recommendation 23 January 2007 </textual><link class="po-inline e206 e206" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual"> http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/ </textual></link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e207 e207" xml:id="PatHen09" xreflabel="Patterson &amp; Hennessey 09"><textual class="po-textual">D Patterson, J Hennessey </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e208 e208"><textual class="po-textual">Computer
                Organization and Design: The Hardware/Software Interface</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 4th edition,
            Morgan Kaufmann 2009. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e209 e209" xml:id="NESL" xreflabel="Blelloch et al 94"><textual class="po-textual">G Blelloch et al </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e210 e210"><textual class="po-textual"> Implementation of a Portable
                Nested Data-Parallel Language </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Journal of Parallel and Distributed
            Computing, 21(1), April 1994. doi: </textual><biblioid class="po-atom e211 doi e211"><textual class="po-textual">10.1006/jpdc.1994.1038</textual></biblioid></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e212 e212" xml:id="Dem02" xreflabel="Demaine 02"><textual class="po-textual">E Demaine </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e213 e213"><textual class="po-textual">Cache-Oblivious Algorithms and Data Structures
            </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> EEF Summer School on Massive Data Sets June 27-July 1, 2002, BRICS,
            University of Aarhus, Denmark </textual><link class="po-inline e214 e214" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.brics.dk/MassiveData02/</textual></link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e215 e215" xml:id="BRICS02" xreflabel="Massive Data Sets 02"><textual class="po-textual">EEF Summer School on Massive Data Sets 2002, BRICS,
            University of Aarhus, Denmark </textual><link class="po-inline e216 e216" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.brics.dk/MassiveData02/</textual></link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e217 e217" xml:id="HG09" xreflabel="Head et al 09"><textual class="po-textual">M Head &amp; M Govindaraju </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e218 e218"><textual class="po-textual">Performance enhancement with
                speculative execution based parallelism for processing large-scale xml-based
                application data </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 18th ACM international symposium on High performance
            distributed computing 2009. doi: </textual><biblioid class="po-atom e219 doi e219"><textual class="po-textual">10.1145/1551609.1551615</textual></biblioid></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e220 e220" xml:id="Wrightson05" xreflabel="Wrightson 05"><textual class="po-textual"> A Wrightson </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e221 e221"><textual class="po-textual">Semantics of Well Formed XML as a Human
                and Machine Readable Language</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">Extreme Markup Languages 2005</textual></bibliomixed></bibliography></article></classedDocument>