<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">Report from the Field: PubMed Central, an XML-based Archive of Life Sciences Journal
    Articles</textual></title><info class="po-record e2 e2"><confgroup class="po-record e3 e3"><conftitle class="po-field e4 e4"><textual class="po-textual">International Symposium on XML for the Long Haul:  Issues in the Long-term Preservation of XML</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">August 2, 2010</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e6 e6"><para class="po-block e7 e7"><textual class="po-textual">PubMed Central (PMC) is an XML-based archive of life sciences journal literature at the
        U.S. National Institutes of Heath that allows public access to full-text journal articles.
        The archive was created in 2000 and has grown steadily to over 2 million records. The
        project has been successful in part because of the strict XML control and the flexibility
        that PMC givesre its submitters. </textual></para><para class="po-block e8 e8"><textual class="po-textual">This paper gives an overview of the PMC data evaluation process; the XML processing
        model; the PMC philosophy toward XML use, including use of the NLM DTD, XML Taggging Style,
        usability or reusablilty of the XML, public XML tools, and our people; and some challenges
        we continue to face maintaining the archive. </textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e9 e9"><personname class="po-record e10 e10"><firstname class="po-field e11 e11"><textual class="po-textual">Jeff</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e12 e12"><textual class="po-textual">Beck</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e13 e13"><para class="po-block e14 e14"><textual class="po-textual">Jeff has been involved in the PubMed Central project at NLM since 2000. He has been
          working journal publishing since the early 1990.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e15 e15"><jobtitle class="po-field e16 e16"><textual class="po-textual">Technical Information Specialist</textual></jobtitle><orgname class="po-block e17 e17"><textual class="po-textual">National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI), National Library of Medicine
          (NLM), National Institutes of Heath (NIH)</textual></orgname></affiliation></author><legalnotice class="po-container e18 e18"><para class="po-block e19 e19"><textual class="po-textual">Author's contribution to the Work was done as part of the Author's official duties as an NIH employee and is a Work of the United States Government.  Therefore, copyright may not be established in the United States. 17 U.S.C. § 105.  If Publisher intends to disseminate the Work outside the U.S., Publisher may secure copyright to the extent authorized under the domestic laws of the relevant country, subject to a paid-up, nonexclusive, irrevocable worldwide license to the United States in such copyrighted work to reproduce, prepare derivative works, distribute copies to the public and perform publicly and display publicly the work, and to permit others to do so.</textual></para></legalnotice></info><para class="po-block e20 e20"><textual class="po-textual">PubMed Central </textual><citation class="po-atom e21 e21" linkend="PMC01"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC01]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual"> is the U.S. National Institutes
    of Health's free digital archive of full-text biomedical and life sciences journal literature.
    Content is stored in XML at the article level. Structures above article (issues, volumes, etc.)
    are built as collections of articles. The content is displayed dynamically from the archival XML
    every time that a user retrieves an article. In that respect, every request confirms that the
    archival copy is still functional. </textual></para><para class="po-block e22 e22"><textual class="po-textual">PMC contains over 2 million article records from over 1,000 titles with 10-15,000 new
    records being added each month. On average, 600,000-700,000 articles are retrieved by 400,000
    unique users each day </textual><citation class="po-atom e23 e23" linkend="PMC02"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC02]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para><para class="po-block e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">PubMed Central was started in 1999 to allow free full-text access to journal articles.
    Participation by journals is voluntary. From the beginning there has always been a requirement
    that participating journals provide their content to NCBI marked up in some "reasonable" SGML or
    XML format along with the highest-resolution images available, PDF files (if available), and all
    supplementary material. Complete details on the PMC's file requirements are available </textual><citation class="po-atom e25 e25" linkend="PMC03"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC03]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para><para class="po-block e26 e26"><textual class="po-textual">A discussion of what makes a "reasonable" SGML or XML format could be an interesting topic
    for another paper. For now, "reasonable" means that there is sufficient granularity in the
    source model to map those elements critical to the understanding of the article (and/or its
    functioning in the PMC system) from the original article to the appropriate place in the PMC XML
    model. </textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e27 e27"><title class="po-block e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">The Data Evaluation Process</textual></title><para class="po-block e29 e29"><textual class="po-textual">Journals joining PMC must pass two tests. First, the content must be approved for the NLM
      collection </textual><citation class="po-atom e30 e30" linkend="NLM01"><textual class="po-textual">[NLM01]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">. Essentially this is just a check to
      be sure that the content is "in scope" for a medical library. </textual></para><para class="po-block e31 e31"><textual class="po-textual">Next the journal must go through a technical evaluation to "be sure that the journal can
      routinely supply files of sufficient quality to generate complete and accurate articles online
      without the need for human action to correct errors or omissions in the data." </textual><citation class="po-atom e32 e32" linkend="PMC03"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC03]</textual></citation></para><para class="po-block e33 e33"><textual class="po-textual">For the evaluation, a journal supplies a sample set of articles (at least 50). These
      articles are put through a series of automated and human checks to ensure that the XML is
      valid and that it accurately represents the article content. There is a set of "Minimum Data
      Requirements" that must be met before the evaluation proceeds to the more human-intense
      content accuracy checking </textual><citation class="po-atom e34 e34" linkend="PMC04"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC04]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">. These minimum criteria
      are listed briefly below: </textual><orderedlist class="po-table e35 e35"><listitem class="po-container e36 e36"><para class="po-block e37 e37"><textual class="po-textual">Each sample package must be complete: all required data files (XML/SGML, PDF if
            available, image files, supplementary data files) for every article in the package must
            be present and named correctly.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e38 e38"><para class="po-block e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">All XML files must conform to an acceptable journal article DTD.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e40 e40"><para class="po-block e41 e41"><textual class="po-textual">All XML/SGML files must parse according to their DTD.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e42 e42"><para class="po-block e43 e43"><textual class="po-textual">Regardless of the XML/SGML DTD used, the following metadata information must be
            present and tagged with correct values in every sample file: </textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e44 e44"><listitem class="po-container e45 e45"><para class="po-block e46 e46"><textual class="po-textual">Journal ISSN or other unique Journal ID</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e47 e47"><para class="po-block e48 e48"><textual class="po-textual">Journal Publisher</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e49 e49"><para class="po-block e50 e50"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright statement (if applicable)</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e51 e51"><para class="po-block e52 e52"><textual class="po-textual">License statement (if applicable)</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e53 e53"><para class="po-block e54 e54"><textual class="po-textual">Volume number</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e55 e55"><para class="po-block e56 e56"><textual class="po-textual">Issue number (if applicable)</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e57 e57"><para class="po-block e58 e58"><textual class="po-textual">Pagination/article sequence number</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e59 e59"><para class="po-block e60 e60"><textual class="po-textual">Issue-based or Article-based publication dates. Articles submitted to PMC must
                  contain publication dates that accurately reflect the journal’s publication
                  model.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e61 e61"><para class="po-block e62 e62"><textual class="po-textual">All image files for figures must be legible, and submitted in high-resolution TIFF
            or EPS format, according to the PMC Image File Requirements.</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e63 e63"><textual class="po-textual">These seem like simple and obvious things - xml files must be valid - but the minimum data
      requirements have greatly reduced the amount of rework that the PMC Data Evaluation group has
      to do. Certainly it helps to be explicit about even the most obvious of things. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e64 e64"><title class="po-block e65 e65"><textual class="po-textual">PMC Processing Model</textual></title><para class="po-block e66 e66"><textual class="po-textual">The PMC processing model is diagrammed in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e67 e67" linkend="F1"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">. For each article, we
      receive a set of files that includes the text in SGML or XML, the highest resolution figures
      available, a PDF file if one has been created for the article, and any supplementary material
      or supporting data. The text is converted to the current version of the NLM Archiving and
      Interchange DTD </textual><citation class="po-atom e68 e68" linkend="JATS01"><textual class="po-textual">[JATS01]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">, and the images are converted
      to a web-friendly format. The source SGML or XML, original images, supplementary data files,
      PDFs, and NLM XML files are stored in the archive. Articles are rendered online using the NLM
      XML, PDFs, supplementary data files, and the web-friendly images. </textual><figure class="po-container e69 e69" xml:id="F1" xreflabel="Fig. 1"><title class="po-block e70 e70"><textual class="po-textual">PMC Processing Model</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e71 e71"><imageobject class="po-container e72 e72"><imagedata class="po-meta e73 e73" fileref="../../../vol6/graphics/Beck01/Beck01-001.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></para><para class="po-block e74 e74"><textual class="po-textual">This processing model seems obvious now, but this is not how the content was always
      handled. The early PMC processing model is shown in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e75 e75" linkend="F2"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">. </textual><figure class="po-container e76 e76" xml:id="F2" xreflabel="Fig. 2"><title class="po-block e77 e77"><textual class="po-textual">Original PMC Processing Model</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e78 e78"><imageobject class="po-container e79 e79"><imagedata class="po-meta e80 e80" fileref="../../../vol6/graphics/Beck01/Beck01-002.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><textual class="po-textual"> The images, PDFs, and supplementary material were handled in much the same way, but
      they are not interesting for this paper so I will just be concentrating on the text processing
      from now on. The SGML or XML was loaded into a database in its native format. When the article
      was requested by a user, the original text was pulled from the database and run through a
      piece of proprietary software to render it in HTML on the web. It is easy to see that this is
      not a scalable solution - especially if we were planning for any kind of success.</textual></para><para class="po-block e81 e81"><textual class="po-textual">As we started getting more and more submitters, it became obvious that we needed to take
      the processing hit of conversion to a single text format up front and allow the database and
      rendering system concentrate on only one type of XML (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e82 e82" linkend="F3"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">). We created the
      pmc-1.dtd </textual><citation class="po-atom e83 e83" linkend="PMC05"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC05]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">, which was based on the first
      two submission DTDs that we had to PMC: keton.dtd, an SGML DTD somehow descended from
      ISO12083, and the BioMed Central article.dtd, an XML DTD that was very similar. </textual><figure class="po-container e84 e84" xml:id="F3" xreflabel="Fig. 3"><title class="po-block e85 e85"><textual class="po-textual">Updated PMC Processing Model</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e86 e86"><imageobject class="po-container e87 e87"><imagedata class="po-meta e88 e88" fileref="../../../vol6/graphics/Beck01/Beck01-003.png" format="png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e89 e89"><textual class="po-textual">The pmc-1.dtd was written to simplify access to full-text articles online. It was a small
      and simple DTD that soon showed its limitations as we started to convert more submission
      formats into it. It grew quickly, and quickly grew unwieldy. At this point, work began on a
      new DTD that became the NLM Archiving and Interchange Tag Suite </textual><citation class="po-atom e90 e90" linkend="Beck01"><textual class="po-textual">[Beck01]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e91 e91"><title class="po-block e92 e92"><textual class="po-textual">XML Philosophy</textual></title><para class="po-block e93 e93"><textual class="po-textual">There are a number of things in our XML Philosophy, which may at first seem contradictory,
      that have lead to the success of PMC and the manageability of the article ingest work. In
      general, we have found a balance between strictness and flexibility that allows us to keep a
      certain amount of control but not be too restrictive on our submitters. </textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e94 e94"><title class="po-block e95 e95"><textual class="po-textual">Some Strict Things</textual></title><para class="po-block e96 e96"><textual class="po-textual">The first thing we are strict about is that we do a complete review of any new DTD in
      which content is being submitted, as described above. We do not take articles in HTML. We also do a complete review of sample articles for each new journal to be sure that the content provider is able to provide content that is
      structurally and semantically correct.</textual></para><para class="po-block e97 e97"><textual class="po-textual">Another thing we are strict about is that all content must be valid according to the DTD
      in which it was submitted - not just during data evaluation but in the ongoing production process as well. This seems like an obvious one, but there was a surprising amount
      of controversy about this in the early days of PMC, and we still get invalid files. Problems
      usually arise now because the submitter has made a DTD change (as simple as adding a new
      character entity to the DTD) without telling us or sending an updated DTD. </textual></para><para class="po-block e98 e98"><textual class="po-textual">Also, we do not fix text; all content changes must be made by the submitter, and the
      content must be resubmitted.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e99 e99"><title class="po-block e100 e100"><textual class="po-textual">Some Flexible Things</textual></title><para class="po-block e101 e101"><textual class="po-textual">Some things we are not so strict about, which reduces some of the burden on our
      submitters. First, we don't require all content to be in our format or to follow our tagging
      rules. We don't force updates of content to latest DTD version, and we generally follow
      journal style where it does not interfere with our systems.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e102 e102"><title class="po-block e103 e103"><textual class="po-textual">The DTD</textual></title><para class="po-block e104 e104"><textual class="po-textual">We use the NLM Archiving and Interchange DTD as the format for all articles loaded to
        the PMC database. This model was created specifically for archiving article content. It was
        designed to be an "easy target to hit" when transforming content from the over 40 different
        input models that we receive content in. Currently we are writing content into version
        3.0.</textual></para><para class="po-block e105 e105"><textual class="po-textual">We do not migrate all content to each new version of the NLM DTD when it comes out. The
        system is robust enough to handle content from version 1.0 of the DTD through version 3.0,
        so we are not constantly churning the data.</textual></para><para class="po-block e106 e106"><textual class="po-textual">We manage all of the versions of the DTD with an
        XML Catalog, which we also use to manage all of the input DTDs (SGML and XML). We maintain
        all mappings of PUBLIC and SYSTEM IDs for any DTD that we use in the XML catalog on our
        Linux machines and then create other catalogs from it each time it is updated. We create an
        SGML Catalog for the SGML tools that we use; a single "Oxygen" catalog that
        everyone on the team can use over the network with the XML editor; and a copy of the catalog that refers to
        http-based copies of the DTDs for PMC International sites. The XML Catalog is an essential
        piece of the PMC system.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e107 e107"><title class="po-block e108 e108"><textual class="po-textual">PMC Tagging Style</textual></title><para class="po-block e109 e109"><textual class="po-textual">Next, we've defined a set of rules for objects within articles that is more restrictive
        than the DTD. This allows us to have normalized structures (figures, tables, contributors)
        in articles for ease of processing and rendering. We call these rules the PMC Tagging Style,
        and all articles must "pass style" before being loaded to the database. They are documented
        in the PMC Tagging Guidelines </textual><citation class="po-atom e110 e110" linkend="PMC06"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC06]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e111 e111"><title class="po-block e112 e112"><textual class="po-textual">(Re)Usability of XML</textual></title><para class="po-block e113 e113"><textual class="po-textual">Finally, our XML must be useable by others. The NLM XML that we create from whatever was
        submitted to us is always available to the submitting publisher (the content owner), and a
        subset of the articles that are Open Access are available to anyone for download through the
        PMC Open Archives Service </textual><citation class="po-atom e114 e114" linkend="PMC07"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC07]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">. This keeps us
        honest. We can't allow ourselves to take shortcuts with the data. All articles must be valid
        according to the public NLM DTD version that they reference, and we only use Processing
        Instructions for instructions about processing.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e115 e115"><title class="po-block e116 e116"><textual class="po-textual">PMC Tools</textual></title><para class="po-block e117 e117"><textual class="po-textual">Another thing that has been helpful is that we share tools we've built with our
        submitters. The more help we can give to people sending us content, the cleaner the content
        is, and the easier it is for us to process. Reducing or eliminating correction cycles
        greatly reduces cost and stress on the PMC team. </textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e118 e118"><listitem class="po-container e119 e119" xml:id="LI1" xreflabel="Tools section"><para class="po-block e120 e120"><textual class="po-textual">PMC Tagging Guidelines </textual><citation class="po-atom e121 e121" linkend="PMC06"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC06]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual"> - This
              is a document that describes the PMC Tagging Style mentioned above. We first created
              the guidelines as an internal document that we would use to keep track of any tagging
              rules we set up to keep our XML as normal as possible. As we got more and more
              questions from providers about how structures should be tagged, we decided to share
              our internal document.</textual></para><para class="po-block e122 e122"><textual class="po-textual">The DTD allows many ways to tag certain structures, but we do
              have a preference for many of them, and sharing them has been helpful both for us and
              for PMC submitters. While we don't require content that is submitted to PMC be "to
              style", we certainly aren't going to turn it away. </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e123 e123"><para class="po-block e124 e124"><textual class="po-textual">PMC StyleChecker </textual><citation class="po-atom e125 e125" linkend="PMC08"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC08]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual"> - This is a
              tool that applies the rules defined in the Tagging Guidelines. It is an XSL transform
              that reviews each article and reports what it finds. This is the same transform that
              we have inline in our production process after validation against the DTD to confirm
              that the structures withing the articles we are loading into the database meet our
              standards for tagging.</textual></para><para class="po-block e126 e126"><textual class="po-textual">It is available as an online tool that users can upload one article at a time or
              as a set of stylesheets that data providers can build into their workflow </textual><citation class="po-atom e127 e127" linkend="PMC09"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC09]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">.
              ().
            </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e128 e128"><para class="po-block e129 e129"><textual class="po-textual">Online SGML Validator </textual><citation class="po-atom e130 e130" linkend="PMC10"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC10]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual"> - This is a tool that
              validates SGML against the SGML DTDs that we have in the PMC system as long as the PUBLIC
              or SYSTEM ID is recognized in our SGML Catalog file. That is, as long as we have set
              up the particular SGML DTD for ingest in our system.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e131 e131"><para class="po-block e132 e132"><textual class="po-textual">Online XML Validator </textual><citation class="po-atom e133 e133" linkend="PMC11"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC11]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual"> - This is a tool that
              validates any XML file whose SYSTEM ID is resolvable on the system or whose PUBLIC or
              SYSTEM ID is mapped in our XML Catalog file.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e134 e134"><para class="po-block e135 e135"><textual class="po-textual">PMC Article Previewer </textual><citation class="po-atom e136 e136" linkend="PMC12"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC12]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual"> - This is a
              tool that runs an article through a PMC ingest workflow. First the SGML or XML is
              validated against the DTD per the rules given above for the SGML and XML validators.
              Then, if we recognize the DTD and have a conversion built for it, the article runs
              through the XSL transform to normalized PMC XML. This output is validated against the
              output DTD and is checked with the StyleChecker. If successfull at all of these steps,
              the article is displayed on a page in PMC display format so that the publisher can
              preview the article. Also, he has a good idea that his article will be ingested into
              PMC with no problems. </textual></para><para class="po-block e137 e137"><textual class="po-textual">The Article Previewer requires users to login with a "My NCBI" account </textual><citation class="po-atom e138 e138" linkend="NCBI01"><textual class="po-textual">[NCBI01]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual"> because the
              content stays on the database until the user removes it.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><textual class="po-textual">
      </textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e139 e139"><title class="po-block e140 e140"><textual class="po-textual">Our People</textual></title><para class="po-block e141 e141"><textual class="po-textual">Finally, there has to be some acknowledgment of the people who work on the project. We
      have a fantastic set of programmers that builds us some very nice software, and we have a good
      group of Content Managers who marshall the content through the workflow and deal with the
      exceptions and communicate with the publishers. But, we have a group in the middle that writes
      and maintains the XSL transforms. </textual></para><para class="po-block e142 e142"><textual class="po-textual">It is not easy to find the right people for this group. Our document conversion writers need to have the strong attention to detail, unending curiosity, and a desire to always find a better way to do things of a good programmer. But, they also need to live in a world where mixed-content does not frightent them. Because we are writing transforms to maintain the meaning and intend of the origingal article, we slip out of the black-and-white prgrammer world into a world of grays. We need to represent the article that was submitted to the archive - and not necessarily the file that was submitted. </textual></para><para class="po-block e143 e143"><textual class="po-textual">A successful PMC document conversion writer lives with a foot in both camps: the world of the wants and desires of the content owners and the rule-driven world of people who build and run large systems. This is not something that is unique to PubMed Central by any means, but it does surprise some people that our group is made up of people who studied English, Art, and Library Sciences rather than Systems Design, COBOL or The DOM.</textual></para><para class="po-block e144 e144"><textual class="po-textual">Because we work exclusively with documents and document XML, I have found that it is much
      easier to start with a (technically oriented) person with a publishing or printing background
      and teach them how to write a transform than to take a brilliant programmer and teach them how
      to think about documents. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e145 e145"><title class="po-block e146 e146"><textual class="po-textual">Some Challenges: When Print Goes Away</textual></title><para class="po-block e147 e147"><textual class="po-textual">There are still a few things that give us problems in PMC. First, because of the rapid
      changes in article publishing since the invention of the Internet, journal publishing models
      have started to change. A business that had a pretty stable model of articles in issues that
      printed and mailed on a periodic schedule has been shifting to publishing on a continuous
      basis - with articles made available online as soon as they are ready and then collected into
      print issues after some time (or not collected and printed at all). </textual></para><para class="po-block e148 e148"><textual class="po-textual">Early PMC was created based on the issue model, and we have had to be flexible to handle these changes.</textual></para><para class="po-block e149 e149"><textual class="po-textual">One thing that we have done to remain flexible here to allow us to deal with this continuous publication model is to be very strict about publication
      dates in articles. Depending on the publication model of a journal, an article may have one
      publication date (for traditional print-based journals) or an article-level publication date
      and a collection-level publication date (for articles that are published online and then
      collected into a print or online issue. volume, or collection. See the essay on
      &lt;pub-date&gt; in the Tagging Guidelines </textual><citation class="po-atom e150 e150" linkend="PMC06"><textual class="po-textual">[PMC06]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para><para class="po-block e151 e151"><textual class="po-textual">The rise of the internet has also brought about another "Continuous publication" idea, and that is continuous publication of the same document - or updates to an article. We have not seen too much of this in PMC yet, but we have been preparing ourselves. Each article in the PMC database is assigned an ArticleID and an ArticleInstanceID. Any new version of an article creates a new ArticleInstance, and all ArticleInstances for a given article have the same ArticleID. This allows us to store multiple versions of articles, retrieve the latest (by ArticleID), and to retrieve any version (by ArticleInstanceID). Fortunately, how the Journal Publishers will handle will need to be decided by the Journal Publishers. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e152 e152"><title class="po-block e153 e153"><textual class="po-textual">Conclusion</textual></title><para class="po-block e154 e154"><textual class="po-textual">The success we have had at PMC has really been due to a combination of factors including our strictness to upholding the XML models that we use, our flexibility (to a point) that we have with our content providers, the tools that we've put together to make our jobs and the jobs of our content providers easier, and teh fine people we have working on the team. To be fair, it is also nice to have the resources of the National Center for Biotechnology Information and the National Library of Medicine behind us as well as the support of the NIH in general, who have declared that copies of all peer-reviewed articles that report on NIH-funded research must be deposited to PubMed Central and made available within 12 months of the publication date </textual><citation class="po-atom e155 e155" linkend="Beck02"><textual class="po-textual">[Beck02]</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual">. I have to include that just to be fair.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e156 e156"><title class="po-block e157 e157"><textual class="po-textual">Acknowledgments</textual></title><para class="po-block e158 e158"><textual class="po-textual">This work was supported by the Intramural Research Program of the NIH, National Library of
      Medicine, National Center for Biotechnology Information.</textual></para></section><bibliography class="po-hcontainer e159 e159"><title class="po-block e160 e160"><textual class="po-textual">References</textual></title><bibliomixed class="po-block e161 e161" xml:id="PMC01"><textual class="po-textual">PubMed Central, </textual><link class="po-inline e162 e162" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e163 e163" xml:id="PMC02"><textual class="po-textual">PubMed Central National Avisory Committee. (2009) Minutes of the
      PubMed Central National Avisory Committee Meeting, June 15, 2009. National Institutues of
      Health, Bethesda, MD.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e164 e164" xml:id="PMC03"><textual class="po-textual">How to Join PMC, </textual><link class="po-inline e165 e165" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/about/pubinfo.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/about/pubinfo.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e166 e166" xml:id="NLM01"><textual class="po-textual">NLM Collection Development and Acquisitions, </textual><link class="po-inline e167 e167" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.nlm.nih.gov/tsd/acquisions/mainpage.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.nlm.nih.gov/tsd/acquisions/mainpage.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e168 e168" xml:id="PMC04"><textual class="po-textual">Minimum Criteria for PMC Data Evaluation Submissions, </textual><link class="po-inline e169 e169" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/pmcdoc/mindatareq.pdf" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/pmcdoc/mindatareq.pdf</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e170 e170" xml:id="JATS01"><textual class="po-textual">NLM Archving and Interchange DTD, </textual><link class="po-inline e171 e171" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e172 e172" xml:id="PMC05"><textual class="po-textual">pmc-1.dtd, </textual><link class="po-inline e173 e173" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/pmcdoc/dtd/pmc-1.dtd" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/pmcdoc/dtd/pmc-1.dtd</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e174 e174" xml:id="Beck01"><textual class="po-textual">Beck and Lapeyre (2003) New Public Domain Journal Archiving and Interchange DTDs. XML 2003. </textual><link class="po-inline e175 e175" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://       www.idealliance.org/papers/dx_xml03/papers/04-01-02/04-01-02.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://
      www.idealliance.org/papers/dx_xml03/papers/04-01-02/04-01-02.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e176 e176" xml:id="PMC06"><textual class="po-textual">PMC Tagging Guidelines, </textual><link class="po-inline e177 e177" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/pmcdoc/tagging-guidelines/article/style.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/pmcdoc/tagging-guidelines/article/style.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e178 e178" xml:id="PMC07"><textual class="po-textual">PMC Open Archive Interface, </textual><link class="po-inline e179 e179" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/about/oai.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/about/oai.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e180 e180" xml:id="PMC08"><textual class="po-textual">PMC Online StyleChecker, </textual><link class="po-inline e181 e181" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/utils/style_checker/stylechecker.cgi" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/utils/style_checker/stylechecker.cgi</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e182 e182" xml:id="PMC09"><textual class="po-textual">PMC Downloadable StyleChecker, </textual><link class="po-inline e183 e183" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/pmcdoc/tagging-guidelines/stylechecker/stylecheck-README.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/pmcdoc/tagging-guidelines/stylechecker/stylecheck-README.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e184 e184" xml:id="PMC10"><textual class="po-textual">PMC SGML Validator, </textual><link class="po-inline e185 e185" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/utils/validate/sgmlcheck.cgi" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/utils/validate/sgmlcheck.cgi</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e186 e186" xml:id="PMC11"><textual class="po-textual">PMC XML Validator, </textual><link class="po-inline e187 e187" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/utils/validate/xmlcheck.cgi" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/utils/validate/xmlcheck.cgi</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e188 e188" xml:id="PMC12"><textual class="po-textual">PMC Article Previewer, </textual><link class="po-inline e189 e189" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/utils/pv/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/utils/pv/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e190 e190" xml:id="NCBI01"><textual class="po-textual">My NCBI, </textual><link class="po-inline e191 e191" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/myncbi/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/myncbi/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e192 e192" xml:id="Beck02"><textual class="po-textual">Beck, Jeff. “How XML made the NIH "Policy on Enhancing Public Access to Archived Publications Resulting from NIH-Funded Research" possible.” In Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages 2005. </textual><link class="po-inline e193 e193" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://conferences.idealliance.org/extreme/html/2005/Beck01/EML2005Beck01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://conferences.idealliance.org/extreme/html/2005/Beck01/EML2005Beck01.html</textual></link></bibliomixed></bibliography></article></classedDocument>