<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">Metadata for Long Term Preservation of Product Data</textual></title><info class="po-record e2 e2"><confgroup class="po-record e3 e3"><conftitle class="po-field e4 e4"><textual class="po-textual">International Symposium on XML for the Long Haul:  Issues in the Long-term Preservation of XML</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">August 2, 2010</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e6 e6"><para class="po-block e7 e7"><textual class="po-textual">

Product data can be usefully defined as structured information about
objects that are produced by industrial and business processes. In
terms of information types, data formats, usage, and lifespan, product
data is both complex and diverse, encompassing 3D image
modeling information, dimensions, tolerances, and other model
annotations, supplementary material such as test analysis, videos,
datasets, and human-readable documentation. Although the metadata
issues in this problem space present some unique challenges, there are
valuable lessons to be learned from the library metadata and packaging
standards and how they relate to product metadata. Extending the
library standards to represent subsets of information from emerging
product lifecycle management standards could help tame the complexity
of long-term archival of product data.

      </textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e8 e8"><personname class="po-record e9 e9"><firstname class="po-field e10 e10"><textual class="po-textual">Joshua</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e11 e11"><textual class="po-textual">Lubell</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e12 e12"><para class="po-block e13 e13"><textual class="po-textual">

Josh Lubell uses information technology to solve manufacturing
engineering and e-business software interoperability problems. He is
particularly interested in long-term retention of digital data and was
awarded the Department of Commerce Silver Medal for his leadership in
developing ISO 10303-203:2008, a standard for representation and
exchange of computer-aided designs.

	</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e14 e14"><jobtitle class="po-field e15 e15"><textual class="po-textual">Computer Scientist</textual></jobtitle><orgname class="po-block e16 e16"><textual class="po-textual">National Institute of Standards and Technology</textual></orgname></affiliation><email class="po-field e17 e17"><textual class="po-textual">lubell@nist.gov</textual></email></author><legalnotice class="po-container e18 e18"><para class="po-block e19 e19"><textual class="po-textual">Official contribution of the National Institute of Standards and Technology; not subject to copyright in the United States.</textual></para></legalnotice><keywordset class="po-table e20 e20" role="author"><keyword class="po-field e21 e21"><textual class="po-textual">PDM</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e22 e22"><textual class="po-textual">PLM</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e23 e23"><textual class="po-textual">metadata</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">semantic technology</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e25 e25"><textual class="po-textual">RDF</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e26 e26"><textual class="po-textual">PLCS</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e27 e27"><textual class="po-textual">reference data</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">LOTAR</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e29 e29"><textual class="po-textual">STEP</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e30 e30"><textual class="po-textual">technical data package</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e31 e31"><textual class="po-textual">OAIS</textual></keyword><keyword class="po-field e32 e32"><textual class="po-textual">descriptive information</textual></keyword></keywordset></info><section class="po-hcontainer e33 e33" xml:id="sec-challenges"><title class="po-block e34 e34"><textual class="po-textual">Digital Product Data Archiving Challenges</textual></title><para class="po-block e35 e35"><textual class="po-textual">

ISO 10303 — also known as STEP (the Standard for the Exchange
of Product Model Data) — defines a </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e36 e36" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">product</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> as </textual><quote class="po-inline e37 e37"><textual class="po-textual">a thing or substance produced
by a natural or artificial process</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e38 e38" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">product data</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> as </textual><quote class="po-inline e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">a representation of
information about a product in a formal</textual><footnote class="po-popup e40 e40"><para class="po-block e41 e41"><textual class="po-textual">The authors of
STEP do not give an explicit definition for
</textual><quote class="po-inline e42 e42"><textual class="po-textual">formal.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> However, based on their usage of the word
throughout the standard, it seems </textual><quote class="po-inline e43 e43"><textual class="po-textual">formal</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> is intended to
mean unambiguous and adequate for specifying an
implementation.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> manner suitable for communication,
interpretation, or processing by human beings or by computers.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">
[</textual><xref class="po-milestone e44 e44" linkend="iso10303-1"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] Despite the breadth of what STEP
considers to be a product, product data is overwhelmingly used in
practice to mean structured information about things produced by
industrial or business processes.

    </textual></para><para class="po-block e45 e45"><textual class="po-textual">

Prior to the digital information age, product geometry was specified
using technical drawings on paper. These drawings were copied using
blueprint and other reproduction methods. [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e46 e46" linkend="blueprint"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] The drawings were often archived on microfiche, a
medium which can last as long as 100 or more years. [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e47 e47" linkend="microfiche"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] Nowadays many Computer Aided Design (CAD)
systems provide a means for engineers to specify product data through
annotated 3D digital models. Thus the de facto definition of a
product is no longer drawing-based, but rather is model-based.

</textual></para><para class="po-block e48 e48"><textual class="po-textual">

Product data is complex and diverse, both in terms of information
types and in terms of formats. Therefore, it is not surprising that useful
long-term archiving of product data is difficult. Some reasons why are as
follows:

</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e49 e49"><listitem class="po-container e50 e50"><para class="po-block e51 e51"><textual class="po-textual">

Engineers often want the digital models and systems they
build today to be extensible and reusable by subsequent generations of
technologists. This requirement presents a challenge as a digital product
model may have a longer lifespan than the data formats, application
software and computing platforms used to create the model.

    </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e52 e52"><para class="po-block e53 e53"><textual class="po-textual">

Archived digital product models should be semantically rich enough to
address long-term socio-technical concerns such as forensics (accident
and incident investigation) and environmental issues (carbon
footprint, disposal). For example, the former might require
representation of the rationale behind design decisions, while the
latter might require a product model highlighting any hazardous substances
needed to build a part.

    </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e54 e54"><para class="po-block e55 e55"><textual class="po-textual">

Although content information standards such as STEP are a critical
ingredient for long term archiving, not all relevant content
information can be made available using standards. Standards' representational capabilities sometimes
lag behind those of information models implemented in commercial software, as
vendors are constantly adding new enhancements to distinguish their
offerings from the competition. Thus content information may use a mix
of standard and proprietary formats.

    </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e56 e56"><para class="po-block e57 e57"><textual class="po-textual">

Data accuracy is required for product quality and
manufacturability. A small anomaly in an
engineering design can have great economic and social consequences
throughout a product’s lifecycle. The verification and validation of
engineering data requires complex computations.

    </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e58 e58"><para class="po-block e59 e59"><textual class="po-textual">

There are many different data types such as product models, geometry,
and simulation data such as finite element models. In addition, there may be
associated documentation, multimedia, and other information – leading
to a variety of different digital formats. Not only do all these data
types and formats need to be transparent, but the relationships
between the information units that are part of these data types must
also be made explicit. Digital formats can include neutral exchange
standards such as STEP, 3D visualization formats, office document
formats, and proprietary modeling formats.

    </textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></para><para class="po-block e60 e60"><textual class="po-textual">

Product Manufacturing Information (PMI) is a particularly critical
constituent of product data. Loosely defined, PMI can include any sort
of information defining a product’s components for manufacturing,
inspection and sustainment. PMI includes geometric dimensions and
tolerances (GD&amp;T) specified in a formal language whose syntax and
semantics are defined in several American Society of Mechanical
Engineers (ASME) and ISO standards. PMI is essential to product
data. Manufacturing cannot take place without it. Today's CAD systems
must support not only the ability to edit and display PMI, but also
must be able to feed GD&amp;T semantics to computer-aided
manufacturing (CAM) systems and other downstream applications. [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e61 e61" linkend="srinivasan"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]

  </textual></para><figure class="po-container e62 e62" xml:id="fig-bracket"><mediaobject class="po-container e63 e63"><imageobject class="po-container e64 e64"><imagedata class="po-meta e65 e65" fileref="../../../vol6/graphics/Lubell01/Lubell01-001.jpg" width="100%"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e66 e66"><para class="po-block e67 e67"><textual class="po-textual">3D visualization of a bracket part with PMI, displayed
	in Adobe Reader. </textual><footnote class="po-popup e68 e68"><para class="po-block e69 e69"><textual class="po-textual">

Mention of commercial products or services in this paper does not
imply approval or endorsement by NIST, nor does it imply that such
products or services are necessarily the best available for the
purpose.

</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
	</textual></para></caption></figure><para class="po-block e70 e70"><textual class="po-textual">

As an example of product data consider </textual><xref class="po-milestone e71 e71" linkend="fig-bracket"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">,
a screen shot of a 3D visualization of a bracket part created from a
digital 3D model developed with a CAD system.
There are several points worth mentioning about this example.

</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e72 e72"><listitem class="po-container e73 e73"><para class="po-block e74 e74"><textual class="po-textual">

The visualization can be rotated and otherwise manipulated to maximize
understanding by humans. However, it is not intended for exchange
between CAD systems. It
complements rather than replaces the original CAD model.

    </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e75 e75"><para class="po-block e76 e76"><textual class="po-textual">

The image has PMI callouts, using the standard syntax to specify
GD&amp;T annotations. Even though the visualization lacks the full
semantics of the original CAD model, it is helpful in
communicating how to manufacture the part — arguably more so
than an annotated 2D drawing would be.

    </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e77 e77"><para class="po-block e78 e78"><textual class="po-textual">

The callout at the top of the figure is unstructured text. This is
also part of the product data. In fact, product data can include
arbitrary attachments such as spreadsheets containing analysis
results, video data, and other associated information relevant to the
product. These attachments are important and need to be managed and monitored, even if CAD and CAM systems do not </textual><quote class="po-inline e79 e79"><textual class="po-textual">understand</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">
their data formats.

    </textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><textual class="po-textual">
</textual></para><para class="po-block e80 e80"><textual class="po-textual">

Manufacturers recognize the need for long-term archiving of digital
product data and the challenges associated with doing so. As a result,
industry-led standardization efforts are beginning to emerge. The most
prominent and farthest along of these is LOTAR (LOng Term ARchiving),
a suite of standards being developed by an international consortium of
aerospace companies. [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e81 e81" linkend="lotar"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] LOTAR's approach is
based upon the Open Archival Information System (OAIS) reference model
[</textual><xref class="po-milestone e82 e82" linkend="oais"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], a framework widely adopted by archivists and
preservationists. LOTAR favors the use of STEP in the archival
process while recognizing the reality that a mix of product data
archival formats must be supported.

    </textual></para><para class="po-block e83 e83"><textual class="po-textual">

Of course the need for archiving information is not unique to product
manufacturers, but in fact applies to many disciplines. For
instance, those of us working in archival of digital products can
learn much from librarians. They were among the first to embrace OAIS
and have implemented numerous tools and standards for digital archives
and repositories. In particular, they have long recognized the
importance of metadata. Metadata is an information retrieval system's
lifeblood. The choice and quality of metadata has a major impact not
only on delivery of data, but also on long-term preservation of that
data. [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e84 e84" linkend="gartner"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] Librarians understand this well and, in fact, have
standardized a multitude of metadata vocabularies, many of them based
on the Extensible Markup Language (XML). [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e85 e85" linkend="xml"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]

    </textual></para><para class="po-block e86 e86"><textual class="po-textual">

Similarly, this paper takes a metadata-centric approach to product data
archiving. The </textual><xref class="po-milestone e87 e87" linkend="sec-reqts"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> discusses metadata requirements
unique to long-term product data access and how these requirements fit
into the framework of OAIS. The </textual><xref class="po-milestone e88 e88" linkend="sec-meta"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> gives an
overview of digital library metadata vocabularies and contrasts them
with two metadata standards from the world of product data. The </textual><xref class="po-milestone e89 e89" linkend="sec-conclusion"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> provides some closing remarks and
suggestions for future work.

    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e90 e90" xml:id="sec-reqts"><title class="po-block e91 e91"><textual class="po-textual">Engineering-specific Metadata Requirements for Long-term
    Archiving</textual></title><para class="po-block e92 e92"><textual class="po-textual">

The linchpin of the OAIS reference model is the </textual><quote class="po-inline e93 e93"><textual class="po-textual">information
package,</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> an object containing content (e.g., product model
data) along with the metadata needed to adequately interpret,
preserve, maintain, and access the content. OAIS provides a taxonomy
of metadata types used with information packages. In this paper I
consider the three OAIS metadata types most widely implemented in XML:

</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e94 e94"><listitem class="po-container e95 e95"><para class="po-block e96 e96"><textual class="po-textual">Preservation Description Information (PDI): enables
    adequate preservation of content (includes chain of
    custody, identification, authentication, and contextual
    metadata)</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e97 e97"><para class="po-block e98 e98"><textual class="po-textual">Packaging Information: aggregates and identifies the
    constituents of an Information Package</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e99 e99"><para class="po-block e100 e100"><textual class="po-textual">Descriptive Information (DI): supports </textual><quote class="po-inline e101 e101"><textual class="po-textual">the
    search and retrieval of archived information</textual></quote></para></listitem></itemizedlist><textual class="po-textual">

Among these metadata types, DI (also called </textual><quote class="po-inline e102 e102"><textual class="po-textual">descriptive
metadata</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">) is most closely connected with enabling and
facilitating access to archived data. DI is more domain-sensitive than
PDI or packaging information in that a DI schema for product data is
likely to look very different from a DI schema for library holdings or
archived emails. Because DI is domain-sensitive, and enabling efficient access to archived product
data is so important, this section focuses on product model-specific DI
requirements.  The </textual><xref class="po-milestone e103 e103" linkend="sec-meta"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> discusses existing
metadata vocabularies for all three types.

    </textual></para><para class="po-block e104 e104"><textual class="po-textual">

In the following subsections I discuss in depth some factors that
determine descriptive product model metadata. I first present a
classification of types of engineering data archive access I call the
</textual><quote class="po-inline e105 e105"><textual class="po-textual">3Rs.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e106 e106" linkend="lubell"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] I then discuss the
multitude, complexity, and evolution of digital formats for product
model data. Finally, I discuss the mismatch between standards and
implementations. 

    </textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e107 e107" xml:id="sec-3r"><title class="po-block e108 e108"><textual class="po-textual">Product Models and the </textual><quote class="po-inline e109 e109"><textual class="po-textual">3Rs</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">: Reference,
      Reuse, and Rationale</textual></title><para class="po-block e110 e110"><textual class="po-textual">

A key challenge in long-term archiving is ensuring that information be
available in the best form for whatever access scenarios the future
might bring. This is particularly true for product data.
When validating engineering knowledge, it is crucial to be able to
replicate the intended behavior of a designed artifact. Successful
validation requires that the information be available in forms
sufficiently supporting retrieval and reuse. The need to know a
designer’s intent becomes important in the context of redesign and
reuse of existing parts. Another important aspect of engineering
archiving is the ability to store the digital objects at different
levels of granularity and abstractions as required by design
decision making tasks. Without the ability to compose different
digital objects for archiving, it would not be possible to maintain
the ability to encode rationale or reuse-based access needs.

    </textual></para><para class="po-block e111 e111"><textual class="po-textual">

I therefore consider end-user needs from the point of view of
reference, reuse, and rationale – the </textual><quote class="po-inline e112 e112"><textual class="po-textual">3Rs</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> – to better understand the
level of granularity and abstractions required in the definition of
digital objects. By </textual><quote class="po-inline e113 e113"><textual class="po-textual">end user,</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> I mean entities who are consumers of
OAIS information packages.

    </textual></para><para class="po-block e114 e114"><textual class="po-textual">

The 3Rs – reference, reuse, and rationale – define a set of access
capabilities for a designated community. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e115 e115" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Reference</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, the most elementary type of access,
is the ability to read the digital object and produce the digital
object for proper reproduction in a given display medium (computer
display, paper, etc.). </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e116 e116" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Reuse</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> is the
ability to refer to and modify the digital object in an appropriate
system environment (software and hardware). </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e117 e117" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Rationale</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> is the highest level of access in
which the end user should be able to refer, reuse, and explain the
decisions about the content of the digital object. The need to know a
designer’s intent becomes important in the context of redesign and
reuse of existing parts.

    </textual></para><para class="po-block e118 e118"><textual class="po-textual">

The primary driver for the 3Rs is the specific retrieval needs of each
of these scenarios. For example, a product data repository intended
primarily for reference may need to be organized differently than one
intended for reuse, where not only the geometric aspects of the
product are sought but also additional information regarding
manufacturing, performance requirements, assembly, and other aspects. In a
similar vein, rationale may require content being organized in a different manner to support the inclusion of requirements information along with
other performance data on the part or the assembly. Given the range of
uses and perspectives of the end users, their needs will have a large
impact on the process of archiving and retrieval.

    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e119 e119"><title class="po-block e120 e120"><textual class="po-textual">Variety of Formats</textual></title><para class="po-block e121 e121"><textual class="po-textual">

As discussed in the </textual><xref class="po-milestone e122 e122" linkend="sec-challenges"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, many formats are used to
represent product model data. Some are native to a specific software
application. Others are neutral with respect to software
applications. Some are proprietary. Others are open or
standards-based. The selection of the product model data format
depends upon factors such as the type of data defined in the product
model, design stage, and the availability of translators. Because an
archive must capture all of the data required to completely define the
product and associated processes, the archive may need a variety of
data formats, possibly causing redundancies. Good metadata is
essential for helping consumers evaluate the quality of data accessed
from the archive.

      </textual></para><para class="po-block e123 e123"><textual class="po-textual">

Native formats are typically binary, proprietary, and have a
specification not available to the general public. In spite of
long-term access concerns, archiving the native data is done as a
matter of course because it has such a small impact on resources and
because it is universally accepted as a good system management
practice. [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e124 e124" linkend="kassel"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] STEP provides an open alternative
to native formats for long-term retention of product
information. Because STEP is an international standard developed by
consensus, it is less subject to change than a proprietary format.

      </textual></para><para class="po-block e125 e125"><textual class="po-textual">

STEP application protocols (APs) specify information models for a
specific engineering domain. STEP physical files (informally known as
Part 21 files or STEP files) use an ASCII format defined in ISO
10303-21. [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e126 e126" linkend="iso10303-21"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] A STEP processor can be any
software application capable of interpreting and/or generating STEP
physical files, for example a computer-aided design (CAD) tool capable
of importing and exporting STEP files, or a visualization tool that
can import STEP data. The objects represented and exchanged using
STEP, as well as the associations between these objects, are defined
in schemas written in EXPRESS (ISO 10303-11) [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e127 e127" linkend="iso10303-11"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], a product data information modeling
language. Recognizing the popularity of XML as an implementation
method, the developers of STEP later standardized Part 28 [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e128 e128" linkend="iso10303-28"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], specifying an alternative representation of
STEP schemas and data using XML.

      </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e129 e129"><title class="po-block e130 e130"><textual class="po-textual">Mismatch Between Standards and Implementations</textual></title><para class="po-block e131 e131"><textual class="po-textual">

Although open non-proprietary standardized formats are desirable for
long-term data retention, even information represented using
standards-based methods is subject to format change. For example,
consider a long-term archival scenario from the domain of shipbuilding
[</textual><xref class="po-milestone e132 e132" linkend="kassel"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] attempting to maximize the use of STEP to
represent detail design product model data.

      </textual></para><para class="po-block e133 e133"><textual class="po-textual">

Although there are STEP APs that define information models well-tailored to the
ship domain, these APs have not yet been implemented in commercial
off-the-shelf software. Other APs such as AP203
(configuration controlled 3D design) and AP214 (core data for
automotive mechanical design processes) are supported by today’s CAD
software applications, but the information models of these APs cannot represent
some concepts specific to shipbuilding. So how might ship data be archived, given this
imperfect state of affairs? Initially, the data is created in a native
format, and the neutral file format is selected as a function of the
quality of the available translators. If the desired translators are
not available, a compromise is made in order to allow the data to be
accessible to the applications used during a specific design
phase where access to this neutrally represented data is required. The evolution from this point forward could be as follows.

      </textual></para><para class="po-block e134 e134"><textual class="po-textual">

First, geometry is exchanged using any means possible, but most
likely using AP214 or AP203. The non-graphical data can be extracted
separately and saved in a project-specific XML format. The XML often
contains only basic product structure, enabling minimal
exchange of geometric data, graphics, and basic properties. It also has the
greatest potential for minimizing the dependency on a particular CAD
vendor. 

      </textual></para><para class="po-block e135 e135"><textual class="po-textual">

A more desirable long-term solution would be for the product model
software supplier to implement AP239 (the Product Life Cycle Support (PLCS)
standard) [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e136 e136" linkend="plcs"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] to define product structure, the
relationships between objects, and reference data libraries to define
an extensible set of properties. The </textual><xref class="po-milestone e137 e137" linkend="sec-plm"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">
discusses PLCS in further detail.

      </textual></para><para class="po-block e138 e138"><textual class="po-textual">

Assuming future vendor support, the ideal long-term solution would be
to employ implementations of AP214 for general purpose geometry and
PLCS for configuration management and product structure. This approach would be further enhanced by defining application-specific product model data using APs with a more
specific scope, such as the shipbuilding APs.

      </textual></para><para class="po-block e139 e139"><textual class="po-textual">

In summary, even with a policy favoring STEP for representing product
information, the detail design data may manifest itself in many
different formats, each conforming to a different AP, or in some
cases not conforming to STEP at all. Over the life of the product,
format choices will evolve as a function of the product model
complexity, the quality of the translators, and the evolution of the
standard itself. Therefore, the goal of a single standard to represent
product model data may not be realistic, and we should be prepared to
encounter multiple formats over the lifecycle of a product.

      </textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e140 e140" xml:id="sec-meta"><title class="po-block e141 e141"><textual class="po-textual">Metadata Vocabularies in the Library and Product Data
    Worlds</textual></title><para class="po-block e142 e142"><textual class="po-textual">

So far I have discussed product data's diversity and complexity, the
importance of metadata in archival systems in general, and why
Descriptive Information (DI)
in particular is key to ensuring the long-term usability of product
data. Now I attempt to answer two questions:

</textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e143 e143"><listitem class="po-container e144 e144"><para class="po-block e145 e145"><textual class="po-textual">How should we go about defining metadata vocabularies needed for
    product data archival information systems?</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e146 e146"><para class="po-block e147 e147"><textual class="po-textual">Can the metadata vocabularies developed for digital
    libraries help?</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><textual class="po-textual">

    </textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e148 e148"><title class="po-block e149 e149"><textual class="po-textual">Digital Library Metadata Standards</textual></title><para class="po-block e150 e150"><textual class="po-textual">

I begin by addressing the second question, surveying some of the more
widely adopted XML-based metadata vocabularies for digital
libraries. The Metadata Encoding and Transmission Standard (METS)
[</textual><xref class="po-milestone e151 e151" linkend="mets"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] specifies an XML schema [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e152 e152" linkend="xsd"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] for encoding packaging information and is extensible
such that other vocabularies can be incorporated for encoding PDI and
DI. METS Profiles, detailed and unambiguous descriptions of classes of
METS instances, are used to document METS schema extensions and
customizations. The PREMIS (</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e153 e153" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Pre</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">servation </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e154 e154" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">M</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">etadata: </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e155 e155" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">I</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">mplementation </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e156 e156" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">S</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">trategies) data dictionary and XML schema
[</textual><xref class="po-milestone e157 e157" linkend="premis"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] define a vocabulary suitable for
representing PDI. METS and PREMIS are often combined to create a more expressive schema, though there are some inconsistencies and overlaps. [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e158 e158" linkend="guenther"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] Dublin Core (DC) [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e159 e159" linkend="dc"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] and the Metadata Object Description Schema (MODS)
[</textual><xref class="po-milestone e160 e160" linkend="mods"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] are both vocabularies for descriptive
metadata and are easy to integrate with METS. MODS offers more
precision than DC, but DC is more widely used. [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e161 e161" linkend="gartner"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]

    </textual></para><para class="po-block e162 e162"><textual class="po-textual">

An additional advantage of DC is that it is encoded using the Resource
Description Framework (RDF). [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e163 e163" linkend="rdf"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] RDF's simple,
modular data model facilitates extensions to DC. The wide variety of
software tools available for RDF can be used to edit, process, and
query DC metadata. Most important, it is easy to merge and harmonize
RDF metadata from heterogeneous sources. The importance of this last
benefit will become clearer later on in this paper.

    </textual></para><para class="po-block e164 e164"><textual class="po-textual">

Given the variety and widespread adoption of digital library metadata
vocabularies, it would seem that these vocabularies could be helpful
for encoding the packaging information, PDI, and DI needed for a
product data information package. But there is one big caveat, and
this is that the DI requirements for product data archives differ
significantly from those of digital libraries, as previously discussed
in the </textual><xref class="po-milestone e165 e165" linkend="sec-reqts"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">. Not surprisingly, product data-specific
distinctions such as the 3Rs, product model evolution, and changing
data formats are outside the scope of the digital library metadata
standards.

    </textual></para><para class="po-block e166 e166"><textual class="po-textual">

In the next subsections, I will try to answer the first
question by looking at two potential metadata sources unique to the
world of product data: technical data packages (TDPs) and product data
and lifecycle management (PDM/PLM) information. A TDP defines and aggregates the
information objects needed to support a specific activity in a
product's lifecycle, and is analogous to OAIS packaging
information. PDM/PLM information is highly detailed metadata used to
</textual><quote class="po-inline e167 e167"><textual class="po-textual">integrate people, data, processes, and business systems and
provide a product information backbone for companies and their
extended enterprise.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e168 e168" linkend="plm"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]

    </textual></para><figure class="po-container e169 e169" xml:id="fig-infopackage"><mediaobject class="po-container e170 e170"><imageobject class="po-container e171 e171"><imagedata class="po-meta e172 e172" fileref="../../../vol6/graphics/Lubell01/Lubell01-002.png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e173 e173"><para class="po-block e174 e174"><textual class="po-textual">Metadata sources for OAIS Information Packages in the
	digital library world versus the product data world.
	</textual></para></caption></figure><para class="po-block e175 e175"><textual class="po-textual">

But first let us review our discussion so far regarding OAIS and
metadata. As shown in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e176 e176" linkend="fig-infopackage"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, an OAIS
information package is a container bound via packaging information,
inside of which is content as well as PDI providing the administrative
metadata needed for long-term preservation of the content. DI is
domain-sensitive metadata used to facilitate information retrieval
from the archive.  XML metadata standards for digital libraries (shown
as hexagons) provide vocabularies for representing packaging
information, PDI, and DI. However, the digital library vocabularies
for DI do not address product data-specific retrieval concerns.

    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e177 e177"><title class="po-block e178 e178"><textual class="po-textual">Technical Data Packages</textual></title><para class="po-block e179 e179"><textual class="po-textual">

The United States Department of Defense defines a Technical Data Package (TDP) as follows in
MID-STD-31000 [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e180 e180" linkend="tdp"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]: </textual><blockquote class="po-container e181 e181"><para class="po-block e182 e182"><textual class="po-textual">A technical
description of an item adequate for supporting an acquisition
strategy, production, and engineering and logistics support. The
description defines the required design configuration or performance
requirements, and procedures required to ensure adequacy of item
performance. It consists of applicable technical data such as models,
drawings, associated lists, specifications, standards, performance
requirements, quality assurance provisions, software documentation and
packaging details.</textual></para></blockquote><textual class="po-textual"> As the MIL-STD-31000 options
selection worksheet in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e183 e183" linkend="fig-tdp"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> shows, a TDP provides
packaging and administrative information as well as some DI such as
whether the product model data is conceptual, a more detailed design,
or sufficient for manufacturing (e.g., box 1.A.).

      </textual></para><figure class="po-container e184 e184" xml:id="fig-tdp"><mediaobject class="po-container e185 e185"><imageobject class="po-container e186 e186"><imagedata class="po-meta e187 e187" fileref="../../../vol6/graphics/Lubell01/Lubell01-003.png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e188 e188"><para class="po-block e189 e189"><textual class="po-textual">Technical Data Package option selection worksheet from
	MIL-STD-31000.</textual></para></caption></figure><para class="po-block e190 e190"><textual class="po-textual">

The options selection worksheet and accompanying instructions in
MIL-STD-31000 imply a schema for TDP metadata. Instances of the
implicit schema can be thought of as contracts between various parties
in a product's lifecycle specifying the TDP contents needed for the
lifecycle activity. The TDP metadata and contents vary depending on
the activity, actors, and lifecycle stage. For example, consider a TDP
supporting procurement by an aircraft manufacturer of a jet engine
from a tier 1 supplier versus a TDP supporting maintenance of the
aircraft. The procurement TDP might require a 3D model (or
visualization) specifying PMI needed for the supplier to manufacture a
jet engine compatible with the aircraft design. The TDP supporting
maintenance, on the other hand, might require technical manuals and
troubleshooting documentation.

      </textual></para><para class="po-block e191 e191"><textual class="po-textual">

From an OAIS viewpoint, a TDP is an information package that may
contain any
content and metadata necessary for a product to be designed,
manufactured, purchased and/or maintained. Recalling </textual><xref class="po-milestone e192 e192" linkend="fig-infopackage"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, the library metadata standards
collectively can represent much of an information package's metadata. But can
these standards also represent TDP metadata? To answer this question,
consider the following four top-level elements of the METS
schema. </textual><code class="po-atom e193 e193"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;dmdSec&gt;</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> defines an information package's DI (represented with
embedded Dublin Core or MODS). </textual><code class="po-atom e194 e194"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;admSec&gt;</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> defines the information
package's PDI (with embedded PREMIS markup). </textual><code class="po-atom e195 e195"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;fileSec&gt;</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> specifies the
locations and grouping of files comprising the information
package. </textual><code class="po-atom e196 e196"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;structMap&gt;</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> defines the information package's lexical
structure and relates it to the files in </textual><code class="po-atom e197 e197"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;fileSec&gt;</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">.

    </textual></para><para class="po-block e198 e198"><textual class="po-textual">

Now consider the TDP option selection worksheet in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e199 e199" linkend="fig-tdp"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">. </textual><xref class="po-milestone e200 e200" linkend="table-mets-tdp"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> shows how the
numbered sections of the worksheet could map into the top-level METS
elements. The table is a first step toward demonstrating the
feasibility of using library standards to encode TDP metadata. As
mentioned in the </textual><xref class="po-milestone e201 e201" linkend="sec-reqts"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, DI is the most
domain-sensitive component of information package metadata. Looking at
the TDP metadata, it indeed seems to be true that the DI (e.g.,
TDP level, applicability of PMI standards) is more unique to product
data and more challenging to encode using library standards than the
non-DI metadata (e.g., CAGE codes, document numbers).

    </textual></para><table class="po-container e202 e202" xml:id="table-mets-tdp"><caption class="po-container e203 e203"><para class="po-block e204 e204"><textual class="po-textual">Possible mapping of TDP metadata to top-level
      METS elements.</textual></para></caption><thead class="po-container e205 e205"><tr class="po-table e206 e206"><td class="po-block e207 e207"><emphasis class="po-inline e208 e208" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">METS section</textual></emphasis></td><td class="po-block e209 e209"><emphasis class="po-inline e210 e210" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">TDP metadata</textual></emphasis></td></tr></thead><tbody class="po-table e211 e211"><tr class="po-table e212 e212"><td class="po-block e213 e213"><textual class="po-textual">Descriptive Metadata (</textual><code class="po-atom e214 e214"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;dmdSec&gt;</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">)</textual></td><td class="po-block e215 e215"><textual class="po-textual">TDP Level, Drawing Formats, Applicability of Standards</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e216 e216"><td class="po-block e217 e217"><textual class="po-textual">Administrative Metadata (</textual><code class="po-atom e218 e218"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;admSec&gt;</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">)</textual></td><td class="po-block e219 e219"><textual class="po-textual">Type and Format, CAGE Code</textual><footnote class="po-popup e220 e220"><para class="po-block e221 e221"><textual class="po-textual">A CAGE
	  (Commercial and Government Entity) code, as defined in
	  MIL-STD-31000, is a five character identifier assigned to
	  vendors doing business with the
	  Government.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> and Document Numbers</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e222 e222"><td class="po-block e223 e223"><textual class="po-textual">File Section (</textual><code class="po-atom e224 e224"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;fileSec&gt;</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">)</textual></td><td class="po-block e225 e225"><textual class="po-textual">[locations of required TDP elements and associated lists]</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e226 e226"><td class="po-block e227 e227"><textual class="po-textual">Structural Map (</textual><code class="po-atom e228 e228"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;structMap&gt;</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">)</textual></td><td class="po-block e229 e229"><textual class="po-textual">TDP Elements Required, Associated List</textual></td></tr></tbody></table><para class="po-block e230 e230"><textual class="po-textual">

Given the preceding discussion, it stands to reason that success using
the library standards approach to represent TDP metadata hinges on
being able to extend library DI standards (MODS or Dublin Core) such
that they can be used within a METS instance to specify TDP
descriptive metadata. Because Dublin Core is encoded in RDF and has
provisions for defining application profiles (context-specific
extensions to the basic DC metadata terms) [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e231 e231" linkend="dcap"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">],
it appears to be the strongest candidate for representing TDP DI.
Thus the discussion in this section suggests that using METS and
Dublin Core is a promising approach for
encoding a TDP in a manner interoperable with digital repository
frameworks and other software applications supporting library metadata
standards. By creating TDP-specific application profiles for METS and
Dublin Core, these standards can represent
the TDP metadata elements specified in MIL-STD-31000.

    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e232 e232" xml:id="sec-plm"><title class="po-block e233 e233"><textual class="po-textual">Product Data and Lifecycle Management</textual></title><para class="po-block e234 e234"><textual class="po-textual">

Product Data Management systems have evolved over the years from
simple file managers for engineering drawings into complex software
suites satisfying a wide variety of functions. Currently supported
capabilities include version control of product models,
management of design modifications, and management of engineering and
business processes. A thorough discussion of PDM systems would require
a paper all its own, and those who wish to learn more are encouraged
to read Srinivasan's chapter in </textual><quote class="po-inline e235 e235"><textual class="po-textual">Advanced Design and
Manufacturing Based on STEP</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e236 e236" linkend="srinivasan"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] for a detailed introduction to
PDM and PDM standards. Suffice it to say that the information used in
PDM systems is essentially product metadata. Because of the
complexities of product data, PDM systems must provide very rich
vocabularies for describing parts, people, resources, documents,
activities, and other entities involved in the design, manufacturing,
and support of products.

      </textual></para><para class="po-block e237 e237"><textual class="po-textual">

Since PDM is such an integral part of product development, STEP not
only supports the exchange of 3D product geometry and PMI but also
supports the exchange of PDM information as well. Ongoing growth of the
capabilities of PDM systems has resulted in the emergence of newer
standards that build upon the STEP information model for PDM. The
newest of these standards is the Product Lifecycle Support (PLCS)
suite of data exchange specifications [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e238 e238" linkend="plcs"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] from
the Organization for the Advancement of Structured Information
Standards (OASIS) and based on STEP AP239.

      </textual></para><para class="po-block e239 e239"><textual class="po-textual">

PLCS has a number of appealing characteristics as a source of DI for
product data: </textual><itemizedlist class="po-table e240 e240"><listitem class="po-container e241 e241"><para class="po-block e242 e242"><textual class="po-textual">

Its scope covers the entire product lifecycle, including later stages
such as maintenance and disposal. Therefore, PLCS can represent
product metadata for a wide variety of access scenarios spanning the
3Rs (discussed in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e243 e243" linkend="sec-3r"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">).

  </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e244 e244"><para class="po-block e245 e245"><textual class="po-textual">

PLCS embraces implementation technologies popular with software
developers such as XML and semantic technologies based on RDF.

  </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e246 e246"><para class="po-block e247 e247"><textual class="po-textual">

PLCS has a Reference Data Library (RDL), a managed collection of
classes and individuals defining an extensible controlled vocabulary
for representing business-specific concepts. The RDL is encoded in the
the Web Ontology Language (OWL) [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e248 e248" linkend="owl"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]. Because the
RDL is an OWL ontology, it can be browsed, queried, and processed
using the many software tools developed for the semantic web.

      </textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><textual class="po-textual">
      </textual></para><para class="po-block e249 e249"><textual class="po-textual">

</textual><xref class="po-milestone e250 e250" linkend="fig-rd"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> shows the reference data class representing a
CAGE code, its ancestors, and its siblings. PLCS models
</textual><code class="po-atom e251 e251"><textual class="po-textual">CAGE_code</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and its siblings (</textual><code class="po-atom e252 e252"><textual class="po-textual">DUNS_code</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and
</textual><code class="po-atom e253 e253"><textual class="po-textual">NCAGE_code</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">) as subclasses of
</textual><code class="po-atom e254 e254"><textual class="po-textual">Organization_identification_code</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, which is a subclass of
</textual><code class="po-atom e255 e255"><textual class="po-textual">Identification_code</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, which in turn is a subclass of
</textual><code class="po-atom e256 e256"><textual class="po-textual">Identifier_type</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">. To keep the size of the example
manageable, </textual><xref class="po-milestone e257 e257" linkend="fig-rd"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> hides the numerous siblings of
</textual><code class="po-atom e258 e258"><textual class="po-textual">Identification_code</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and of
</textual><code class="po-atom e259 e259"><textual class="po-textual">Identifier_type</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">. This example illustrates only a tiny
subset of PLCS. The standard RDL contains hundreds of classes and
covers a wide variety of PDM/PLM concepts such as assemblies,
bills of material, work breakdown structures, maintenance procedures
and more. And the RDL continues to grow as new PLCS data exchange
specifications get standardized.

      </textual></para><figure class="po-container e260 e260" xml:id="fig-rd"><mediaobject class="po-container e261 e261"><imageobject class="po-container e262 e262"><imagedata class="po-meta e263 e263" fileref="../../../vol6/graphics/Lubell01/Lubell01-004.png" width="100%"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e264 e264"><para class="po-block e265 e265"><textual class="po-textual">Portion of the PLCS RDL showing </textual><code class="po-atom e266 e266"><textual class="po-textual">CAGE_code</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, its
	  ancestors, and its siblings.
	  </textual></para></caption></figure><para class="po-block e267 e267"><textual class="po-textual">

The PLCS RDL provides a comprehensive and fine-grained source
of product metadata. But DI need only be sufficient for facilitating
access to an archival information system. Therefore DI should be
coarser-grained and less encompassing than PLCS. The good news is
that, thanks to the RDL being encoded in OWL — a language built
upon RDF — reference data subsets can easily be extracted and
combined with DI represented using Dublin Core. The challenge is
determining the subsets to extract. Analysis of access use cases
similar to those discussed in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e268 e268" linkend="sec-reqts"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> can guide the
selection of the RDL subsets. 

      </textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e269 e269" xml:id="sec-conclusion"><title class="po-block e270 e270"><textual class="po-textual">Summary and Moving Forward</textual></title><para class="po-block e271 e271"><textual class="po-textual">

In this paper, I explained why it is difficult to archive product data,
discussing requirements and challenges unique to engineering. Next, I
surveyed some of the more widely used metadata standards from the
digital library community and argued that, although they could be
useful in a product data archival system, they need augmentation in
order to represent product data Descriptive Information. I then
discussed two sources of product metadata — the options
selection worksheet for Technical Data Packages and the PLCS Reference
Data Library. While TDP metadata is of a top-down nature and maps well
to METS, the PLCS RDL is extremely detailed and is more
bottom-up. However, useful DI should be extractable from the RDL by
considering potential long-term access scenarios. This RDL subset 
can then serve to enrich the more generic Dublin Core metadata terms
standardized by Dublin Core Metadata Initiative. [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e272 e272" linkend="dcmi"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]

    </textual></para><para class="po-block e273 e273"><textual class="po-textual">

The next step is to test the effectiveness of these ideas by developing
a METS profile for TDPs and implementing a product data ingest and
access prototype. The prototype should support one or more access
scenarios, with the scenario's data requirements determining the subset to be
extracted from the RDL. The METS descriptive metadata (</textual><code class="po-atom e274 e274"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;dmdSec&gt;</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">) section
should contain RDF-encoded Dublin Core combined with the RDL subset,
using semantic technologies to merge and harmonize the 
information. If successful, the METS profile and prototype implementation
could benefit developers and implementers of product data archival standards.

    </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e275 e275"><title class="po-block e276 e276"><textual class="po-textual">Acknowledgments</textual></title><para class="po-block e277 e277"><textual class="po-textual">

I am grateful to Paul Witherell and Barbara Guttman for their
meticulous and helpful reviews of an earlier draft of this paper. Any
remaining mistakes are my sole responsibility. I also wish to thank my
colleagues in the NIST Design and Process Group for many
thought-provoking discussions about long-term archiving, information
modeling, and engineering design.

    </textual></para></section><bibliography class="po-hcontainer e278 e278"><title class="po-block e279 e279"><textual class="po-textual">References</textual></title><bibliomixed class="po-block e280 e280" xml:id="dcap" xreflabel="DCAP"><textual class="po-textual">K. Coyle and
T. Baker. </textual><quote class="po-inline e281 e281"><textual class="po-textual">Guidelines for Dublin Core Application
Profiles.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> DCMI Recommended Resource. 2009-05-18. 
</textual><link class="po-inline e282 e282" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://dublincore.org/documents/profile-guidelines</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.
</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e283 e283" xml:id="dc" xreflabel="DCMI"><textual class="po-textual">DCMI Home: Dublin Core
Metadata Initiative
(DCMI). </textual><link class="po-inline e284 e284" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://dublincore.org/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e285 e285" xml:id="dcmi" xreflabel="DCMI"><textual class="po-textual">Dublin Core Metadata
Initiative. DCMI Metadata Terms. DCMI
Recommendation. 2008-01-14. </textual><link class="po-inline e286 e286" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e287 e287" xml:id="gartner" xreflabel="Gartner"><quote class="po-inline e288 e288"><textual class="po-textual">Metadata for
digital libraries: state of the art and future directions.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">
JISC Technology and Standards Watch. April
2008. </textual><link class="po-inline e289 e289" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.jisc.ac.uk/techwatch</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e290 e290" xml:id="guenther" xreflabel="Guenther"><textual class="po-textual">R. Guenther, et
al. </textual><quote class="po-inline e291 e291"><textual class="po-textual">Guidelines for using PREMIS with METS for exchange.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">
Revised September 17, 2008. 
</textual><link class="po-inline e292 e292" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/guidelines-premismets.pdf</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.
</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e293 e293" xml:id="iso10303-1" xreflabel="ISO10303-1"><textual class="po-textual"> ISO
10303-1. Industrial automation systems and integration —
Product data representation and exchange — Part 1: Overview and
fundamental principles. First edition 1994-12-15.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e294 e294" xml:id="iso10303-11" xreflabel="ISO10303-11"><textual class="po-textual">ISO
10303-11:2004: Industrial automation systems and integration —
Product data representation and exchange — Part 11: Description
methods: The EXPRESS language reference manual.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e295 e295" xml:id="iso10303-21" xreflabel="ISO10303-21"><textual class="po-textual">ISO
10303-21:2002. Industrial automation systems and integration —
Product data representation and exchange — Part 21:
Implementation methods: Clear text encoding of the exchange
structure.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e296 e296" xml:id="iso10303-28" xreflabel="ISO10303-28"><textual class="po-textual">ISO
10303-28:2007. Industrial automation systems and integration —
Product data representation and exchange — Part 28:
Implementation methods: XML representations of EXPRESS schemas and
data, using XML schemas.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e297 e297" xml:id="oais" xreflabel="ISO14721"><textual class="po-textual"> ISO
14721:2003. Space data and information transfer systems — Open
archival information system — Reference model.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e298 e298" xml:id="kassel" xreflabel="Kassel"><textual class="po-textual">]B. Kassel,
P. David. </textual><quote class="po-inline e299 e299"><textual class="po-textual">Long Term Retention of Product Model Data.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> In
Proceedings of the 2006 SNAME Maritime Technology Conference and Ship
Production Symposium (Fort Lauderdale, Florida, October 10-13,
2006).</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e300 e300" xml:id="lotar" xreflabel="LOTAR"><textual class="po-textual">LOng Term ARchiving -
LOTAR
International. </textual><link class="po-inline e301 e301" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.lotar-international.org</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e302 e302" xml:id="lubell" xreflabel="Lubell"><textual class="po-textual">J. Lubell, S. Rachuri,
M. Mani, E. Subrahmanian. </textual><quote class="po-inline e303 e303"><textual class="po-textual">Sustaining Engineering Informatics:
Toward Methods and Metrics in Digital Curation.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> International
Journal of Digital Curation. Vol 3. No 2
(2008). </textual><link class="po-inline e304 e304" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.ijdc.net/index.php/ijdc/article/view/87</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.
</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e305 e305" xml:id="mets" xreflabel="METS"><textual class="po-textual">Metadata Encoding and
Transmission Standard (METS) Official Web
Site. </textual><link class="po-inline e306 e306" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.loc.gov/standards/mets/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e307 e307" xml:id="mods" xreflabel="MODS"><textual class="po-textual">Metadata Object
Description Schema: MODS (Library of
Congress). </textual><link class="po-inline e308 e308" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e309 e309" xml:id="owl" xreflabel="OWL"><textual class="po-textual">
World Wide Web Consortium. OWL 2 Web Ontology Language
Document Overview. W3C Recommendation 27 October
2009. </textual><link class="po-inline e310 e310" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.w3.org/TR/owl-overview</textual></link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e311 e311" xml:id="plcs" xreflabel="PLCS"><textual class="po-textual">Product Life Cycle Support
(PLCS). 
</textual><link class="po-inline e312 e312" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.plcs-resources.org</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.
</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e313 e313" xml:id="plm" xreflabel="PLM"><textual class="po-textual">
PLM Technology Guide. </textual><link class="po-inline e314 e314" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://plmtechnologyguide.com</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.
</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e315 e315" xml:id="premis" xreflabel="PREMIS"><textual class="po-textual">PREMIS: Preservation
Metadata Maintenance Activity (Library of
Congress). </textual><link class="po-inline e316 e316" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e317 e317" xml:id="rdf" xreflabel="RDF"><textual class="po-textual">
World Wide Web Consortium. RDF Primer. W3C Recommendation 10 February
2004. </textual><link class="po-inline e318 e318" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-primer</textual></link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e319 e319" xml:id="tdp" xreflabel="MID-STD-31000"><textual class="po-textual">U.S. Army. MIL-STD-31000. Defense Standard:
Technical Data Packages. Draft. 8 September 2009.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e320 e320" xml:id="srinivasan" xreflabel="Srinivasan"><textual class="po-textual">V.
Srinivasan. </textual><quote class="po-inline e321 e321"><textual class="po-textual">STEP in the Context of Product Data
Management.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> In </textual><quote class="po-inline e322 e322"><textual class="po-textual">Advanced Design and Manufacturing Based
on STEP.</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> Xun Xu and Andrew Y.C. Nee eds. Springer London. doi:
</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e323 doi e323"><textual class="po-textual">10.1007/978-1-84882-739-4</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">. 2009. Pages 353-381.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e324 e324" xml:id="blueprint" xreflabel="Wikipedia1"><textual class="po-textual">Blueprint -
Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia. 
</textual><link class="po-inline e325 e325" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blueprint</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e326 e326" xml:id="microfiche" xreflabel="Wikipedia2"><textual class="po-textual">Microform -
Wikipedia, the free
encyclopedia. </textual><link class="po-inline e327 e327" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microform</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e328 e328" xml:id="xml" xreflabel="XML"><textual class="po-textual">
World Wide Web Consortium. Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0 (Fifth
Edition). W3C Recommendation 26 November
2008. </textual><link class="po-inline e329 e329" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.w3.org/TR/xml/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e330 e330" xml:id="xsd" xreflabel="XSchema"><textual class="po-textual">
World Wide Web Consortium. XML Schema Part 0: Primer Second
Edition. W3C Recommendation 28 October
2004. </textual><link class="po-inline e331 e331" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-0/</textual></link></bibliomixed></bibliography></article></classedDocument>