<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">Opening up and closing down</textual></title><info class="po-record e2 e2"><confgroup class="po-record e3 e3"><conftitle class="po-field e4 e4"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">August 2 - 5, 2011</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e6 e6"><para class="po-block e7 e7"><textual class="po-textual">Negotiating tradeoffs of flexibility and reliability, freshness and
            permanence.</textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e8 e8"><personname class="po-record e9 e9"><firstname class="po-field e10 e10"><textual class="po-textual">C. M.</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e11 e11"><textual class="po-textual">Sperberg-McQueen</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e12 e12"><para class="po-block e13 e13"><textual class="po-textual">C. M. Sperberg-McQueen is a consultant specializing in
          preserving and providing access to cultural and scientific
          data. He has served as co-editor of the XML 1.0
          specification, the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e14 e14"><textual class="po-textual">Guidelines</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> of the
          Text Encoding Initiative, and the XML Schema Definition
          Language (XSD) 1.1 specification.  He holds a doctorate in
          comparative literature.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e15 e15"><orgname class="po-block e16 e16"><textual class="po-textual">Black Mesa Technologies</textual></orgname></affiliation></author></info><para class="po-block e17 e17"><textual class="po-textual">One of the reasons to come to a conference like this is to
  learn new things.  And as Tommie Usdin reminded us in the opening
  session [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e18 e18" linkend="Usdin"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], confrontation with other people
  and listening to things other people have done, including (or even
  especially including) things we don’t expect in advance to
  find especially interesting, can open our minds to new possibilities.
  And opening new possibilities is, in a way, how many of us presumably
    got here.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e19 e19"><para class="po-block e20 e20"><textual class="po-textual">This is a lightly revised transcription of my remarks at
	the closing of Balisage 2011; I have corrected a few errors,
	broken up a few leggy sentences, and deleted some side
	remarks, but otherwise left things as they are, even where the
	line of discussion could use a thorough reorganization.  I am
	grateful to Tonya Gaylord of Mulberry Technologies for
	preparing the transcript.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
  </textual></para><para class="po-block e21 e21"><textual class="po-textual">One reason to get interested in a new technology or a new
  programming language or a new markup language or a new kind of
  document language is that it opens up possibilities that you
  didn’t have before.  By looking at SGML and thinking about what
  SGML gave us, those of us who got interested in descriptive markup
  in the form of SGML learned about ways in which WordPerfect or
  WordStar or Waterloo Script or troff had been closing down
  possibilities for us — possibilities we hadn’t missed
  because we hadn’t thought about them, because the tool shapes the
  hand that wields it and the intellectual tool shapes the mind that
  uses it.  If your document description language is focused, as so
  many of them were and are, on putting ink on paper, then you’re
  going to think that document description and information management
  is about fonts and layout.  And it’s only when you get a language
  that says, “No, documents are about more than that.” (a
  language that ironically received much of its original impetus from
  typesetters, who know perfectly well that fonts can change in
  different renderings of the same document) — it’s only when
  you see that that you begin to think about other possibilities.  
  </textual></para><para class="po-block e22 e22"><textual class="po-textual">And that opening up of possibilities can easily give you the
    sense that you are seeing the dawn of a new day.</textual></para><para class="po-block e23 e23"><textual class="po-textual">That’s why some of us at least got interested in
    descriptive markup as opposed to WYSIWYG.  (As Brian Kernighan is
    quoted as saying, “The problem with ‘what you see is
    what you get’ is that what you see is all you get.”
    And when that’s all you’ve ever gotten, you may not miss the
    things that it doesn’t give you.)  That’s one of the reasons
    that other people got interested in XML as opposed to straight
    HTML. That’s one reason people get interested in multiple
    languages instead of a single language or, generalizing, in
    a metalanguage as opposed to an object language.</textual></para><para class="po-block e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">New technologies can open new possibilities.  So new specs
    defining new technologies are always interesting. In this context
    recall the papers we got from Cornelia Davis about the systematic
    application of new specs in the XML space (and some old specs in
    the XML space!) to make new things possible [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e25 e25" linkend="Davis"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], or Eric Freese’s report on EPUB3 [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e26 e26" linkend="Freese"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], or Piotr Bański’s application of
    the TEI ODD system to the ISO Linguistic Markup Framework [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e27 e27" linkend="Banski"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  All of these are showing us ways of opening
    up new possibilities.</textual></para><para class="po-block e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">Sometimes new views on existing specs can open up some
    surprising perspectives, as we found on Tuesday, when
    Hans-Jürgen Rennau reported on the work that he and David Lee
    had done on XDML [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e29 e29" linkend="Rennau"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  And sometimes we get
    new perspectives, new possibilities, from the collision of
    existing specs: think of Kurt Cagle talking about the collsion of
    XQuery and SparQL [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e30 e30" linkend="Cagle"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  In the other track
    about the same time, Julien Seinturier had some very interesting
    remarks about the different way that domain specialists — in
    his case, linguists — react to XQuery and SparQL [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e31 e31" linkend="Seinturier"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] that made me think about ways it might
    make sense to change what I teach when I teach XQuery.</textual></para><para class="po-block e32 e32"><textual class="po-textual">Sometimes the collision with other specs leads us to seek
    better ways of co-existence.  You know, sometimes you’d really
    like to conquer the world and get the other spec out of the way.
    (SGML did manage to displace ODA; that was a long hard struggle,
    but I haven’t heard anybody but SGML people mention ODA for a
    long, long time.)  But in the short term, XML is going to co-exist
    with JSON for quite a while, so I’m glad to see David Lee
    looking for a way to get back-and-forth without information loss
    and with at least reasonably plausible translation results so the
    product of the transformation doesn’t always sound like the
    output of a badly trained machine translation program [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e33 e33" linkend="Lee"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  Even within the XML community, XQuery and
    XSLT are going to co-exist for a while, so Evan Lenz’s ideas
    for hybridizing them may give us new perspectives for the future
    [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e34 e34" linkend="Lenz"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].</textual></para><para class="po-block e35 e35"><textual class="po-textual">People talk about turning over a new leaf.  It took me a long
    time to understand that idiom.  Eventually, I concluded that in
    its original sense it refers to a school boy who has spoiled one
    page by spilling too much ink turning over a new page, and now
    it’s a fresh new opening.  There’s nothing wrong with this
    new leaf; it’s full of possibility.  The French poet,
    Stéphane Mallarmé, talks about this.  He talks about
    the empty page whose blankness defends it.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e36 e36"><para class="po-block e37 e37"><quote class="po-inline e38 e38"><textual class="po-textual">le vide papier que la blancheur
          défend</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">; the words are from the poem
        </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e39 e39"><textual class="po-textual">Brise marine</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e40 e40"><textual class="po-textual">Sea
          breeze</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">), which is reprinted ubiquitously  [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e41 e41" linkend="Mallarme"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]; there are also numerous copies on the
        Web.
      </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> Why does the blankness </textual><quote class="po-inline e42 e42"><textual class="po-textual">defend</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> the page?
    Because the page is currently full of possibilities, and as soon
    as I write a word on it, I’ve spoiled an infinite number of
    them.  This thought can lead to paralysis, of course.</textual></para><para class="po-block e43 e43"><textual class="po-textual">Sometimes those of us who are predicting the dawn of a new day
    will also assume or predict that everyone is going to see the
    beauty of these possibilites, rejoice in them, and adopt this new
    technology.  And sometimes the rosy possibilities that we foresee
    will accrue only if everybody does adopt the new technology. Some
    of you will be thinking, along about now, about all of the
    rhetoric that we regularly hear — I associate it especially
    with the web application development community — about the
    advantages of network effects and the advantages of ubiquity.  I
    think the biologist Richard Dawkins</textual><footnote class="po-popup e44 e44"><para class="po-block e45 e45"><textual class="po-textual">With the invention of the concept of </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e46 e46"><textual class="po-textual">meme</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, in his book
          </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e47 e47"><textual class="po-textual">The Selfish Gene</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> has spawned
    (particularly in the IT community for some reason) a whole
    generation of intellectual social Darwinists who evaluate ideas
    exclusively in termes of how widely they spread, and not how how
    coherent or true they might be.  This is a sort of
    propagandists’ view of ideas, whose coarseness and
    naïveté would shame even the most outrageous of the
    19th century thinkers who invented that misapplication of
    biological theory to human ethics which is social
    Darwinism.</textual></para><para class="po-block e48 e48"><textual class="po-textual">So it’s nice to have some cases where advantages will
    accrue and new possibilities will open up regardless of whether
    anybody else sees them or adopts the new technology or not, where
    the advantages accrue for individuals and not just huge
    collectives.  It's nice because it frees us from the need to make
    technological choices based solely on our predictions about what
    other people are going to think is good technology; it allows us
    to evaluate the technology on its merits.  As technical people,
    most of us are likely to be better at evaluating the technical
    merits of technologies than at predicting the crowd psychology of
    marketplaces.  As Michael Kay said several times during this
    conference, “I really hate to try to make predictions about
    the future.  It’s very hard.” That’s true for all of
    us.</textual></para><para class="po-block e49 e49"><textual class="po-textual">I had occasion recently to
    reread the paper published by James Coombs, Allen Renear, and
    Steve DeRose in the November 1987 </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e50 e50" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Communications of the ACM</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">,</textual><footnote class="po-popup e51 e51"><para class="po-block e52 e52"><textual class="po-textual">ACM = Association for Computing Machinery.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> and I was struck that they say:
    
    </textual><blockquote class="po-container e53 e53"><para class="po-block e54 e54"><textual class="po-textual">We do not advocate waiting for SGML to become dominant.  As we
        have illustrated, [</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e55 e55"><textual class="po-textual">Aside: Only illustrated, not
          proven? Interesting, Dr. Renear.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">] descriptive
        markup is vastly superior to both presentational and procedural
        markup.  The superiority of descriptive markup is not dependent
        on its becoming a standard; instead, descriptive markup is the
        basis of the standard because of its inherent superiority over
      other forms of markup.</textual></para><para class="po-block e56 e56"><textual class="po-textual">Those of us who have converted to descriptive markup are
        already enjoying some of these outlined benefits. ... [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e57 e57" linkend="Coombs"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]</textual></para></blockquote><textual class="po-textual">  
  </textual></para><para class="po-block e58 e58"><textual class="po-textual">I think that’s true, and it’s useful to focus on the
    benefits you can get by adopting a technology even if the browser
    makers or the large community of web application developers never
    see it and never adopt it.  In that respect I’m particulary
    grateful to Eric van der Vlist for showing us how we can bring
    hypertext on the web forward into the 1960s</textual><footnote class="po-popup e59 e59"><para class="po-block e60 e60"><textual class="po-textual">This is a veiled reference to the way Bill Smith of Sun,
        then the chair of the W3C XLink working group, used to
        describe that group's goal.  Unfortunately, they did not
        achieve it.
      </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
 with multi-ended links
    that run in browsers today without requiring that we persuade the
    guys at Netscape or Opera or those other places [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e61 e61" linkend="Vlist01"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].</textual></para><para class="po-block e62 e62"><textual class="po-textual">On the other hand, as that quotation from Mallarmé
    illustrates, turning over a new leaf may open so many new
    possibilities that the experience becomes a little paralyzing.
    Working with metalanguages can make things so abstract it’s
    hard to find your way.  And working with standards or
    specifications that leave a lot freedom to their implementors and
    their uses can leave so many possibilities open that you wonder
    whether you gained anything at all by adopting the standard or
    using the specification.  When you’re using PDFs, at least
    there is a Big Daddy over there in San Jose that tells the world
    what PDFs mean, and it doesn’t matter how gnarly they get
    inside, because the only people who see the gnarliness inside a
    PDF file are the people who write PDF display software, and most
    of them work for Adobe and are very well paid, and the others will
    either do the same thing the Adobe browser does or they will be
    punished, and we don’t need to worry about it.</textual></para><para class="po-block e63 e63"><textual class="po-textual">XML, SGML, descriptive markup in general, takes away that
    comforting dependence on somebody else to decide what’s
    important and what counts.  It puts the responsibility on you, and
    that can be frightening.  Even when we do not find it frightening,
    it can be an onerous responsibility.  As a well-known critic of
    SGML (Darrell Raymond) once said, “Descriptive markup frees
    authors from the tyranny of typography only to plunge them
    headlong into the hellfire of ontology.”</textual><footnote class="po-popup e64 e64"><para class="po-block e65 e65"><textual class="po-textual">This pronouncement (cited from memory) appeared in an
        early draft of the paper ultimately published as </textual><xref class="po-milestone e66 e66" linkend="Raymond"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">; from
        a rhetorical point of viuew, it’s a bit of a shame that
        they took this sentence out before they actually published the
        paper, but perhaps they thought it was too inflammatory.
      </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
 </textual></para><para class="po-block e67 e67"><textual class="po-textual">You see traces of that difficulty in the problem that Norm
    Walsh talked about: the difficulty of finding an editor that end
    users will like that preserves the freedom that XML gives you
    [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e68 e68" linkend="Walsh"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  It’s a lot easier to write simple
    interfaces if the user doesn’t have that many possibilities.
    Sometimes freedom is bewildering and threatening.  The report by
    Ravit David and others, on their experience loading XML ebooks,
    illustrates those difficulties [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e69 e69" linkend="David"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  Jeff
    Beck’s report on the self-delusions you may fall into when
    you’re working in a closed system [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e70 e70" linkend="Beck"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] is
    also relevant here.  One of the sentences that people will
    remember from this conference is the observation “If XML is
    like a conversation, running a closed XML system is like listening
    to the voices in your head.”</textual></para><para class="po-block e71 e71"><textual class="po-textual">And, of course, when anything at all is possible, the person
    you’re listening to may be lying.  I bet most of you didn’t
    realize that Lynne Price’s game was part of the technical
    program. I didn’t either until I realized: it’s another
    instantiation of this problem. </textual><footnote class="po-popup e72 e72"><para class="po-block e73 e73"><textual class="po-textual">On the second day of Balisage 2011, Lynne Price organized
        a lunchtime </textual><quote class="po-inline e74 e74"><textual class="po-textual">entertainment</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> under the title
        </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e75 e75"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage bluff</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, in which improbable
        markup-related tales were told and the audience had to try to
        tell which were truth and which were fiction.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">  Infinite possibilities include infinite methods of
    deceit and threat.  And even if your interlocutors are not trying
    to deceive you, they may just be plain wrong, as Ken Sall mentioned
    this morning [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e76 e76" linkend="Sall"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  Did Jeff Beck really play
    on that record, and if so, was it this Jeff Beck or was it a
    different Jeff Beck?  Maybe I have always thought that Jeff was a
    great guitar player in his spare time — I only saw one side
    of him, as a markup geek at the National Library of Medicine,
    but in his secret life he was a rock star.
    [</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e77 e77"><textual class="po-textual">Laughter.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">]</textual></para><para class="po-block e78 e78"><textual class="po-textual">Sometimes, possibly for this reason — it seems related
    — the way forward seems to be not to open up more
    possibilities but to start closing possibilities down. That’s
    why many people thought then and think now that Scribe was a step
    forward vis-à-vis troff.  Why?  Because it cut off a whole
    lot of spaces, particularly spaces of bad typography and bad
    document structure, and put a very limited palette of
    possibilities in front of the user.  It’s one of the things
    that the designers of XML tried to accomplish with XML: to close
    off some of the possibilities of SGML.  Let’s not fool
    ourselves; there is a loss of flexibility in XML vis-à-vis
    SGML.  The design goal was to make that loss of flexibility
    involve the things you don’t care about and not the things you
    do care about.  So XML doesn’t reduce possibilities for the
    document owners or the vocabulary designers, only for the software
    developers.  There’s a trade-off: You have to think
    “Which is more valuable to you?  Having more conforming
    parsers than you can count on the fingers of a single hand (and
    more non-conforming parsers than you can count on fingers and
    toes, and possibly some fingers and toes of some friends)?  Or, on
    the other hand, the ability to use backslash rather than ampersand
    as a general entity reference opener?” On the whole, I’m
    happy to give up on a backslash as a general entity reference open
    delimiter in order to have more parsers.  So I’m happy with
    that trade-off.  And those of us who prefer to use SGML can still
    use SGML because it’s there; it’s a spec, and its
    implementations are not going away, although, as far as I know,
    most of them have not been updated recently.
    </textual><textual class="po-textual">
  </textual></para><para class="po-block e79 e79"><textual class="po-textual">That same simplification through reducing choices is probably
    responsible for the fact that many, many more people use TEI-Lite
    than full TEI.  You can’t use full TEI without making an awful
    lot of decisions.  Quite often they’re decisions that you
    don’t feel in a position to make upfront because until
    you’ve had some experience you don’t know whether you want
    that module or not.  Blind interchange similarly requires closing
    off possibilities and reducing variation. (We’ll come back to
    that.)  To write any text at all on the page — even a text
    as beautiful as the poem </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e80 e80" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Sea
      Breeze</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> — Mallarmé [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e81 e81" linkend="Mallarme"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] had to take a stand; he had to put something
    down on the page.  He had to shut out an infinite number of other
    possible texts in order to get the text he did write, and he had
    to risk an ink blot or two.  Similarly, growing up requires that
    you stop changing your mind about what you want to be when you
    grow up and start focusing; at least, that’s what I’ve been
    told by people who have grown up.</textual></para><para class="po-block e82 e82"><textual class="po-textual">Even at relatively low levels, regularity, predictability, and
    explicit structure can open up new possibilities.  The simple
    regularity of markup — the ability to distinguish markup
    from non-markup — allows Daniel Jettka and Maik
    Stührenberg to produce tools to do visualization of documents
    [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e83 e83" linkend="Jettka"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  You know, visualizing the structure of TeX
    documents or troff documents would be an NP-complete problem.  It
    would require artificial intelligence because you would
    essentially have to write a troff processor and then you’d have
    to do artificial intelligence to analyze the shape of the page to
    decide what the structure of the document was.  Having the
    structure explicitly marked allows Jettka and Stührenberg to
    draw trees without occupying the mainframe computer center for
    three weeks in order to document the structure of the first
    document they try, and then another three weeks to get the second
    one to compare with it.  Consider the paper of Jean-Yves
    Vion-Dury, in which he exploits the distinction between markup and
    content in order to encrypt them differently so that you can
    semi-trust people, semi-trusting your service vendors so they can
    perform operations without having to understand either the
    operations or your documents fully [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e84 e84" linkend="Vion-Dury"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  You couldn’t do that if you
    didn’t have a reliable guide to the structure that you’re
    exposing to them (or, in some cases, potentially hiding from them)
    independent of the content.  Or recall the work that Jacques
    Durand did in XTemp [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e85 e85" linkend="Durand"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]; I think that’s
    aided by
    the generality at one level and the utter predictability at
    another level of the message structure of the messages they have
    to deal with.</textual></para><para class="po-block e86 e86"><textual class="po-textual">Now, the difficulties of uncertainty and freedom, and the
    advantages of restriction — I’m tempted to say
    “voluntary slavery” — apply not just at the
    psychological level and not just at the application level (even at
    a very low level).  Why are Michael Kay and O’Neil Delpratt
    able to optimize certain things and not others [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e87 e87" linkend="Delpratt"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">]?  They are able to optimize those things
    which they can decide at compile time, and they cannot optimize
    things which cannot be determined until run time.  If they know,
    at compile time, that certain things are not going to happen at
    run time, then they can compile into byte code, and the stylesheet
    can run faster. Freedom leads to uncertainty, and uncertainty
    leads to doubt, and doubt leads to ... slower processing ... at
    many, many levels.</textual></para><para class="po-block e88 e88"><textual class="po-textual">Eliminating the possibilities that you don’t want to
    exercise can help in a lot of ways.  To inter-operate with other
    software, to make XML data more tractable for people who don’t
    have an XML mindset requires clean APIs — requires APIs like
    the one Liam Quin sketched, which try to make XML easier to write
    for people who don’t think in XML [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e89 e89" linkend="Quin"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  We
    may wish that they would just start using native XML programming
    languages like XQuery and XSLT, but historically they have
    perversely enough exercised their freedom not to do so. And rather
    than putting them in chains and forcing them, it’s probably a
    good idea to try to make things easy. Similarly, I’m happy to
    see the work on XML serialization into C# and Java Objects that
    Carlos Jaimez-Gonzalez described [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e90 e90" linkend="Jaimez-Gonzalez"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], or the packaging work that Chris
    Maloney described this morning [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e91 e91" linkend="Maloney"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  To
    make progress on certain tasks, including the development of
    applications, can just require that you put your head down and you
    make decisions and you put a stake in the ground and you risk an
    ink blot or two.</textual></para><para class="po-block e92 e92"><textual class="po-textual">Recall the work of Julien Seinturier on XML engines for
    multimodal linguistic annotations [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e93 e93" linkend="Seinturier"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">],
    or similarly, Alexander “Sasha” Schwarzman’s
    description of the work he and others have done dealing with all
    the complications of supplemental material for journal articles
    [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e94 e94" linkend="Schwarzman"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  Those case studies reflect one of
    the kinds of work we need to do in order to make XML realize some
    of the possibilities for our culture that we want it to realize,
    even though, of course, one of the first things you discover when
    you do that kind of work is that you’ve uncovered a whole lot
    of new problems you didn’t know you had before, including
    the perennial problem “Oh, this is really interesting, but
    who is actually going to pay for this additional work for the
    preservation of this additional material?” We now know
    it’s essential, but we haven’t necessarily found new
    income.</textual></para><para class="po-block e95 e95"><textual class="po-textual">I have seen the future, and it will require better
  documentation.</textual></para><para class="po-block e96 e96"><textual class="po-textual">That’s part of the cussedness of human beings.  Human
    beings can do things in a whole lot of different ways.  We can
    understand each other because out of the infinite number of
    possible human languages, there is only a finite number of human
    languages actually in use at any given time and an even smaller
    finite number that are typically used in a particular location. So
    if we address each other in 21st-century English or 21st-century
    French, here in Montréal, we’re likely to succeed fairly
    quickly in finding a language that our interlocutor understands.
    Fortunately, we can restrict our attention to 21st-century English
    and 21st-century French — We don’t have to experiment
    with Chaucerian English or Old High German or Gothic or Uyghur or
    historical versions of that very large number of attested
    languages. But if we want to preserve our information for the
    long-term, the recipients of that information in the long-term
    won’t have all of the context that we have that reduces the
    number of possibilities we have to try. So as David Dubin reminded
    us the other day [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e97 e97" linkend="Dubin"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">], we are going to have to document things a
    lot better than we might think.  It is precisely those things
    which are so obvious that we don’t think of them as needing
    documentation, the things that would be almost an insult to say
    explicitly (because it would make your interlocutor wonder whether
    you doubt their mental capacity) that may be most important to
    document.  So I’m glad that people like David Dubin or people
    like Daan Broeder and Andreas Witt and Oliver Schonefeld and their
    colleagues are working on long-term preservation [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e98 e98" linkend="Dubin"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">,
    </textual><xref class="po-milestone e99 e99" linkend="Broeder"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] and how to make it work, and trying to
    figure out how to elicit the documentation that we need and how to
    store it in ways that people in the future will have a fighting
    chance at understanding.</textual></para><para class="po-block e100 e100"><textual class="po-textual">Sometimes we may resist nailing things down because there’s
    the risk of getting it wrong; there is the risk of foreclosing
    possibilities that were really what we wanted.  And I’ll tell
    you a story I’m embarrassed about: Sometime late in the
    development of the XML 1.0 spec, Dan Connolly who was the W3C
    staff contact for the Working Group, said to me, “What is an
    XML document?  Of what set of objects is the set of XML documents
    a subset?” And I said, rather guardedly, “Why do you
    want to know?” I had worked enough with Dan that I was
    worried about a trap.  And he said, “It’s just a sort of
    intellectual hygiene; it’s part of the definition of any set.
    Modern set theory says if you want to make sure that it’s safe
    to apply the axioms and theorems of set theory, you have to define
    sets in certain ways to avoid well-known intellectual
    problems.” And I said, “You know, I really don’t
    think that we’re going to run into Russell’s Paradox if we
    don’t specify whether an XML document is a string of characters
    or an abstract structure of some kind, so no, I don’t want to
    go there.”</textual><footnote class="po-popup e101 e101"><para class="po-block e102 e102"><textual class="po-textual">Russell's Paradox arises whenever we assume that for any
        property we can describe, we can assume a set of things that
        have that property.  Some sets, Russell observed, have the
        property that they are members of themselves, others the
        property of not being members of themselves.  But consider the
        set of all sets which are not members of themselves — is
        it a member of itself or not?  If not, then it should be; if
        so, then it should not be.  Either way of deciding the
        question leads directly to a contradiction.
      </textual></para><para class="po-block e103 e103"><textual class="po-textual">
        Over the years, mathematicians have proposed a number of rules
        for the definition of sets whose primary motivation is to
        ensure that no analogue of Russell's Paradox can arise in the
        system so constrained; the rule mentioned by Dan Connolly is
        imposed by Zermelo-Fraenkel set theory, which is the most
        commonly used axiomatic system for set theory.  
      </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> I have no idea whether anybody else in the Working
    Group thought about this problem; Dan and I, I think, were talking
    offline, and I resisted because I did not want to nail down the
    nature of an XML document in a specific way because I foresaw that
    other people would use that to sort of close down other
    possibilities.  And the result has, of course, cost later working
    groups some indeterminate number of months or years</textual><footnote class="po-popup e104 e104"><para class="po-block e105 e105"><textual class="po-textual">If we count person-months, the number is way too high, so
        we’re talking about multiple person-years or person-decades
        of time.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">
    trying to patch problems in the formal underpinnings of their
    specifications.  Some XML specifications, for example, appeal to
    the notion of identity of XML elements — these two things,
    they may say, are the same if they are, or are derived from, the
    same XML element.  Sometimes, working group members are surprised
    to discover that their specification has a hole in its foundation
    as a result, since the XML spec doesn’t actually define
    identity criteria for XML documents or XML elements.  If identity
    is not defined for XML elements, you cannot appeal to identity of
    XML elements to determine the identity or non-identity of other
    things of interest to your specification.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e106 e106"><para class="po-block e107 e107"><textual class="po-textual">Sometimes, working group members are not only surprised,
        but are upset with me for pointing this out, even while they
        hotly deny that it is true.   Sometimes they also deny that it
        matters, even if it were true.
      </textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> And it’s my fault.</textual></para><para class="po-block e108 e108"><textual class="po-textual">It would be better to have nailed it down.  It would be better
  to have identified the possibilities I was trying to keep open and
  define each of them, so that we had terms with which we could talk
  about them.</textual></para><para class="po-block e109 e109"><textual class="po-textual">
    Trying to avoid nailing things down may be understandable when
    you’re trying to preserve possibilities, but trying to avoid
    clarity is not the right way.  So I’m grateful to Allen Renear
    and his colleagues, even though I disagree with them on the nature
    of the identifier </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e110 e110"><textual class="po-textual">I42</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. I’m grateful to
    them for asking the question “What is the logical form of a
    metadata record?” [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e111 e111" linkend="Renear"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">] It’s the right kind of question; it’s an
    essential kind of question that we need to ask. I’m grateful to
    Walter Perry for asking a related question [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e112 e112" linkend="Perry"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  It’s true that you may risk, when you
    talk about these things, having someone stand up and say,
    “I’m lost.”</textual><footnote class="po-popup e113 e113"><para class="po-block e114 e114"><textual class="po-textual">It should perhaps be mentioned, for the benefit of those
        who didn't attend the conference, that this did in fact happen
        to Walter Perry, who took it in stride.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> But we have to ask these questions; it will take us a
    while to find answers that we can successfully communicate to each
    other, but if we don’t ask the questions, we’re never going
    to get there.  And I’m grateful to Lars Johnsen and Claus
    Huitfeldt for the same reason; I don’t understand what those
    lattices they are talking about mean, but I now know there’s
    something I have to work on understanding [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e115 e115" linkend="Johnsen"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].</textual></para><para class="po-block e116 e116"><textual class="po-textual">But now we have a contradiction.  (Some of you will have
    noticed this some time ago, but it took me a while to get around
    to it.)  Now we have a contradiction because on the one hand we
    want openness and we want freedom and we want flexibility, but we
    notice that that sometimes leads to paralysis.  And on the other
    hand, we want to avoid closed-down options and foreclosure of
    possibilities and inflexibility and rigidity, but if we also want
    blind interchange and interoperability, that seems to be the way
    to get there.  How do we balance these competing interests?  Do we
    have to choose one and let the other one go to the dogs?  Can we
    trade them off somehow?  Do we have to choose whether to eat the
    cake today or save it for tomorrow?  </textual><textual class="po-textual"> Or can we have them both?
    And what I think of as the big theme of this conference is
    precisely the question: Can we have them both?  In his paper,
    Eliot Kimber explained the way DITA has striven to make the notion
    of architectural forms concrete and executable and managed to make
    DITA comprehensible in ways that I had ever managed to find it
    before [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e117 e117" linkend="Kimber"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  The DITA approach, as he
    described it, seems to provide a way to have a certain kind of
    freedom within constrained limits and provide precisely the
    constraints that you need in order to allow at least a certain
    level of quality in default processing — to have at least
    some of the advantages of both poles.  And if things work right
    and if you get the right set of primitive types, maybe the
    advantages you have over here that are preserved and the
    advantages you have over there that are preserved and not lost are
    the ones you care about, and the advantages that you’ve lost
    are the ones you didn’t care about, like changing your
    delimiters.</textual></para><para class="po-block e118 e118"><textual class="po-textual">Syd Bauman’s talk touched on that very topic of interchange
    and interoperability [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e119 e119" linkend="Bauman"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  Wendell Piez
    discussed ways to provide controlled extension points, not just in
    the schema and not just outside the schema: having them both
    seemed to suggest a way that we may be able to manage those
    difficult trade-offs [</textual><xref class="po-milestone e120 e120" linkend="Piez"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">].  I still don’t fully understand this, but the
    DITA mechanism that Eliot described and the local extensibility
    mechanisms that Wendell described feel to me similar at some deep
    level to the definition of forward processing in processor
    specs.</textual></para><para class="po-block e121 e121"><textual class="po-textual">Another anecdote: The XML Schema Working Group was aware that
    versioning was a terribly difficult problem, and we were
    desperately afraid of getting it wrong, so in XSD 1.0 we in fact
    said nothing.  The XSLT Working Group — the group that
    developed XSLT 1.0 — was also aware that it was important,
    and they were also afraid of getting it wrong, but they took a
    risk and defined a forward processing mode for XSLT 1.0
    processors.  And as Michael (Kay), or anybody who has actually
    worked with XSLT 1.0 processors in the presence of XSLT 2.0
    stylesheets, will tell you, they didn’t get it completely
    right, and the parts they did get right weren’t always
    correctly implemented, but ask yourself: “Which set of users
    is currently in a better situation in the presence of new
    constructs?  The users of XSD 1.0 or the users of XSLT 1.0?”
    I am in both sets, and I tell you I am a lot happier as an XSLT
    programmer than I am as a schema writer, because the one way to be
    absolutely sure of getting it entirely wrong is to say nothing in
    a misguided attempt to leave all of your options open.</textual></para><para class="po-block e122 e122"><textual class="po-textual">There comes a time for opening things up, and there is a time
  for closing things down.  One part of growing up is realizing that
  some problems don’t have a permanent solution, so the times
  for opening things up and the times for closing things down are
  likely to alternate, and you’ll have to decide what kind of
  time is this.  We’re not going to find any permanent
  solution to the problem of deciding which kinds of freedom we have
  to preserve and which kinds of voluntary slavery are worth entering
  into.  Those are questions that require human judgment.  One of the
  things we can do as technology people is to help make tools that
  will support that human judgment and allow humans to make human and
  humane judgments and not be consumed by clerical work.  To make
  those tools we are, from time to time, going to have to close down
  some possibilities, to keep things as simple as they can be (but
  remember security), to take a stand, to put a stake in the ground,
  to risk an ink blot, to work not just at a metalanguage level or the
  meta-metalanguage level or the meta-meta-metalanguage level, but
  — gasp! — at the object level, to write real documents
  and real vocabularies and to say relatively concrete things about
  relatively concrete entities.</textual></para><para class="po-block e123 e123"><textual class="po-textual">Right now it’s time to close down Balisage 2011 so you
  can all go home and do that work.  Soon enough it will be time for
  the pendulum to swing in the other direction, when what you will
  want to do is to think about the new things that you learned here
  that you haven’t thought before, to look at your problems
  from a new angle, to open up your mind again to new possibilities.
  I can think of a really good place to open up your mind to new
  possibilities, to do that kind of thing. So “So long!”
  and I look forward to seeing you in Montréal for Balisage
  2012.</textual></para><bibliography class="po-hcontainer e124 e124"><title class="po-block e125 e125"><textual class="po-textual">Bibliography</textual></title><bibliomixed class="po-block e126 e126" xml:id="Banski"><textual class="po-textual">Bański, Piotr. “</textual><link class="po-inline e127 e127" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Banski01/BalisageVol7-Banski01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Literate
  serialization of linguistic metamodels</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada,
  August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e128 e128" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e129 doi e129"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Banski01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e130 e130" xml:id="Bauman"><textual class="po-textual">Bauman, Syd. “</textual><link class="po-inline e131 e131" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Bauman01/BalisageVol7-Bauman01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Interchange
  vs. Interoperability</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at Balisage: The
  Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada, August 2 - 5,
  2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e132 e132" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup
  Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies,
  vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e133 doi e133"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Bauman01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e134 e134" xml:id="Beck"><textual class="po-textual">Beck, Jeff. “</textual><link class="po-inline e135 e135" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Beck01/BalisageVol7-Beck01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">The
  False Security of Closed XML Systems</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada,
  August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e136 e136" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e137 doi e137"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Beck01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e138 e138" xml:id="Broeder"><textual class="po-textual">Broeder, Daan, Oliver Schonefeld,
  Thorsten Trippel, Dieter Van Uytvanck and Andreas
  Witt. “</textual><link class="po-inline e139 e139" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Broeder01/BalisageVol7-Broeder01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">A
  pragmatic approach to XML interoperability — the Component
  Metadata Infrastructure (CMDI)</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada,
  August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e140 e140" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e141 doi e141"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Broeder01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e142 e142" xml:id="Cagle"><textual class="po-textual">Cagle, Kurt. “</textual><link class="po-inline e143 e143" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Cagle01/BalisageVol7-Cagle01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">When
  XQuery and SparQL Collide</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at Balisage: The
  Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada, August 2 - 5,
  2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e144 e144" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup
  Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies,
  vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e145 doi e145"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Cagle01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e146 e146" xml:id="Coombs"><textual class="po-textual">Coombs, James H., Allen H. Renear and
    Steven J. DeRose. “Markup systems and the future of
    scholarly text processing.” </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e147 e147" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Communications of the ACM</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> 1987 Nov;
    30(11):933-947. doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e148 doi e148"><textual class="po-textual">10.1145/32206.32209</textual></biblioid></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e149 e149" xml:id="David"><textual class="po-textual">David, Ravit H., Shahin Ezzat Sahebi,
  Bartek Kawula and Dileshni Jayasinghe. “</textual><link class="po-inline e150 e150" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/David01/BalisageVol7-David01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Challenges
  and Potential of Local Loading of XML Ebooks</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.”
  Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal,
  Canada, August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e151 e151" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e152 doi e152"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.David01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e153 e153" xml:id="Davis"><textual class="po-textual">Davis, Cornelia. “</textual><link class="po-inline e154 e154" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Davis01/BalisageVol7-Davis01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Programming
  Application Logic for RESTful Services Using XML
  Technologies</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at Balisage: The Markup
  Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada, August 2 - 5, 2011. In
  </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e155 e155" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference
  2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 7
  (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e156 doi e156"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Davis01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e157 e157" xml:id="Delpratt"><textual class="po-textual">Delpratt, O’Neil Davion, and
  Michael Kay. “</textual><link class="po-inline e158 e158" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Delpratt01/BalisageVol7-Delpratt01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">The
  Effects of Bytecode Generation in XSLT and XQuery</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.”
  Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal,
  Canada, August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e159 e159" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e160 doi e160"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Delpratt01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e161 e161" xml:id="Dubin"><textual class="po-textual">Dubin, David, Karen Wickett and Simone
  Sacchi. “</textual><link class="po-inline e162 e162" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Dubin01/BalisageVol7-Dubin01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Content,
  Format, and Interpretation</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at Balisage:
  The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada, August 2 - 5,
  2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e163 e163" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup
  Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies,
  vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e164 doi e164"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Dubin01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e165 e165" xml:id="Durand"><textual class="po-textual">Durand, Jacques, Hyunbo Cho, Dale
  Moberg and Jungyub Woo. “</textual><link class="po-inline e166 e166" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Durand01/BalisageVol7-Durand01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">XTemp:
  Event-driven Testing and Monitoring of Business processes:
  Leveraging XML, XPath and XSLT for a Practical Event
  Processing</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at Balisage: The Markup
  Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada, August 2 - 5, 2011. In
  </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e167 e167" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference
  2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 7
  (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e168 doi e168"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Durand01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e169 e169" xml:id="Freese"><textual class="po-textual">Freese, Eric. “</textual><link class="po-inline e170 e170" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Freese01/BalisageVol7-Freese01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Report
  from the Front: EPUB3</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at Balisage: The
  Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada, August 2 - 5,
  2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e171 e171" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup
  Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies,
  vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e172 doi e172"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Freese01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e173 e173" xml:id="Jaimez-Gonzalez"><textual class="po-textual">Jaimez-Gonzalez, Carlos R.,
  Simon M. Lucas and Erick J. Lopez-Ornelas. “</textual><link class="po-inline e174 e174" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Jaimez01/BalisageVol7-Jaimez01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Easy
  XML Serialization of C# and Java Objects</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented
  at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada,
  August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e175 e175" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e176 doi e176"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Jaimez01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e177 e177" xml:id="Jettka"><textual class="po-textual">Jettka, Daniel, and Maik
  Stührenberg. “</textual><link class="po-inline e178 e178" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Jettka01/BalisageVol7-Jettka01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Visualization
  of concurrent markup: From trees to graphs, from 2D to
  3D</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference
  2011, Montréal, Canada, August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e179 e179" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference
  2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 7
  (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e180 doi e180"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Jettka01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e181 e181" xml:id="Johnsen"><textual class="po-textual">Johnsen, Lars G, and Claus
  Huitfeldt. “</textual><link class="po-inline e182 e182" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Johnsen01/BalisageVol7-Johnsen01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">TagAl:
  A tag algebra for document markup</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada,
  August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e183 e183" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e184 doi e184"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Johnsen01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e185 e185" xml:id="Kimber"><textual class="po-textual">Kimber, Eliot. “</textual><link class="po-inline e186 e186" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Kimber01/BalisageVol7-Kimber01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">DITA
  Document Types: Enabling Blind Interchange Through Modular
  Vocabularies and Controlled Extension</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada,
  August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e187 e187" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e188 doi e188"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Kimber01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e189 e189" xml:id="Lee"><textual class="po-textual">Lee, David. “</textual><link class="po-inline e190 e190" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Lee01/BalisageVol7-Lee01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">JXON:
  an Architecture for Schema and Annotation Driven JSON/XML
  Bidirectional Transformations</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at Balisage:
  The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada, August 2 - 5,
  2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e191 e191" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup
  Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies,
  vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e192 doi e192"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Lee01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e193 e193" xml:id="Lenz"><textual class="po-textual">Lenz, Evan. “</textual><link class="po-inline e194 e194" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Lenz01/BalisageVol7-Lenz01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Carrot:
  An appetizing hybrid of XQuery and XSLT</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada,
  August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e195 e195" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e196 doi e196"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Lenz01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e197 e197" xml:id="Maloney"><textual class="po-textual">Maloney, Chris. “</textual><link class="po-inline e198 e198" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Maloney01/BalisageVol7-Maloney01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">JATSPack
  and JATSPAN, a packaging format and infrastructure for the NLM/NISO
  Journal Archiving Tag Suite (JATS)</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada,
  August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e199 e199" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e200 doi e200"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Maloney01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e201 e201" xml:id="Mallarme"><textual class="po-textual">Mallarmé, Stéphane. 
      “Brise marine”. 
      In
      </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e202 e202"><textual class="po-textual">Anthologie de la poésie
        française</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">,
      Nouvelle Édition suvie d'un post-scriptum,
      ed. Georges Pompidou
      (Paris: Hachette, 1961), p. 403.
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e203 e203" xml:id="Perry"><textual class="po-textual">Perry, Walter E. “</textual><link class="po-inline e204 e204" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Perry01/BalisageVol7-Perry01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">REST
  for document resource nodes: IPSA RE for the arcs</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.”
  Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal,
  Canada, August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e205 e205" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e206 doi e206"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Perry01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e207 e207" xml:id="Piez"><textual class="po-textual">Piez, Wendell. “</textual><link class="po-inline e208 e208" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Piez01/BalisageVol7-Piez01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Abstract
  generic microformats for coverage, comprehensiveness, and
  adaptability</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at Balisage: The Markup
  Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada, August 2 - 5, 2011. In
  </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e209 e209" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference
  2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 7
  (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e210 doi e210"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Piez01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e211 e211" xml:id="Quin"><textual class="po-textual">Quin, Liam. “</textual><link class="po-inline e212 e212" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Quin01/BalisageVol7-Quin01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">XML
  out — reducing clutter</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at Balisage:
  The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada, August 2 - 5,
  2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e213 e213" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup
  Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies,
  vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e214 doi e214"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Quin01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e215 e215" xml:id="Raymond"><textual class="po-textual">Raymond, Darrell, Frank Tompa, and
      Derick Wood. 
      “From Data Representation to Data Model: Meta-Semantic
      Issues in the Evolution of SGML.”
      </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e216 e216"><textual class="po-textual">Computer Standards &amp; Interfaces</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
      18 (1996):  25-36.
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e217 e217" xml:id="Sall"><textual class="po-textual">Reck, Ronald P., Kenneth B. Sall and
  Wendy A. Swanbeck. “</textual><link class="po-inline e218 e218" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Sall01/BalisageVol7-Sall01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Determining
  the Impact of Eric Clapton on Music Using RDF Graphs: Selected
  Challenges of Semantics Across and Within Datasets</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.”
  Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal,
  Canada, August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e219 e219" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e220 doi e220"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Sall01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e221 e221" xml:id="Renear"><textual class="po-textual">Renear, Allen H., Richard J. Urban and
  Karen M. Wickett. “</textual><link class="po-inline e222 e222" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Renear01/BalisageVol7-Renear01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Meditations
  on the logical form of a metadata record</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented
  at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada,
  August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e223 e223" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e224 doi e224"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Renear01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e225 e225" xml:id="Rennau"><textual class="po-textual">Rennau, Hans-Jürgen, and David
  Lee. “</textual><link class="po-inline e226 e226" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Rennau01/BalisageVol7-Rennau01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">XDML
  - an extensible markup language and processor for
  XDM</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference
  2011, Montréal, Canada, August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e227 e227" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference
  2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 7
  (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e228 doi e228"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Rennau01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e229 e229" xml:id="Schwarzman"><textual class="po-textual">Schwarzman,
  Alexander. “</textual><link class="po-inline e230 e230" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Schwarzman01/BalisageVol7-Schwarzman01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Supplemental
  materials to a journal article</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada,
  August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e231 e231" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e232 doi e232"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Schwarzman01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e233 e233" xml:id="Seinturier"><textual class="po-textual">Seinturier, Julien, Elisabeth
  Murisasco and Emmanuel Bruno. “</textual><link class="po-inline e234 e234" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Seinturier01/BalisageVol7-Seinturier01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">An
  XML engine to model and query multimodal concurrent linguistic
  annotations: Application to the OTIM Project</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.”
  Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal,
  Canada, August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e235 e235" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e236 doi e236"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Seinturier01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e237 e237" xml:id="Usdin"><textual class="po-textual">Usdin, B. Tommie. “</textual><link class="po-inline e238 e238" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Usdin01/BalisageVol7-Usdin01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Serendipity</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.”
  Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal,
  Canada, August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e239 e239" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e240 doi e240"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Usdin01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e241 e241" xml:id="Vlist01"><textual class="po-textual">van der Vlist, Eric. “</textual><link class="po-inline e242 e242" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Vlist01/BalisageVol7-Vlist01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">One
  Href is not Enough: We need n hrefs</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada,
  August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e243 e243" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e244 doi e244"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Vlist01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e245 e245" xml:id="Vion-Dury"><textual class="po-textual">Vion-Dury, Jean-Yves. “</textual><link class="po-inline e246 e246" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Vion-Dury01/BalisageVol7-Vion-Dury01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Secured
  Management of Online XML Document Services through Structure
  Preserving Asymmetric Encryption</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011, Montréal, Canada,
  August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e247 e247" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of
  Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on
  Markup Technologies, vol. 7 (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e248 doi e248"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Vion-Dury01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e249 e249" xml:id="Walsh"><textual class="po-textual">Walsh, Norman. “</textual><link class="po-inline e250 e250" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Walsh01/BalisageVol7-Walsh01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">What
  will it take to get (end user) XML editors that people will
  use</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.” Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference
  2011, Montréal, Canada, August 2 - 5, 2011. In </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e251 e251" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference
  2011</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 7
  (2011). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e252 doi e252"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Walsh01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed></bibliography></article></classedDocument>