<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">Agile Business Objects Management Application for Electronic Records Archive Transfer
    Process</textual></title><info class="po-record e2 e2"><confgroup class="po-record e3 e3"><conftitle class="po-field e4 e4"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">August 11 - 14, 2009</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e6 e6"><para class="po-block e7 e7"><textual class="po-textual">In order to continue to fulfill its mission in the information technology age, the
        National Archives and Records Administration (NARA) has made the decision to develop the
        Electronic Records Archives (ERA) system. One of the goals is to provide to the archivists a
        modernized system with automatic workflow that can streamline the digital archive business
        process.</textual></para><para class="po-block e8 e8"><textual class="po-textual">For an archival system, Ingest is one of the core components. As part of the ingest
        process, this component would allow the record Producer to negotiate submission agreement
        before transferring digital materials into the system. Within the framework of a
        service-oriented architecture with business process management, the ERA system uses XML to
        represent business objects and metadata. In this paper, we will show how the synergetic
        combination of XForms and Genericode makes the system agile and responsive to business user
        requirements. Furthermore, the approach fits well with ERA's design principle to use
        international and industry standards, and facilitates the integration of XML business
        objects and the electronic records metadata. We believe that the standard-based approach of
        XForms+Genericode exposed in this paper can be generalized to develop any e-Forms system
        with a set of control values and vocabularies. </textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e9 e9"><personname class="po-record e10 e10"><firstname class="po-field e11 e11"><textual class="po-textual">Quyen </textual></firstname><othername class="po-field e12 e12"><textual class="po-textual">L.</textual></othername><surname class="po-field e13 e13"><textual class="po-textual">Nguyen</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e14 e14"><para class="po-block e15 e15"><textual class="po-textual">Quyen Nguyen is currently working in the Systems Engineering Division of the ERA
          Program Management Office at the U.S. National Archives and Records Administration. Before
          joining the National Archives, he has worked for telecommunications software companies.
          His experience is in developing software systems for large scale deployment. He has a BS
          in Computer and Information Science and Applied Mathematics from the University of
          Delaware and a MS in Computer Science from the University of California at
          Berkeley.</textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e16 e16"><orgname class="po-block e17 e17"><textual class="po-textual">National Archives and Records Administration, Systems Engineering Division of ERA
          Program Management Office</textual></orgname></affiliation></author><author class="po-record e18 e18"><personname class="po-record e19 e19"><firstname class="po-field e20 e20"><textual class="po-textual">Betty </textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e21 e21"><textual class="po-textual">Harvey</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e22 e22"><para class="po-block e23 e23"><textual class="po-textual"> As President of Electronic Commerce Connection, Inc. since 1995, Ms. Harvey has led
          many federal government and commercial enterprises in planning and executing their
          migration to the use of structured information for their critical functions. Over the past
          14 years she has helped develop strategic XML solutions for her clients. Ms. Harvey has
          been instrumental in developing industry XML standards. Ms. Harvey is a member of OASIS
          Open and is currently an active participant in the Universal Business Language initiative.
          Previously she was a member of the Core Components subcommittee of the ebXML initiative.
          She is the co-author of "Professional ebXML Foundations" published by Wrox. Ms. Harvey
          founded the Washington, DC Area SGML/XML Users Group in 1995. She still coordinates the
          users group which is the longest standing XML users group. Ms. Harvey is also a member of
          "The XML Guild" and recently coauthored the book "Advanced XML Applications From the
          Experts at The XML Guild" published by Thomson. Currently, Ms. Harvey is working with the
          National Archives and Records Administration (NARA) on developing future system evolution
          for the Electronic Records Archive (ERA) system. </textual></para></personblurb><affiliation class="po-record e24 e24"><orgname class="po-block e25 e25"><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual><link class="po-inline e26 e26" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.eccnet.com" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">Electronic Commerce Connection, Inc.</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">
        </textual></orgname></affiliation></author><legalnotice class="po-container e27 e27"><para class="po-block e28 e28"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright © 2009 by the authors. Used with permission.</textual></para></legalnotice></info><section class="po-hcontainer e29 e29"><title class="po-block e30 e30"><textual class="po-textual">
      </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e31 e31" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Introduction</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></title><para class="po-block e32 e32"><textual class="po-textual">In response to the growing usage of information technology for conducting business by
      federal agencies, NARA has made the decision to build the ERA system. Its main goal is "to
      preserve electronic records independent of the hardware and software that created them" </textual><xref class="po-milestone e33 e33" linkend="r1"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">. For the ERA system to store, preserve, and provide access to electronic
      records, it has to cope with the following challenges</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e34 e34"><listitem class="po-container e35 e35"><para class="po-block e36 e36"><textual class="po-textual">Scope. As for the mandate, records will come from the entire federal
          government.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e37 e37"><para class="po-block e38 e38"><emphasis class="po-inline e39 e39" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Variety</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Since the federal government deals with
          different application domains, from health care, education, defense, space exploration,
          energy, environmental protection, etc., records will contain various types of knowledge.
          Moreover, their manifestation and representation may have different formats such as
          Microsoft Office documents, relational database files, or GIS artifacts. </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e40 e40"><para class="po-block e41 e41"><emphasis class="po-inline e42 e42" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Obsolescence</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Added to the variety of domain and
          format above is the constantly changing technology and application software that were used
          to create the records. By the time they are ingested into ERA, these applications will be
          most likely obsolete or belong to old versions of the software.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e43 e43"><para class="po-block e44 e44"><emphasis class="po-inline e45 e45" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Volume</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. It is estimated that the total volume of
          incoming records will be enormous, and will continue to grow over the years. Petabyte and
          exabyte range of data is not unimaginable.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e46 e46"><textual class="po-textual">In the face of these functional challenges, the ERA architecture will be designed in such
      a way to satisfy the following system qualities:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e47 e47"><listitem class="po-container e48 e48"><para class="po-block e49 e49"><emphasis class="po-inline e50 e50" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Extensibility</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. New record types, data types, and
          services could be added to the system without extensive redesign.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e51 e51"><para class="po-block e52 e52"><emphasis class="po-inline e53 e53" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Evolvability</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. New technologies in software and
          hardware could be inserted using standards APIs and interfaces.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e54 e54"><para class="po-block e55 e55"><emphasis class="po-inline e56 e56" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Scalability</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. The system must have the ability to
          adapt to the growth of record volume and user community.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e57 e57"><textual class="po-textual">Besides these qualities, the ERA system and its components have to be user-friendly,
      secure, and highly available to protect the assets and serve the public. </textual></para><para class="po-block e58 e58"><textual class="po-textual">This paper is organized as follows. In section 2, we will give an overview of the
      authority lists and the business objects that are used to manage and govern the archival
      system. Sections 3 and 4 discuss the benefits of XForms and Genericode in general as well as
      they are applied to ERA. Then, we describe our approach of combining </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e59 e59" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">XForms</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e60 e60" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Genericode</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, that fits into our
      overall system architecture. Implementation process with concrete examples is also reported.
      In section 6, we show how business objects contribute to the Archival Management Taxonomy that
      can help governing the content. We summarize our design approach in the conclusion. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e61 e61"><title class="po-block e62 e62"><textual class="po-textual">Archival Business Objects Management</textual></title><section class="po-hcontainer e63 e63"><title class="po-block e64 e64"><textual class="po-textual">Archival Business Objects</textual></title><para class="po-block e65 e65"><textual class="po-textual">Before the transfer of any set of records, the Producer (usually a government agency)
        has to submit two business documents, namely Record Schedule and Transfer Request to NARA.
        The Record Schedule contains instructions the general disposition and maintenance of various
        types of records, such as permanent versus temporary records, and the retention period. Over
        the lifecycle of the Record Schedules, Transfer Requests will be created for every physical
        transfer to specify:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e66 e66"><listitem class="po-container e67 e67"><para class="po-block e68 e68"><textual class="po-textual">Transfer mode with detailed information</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e69 e69"><para class="po-block e70 e70"><textual class="po-textual">Access restrictions.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e71 e71"><textual class="po-textual">Transfer mode can be electronic wiring or via physical media such as audio cassette,
        microfilm, CD, DVD, video cassette, parchment, or photographic print. Each business object
        goes through multiple business processes and negotiation of disposition between NARA and the
        producer before records are transferred from the contributing entity to NARA. Access
        restrictions may be applied to records that contain privacy data.</textual></para><para class="po-block e72 e72"><textual class="po-textual">Within the ERA system, Record Schedule, Transfer Request and other archival business
        objects (ABO) are implemented as e-Forms. Currently, ERA e-forms are encoded using JSP (Java
        Server Pages) pages One main advantage of e-Forms over traditional paper documents is that
        e-Forms facilitate deterministic processing by the system thanks to:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e73 e73"><listitem class="po-container e74 e74"><para class="po-block e75 e75"><textual class="po-textual">Elimination of free text form.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e76 e76"><para class="po-block e77 e77"><textual class="po-textual">Structured fields that conform to a pre-defined data model.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e78 e78"><para class="po-block e79 e79"><textual class="po-textual">System validation of input data. Such validation can be performed based on the data
            model with respect to data type specification, or required/optional
            characteristics.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e80 e80"><para class="po-block e81 e81"><textual class="po-textual">Elaborate validation based on embedded business rules during creating/editing
            business objects. For instance, fields may be dependent on each other, and only values
            from authority lists are allowed.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e82 e82"><textual class="po-textual">The ERA users manage these ABOs via the Archival Business Object Management Application
        defined by:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e83 e83"><listitem class="po-container e84 e84"><para class="po-block e85 e85"><textual class="po-textual">Functional requirements for CRUD (create, update and delete) operations on
            ABOs.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e86 e86"><para class="po-block e87 e87"><textual class="po-textual">Non-functional requirements of flexibility, extensibility, user-friendliness, open
            standards, performance and security.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e88 e88"><textual class="po-textual">With respect fo flexibility and extensibility, the design should allow adding or
        modifying a field to an ABO form to be done at low development cost. Moreover, changes to
        business rules that govern the forms or the fields within a form should be easily
        accomodated without requiring a lot of coding effort.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e89 e89"><title class="po-block e90 e90"><textual class="po-textual">Authority Lists</textual></title><para class="po-block e91 e91"><textual class="po-textual">Authority Lists, also known as code lists consist of values used to establish normalized
        values for certain key fields in a business object. The goal of Authority Lists is to
        institute a controlled vocabulary to be used in e-Forms and archival descriptions which is
        part of the NARA metadata. Examples of authority lists are:</textual></para><para class="po-block e92 e92"><textual class="po-textual">50 states with 2-letter abbreviations.</textual></para><table class="po-container e93 e93"><tbody class="po-table e94 e94"><tr class="po-table e95 e95"><td class="po-block e96 e96"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e97 e97"><textual class="po-textual">CA</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e98 e98"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e99 e99"><textual class="po-textual"> California </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e100 e100"><td class="po-block e101 e101"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e102 e102"><textual class="po-textual">MD</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e103 e103"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e104 e104"><textual class="po-textual"> Maryland </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e105 e105"><td class="po-block e106 e106"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e107 e107"><textual class="po-textual">VA</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e108 e108"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e109 e109"><textual class="po-textual"> Virginia </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e110 e110"><td class="po-block e111 e111"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e112 e112"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e113 e113"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e114 e114"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr></tbody></table><para class="po-block e115 e115"><textual class="po-textual">Federal agency names. </textual></para><table class="po-container e116 e116"><tbody class="po-table e117 e117"><tr class="po-table e118 e118"><td class="po-block e119 e119"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e120 e120"><textual class="po-textual"> NARA </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e121 e121"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e122 e122"><textual class="po-textual">National Archives and Records Administration</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e123 e123"><td class="po-block e124 e124"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e125 e125"><textual class="po-textual">USPTO</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e126 e126"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e127 e127"><textual class="po-textual"> United States Patent and Trademark Office</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e128 e128"><td class="po-block e129 e129"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e130 e130"><textual class="po-textual">NOAA</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e131 e131"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e132 e132"><textual class="po-textual">National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e133 e133"><td class="po-block e134 e134"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e135 e135"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e136 e136"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e137 e137"><textual class="po-textual">...</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr></tbody></table><para class="po-block e138 e138"><textual class="po-textual">On the access side, Authority Lists play an important role in building queries from
        various forms of search terms. For instance, with the use of Authority Lists, searching for
          </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e139 e139" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">NARA</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> is the same as </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e140 e140" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">National
          Archives and Records Administration</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Due to its importance and sometimes
        fluidity of the data, the ERA system is required to allow privileged business users the
        ability to manage the Authority Lists. Any update to the Authority Lists should take effect
        immediately and be made available to future creation and updates of business objects and
        forms. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e141 e141"><title class="po-block e142 e142"><textual class="po-textual">Functional Requirements</textual></title><para class="po-block e143 e143"><textual class="po-textual">Notably, the design for the application should exhibit low cost for development and
        maintenance. Moreover, since ERA is an Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) system with
        Business Process Management (BPM) and Enterprise Service Bus (ESB), such design should show
        an ease of integration with the workflow. The functional requirements for ABO can be
        summarized as follows:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e144 e144"><listitem class="po-container e145 e145"><para class="po-block e146 e146"><textual class="po-textual">Presentation. ABO should be viewed and browsed via W3C standard browsers. Moreover,
            the system should provide a friendly format rendering and printing capability of ABOs.
          </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e147 e147"><para class="po-block e148 e148"><textual class="po-textual">Management. CRUDVS (Create, Retrieve, Update, Delete, Versioning, Search) operations
            will be supported. The creation of ABOs can also be based on predefined and
            pre-configured templates.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e149 e149"><para class="po-block e150 e150"><textual class="po-textual">Workflow. According to the requirements, "The system shall provide the capability to
            integrate forms into workflows" </textual><xref class="po-milestone e151 e151" linkend="r18"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">. The system will implement a
            workflow for ABOs, which consists of a simple Draft-View-Approve cycle. In terms of
            governance, the ABOs will play an essential role in managing the lifecycle of electronic
            records to be ingested into the system. Therefore, the management of ABOs should be
            integrated with BPM and BPEL-based system orchestrations </textual><xref class="po-milestone e152 e152" linkend="r9"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">. </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e153 e153"><para class="po-block e154 e154"><textual class="po-textual">XML Format. In order to persist the ABOs for a long term and in a fashion that is
            independent of specific software and hardware environment, the ABOs will be stored as
            XML documents. </textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e155 e155"><textual class="po-textual">The following diagram depicts the components and services of the ABO Application from
        the SOA layer pattern perspective. The applications for Business Object Management, Business
        Object Review, and Business Object Approval can be linked together by a Business Process,
        which can be expressed in (Business Process Management Notation (BPMN) </textual><xref class="po-milestone e156 e156" linkend="r10"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">
        and executed by a BPM engine.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e157 e157"><mediaobject class="po-container e158 e158"><imageobject class="po-container e159 e159"><imagedata class="po-meta e160 e160" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Harvey01/Harvey01-001.jpg" format="jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e161 e161"><para class="po-block e162 e162"><textual class="po-textual">Archival Business Object Management</textual></para></caption></figure></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e163 e163"><title class="po-block e164 e164"><textual class="po-textual">XForms</textual></title><section class="po-hcontainer e165 e165"><title class="po-block e166 e166"><textual class="po-textual">Overview</textual></title><para class="po-block e167 e167"><textual class="po-textual">XForms </textual><xref class="po-milestone e168 e168" linkend="r2"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> is a W3C specification for implementing an XML-based Web
        forms. In some sense, XForms can be viewed as a next-generation of HTML Forms. While HTML
        Forms is a mix of markup for presentation and form data. XForms takes the approach of
        separating data from presentation. Data in XForms can conform to an XML schema which makes
        data validation against the schema pretty straightforward. For Ajax server-side XForms </textual><xref class="po-milestone e169 e169" linkend="r4"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, real-time validation would provide immediate feedback in case of error in
        user input. Therefore, the user doesn't have to finish a lengthy form to know that an error
        has occurred. Note that in the case of an ABO, a form may span more than one scrolled page.
        Unlike the HTML form, the output of an XForms is an XML instance ready to be stored in an
        XML-aware repository. On the other hand, XForms has constructs to control user input events;
        but, these controls are not dependent on the particular presentation modality. Therefore, it
        is possible to create a form that will take input from various input devices, such as
        keyboard and voice. In the paper </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e170 e170" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Multimodal Interaction with
          XForms</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
        </textual><xref class="po-milestone e171 e171" linkend="r6"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e172 e172" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Mikko Honkala et al.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> proposed XForms
        Multi-modality (XFormsMM) to facilitate concurrent support of multiple modalities using
        XForms. The XFormsMM architecture comprises of the following components:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e173 e173"><listitem class="po-container e174 e174"><para class="po-block e175 e175"><textual class="po-textual">Separate abstract user interface (UI) controls from modality specific elements such
            as style sheets</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e176 e176"><para class="po-block e177 e177"><textual class="po-textual">Interaction manager to switch and coordinate different modalities</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e178 e178"><para class="po-block e179 e179"><textual class="po-textual">Set of modality renderers for CSS style sheets</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e180 e180"><textual class="po-textual">The application of the multi-modality is to enable a web form to support various UI
        devices such as desktop, wireless handset, IVR applications, etc. In the case of our
        application, this interesting feature might be exploited to develop user interface providing
        access to all users, impaired and non-impaired.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e181 e181"><title class="po-block e182 e182"><textual class="po-textual">Advantages</textual></title><para class="po-block e183 e183"><textual class="po-textual">The advantages of XForms have been identified in the literature and past conferences
          </textual><xref class="po-milestone e184 e184" linkend="r4"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">
        </textual><xref class="po-milestone e185 e185" linkend="r5"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e186 e186"><listitem class="po-container e187 e187"><para class="po-block e188 e188"><emphasis class="po-inline e189 e189" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Data integrity</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Since XForms is associated with an
            XML schema, data integrity is preserved due to the compliance of the forms with data
            constraints specified by the schema.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e190 e190"><para class="po-block e191 e191"><emphasis class="po-inline e192 e192" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Data exchange</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. The output of an XForms is an XML
            document itself, which can readily carry data between SOA components and services. In
            the case of WSDL (Web Services Description Language), the data will be embedded in SOAP
            messages. If RESTful Web services are used, then the URL will contain the reference to
            the XML instance.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e193 e193"><para class="po-block e194 e194"><emphasis class="po-inline e195 e195" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Performance</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Response time and user experience are
            greatly enhanced as latency is reduced thanks to Ajax-based implementations.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e196 e196"><para class="po-block e197 e197"><emphasis class="po-inline e198 e198" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Consistency</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. XForms specifies a construct to handle
            XML errors, thus facilitates uniform and consistent error handling and error
            messages.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e199 e199"><para class="po-block e200 e200"><emphasis class="po-inline e201 e201" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Modularity </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">and reuse. An XForms document can be
            composed of sections. Consequently, parallel development can be planned and organized.
            Building up a library of reusable XForms sections will therefore be possible. For
            example, in the case of ABO, we have a section for Personal Contact, and another one for
            Organization Information. Moreover, XForms constructs to control user input events will
            definitely save development time and cost.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e202 e202"><para class="po-block e203 e203"><emphasis class="po-inline e204 e204" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Low-cost</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> system requirement. Server-side XForms
            processing does not impose any requirements on end-user browsers. Note that ABO Forms
            are to be used by NARA archivists and agencies' record managers, and we don't want to
            levy any configuration requirements for using the application.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e205 e205"><para class="po-block e206 e206"><emphasis class="po-inline e207 e207" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Standard support</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Being based on XML itself, XForms
            can be easily integrated with other XML-related open standards such as XML Schema, XSLT,
            XSL-FO, XHTML, XPath, and XQuery. </textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e208 e208"><title class="po-block e209 e209"><textual class="po-textual">Genericode</textual></title><section class="po-hcontainer e210 e210"><title class="po-block e211 e211"><textual class="po-textual">Overview</textual></title><para class="po-block e212 e212"><textual class="po-textual">Genericode </textual><xref class="po-milestone e213 e213" linkend="r3"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> defines a standardized model to manage code lists using
        a defined XML schema. Essentially, the idea is for a code to have a code key, and multiple
        code values. Every XML project has controlled lists that need to be supported in the XML
        application. There are two schools of thought for controlling code lists. The Universal
        Business Language (UBL) </textual><xref class="po-milestone e214 e214" linkend="r19"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> is an OASIS-Open standards effort to describe
        business documents, e.g. invoice, purchase orders, etc. in XML. In version 1.0 of the
        standard, all the code lists for codes such as country codes, currency codes, etc. were
        embedded in the XML schemas. As individual countries started adopting UBL, it became
        apparent that placing large code sets in the schemas was a problematic approach. Some of the
        codes change rapidly and during implementation this required modification of the "standard"
        schemas which theoretically meant they were no longer UBL compliant. The definition of the
        codes were in the documentation portion of schema and not readily available to the
        application. Modifying schema to support changing codes became a configuration problem. </textual></para><para class="po-block e215 e215"><textual class="po-textual">Members of the UBL technical committee developed the Genericode concept and it was
        adopted by UBL and other organizations. Genericode has now its own OASIS-Open technical
          committee</textual><xref class="po-milestone e216 e216" linkend="r20"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> , and is currently at version 1.0.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e217 e217"><title class="po-block e218 e218"><textual class="po-textual">Why is Genericode Valuable to NARA Enterprise</textual></title><para class="po-block e219 e219"><textual class="po-textual">Besides the codes that are located in the business objects and metadata descriptions of
        records, NARA receives records from agencies in the U.S. Federal government, as well as some
        private collections. Every record set has its own set of codes. The codes themselves can
        have the same meaning but different codes across multiple records. For example, if we look
        at the records of ship manifests from the Irish Potato Famine, a code as simple as the age
        of the person can have several codes representing the age and/or event depending on
        individual ship manifests. </textual></para><para class="po-block e220 e220"><textual class="po-textual">The logical expectation is that a person"s age is pretty straightforward. However
        looking at the table below, which contains actual values of codes from the passenger list
        maintained by NARA </textual><xref class="po-milestone e221 e221" linkend="r21"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> it is readily apparent and a person"s age in a
        record isn't as cut and dry as some would expect. For example you wouldn't expect to see a
        value of 900 to represent a person's age.</textual></para><table class="po-container e222 e222" xml:id="table1"><caption class="po-container e223 e223"><para class="po-block e224 e224"><textual class="po-textual">Typical Codelist Representation in NARA Records</textual></para></caption><tbody class="po-table e225 e225"><tr class="po-table e226 e226"><td class="po-block e227 e227"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e228 e228"><textual class="po-textual">
                </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e229 e229" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Code</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e230 e230"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e231 e231"><textual class="po-textual">
                </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e232 e232" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Meaning</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e233 e233"><td class="po-block e234 e234"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e235 e235"><textual class="po-textual">900 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e236 e236"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e237 e237"><textual class="po-textual">Born at Sea </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e238 e238"><td class="po-block e239 e239"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e240 e240"><textual class="po-textual">901 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e241 e241"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e242 e242"><textual class="po-textual">Infant in months: 01 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e243 e243"><td class="po-block e244 e244"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e245 e245"><textual class="po-textual">909 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e246 e246"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e247 e247"><textual class="po-textual">Infant in months: 09 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e248 e248"><td class="po-block e249 e249"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e250 e250"><textual class="po-textual">800 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e251 e251"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e252 e252"><textual class="po-textual"> Unknown </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e253 e253"><td class="po-block e254 e254"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e255 e255"><textual class="po-textual">1 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e256 e256"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e257 e257"><textual class="po-textual">age 01 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e258 e258"><td class="po-block e259 e259"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e260 e260"><textual class="po-textual">001 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e261 e261"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e262 e262"><textual class="po-textual">age 01 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e263 e263"><td class="po-block e264 e264"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e265 e265"><textual class="po-textual">2 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e266 e266"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e267 e267"><textual class="po-textual">age 02 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e268 e268"><td class="po-block e269 e269"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e270 e270"><textual class="po-textual">002 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e271 e271"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e272 e272"><textual class="po-textual">age02</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e273 e273"><td class="po-block e274 e274"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e275 e275"><textual class="po-textual">003 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e276 e276"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e277 e277"><textual class="po-textual">age 03 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e278 e278"><td class="po-block e279 e279"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e280 e280"><textual class="po-textual">3 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e281 e281"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e282 e282"><textual class="po-textual">age 03 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e283 e283"><td class="po-block e284 e284"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e285 e285"><textual class="po-textual">03 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e286 e286"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e287 e287"><textual class="po-textual">age 03</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr></tbody></table><para class="po-block e288 e288"><textual class="po-textual">The table below shows a representation of how the Genericode is organized. The advantage
        of the Genericode approach is that multiple codes can represent a single concept.</textual></para><table class="po-container e289 e289" xml:id="table2"><caption class="po-container e290 e290"><para class="po-block e291 e291"><textual class="po-textual">Genericode Table Representation</textual></para></caption><tbody class="po-table e292 e292"><tr class="po-table e293 e293"><td class="po-block e294 e294"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e295 e295"><textual class="po-textual">
                </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e296 e296" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">Meaning</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e297 e297"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e298 e298"><textual class="po-textual">
                </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e299 e299"><textual class="po-textual">Ship1</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e300 e300"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e301 e301"><textual class="po-textual">
                </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e302 e302"><textual class="po-textual">Ship2</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e303 e303"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e304 e304"><textual class="po-textual">
                </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e305 e305"><textual class="po-textual">Ship3</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e306 e306"><td class="po-block e307 e307"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e308 e308"><textual class="po-textual">Born at Sea </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e309 e309"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e310 e310"><textual class="po-textual">900</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e311 e311"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e312 e312"><textual class="po-textual">888</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e313 e313"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e314 e314"><textual class="po-textual">766</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e315 e315"><td class="po-block e316 e316"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e317 e317"><textual class="po-textual">Infant in months: 01 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e318 e318"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e319 e319"><textual class="po-textual">901</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e320 e320"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e321 e321"><textual class="po-textual">.1</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e322 e322"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e323 e323"><textual class="po-textual">500</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e324 e324"><td class="po-block e325 e325"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e326 e326"><textual class="po-textual">Infant in months: 09 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e327 e327"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e328 e328"><textual class="po-textual">909</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e329 e329"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e330 e330"><textual class="po-textual">909</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e331 e331"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e332 e332"><textual class="po-textual">909</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e333 e333"><td class="po-block e334 e334"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e335 e335"><textual class="po-textual"> Unknown </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e336 e336"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e337 e337"><textual class="po-textual">800</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e338 e338"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e339 e339"><textual class="po-textual">800</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e340 e340"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e341 e341"><textual class="po-textual">800</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e342 e342"><td class="po-block e343 e343"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e344 e344"><textual class="po-textual">age 01 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e345 e345"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e346 e346"><textual class="po-textual">1</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e347 e347"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e348 e348"><textual class="po-textual">001</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e349 e349"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e350 e350"><textual class="po-textual">1</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e351 e351"><td class="po-block e352 e352"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e353 e353"><textual class="po-textual">age 02 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e354 e354"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e355 e355"><textual class="po-textual">2</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e356 e356"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e357 e357"><textual class="po-textual">002</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e358 e358"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e359 e359"><textual class="po-textual">002</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e360 e360"><td class="po-block e361 e361"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e362 e362"><textual class="po-textual">age 03 </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e363 e363"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e364 e364"><textual class="po-textual">3</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e365 e365"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e366 e366"><textual class="po-textual">003</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td><td class="po-block e367 e367"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><para class="po-block e368 e368"><textual class="po-textual">3</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></td></tr></tbody></table><para class="po-block e369 e369"><textual class="po-textual">The Genericode standard has 3 major sections:</textual></para><orderedlist class="po-table e370 e370"><listitem class="po-container e371 e371"><para class="po-block e372 e372"><emphasis class="po-inline e373 e373"><textual class="po-textual">Identification:</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Identification and location information
            (metadata).</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e374 e374"><para class="po-block e375 e375"><emphasis class="po-inline e376 e376"><textual class="po-textual">ColumnSet:</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Description for each column in the Genericode
            list.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e377 e377"><para class="po-block e378 e378"><emphasis class="po-inline e379 e379"><textual class="po-textual">SimpleCodeList:</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> The container for the actual code list.</textual></para></listitem></orderedlist><para class="po-block e380 e380"><textual class="po-textual">If we look at the table </textual><xref class="po-milestone e381 e381" linkend="table2"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> above, the Genericode representation
        would be:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e382 e382" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
&lt;CodeList xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/codelist/ns/genericode/1.0/"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"&gt;
    &lt;Identification&gt;
        &lt;ShortName xml:lang="en"&gt;Age Code List&lt;/ShortName&gt;
        &lt;LongName xml:lang="en"&gt;Age Code List Irish Famine, period 1/12/1846 - 12/31/1851&lt;/LongName&gt;
        &lt;Version&gt;0.3&lt;/Version&gt;
        &lt;CanonicalUri/&gt;
        &lt;Agency&gt;
            &lt;LongName xml:lang="en"&gt;
                United States National Archives Records Administration
            &lt;/LongName&gt;
            &lt;Identifier&gt;1&lt;/Identifier&gt;
        &lt;/Agency&gt;
    &lt;/Identification&gt;
    &lt;ColumnSet&gt;
        &lt;Column Id="Description" Use="Required"&gt;
            &lt;ShortName&gt;Description&lt;/ShortName&gt;
            &lt;Data Type="xsd:string" xml:lang="en"/&gt;
        &lt;/Column&gt;
        &lt;Column Id="Ship1" Use="Optional"&gt;
            &lt;ShortName&gt;Ship 1&lt;/ShortName&gt;
            &lt;Data Type="xsd:string" xml:lang="en"/&gt;
        &lt;/Column&gt;
        &lt;Column Id="Ship2" Use="Optional"&gt;
            &lt;ShortName&gt;Ship 2&lt;/ShortName&gt;
            &lt;Data Type="xsd:string" xml:lang="en"/&gt;
        &lt;/Column&gt;
        &lt;Column Id="Ship3" Use="Optional"&gt;
            &lt;ShortName&gt;Ship 3&lt;/ShortName&gt;
            &lt;Data Type="xsd:string" xml:lang="en"/&gt;
        &lt;/Column&gt;
    &lt;/ColumnSet&gt;
    &lt;SimpleCodeList&gt;
        . . .
        &lt;Row&gt;
            &lt;Value ColumnRef="Description"&gt;
                &lt;SimpleValue&gt;age 03&lt;/SimpleValue&gt;
            &lt;/Value&gt;
            &lt;Value ColumnRef="Ship1"&gt;
                &lt;SimpleValue&gt;3&lt;/SimpleValue&gt;
            &lt;/Value&gt;
            &lt;Value ColumnRef="Ship2"&gt;
                &lt;SimpleValue&gt;003&lt;/SimpleValue&gt;
            &lt;/Value&gt;
            &lt;Value ColumnRef="Ship1"&gt;
                &lt;SimpleValue&gt;3&lt;/SimpleValue&gt;
            &lt;/Value&gt;
        &lt;/Row&gt;
        . . .
    &lt;/SimpleCodeList&gt;
&lt;/CodeList&gt;</textual></programlisting></section><section class="po-hcontainer e383 e383"><title class="po-block e384 e384"><textual class="po-textual">Advantages</textual></title><para class="po-block e385 e385"><textual class="po-textual">As stated above, enumerated data can be problematic in XML documents. One approach is to
        have allowed values for a data element be enumerated in an XML schema, so that associated
        XML documents and their enumerated values can easily be validated by a standard XML parser.
        However, if there is a need to add, remove, or change values to the enumeration lists, then
        the schema has to be modified. In </textual><xref class="po-milestone e386 e386" linkend="r12"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, the author proposed different
        solutions to extend the enumeration lists in an XML schema, by using XML mechanisms such as
        &lt;xsd:union&gt;, &lt;xsd:pattern&gt;, or &lt;xsd:annotation&gt;.
        The author argued that some of these solutions are advantageous because they require only
        one pass validation, thus avoiding performance penalty.</textual></para><para class="po-block e387 e387"><textual class="po-textual">On the contrary, Genericode offers an approach that allows the management of the
        enumerations to be independent from the XML schema. Although this would imply a separate
        validation for the code list values, it does have some advantages </textual><xref class="po-milestone e388 e388" linkend="r13"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e389 e389"><listitem class="po-container e390 e390"><para class="po-block e391 e391"><textual class="po-textual">Genericode is a flexible scheme to manage the code lists for applications where
            business logic parsing performance is not a critical requirement. This is the case for
            the ABO Management application.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e392 e392"><para class="po-block e393 e393"><textual class="po-textual">If a change is confined to the display value of a code, then any application data
            using the code key will not be affected.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e394 e394"><para class="po-block e395 e395"><textual class="po-textual">Adding or removing a code from a list can be done directly in the XML code list. All
            forms using that code list will be changed simultaneously without requiring any
            programming, as in the case of using JSP and enumeration in the schema. In our system,
            we can build a simple application to allow NARA policy makers to manage the code lists
            that govern the critical values in the forms for ABOs.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e396 e396"><textual class="po-textual">Another key advantage for NARA to maintain all their code lists in a "generic" common
        format is the ability to create a standard NARA-wide authoring environment for developing
        and maintaining code lists across the enterprise. NARA can ultimately have thousands of code
        lists when preserving and describing electronic records for the entire federal
        government.</textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e397 e397"><title class="po-block e398 e398"><textual class="po-textual">XForms and Genericode Together</textual></title><section class="po-hcontainer e399 e399"><title class="po-block e400 e400"><textual class="po-textual">Advantages</textual></title><para class="po-block e401 e401"><textual class="po-textual">By combining XForms and Genericode, our approach can benefit the advantages of both
        XForms and Genericode. Indeed, the introduction of Genericode into XForms provides a
        separation of concerns in the software and data development:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e402 e402"><listitem class="po-container e403 e403"><para class="po-block e404 e404"><emphasis class="po-inline e405 e405"><textual class="po-textual">Evolvability</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. From the data management perspective, the XML
            schemas associated to the ABOs and the controlled enumerations can evolve independently
            of each other. Thus, their maintenance will be more efficient. In business practice, the
            code lists would experience more changes than the schema. Moreover, with respect to
            software maintenance, it would not be desirable to change too frequently XML
            schemas.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e406 e406"><para class="po-block e407 e407"><emphasis class="po-inline e408 e408" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Modularity</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. From the software engineering
            perspective, we can easily design and develop two separate modules: one to process the
            XForms, and the other to manage the code lists. Due to the separation of data, changes
            to the code lists would not affect the XForms processing module.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e409 e409"><para class="po-block e410 e410"><emphasis class="po-inline e411 e411" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Separation of Control</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. The modularity of software
            fits the business organization of NARA, where the group responsible to control the code
            lists is different from the one managing the ABOs. Access to each of these modules can
            be implemented using RBAC (Role-based Access). Note that the potential users of the ABOs
            include NARA archivists as well as record managers from all federal agencies.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></section><section class="po-hcontainer e412 e412"><title class="po-block e413 e413"><textual class="po-textual">Development Process</textual></title><para class="po-block e414 e414"><textual class="po-textual">The development process for XForms-based approach consists of the following
        steps:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e415 e415"><listitem class="po-container e416 e416"><para class="po-block e417 e417"><textual class="po-textual">Develop XForms model based on XML Schema, which conforms to and ERA conceptual data
            model.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e418 e418"><para class="po-block e419 e419"><textual class="po-textual">Develop XForms input control for the data elements in the XForms model.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e420 e420"><para class="po-block e421 e421"><textual class="po-textual">Develop XForms data validation rules based on the business rules provided by the
            record managers and processors. The implementation makes use of XForms binds derived
            from the XML schema constraints.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e422 e422"><para class="po-block e423 e423"><textual class="po-textual">Develop error handling, and error message in order to provide consistency, hence
            user-friendly and ease of maintenance.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e424 e424"><para class="po-block e425 e425"><textual class="po-textual">Develop CSS (Cascading Style Sheets) for each form. This phase would involve
            interactions with end-users in order to get their feedback and suggestions.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e426 e426"><para class="po-block e427 e427"><textual class="po-textual">Define SOAP messages used in Web Services that implement business workflow to
            process XForms instance upon XForms submission.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></section><section class="po-hcontainer e428 e428"><title class="po-block e429 e429"><textual class="po-textual">Implementation</textual></title><para class="po-block e430 e430"><textual class="po-textual">Our implementation of XForms/Genericode uses the Apache Tomcat application server as the
        infrastructure. The Orbeon XForms Server is used as a platform for managing the forms. We
        chose Orbeon over other XForms applications for the following reasons:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e431 e431"><listitem class="po-container e432 e432"><para class="po-block e433 e433"><textual class="po-textual">A large user base</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e434 e434"><para class="po-block e435 e435"><textual class="po-textual">Capability for support in the future</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e436 e436"><para class="po-block e437 e437"><textual class="po-textual">Well deployed</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e438 e438"><para class="po-block e439 e439"><textual class="po-textual">Ability to easily integrate with XML repository </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e440 e440"><para class="po-block e441 e441"><textual class="po-textual">XInclude support</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e442 e442"><textual class="po-textual">We chose to use a standard XML database as the repository for storing XML components.
        Initially we used eXist Open Source repository then moved to MarkLogic (commercial software)
        for the prototype that integrates XForms and BPM </textual><xref class="po-milestone e443 e443" linkend="xforms-bpm"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e444 e444"><listitem class="po-container e445 e445"><para class="po-block e446 e446"><textual class="po-textual">Reusable XForm components</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e447 e447"><para class="po-block e448 e448"><textual class="po-textual">Genericode code lists</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e449 e449"><para class="po-block e450 e450"><textual class="po-textual">Converted code lists used for consumption in the form</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e451 e451"><para class="po-block e452 e452"><textual class="po-textual">XML business objects saved from form</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e453 e453"><textual class="po-textual">The figure below shows the interaction of the forms to the Genericode. </textual></para><figure class="po-container e454 e454"><mediaobject class="po-container e455 e455"><imageobject class="po-container e456 e456"><imagedata class="po-meta e457 e457" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Harvey01/Harvey01-002.jpg" format="jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e458 e458"><para class="po-block e459 e459"><textual class="po-textual">XForms+Genericode Architecture</textual></para></caption></figure><para class="po-block e460 e460"><textual class="po-textual">Maintaining the code list external to the form provides the ability for the use of the
        same code list in multiple forms or multiple applications. When a code list is updated, all
        the forms that consume the code list will be automatically updated without any recompilation
        of code. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e461 e461"><title class="po-block e462 e462"><textual class="po-textual">Populating Fields from Code List Lookups</textual></title><para class="po-block e463 e463"><textual class="po-textual">Certain fields can be automatically populated based on the selection of a single code.
        There are several places when this becomes important for NARA. A good example is the
          "</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e464 e464" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Record Group </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">". NARA classifies all records by a number
        which represents a title of the record group. A record group number can represent an agency
        or a collection records. For example the record group 21 represents"</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e465 e465" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">
          Records of District Courts of the United States</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> ". Once a record group is
        assigned it never changes. Every federal agency is associated with one or more record groups
        (usually just one). </textual></para><para class="po-block e466 e466"><textual class="po-textual">In an ABO form, the user selecting his/her agency will only be presented with the record
        group(s) associated with his/her agency. Once they select the record group, the record group
        title is automatically populated in the XML. Below is the XForms code which provides this
        functionality:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e467 e467" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
    &lt;xforms:variable
      name="AgencyName"
      select="../era:OrganizationInformation/era:AgencyInformation/era:AgencyName"/&gt;
    &lt;xforms:select1
      ref="instance('TransferRequest-instance')//era:RecordGroupNumber"
      appearance="full"&gt;
        &lt;xforms:itemset
          nodeset="instance('AgencyRecordGroup-instance')/Row[AgencyName
          = $AgencyName]/RecordGroup"&gt;
            &lt;xforms:label ref="."/&gt;
            &lt;xforms:value ref="."/&gt;
        &lt;/xforms:itemset&gt;
    &lt;/xforms:select1&gt;
&lt;/xforms:group&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e468 e468"><textual class="po-textual">The example above shows that the pull-down list is being populated from the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e469 e469" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">AgencyRecordGroup-instance</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> XML codelist. This codelist is set in
        the XForms model section using the &lt;xforms:instance&gt; element shown
        below.</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e470 e470" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
&lt;xforms:instance
  id="AgencyRecordGroup-instance"
  src="http://localhost:8080/exist/rest/db/home/era/CodeLists/Agency-RecordGroup-Form.xml"/&gt;
</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e471 e471"><textual class="po-textual">The codelist is being pulled from an eXist XML repository. An major advantage to having
        the codelist maintained in a external XML file is that if an agency name changes (and they
        do quite often), the form does not require modification. Once the code list is updated, all
        forms using the code list are automatically updated. The record title gets populated by
        using an XForms &lt;xforms:bind&gt; function using an XPath statement. The attribute
          </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e472 e472" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">calculate</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> attribute is used to set the value. </textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e473 e473" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
&lt;xforms:bind
  nodeset="instance('TransferRequest-instance')/era:IdentificationInformation/era:RecordGroupTitle"
  calculate="instance('RecordGroupTitle-instance')/RecordGroupInfo[RecordGroupNumber
  = $RecordGroupNumber]/RecordGroupTitle"/&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e474 e474"><textual class="po-textual">The XPath statment in the </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e475 e475" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">calculate</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> statement above
        basically says get the value of the record group title from the code list instance called
        "RecordGroupTitle-instance" where the &lt;RecordGroupNumber&gt; in the list matches
        the "RecordGroupNumber" variable. The $RecordGroupNumber has been set previously in the
        form.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e476 e476"><title class="po-block e477 e477"><textual class="po-textual">Business Rules</textual></title><para class="po-block e478 e478"><textual class="po-textual">The ABO forms must follow business rules that dictate the dependencies between the
        fields within a form, and also between the fields in one ABO to another. For example, if the
        "Required" indicator of a group of fields is checked, then valid values must be supplied to
        all fields within that group.</textual></para><para class="po-block e479 e479"><textual class="po-textual">Some of the rules for the interaction of code lists in forms can be quite complex. The
        use of XForms and XML code lists allow the ability to define these rules using XPath
        statements.</textual></para><para class="po-block e480 e480"><textual class="po-textual">Figure 3 show a pull-down selection bar for access restrictions. The form components
        change based on the selection in he pull-down list. The values of the pull-down list are
        populated by a code list for access restrictions. There are business rules associated with
        what information needs to be completed based on the value of the access restriction. For
        instance, if the user selects " </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e481 e481" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Presidential Records Act (p)(3)
          Statute</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> " the user must select a statutory citation. (See Figure 4)</textual></para><figure class="po-container e482 e482"><mediaobject class="po-container e483 e483"><imageobject class="po-container e484 e484"><imagedata class="po-meta e485 e485" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Harvey01/Harvey01-003.jpg" format="jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e486 e486"><para class="po-block e487 e487"><textual class="po-textual">Example Pull-down List</textual></para></caption></figure><figure class="po-container e488 e488"><mediaobject class="po-container e489 e489"><imageobject class="po-container e490 e490"><imagedata class="po-meta e491 e491" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Harvey01/Harvey01-004.jpg" format="jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e492 e492"><para class="po-block e493 e493"><textual class="po-textual">Statutory Citation pops up.</textual></para></caption></figure><para class="po-block e494 e494"><textual class="po-textual">The XForms construct that controls whether the field is displayed based on the selection
        is below:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e495 e495" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">
&lt;xforms:group ref="era:AccessRestriction[contains(., 'FOIA(b)(3) Statute')] |
era:AccessRestriction[contains(., 'Presidential Records Act (p)(1)
  ')]"&gt;
. . .
&lt;/xforms:group&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e496 e496"><textual class="po-textual">The XPath above states that if the access restriction contains "FOIA (b)(3) Statute" or
        "'Presidential Records Act (p)(1)" then display the field.</textual></para><para class="po-block e497 e497"><textual class="po-textual">Figure 5 shows the user selecting "</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e498 e498" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">PRMPA- Personal Privacy (D)".
        </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">You will notice that in Figure 6, nothing is provided the user.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e499 e499"><mediaobject class="po-container e500 e500"><imageobject class="po-container e501 e501"><imagedata class="po-meta e502 e502" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Harvey01/Harvey01-005.jpg" format="jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e503 e503"><para class="po-block e504 e504"><textual class="po-textual">PRMPA - Personal Privacy (D) Selection</textual></para></caption></figure><figure class="po-container e505 e505"><mediaobject class="po-container e506 e506"><imageobject class="po-container e507 e507"><imagedata class="po-meta e508 e508" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Harvey01/Harvey01-006.jpg" format="jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e509 e509"><para class="po-block e510 e510"><textual class="po-textual">PRMPA- Personal Privacy (D) Selection Result Screen</textual></para></caption></figure></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e511 e511"><title class="po-block e512 e512"><textual class="po-textual">Content Governance</textual></title><para class="po-block e513 e513"><textual class="po-textual">As mentioned earlier, the ABOs serve to administer the transfer of archival records into
      the open archival system. Therefore, the ABOs will provide provenance and management metadata
      to the digital objects ingested and stored in the system according the Archival Information
      System (OAIS) information reference model </textual><xref class="po-milestone e514 e514" linkend="r14"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">. In ERA, the metadata of a
      digital object is embodied in an Asset Catalog Entry (ACE).</textual></para><section class="po-hcontainer e515 e515"><title class="po-block e516 e516"><textual class="po-textual">Asset Catalog Entry</textual></title><para class="po-block e517 e517"><textual class="po-textual">An ACE is represented by an XML document that conforms to a well-defined XML schema. At
        the high level, the structure of an ACE is compliant with the various kinds of metadata as
        described in the OAIS information reference model </textual><xref class="po-milestone e518 e518" linkend="r14"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">. The following
        aspects have been considered in the design of the ACE structure:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e519 e519"><listitem class="po-container e520 e520"><para class="po-block e521 e521"><emphasis class="po-inline e522 e522"><textual class="po-textual">Information type</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. From the OAIS model, an ACE should contain
            information about its associated digital object in terms:</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e523 e523"><para class="po-block e524 e524"><emphasis class="po-inline e525 e525"><textual class="po-textual">Reference</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> for uniquely identifying the digital object. Usually,
            this identifier is location and protocol independent.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e526 e526"><para class="po-block e527 e527"><emphasis class="po-inline e528 e528"><textual class="po-textual">Provenance</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> for preserving the history and chain of custody of
            the object.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e529 e529"><para class="po-block e530 e530"><emphasis class="po-inline e531 e531"><textual class="po-textual">Context</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> for recording the circumstances of the object's
            creation.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e532 e532"><para class="po-block e533 e533"><emphasis class="po-inline e534 e534"><textual class="po-textual">Fixity</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> for storing authenticity mechanisms of records such as
            digital signature, and checksum.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e535 e535"><para class="po-block e536 e536"><emphasis class="po-inline e537 e537"><textual class="po-textual">Descriptive</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> used for object search and discovery.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e538 e538"><para class="po-block e539 e539"><emphasis class="po-inline e540 e540"><textual class="po-textual">Standard integration</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Given the diversity of data, business and
            knowledge domains as well as types, one standard alone cannot cover all the information
            types of an ACE. Therefore, the structure of an ACE should facilitate the integration of
            different XML standards. For instance, the ACE's schema should incorporate PREMIS
            (Preservation Metatdata Maintenance Activity) standard </textual><xref class="po-milestone e541 e541" linkend="r16"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> for
            preservation metadata. If the digital object is a still image, then MIX standard </textual><xref class="po-milestone e542 e542" linkend="r17"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> will be included to describe the technical metadata of the image
            object. NARA has its standard called Lifecycle Data Requirements Guide </textual><xref class="po-milestone e543 e543" linkend="r15"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> that archivists have used to convey descriptive information of an
            object. </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e544 e544"><para class="po-block e545 e545"><emphasis class="po-inline e546 e546"><textual class="po-textual">Metadata aggregation</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. The processing of an archived digital
            object can be performed by different archivist groups using varied archival processing
            systems and technologies. Associated metadata will be collected at each stage, and
            finally accumulated in the ACE stored into the ERA system. Within this environment, the
            ACE structure should be designed in such a way to facilitate easy and efficient import
            of metadata generated by the processing applications. In order to achieve this, the ACE
            can be divided into slots. Each slot is reserved for an archival processing system, and
            will have disjoint data elements to avoid duplication and complex crosswalk.</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e547 e547"><para class="po-block e548 e548"><emphasis class="po-inline e549 e549"><textual class="po-textual">Technical aspect</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. One last challenging aspect to consider is
            that some metadata is unchanged since the time of ingest into ERA such as file type and
            size. Other metadata of the same object will certainly undergo changes such as
            description, and access rights. Therefore, two types of data management systems have to
            be combined to accommodate these two modes of metadata, mutable vs. immutable parts.
          </textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist></section><section class="po-hcontainer e550 e550"><title class="po-block e551 e551"><textual class="po-textual">Archival Management Taxonomy</textual></title><para class="po-block e552 e552"><textual class="po-textual">The design of ACE structure should allow the classification of digital objects in ERA
        according to different taxonomies. Archival Management Taxonomy is a special taxonomy that
        is mostly used by archivists, or record managers from federal agencies. A public user would
        be most likely interested in other taxonomies associated with the domain of the content of
        the data. In order to support the Archival Management Taxonomy, an ACE must include
        information extracted from the ABOs (Record Schedule and Transfer Request) that were created
        before the digital object represented by this ACE got ingested. With this organization, we
        can develop an application that allows business users to browse all digital objects grouped
        under a set of related ABOs. </textual></para></section></section><section class="po-hcontainer e553 e553" xml:id="xforms-bpm"><title class="po-block e554 e554"><textual class="po-textual">XForms and Business Process Management (BPM)</textual></title><para class="po-block e555 e555"><textual class="po-textual">Recently the NARA ERA Systems Engineering Division developed a prototype to determine the
      feasability and challenges of interjecting new technologies based on standards into the
      current system. The ERA system requires that workflow processing be flexible and incorporated
      into the system in a timely fashion by avoiding hard-wired and high maintenance cost business
      orchestrations. The goals of the prototype were:</textual></para><orderedlist class="po-table e556 e556"><listitem class="po-container e557 e557"><para class="po-block e558 e558"><textual class="po-textual">Find the best of breed BPM tool that supports modeling human interactions with the
          business process compliant with BPMN (Business Process Modeling Notation) standard.
        </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e559 e559"><para class="po-block e560 e560"><textual class="po-textual">The BPM workflow should integrate seamlessly with our Forms Management (XForms)
          solution. </textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e561 e561"><para class="po-block e562 e562"><textual class="po-textual">Find the best of breed system orchestration tool compliant with BPEL (Business Process
          Execution Language) </textual><xref class="po-milestone e563 e563" linkend="r22"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">. BPEL orchestrations run on ESB should be able
          to integrate seamlessly with the BPM workflow above. </textual></para></listitem></orderedlist><para class="po-block e564 e564"><textual class="po-textual">One of the challenges was the current lack of support for XForms solution among BPM
      vendors. All BPM vendors have their own forms management system internal to their software.
      Since the business objects (forms) are an integral part of the ABO Application capability, it
      would be desirable to have a plug and play architecture. It would be difficult to replace BPM
      software with another BPM if the forms were tied up in a proprietary format. Therefore, we
      only consider products that support the abstraction of the form from the application layer.
      The XForms/BPM prototype simulated business process capability of XForms interacting with
      various BPM candidate software packages using a web service call to the BPM. The same web
      service was used to interact with these packages for testing and evaluation. In the current
      system, LDAP was used to authenticate the user and their roles in the portal. </textual></para><para class="po-block e565 e565"><textual class="po-textual">The graphic below demonstrates the flow and interaction of the various components. </textual></para><figure class="po-container e566 e566"><mediaobject class="po-container e567 e567"><imageobject class="po-container e568 e568"><imagedata class="po-meta e569 e569" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Harvey01/Harvey01-007.jpg" format="jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e570 e570"><textual class="po-textual">For illustration, we are showing in the following diagram a BPMN Workflow for the creation
      of a Transfer Request (TR). A TR is normally required every time a Producer wants to transfer
      electronic materials to the system. This business object must be created and approved before
      any actual transfer can occur. It should be noted that the workflow integrates different key
      technologies presented in this paper: XForms, Genericode, BPM, BPEL, and XML database. Thanks
      to the component and service architecture as exhibited in the diagram, the design is very
      flexible and offers low cost maintenance, should we need to modify the workflow. Moreover, the
      actual implementation and evolutio of components and services involved in the workflow should
      not affect each other as long as the interface is maintained.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e571 e571"><mediaobject class="po-container e572 e572"><imageobject class="po-container e573 e573"><imagedata class="po-meta e574 e574" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Harvey01/Harvey01-008.jpg" format="jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e575 e575"><para class="po-block e576 e576"><textual class="po-textual">BPMN Worlkflow for a Transfer Request Business Object</textual></para></caption></figure></section><section class="po-hcontainer e577 e577"><title class="po-block e578 e578"><textual class="po-textual">Conclusion</textual></title><para class="po-block e579 e579"><textual class="po-textual">In this paper, we have described an agile approach which is integrated into our XML-based
      stack from presentation, business logic, to persistence store for managing Archival Business
      Objects.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e580 e580"><mediaobject class="po-container e581 e581"><imageobject class="po-container e582 e582"><imagedata class="po-meta e583 e583" fileref="../../../vol3/graphics/Harvey01/Harvey01-009.jpg" format="jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e584 e584"><para class="po-block e585 e585"><textual class="po-textual">XML-based Stack for ABO Management.</textual></para></caption></figure><para class="po-block e586 e586"><textual class="po-textual">Our approach leverages the synergy of various XML standards and technologies at multiple
      layers of the software architecture:</textual></para><itemizedlist class="po-table e587 e587"><listitem class="po-container e588 e588"><para class="po-block e589 e589"><textual class="po-textual">Presentation layer with XHTML, XSL-FO</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e590 e590"><para class="po-block e591 e591"><textual class="po-textual">Form layer with XForms</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e592 e592"><para class="po-block e593 e593"><textual class="po-textual">Data layer with XSD and Genericode</textual></para></listitem><listitem class="po-container e594 e594"><para class="po-block e595 e595"><textual class="po-textual">Persistence storage layer with XML database.</textual></para></listitem></itemizedlist><para class="po-block e596 e596"><textual class="po-textual">We have shown that the combined application of XForms+Genericode provides such a
      flexibility that the software process can easily adapt to changing and evolving business
      requirements at NARA. Although the paper was based on our experience in developing ERA, we
      believe that the scheme described herein can be generalized to other applications that need a
      flexible management of business objects via web forms with code lists. Furthermore, the
      integration with BPM and BPEL greatly enhance the flexibility of the whole design.</textual></para></section><appendix class="po-hcontainer e597 e597"><title class="po-block e598 e598"><textual class="po-textual">Acronyms</textual></title><table class="po-container e599 e599"><tbody class="po-table e600 e600"><tr class="po-table e601 e601"><td class="po-block e602 e602"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><para class="po-block e603 e603"><textual class="po-textual">
              </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e604 e604" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">ABO</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e605 e605"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><para class="po-block e606 e606"><textual class="po-textual">Archival Business Objects</textual></para><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e607 e607"><td class="po-block e608 e608"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e609 e609" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">ACE</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e610 e610"><textual class="po-textual">Asset Catalog Entry</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e611 e611"><td class="po-block e612 e612"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e613 e613" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">BPEL</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e614 e614"><textual class="po-textual">Business Process Execution Language</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e615 e615"><td class="po-block e616 e616"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e617 e617" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">BPM</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e618 e618"><textual class="po-textual">Business Process Management</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e619 e619"><td class="po-block e620 e620"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e621 e621" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">BPMN</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e622 e622"><textual class="po-textual">Business Process Management Notation</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e623 e623"><td class="po-block e624 e624"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e625 e625" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">CRUD</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e626 e626"><textual class="po-textual">Create, Retrieve, Update, Delete</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e627 e627"><td class="po-block e628 e628"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e629 e629" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">CRUDVS</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e630 e630"><textual class="po-textual">Create, Retrieve, Update, Delete, Versioning, Search</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e631 e631"><td class="po-block e632 e632"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e633 e633" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">ESB</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e634 e634"><textual class="po-textual">Enterprise Service Bus</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e635 e635"><td class="po-block e636 e636"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e637 e637" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">ERA</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e638 e638"><textual class="po-textual"> Electronic Records Archive </textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e639 e639"><td class="po-block e640 e640"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e641 e641" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">IVR</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e642 e642"><textual class="po-textual">Interactive Voice Response</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e643 e643"><td class="po-block e644 e644"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e645 e645" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">PREMIS </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e646 e646"><textual class="po-textual">PREservation Metadata: Implementation Strategies</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e647 e647"><td class="po-block e648 e648"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e649 e649" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">SOA</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e650 e650"><textual class="po-textual">Service Oriented Architecture</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e651 e651"><td class="po-block e652 e652"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e653 e653" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">SOAP</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e654 e654"><textual class="po-textual">Simple Object Access Protocol</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e655 e655"><td class="po-block e656 e656"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e657 e657" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">UI</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e658 e658"><textual class="po-textual">User Interface</textual></td></tr><tr class="po-table e659 e659"><td class="po-block e660 e660"><textual class="po-textual">
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e661 e661" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">WSDL</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
          </textual></td><td class="po-block e662 e662"><textual class="po-textual">Web Services Description Language</textual></td></tr></tbody></table></appendix><bibliography class="po-hcontainer e663 e663"><title class="po-block e664 e664"><textual class="po-textual"> References </textual></title><bibliomixed class="po-block e665 e665" xml:id="r1" xreflabel="1"><textual class="po-textual"> An Electronic Records Archives (ERA) Update. Available:
      http://www.diglib.org/preserve/ERA2004.htm. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e666 e666" xml:id="r2" xreflabel="2"><textual class="po-textual"> W3C. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e667 e667" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">XForms 1.1</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">.
      Available: http://www.w3.org/TR/xforms11/. 2007. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e668 e668" xml:id="r3" xreflabel="3"><textual class="po-textual"> OASIS. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e669 e669" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Code List Representation
        (Genericode),</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Version 1.0, Committee Specification 01, 28 December 2007.
      Available: HYPERLINK
      "http://docs.oasis-open.org/codelist/cs-genericode-1.0/doc/oasis-code-list-representation-genericode.pdf"
      http://docs.oasis-open.org/codelist/cs-genericode-1.0/doc/oasis-code-list-representation-genericode.pdf </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e670 e670" xml:id="r4" xreflabel="4"><textual class="po-textual"> Eric Bruchez. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e671 e671" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">XForms: an
        Alternative to </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
      </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e672 e672" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Ajax</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
      </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e673 e673" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">?. </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">XTech 2006, Amsterdam, The Netherlands. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e674 e674" xml:id="r5" xreflabel="5"><textual class="po-textual"> Richard Cardone, Danny Soroker, and Alpana Tiwari.
        </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e675 e675" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Using XForms to Simplify Web Programming. </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">WWW 2005, May
      10-14, 2005, Chiba, Japan. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e676 e676" xml:id="r6" xreflabel="6"><textual class="po-textual"> Mikko Honkala, and Mikko Pohja</textual><emphasis class="po-inline e677 e677" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">.
        Multimodal Interaction with XForms. ICWE’ 06, </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
      </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e678 e678" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">July 11-14, 200</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">6, Palo Alto, California </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e679 e679" xml:id="r7" xreflabel="7"><textual class="po-textual"> R. Bourret. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e680 e680" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">XML and
        Databases</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Available: http://www.rpbourret.com/xml/XMLDBLinks.htm </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e681 e681" xml:id="r8" xreflabel="8"><textual class="po-textual"> Orbeon. Available: http://www.orbeon.org </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e682 e682" xml:id="r9" xreflabel="9"><textual class="po-textual"> OASIS. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e683 e683" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Web Services Business
        Process Execution Language Version 2.0.</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> Available:
      http://docs.oasis-open.org/wsbpel/2.0/wsbpel-v2.0.pdf. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e684 e684" xml:id="r10" xreflabel="10"><textual class="po-textual"> Object Management Group/Business Process Management
      Initiative. http://www.bpmn.org/. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e685 e685" xml:id="r11" xreflabel="11"><textual class="po-textual"> eXist, Open Source XML Database. Available: </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e686 e686" role="bold"><textual class="po-textual">http://exist-db.org/ </textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
    </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e687 e687" xml:id="r12" xreflabel="12"><textual class="po-textual"> W. Paul Kiel. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e688 e688" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Extend enumerated
        lists in XML schema</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
      </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e689 e689" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">– Explore options for your extension solution</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Available:
      http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/x-extenum/. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e690 e690" xml:id="r13" xreflabel="13"><textual class="po-textual"> G. Ken. Holman. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e691 e691" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Introduction to
        Code Lists in XML (Using Controlled Vocabularies in XML Documents)</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Available :
      http://www.xmlprague.cz/2009/presentations/G-Ken-Holman-Introduction-to-Code-List-Implementation.pdf. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e692 e692" xml:id="r14" xreflabel="14"><textual class="po-textual"> The Consultative Committee for Space Data Systems.
      “Reference Model for an Open Archival Information System (OAIS)”, 2002. Available: http://
      public.ccsds.org/publications/archive/650x0b1.pdf [Feb. 16, 2009]. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e693 e693" xml:id="r15" xreflabel="15"><textual class="po-textual"> National Archives and Records Administration.
        </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e694 e694" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Lifecycle Data Requirements Guide</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Available:
      http://www.archives.gov/research/arc/about-arc.html#descriptions. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e695 e695" xml:id="r16" xreflabel="16"><textual class="po-textual"> PREMIS. Available:
      http://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e696 e696" xml:id="r17" xreflabel="17"><textual class="po-textual"> NISO Metadata for Images in XML Schema. Available:
      http://www.loc.gov/standards/mix/. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e697 e697" xml:id="r18" xreflabel="18"><textual class="po-textual"> ERA Requirements. Available:
      http://www.archives.gov/era/about/documentation.html#requirements. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e698 e698" xml:id="r19" xreflabel="19"><textual class="po-textual"> OASIS Universal Business Language (UBL), </textual><link class="po-inline e699 e699" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=ubl" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=ubl</textual></link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e700 e700" xml:id="r20"><textual class="po-textual">OASIS Code List Representation,
      http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=codelist</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e701 e701" xml:id="r21"><textual class="po-textual"> Famine Irish Passenger Record Data File (FIPAS), 1/12/1846 -
      12/31/1851. URL: </textual><link class="po-inline e702 e702" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://aad.archives.gov/aad/display-partial-records.jsp?f=640&amp;mtch=11&amp;q=Irish&amp;cat=all&amp;dt=180&amp;tf=F#" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://aad.archives.gov/aad/display-partial-records.jsp?f=640&amp;mtch=11&amp;q=Irish&amp;cat=all&amp;dt=180&amp;tf=F#</textual></link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e703 e703" xml:id="r22"><textual class="po-textual">OASIS Web Services Business Process Execution Language (WSBPEL)
        TC</textual><link class="po-inline e704 e704" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=wsbpel</textual></link></bibliomixed></bibliography></article></classedDocument>