<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><classedDocument><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="po-hcontainer e0 e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3"><title class="po-block e1 e1"><textual class="po-textual">Hierarchies within range space</textual></title><subtitle class="po-block e2 e2"><textual class="po-textual">From LMNL to OHCO</textual></subtitle><info class="po-record e3 e3"><confgroup class="po-record e4 e4"><conftitle class="po-field e5 e5"><textual class="po-textual">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2014</textual></conftitle><confdates class="po-field e6 e6"><textual class="po-textual">August 5 - 8, 2014</textual></confdates></confgroup><abstract class="po-container e7 e7"><para class="po-block e8 e8"><textual class="po-textual">LMNL provides a markup syntax for annotating arbitrary ranges, irrespective of
        hierarchical relations, in text. A LMNL processor can parse this syntax (or any other syntax,
        if mapped) into a generalized data model, which can be queried and processed. Among the
        applications that LMNL supports readily is the creation of visual "sketches" of the markup
        on a document, e.g. using SVG. Such sketches can discover and depict any range relations of
        interest. It turns out the overlap is often less interesting than the hierarchies.</textual></para><para class="po-block e9 e9"><textual class="po-textual">Examining texts showing overlapping hierarchies (MCH or multiple concurrent hierarchies)
        suggests some interesting things about the evolution, purposes and uses of the OHCO (ordered
        hierarchy of content objects) as a concept applied to "documents" or literary artifacts in
        general— and by implication of any hierarchical data model such as XML.</textual></para></abstract><author class="po-record e10 e10"><personname class="po-record e11 e11"><firstname class="po-field e12 e12"><textual class="po-textual">Wendell</textual></firstname><surname class="po-field e13 e13"><textual class="po-textual">Piez</textual></surname></personname><personblurb class="po-container e14 e14"><para class="po-block e15 e15"><textual class="po-textual">Wendell Piez is an independent consultant specializing in XML and XSLT, based in
          Rockville MD.</textual></para></personblurb></author><legalnotice class="po-container e16 e16"><para class="po-block e17 e17"><textual class="po-textual">Copyright © 2013 by the author. Used with permission.</textual></para></legalnotice></info><section class="po-hcontainer e18 e18"><title class="po-block e19 e19"><textual class="po-textual">LMNL experiments</textual></title><para class="po-block e20 e20"><textual class="po-textual">As attendees of prior conferences in this series know, since 2002 I have been
      experimenting with an unorthodox approach to document markup, LMNL (the Layered Markup and
      Annotation Language), conceived by Jeni Tennison and myself with significant contributions and
      support by others. LMNL is similar to XML in its conceptual architecture, distinguishing
      between a markup syntax and a data model capturing an abstraction of </textual><quote class="po-inline e21 e21"><textual class="po-textual">text</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> as it
      is described by the syntax. Unlike XML, however, the LMNL data model represents arbitrary
      ranges over text; in particular, ranges that have any or no hierarchical relation to one
      another are as easily handled as those that fall into the familiar nested element structure of
      XML documents.</textual></para><para class="po-block e22 e22"><textual class="po-textual">A simple example (five lines of a poem by Robert Frost) illustrates the syntax</textual><note class="po-container e23 e23"><para class="po-block e24 e24"><textual class="po-textual">One reviewer recalls correctly that LMNL is defined as a data model, capable of
          various syntactic representations. This is correct, but LMNL also has something we called
            </textual><quote class="po-inline e25 e25"><textual class="po-textual">LMNL syntax</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, defined separately from the model and implementable in its
          own right (inasmuch as it was a text-based format). Not everyone who built a LMNL
          application has had occasion to use the syntax much; but my experiments with Luminescent
            (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e26 e26" linkend="Piez2012"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">) show it is feasible in principle.</textual></para><para class="po-block e27 e27"><textual class="po-textual">For those who wish for more formal references, I offer (with apologies) several
          antiquated documents archived at </textual><link class="po-inline e28 e28" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://lmnl-markup.org</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></note><textual class="po-textual"> in its bare
      form:</textual><programlisting class="po-block e29 e29" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">[sonnet}[octave}[s}[quatrain}[line}[phr}He would have said,{phr] [phr}and could himself believe{line]
[line}That the birds there in all the garden round{line]
[line}Had gathered from the day-long voice of Eve{line]
[line}And added to their own,{phr] [phr}an oversound,{phr]{line]{quatrain]
[quatrain}[line}[phr}Her tone of meaning,{phr] [phr}though without the words.{phr]{line]{s]
...{quatrain]...{octave]...{sonnet]</textual></programlisting></para><para class="po-block e30 e30"><textual class="po-textual">Interestingly, an approach to markup that permits arbitrary overlap, as does LMNL, turns
      out to be highly convenient for marking up multiple concurrent hierarchies (MCH), albeit with
      no built-in "awareness" of them in the model. (These hierarchies, that is, are entirely
      implicit in the data model until they are resolved and processed as hierarchies by a
      processor.) So, in the example just given, two concurrent hierarchies may be discerned in the
      poem. One hierarchy constitutes the formal structure of the sonnet as an example of English
      verse, in which (as represented here) lines are combined into couplets, tercets, quatrains,
      sestets, octaves—some of which may contain other such structures. (So an octave of eight lines
      may decompose into two quatrains of four lines each.) The other constitutes the structure of
      grammar and rhetoric (argument): phrases are joined to constitute sentences. Because sentences
      and indeed phrases may overlap verse structures, these two hierarchies do not align at every
      point. Yet they can nevertheless be discerned, separately or together, within the </textual><quote class="po-inline e31 e31"><textual class="po-textual">range
        space</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> of the text.</textual></para><para class="po-block e32 e32"><textual class="po-textual">MCH is readily visualized in a toolset able to process LMNL markup, build a range model
      from it, and generate an SVG diagram showing the ranges, as illustrated for this poem in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e33 e33" linkend="BirdsAndEveGraph"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">. Such a toolset was demonstrated at Balisage 2012 (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e34 e34" linkend="Piez2012"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">).</textual><note class="po-container e35 e35"><para class="po-block e36 e36"><textual class="po-textual">In case you are wondering, no claim is made that anything can be done here that cannot
          be done in XML without LMNL. LMNL just makes it really really easy because we don't have
          to support XML-based workarounds for dealing with ranges, multiple hierarchies or overlap.
          In XML, we are faced with an XML (engineering) task even before we can get on with the
          markup task.</textual></para></note></para><figure class="po-container e37 e37" xml:id="BirdsAndEveGraph"><title class="po-block e38 e38"><textual class="po-textual">A sonnet by Robert Frost</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e39 e39"><imageobject class="po-container e40 e40"><imagedata class="po-meta e41 e41" fileref="../../../vol13/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-001.png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><para class="po-block e42 e42"><textual class="po-textual">Of particular interest here is the overlap between ranges marked </textual><code class="po-atom e43 e43"><textual class="po-textual">s</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> and
          </textual><code class="po-atom e44 e44"><textual class="po-textual">phr</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> (marking sentences and phrases) and ranges indicating the formal
        structure of the first (</textual><code class="po-atom e45 e45"><textual class="po-textual">line</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><code class="po-atom e46 e46"><textual class="po-textual">quatrain</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> etc.) Indicating how some
        lines are end-stopped, while others enjamb (phrases break across them), these incidences of
        overlap between the two hierarchies—which are largely, but not entirely congruent—reveal the
        movement of the poem's language across its formal foundation.</textual></para></figure></section><section class="po-hcontainer e47 e47"><title class="po-block e48 e48"><textual class="po-textual">The reign of the OHCO</textual></title><para class="po-block e49 e49"><textual class="po-textual">The acronym OHCO, for Ordered Hierarchy of Content Objects, was coined in 1990 to describe
      a tree-shaped data model for texts, or </textual><quote class="po-inline e50 e50"><textual class="po-textual">documents</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> (we set aside an examination
      of what these terms should mean here), in a seminal discussion of text encoding presented by
      Allen Renear and colleagues at Brown University (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e51 e51" linkend="Renear1990"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">). The argument
      presented in that paper makes two claims: first, that a hierarchical model is superior to
      alternatives then prevalent for purposes of electronic document production and application,
      supporting necessary operations that are not so easily addressed by other data models then prevalent;</textual><note class="po-container e52 e52"><para class="po-block e53 e53"><textual class="po-textual">Certainly this point of view has been vindicated; if we do not today speak much of
          OHCOs, in our DOMs, trees, and directed acyclic graphs, we have infrastructures for OHCO
          under other names.</textual></para></note><textual class="po-textual"> and second, that this superiority is not merely pragmatic (an aspect of design and
      functionality), but due to the fact that such a model accurately reflects what a document
      actually </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e54 e54" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">is</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (as an abstraction, in the instance, or by
      definition). In the years since this argument was first made, its authors qualified and
      prevaricated to a degree (see, for example, </textual><xref class="po-milestone e55 e55" linkend="Renear1993"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><footnote class="po-popup e56 e56"><para class="po-block e57 e57"><textual class="po-textual">Indeed, the 1993 consideration (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e58 e58" linkend="Renear1993"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">) of all the problems that
          come with an overly-exclusive OHCO remains an excellent overview of the issues, twenty
          years later. With apologies to DeRose, Durand and Mylonas, in this paper I may sometimes
          refer to them mistakenly under the name </textual><quote class="po-inline e59 e59"><textual class="po-textual">Renear</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual">) in an effort to meet objections on several levels; but Renear, at least, has
      never given up the core metaphysical claim (for example, see </textual><xref class="po-milestone e60 e60" linkend="Renear2004"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">).
      Nor has he really had to, because, despite many objections, the first argument made by that
      paper has clearly carried the day (at least on the web), as SGML, XML, the HTML DOM and
      numerous other technologies have all verified the usefulness and power of the recursive,
      tree-shaped model. </textual></para><para class="po-block e61 e61"><textual class="po-textual">The OHCO thesis attributes three fundamental properties to texts, interdependent but
      distinct. First, a text is a hierarchy (the H in OHCO). Secondly, it is ordered (the O): we
      cannot simply take the constituent parts of a text (such as the lines in a sonnet by Robert
      Frost) and treat them as unordered, or re-order them, without altering (and thereby in some
      sense destroying) the text they make up together. Third (the CO), that these constituent parts
      all have </textual><quote class="po-inline e62 e62"><textual class="po-textual">thingness</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">: they too may be complex (ordered hierarchies of smaller
      objects); and in any case they have distinct properties or sets of properties—we might say
      they are </textual><quote class="po-inline e63 e63"><textual class="po-textual">typed</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. So, although a system is not free to rearrange the objects that
      constitute a text, when it comes to objects of a given type (such as paragraphs, list items,
      or lists containing list items), we can treat them all alike. They are interchangeable, if not
      quite in the sense that one can be substituted for another, then at least insofar as they
      share essential properties that makes it both possible and correct to unify their handling in
      a system. This promises a satisfying power of generalization, since by this account, all
      sonnets can be handled alike, as can all their lines. Where there are exceptions to this, the
      system can and must account for them by subtyping or otherwise qualifying the types (so in XML
      we may assign attributes to elements to drive special handling) or by resolving differences
      based on their ordered, hierarchical relations (their </textual><quote class="po-inline e64 e64"><textual class="po-textual">context</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">). Thus, if some
      lines in a poem appear with extra vertical white space on the page, this is not because they
      are different, as lines, from others, but because the poem as a whole (or perhaps a
      constituent </textual><quote class="po-inline e65 e65"><textual class="po-textual">stanza</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> object) is displayed with extra spacing that belongs
      properly to it, not to its pieces.</textual></para><para class="po-block e66 e66"><textual class="po-textual">Note that from the point of view of today's technologies, this powerful and elegant
      account of text as </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e67 e67" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">system</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> and </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e68 e68" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">organization</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> provides a rationale and justification for two things we have
      learned (since the thesis was proposed in 1990) to separate. On the one hand, in data models
      for XML, we have the ordered hierarchy. On the other, in the idea of a regulation and indeed a
      grammar of element types, we have a rationale for schemas. XML's parent standard, SGML,
      assumed that both were necessary together (in fact in SGML, the document's hierarchical form
      is arguably a side effect of the fact that it is specified with a grammar of element types).
      XML disentangles this dependency—its more consistent syntax maps to a hierarchy irrespective
      of element types and prescribed relations—and in doing so, acquires much greater flexibility
      in application. (This is not to say that XML is more expressive or capable of any application
      than SGML; only that because the XML parse can happen without reference to any schema or
      element specification, XML tools become more lightweight, easier to use and easier to build
      with than SGML tools.) Defining exactly what our content objects are and how they are to be
      treated may now be performed late, forgoing processes such as validation or data binding until
      they are known to be useful. Yet irrespective of the semantics of particular element types, an
      XML parser knows about elements and attributes, and can always present the hierarchy of
      elements for processing. So the tree remains: always there, always dependable, always
      addressable and processable using generic technologies designed for the purpose, such as
      XPath, XSLT and XQuery.</textual></para><para class="po-block e69 e69"><textual class="po-textual">All of this was a very positive development for developers of publishing systems or data
      processing systems in general—and so, indirectly, for users and communities. Yet at the same
      time, handling </textual><quote class="po-inline e70 e70"><textual class="po-textual">overlap</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> in its various forms has remained a complication (at
      worst, a prohibitive one) for many applications of XML, especially applications whose purpose
      is not simply to create and process new texts or new versions of old texts (for example, in
      publishing activities), but to represent texts for scholarly or research purposes, as they are
      found, in all their complexity and nuance. The </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e71 e71" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">retrospective</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
      encoding of texts (see </textual><xref class="po-milestone e72 e72" linkend="Piez2001"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">) would offer encodings of documents that
      trace what we see in them, irrespective of any prior commitments to how these texts are (or
      should be) defined and constituted as texts—</textual><quote class="po-inline e73 e73"><textual class="po-textual">the model of the text has the form of a
        tree</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> being such a prior commitment.</textual></para><para class="po-block e74 e74"><textual class="po-textual">This hasn't stopped us from trying. To represent multiple concurrent hierarchies (MCH) in
      XML, or anything that doesn't fit into the hierarchy, we resort to one of several
      well-understood and well-documented workarounds: </textual><quote class="po-inline e75 e75"><textual class="po-textual">milestone</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> markers, chained
      segments, standoff markup or what have you (see </textual><xref class="po-milestone e76 e76" linkend="Barnard1995"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><xref class="po-milestone e77 e77" linkend="TEIch20"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">). These work by specifying handling for particular elements or
      attributes, in order to represent, indirectly, things (not yet </textual><quote class="po-inline e78 e78"><textual class="po-textual">content objects</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">)
      that cut across the hierarchy. But this necessitates control of these elements'
      properties—identifiers and pointers to them—which indeed entails prior commitments to element
      semantics, as well as cumbersome and opaque methods of processing that are able to resolve
      these relations according to the kind of representation intended. This inevitably means we do
      not benefit much from schema-free processing, and face significant tagging and validation
      overhead just to represent the phenomena we seek to understand.</textual></para><para class="po-block e79 e79"><textual class="po-textual">Thus a paradoxical consequence of XML's so-called </textual><quote class="po-inline e80 e80"><textual class="po-textual">overlap problem</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> is that
      it presents scholars and researchers with a special challenge precisely as we seek to study
      the place, nature and historical development of hierarchies in text. We who are most
      fascinated by the OHCO thesis, and wish most to scrutinize the nature of hierarchies in texts,
      are the most hampered by a data model that imposes a single hierarchy, because we have
      questions not readily addressed when it must be assumed. Because document hierarchies provide
      XML tools with their frames of reference (literally), it is difficult to consider the
      hierarchy of a text, while using XML, as anything but given: using XML to consider how the
      OHCO thesis applies to text is like looking at a rose garden through rose-colored glasses.
      (The world may look nice, but we can only smell, not see, the roses.)</textual></para><para class="po-block e81 e81"><textual class="po-textual">In particular, it becomes difficult to ask questions, using XML encoding, about texts
      whose hierarchies that are not perfectly regular, or about the relation of multiple
      hierarchies (</textual><quote class="po-inline e82 e82"><textual class="po-textual">views</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> according to </textual><xref class="po-milestone e83 e83" linkend="Renear1993"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">) that appear
      together. Are their relations incidental, or systematic and significant? What accounts for the
      structural regularity of texts? Does a single account serve for all texts, or do various
      kinds, genres, or formats of text show different aspects (features, hierarchies) that suggest
      or demand different explanations? Accepting Renear's argument that the OHCO is a </textual><quote class="po-inline e84 e84"><textual class="po-textual">real
        thing</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, where does it come from and how did it come about? Are texts produced before
      the electronic age, as Renear and his colleagues argued, also always ordered hierarchies, and
      do they always have content objects? If so, of what nature are these? With their tree-shaped
      document models, do XML and HTML represent a radical break from prior forms of text, or are
      they a continuity? And if they are a continuity, what do they continue?</textual></para><para class="po-block e85 e85"><textual class="po-textual">One of the most fascinating things about this inquiry is that it is greatly facilitated by
      a technology, such as LMNL, that allows us to mark up and process text without imposing
      hierarchy at all. Where we can have any hierarchy or none, hierarchy itself is immediately
      open for study.</textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e86 e86"><title class="po-block e87 e87"><textual class="po-textual">Ironies of alignment</textual></title><para class="po-block e88 e88"><textual class="po-textual">As illustrated above, it is perfectly possible to discern more than one hierarchy in, say,
      an example of poetry, where we have both formal organization (stanza and line) and grammatical
      structure (sentences and phrases) together. By definition, by distinguishing more than one
      hierarchy, we admit the potential for them to conflict or overlap. (If they were never in
      conflict, then we should be able to accommodate them together within a single hierarchy.) And
      indeed examples of poetry are not hard to find in which there is not perfect alignment between
      these hierarchies.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e89 e89" xml:id="naturundkunst"><title class="po-block e90 e90"><quote class="po-inline e91 e91"><textual class="po-textual">Natur und Kunst sie scheinen sich zu fliehen</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, by J. W. Goethe (ca.
        1800)</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e92 e92"><imageobject class="po-container e93 e93"><imagedata class="po-meta e94 e94" fileref="../../../vol13/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-002.png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><figure class="po-container e95 e95" xml:id="sonnetI"><title class="po-block e96 e96"><textual class="po-textual">Sonnet I, from </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e97 e97" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Sonnets to Orpheus</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, by R. M. Rilke
        (1922)</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e98 e98"><imageobject class="po-container e99 e99"><imagedata class="po-meta e100 e100" fileref="../../../vol13/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-003.png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e101 e101"><textual class="po-textual">Consider two more sonnets: Goethe's </textual><quote class="po-inline e102 e102"><textual class="po-textual">Natur and Kunst sie scheinen sich zu
        fliehen</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> (ca. 1800; shown in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e103 e103" linkend="naturundkunst"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">), and Rilke's Sonett I
      from </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e104 e104" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Sonnets to Orpheus</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (1922, </textual><xref class="po-milestone e105 e105" linkend="sonnetI"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">).
      The notworthy thing about these examples in this context is the contrast between them. The
      earlier, more </textual><quote class="po-inline e106 e106"><textual class="po-textual">classical</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> example shows a perfect alignment between meter and
      grammatical structure (one does not need to be a reader of German to see this); the latter
      poem, anything but.</textual></para><para class="po-block e107 e107"><textual class="po-textual">In each poem, the degree of alignment between these two hierarchies is significant, and
      thematic. Indeed, in each poem, this aspect (especially when we take grammatical structure as
      a proxy for phrasing when read aloud) is integral to the sense of the poem itself, reflecting
      and reinforcing its denotation. Both these sonnets, like many sonnets, are about sonnets.
      Goethe's is a reflection on the art of crafting verse, among other arts, while in Rilke's,
      both the tree of the first line, and the temple it has become in the last, represent the
      singing of Orpheus and thus poetry itself. Goethe's poem might be described as
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e108 e108"><textual class="po-textual">rectilinear</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> and balanced throughout, while Rilke's shows a kind of eddying
      movement that enacts a transition (weaves a spell, we might say) like the one it describes. In
      other words, we have here a kind of signification: in both cases, whether, how much and where
      the sentence structure aligns with the verse, and where it fails to, is part of the poetry
      itself. It says something. Nor are these two examples at all unusual in this, as a
      consideration of a broader selection can show.</textual></para><para class="po-block e109 e109"><textual class="po-textual">We might generalize from this to consider what happens when multiple concurrent
      hierarchies align, or fail to. I believe the proper term for the latter situation—where two
      simultaneous arrangements might coincide, but do not—is </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e110 e110" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">irony</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. Of course, </textual><quote class="po-inline e111 e111"><textual class="po-textual">irony</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> designates a rhetorical trope (a figure of
      speech or signification) in which the meaning being overtly represented is not the same as the
      meaning being communicated.</textual><note class="po-container e112 e112"><para class="po-block e113 e113"><textual class="po-textual">One reviewer asked whether this definition of </textual><citation class="po-atom e114 e114"><textual class="po-textual">irony</textual></citation><textual class="po-textual"> wasn’t too
          broad (so weak as not to disinguish irony from other tropes), and I admit that for me
          almost any trope has ironic potential or capability. But I would contrast irony with
          metaphor (for example) in indicating how irony works by a deliberate </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e115 e115" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">failure</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> of alignment, whereas metaphor works through the alignment itself.
          In any case, these are excellent questions.</textual></para></note><textual class="po-textual"> More generally, it is a signal, by means of a kind of misalignment or variance from
      expectation, that a meaning should not be taken (at least by a knowing audience) at face
      value; the representation must not only be looked </textual><quote class="po-inline e116 e116"><textual class="po-textual">at</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, but also looked
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e117 e117"><textual class="po-textual">through</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, with the understanding that what is seen at the different levels may
      not correspond (and that this failure to correspond can itself tell us something). By this
      account, Goethe is not being ironic in his assertion that </textual><quote class="po-inline e118 e118"><textual class="po-textual">only law can give us
        freedom</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, and he demonstrates the principle he enunciates.</textual><note class="po-container e119 e119"><para class="po-block e120 e120"><textual class="po-textual">At least one reviewer appeared to be under a misconception that I am disparaging what
          is not ironic in favor of the ironic, that Goethe’s work somehow suffers in comparison to
          Rilke's. Nothing could be further from the truth, and to say Goethe’s sonnet is not ironic
          (at least with respect to this particular kind of internal structural alignment between
          sound and form) is not to say that it is not self-conscious (as it certainly is) in other
          ways, for example metaphorically or metonymically. Indeed it might be said that Goethe’s
            </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e121 e121" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">synecdoche</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> here (synecdoche being the </textual><quote class="po-inline e122 e122"><textual class="po-textual">part for
            whole</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> trope) is deliberately and consciously </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e123 e123" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">not</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> ironic—and that Rilke’s irony would have been impossible without
          it.</textual></para></note><textual class="po-textual"> But Rilke's verse is ironic: this poem also follows all applicable rules of
      versification, while at the same time it threatens (or pretends to threaten) to transgress the
      sonnet's strict boundaries in its act of creation. The poem speaks with two voices at once, in
      tension until its end, exuberantly about to burst out of itself at any moment. As readers, we
      are invited to notice this.</textual></para><para class="po-block e124 e124"><textual class="po-textual">I believe that instances like this have much to teach us about the way texts communicate
      and indeed about the ways in which literary and documentary forms of text serve their
      purposes. Even to characterize it this way gives us an opportunity to see an important
      distinction, if we can generalize to say that </textual><quote class="po-inline e125 e125"><textual class="po-textual">literary</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> texts are characterized
      by the capacity for this kind of irony (an irony that may confirm or deepen evident senses
      even while it may superficially undermine them), while </textual><quote class="po-inline e126 e126"><textual class="po-textual">documentary</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> may describe
      that class of texts in which this kind of variance does not happen or is not supposed to. (We
      do not want aircraft maintenance manuals, scientific reports, or maybe even conference papers
      to present such problems for their readers. This is to say nothing in disparagement of texts
      that show little or no ironic transgression of their own forms: they have their own strengths
      and virtues.) If so, this might help explain why an OHCO model is so well suited for so much
      work in publishing and data processing (in which such misalignments within organizations of
      text must be erased or elided lest their complications destabilize regular operations),
      especially for </textual><quote class="po-inline e127 e127"><textual class="po-textual">born-digital</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> materials (which can be made to conform to these
      constraints in their creation)—while at the same time, a model that imposes a single hierarchy
      can be so frustratingly inept for other purposes, even including the study and representation
      of (something called) </textual><quote class="po-inline e128 e128"><textual class="po-textual">text</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. </textual></para></section><section class="po-hcontainer e129 e129"><title class="po-block e130 e130"><textual class="po-textual">What is text, really?</textual></title><para class="po-block e131 e131"><textual class="po-textual">Other examples of overlap in literary texts give rise to similar questions, while
      continuing to suggest that such ironies and misalignments are not always bugs, but features,
      indeed essential ones. Of particular interest to students of literature, for example, are the
      structures of formal narrative. Necessarily, as soon as these conflict with logical and
      presentational arrangements (such as chapters and paragraphs, which may normally fail to align
      with narrative and dialogue), a model such as XML's, which reflects a simple OHCO, forces us
      to foreground one or the other hierarchy, while likewise inhibiting our ability to see how
      they work together despite (and because of) their tensions, because whichever hierarchy we
      push into the background is not easily or immediately recognizable as a hierarchy.</textual></para><para class="po-block e132 e132"><textual class="po-textual">One vivid example of such a text is Mary Shelley's novel of 1818, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e133 e133" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Frankenstein, or, the Modern Prometheus</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> (revised 1831). A canonical example of
      the Gothic genre, it shows a set of anomalies that are both interestingly illustrative for
      this text, and yet also suggestive of issues for any such text.</textual></para><para class="po-block e134 e134"><textual class="po-textual">We will follow the lead of the 1993 revised statement regarding OHCO (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e135 e135" linkend="Renear1993"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">) in suggesting that any adequate accounting for what the text
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e136 e136"><textual class="po-textual">is</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> must correspond at least generally with our intuitions. A very simple
      intuition is that a text (at any rate, a text of the nineteenth century) is going to be a
      sequence of printed (or manuscript) pages; and indeed, one of the first things we find we can
      do using LMNL is mark, as ranges named </textual><code class="po-atom e137 e137"><textual class="po-textual">page</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, the extents of pages of the novel in
      whatever edition(s) we choose (in this case, the revised edition of 1831, which is the version
      known to most readers), and not only (as is more usual in XML) their starting points. The fact
      that pages may overlap with paragraphs and chapters is not a problem when using a markup
      regime that imposes no containment. And if such a concept of text is evidently too
      unsophisticated to take us far, that's okay too: since the markup technology permits it, we
      can proceed to mark the pages as ranges (not only insert markers for the page breaks) If the
      page hierarchy is interesting (as it may be to students of printed media and their history),
      that is enough. Or even only useful, because it allows us readily to retrieve pages in the
      edition (see </textual><xref class="po-milestone e138 e138" linkend="LuminescentQueries"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">). In any case, marking up pages in addition
      to anything else is easy and straightforward, without concern for whether hierarchies will
      inhibit the markup of other features we expect to see on a closer look. We don't have to
      invent, then test and enforce, any special schemes or implicit processing logic to accomplish
      this, resolving the actual </textual><quote class="po-inline e139 e139"><textual class="po-textual">pages</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, with their content, and not just breaks
      between them.</textual></para><para class="po-block e140 e140"><textual class="po-textual">Of course the ordered hierarchy we will usually prefer will be that of of chapters and
      paragraphs. Yet in this novel, these are not quite adequate for a comprehensive account. Not
      only are there an Introduction and a Preface (assuming we consider them to be part of
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e141 e141"><textual class="po-textual">the text</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, we can think of them to be specialized chapters if we like), but
      also, we find the chapters of the novel do not account for its entirety. (See </textual><xref class="po-milestone e142 e142" linkend="ChaptersOnly"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">). Before the chapters begin we are presented with a framing
      narrative, consisting of letters, one of which (the last) contains several entries, in the
      midst of one of which, the sequence of chapters begins. So the </textual><quote class="po-inline e143 e143"><textual class="po-textual">logical</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> view is
      deeper than most modern novels, having an epistolary form wrapped around the primary
      narrative—the sort of complication that is not unusual in the Gothic genre. A
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e144 e144"><textual class="po-textual">map</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> of the novel showing all this structure is presented in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e145 e145" linkend="StructureMap"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para><note class="po-container e146 e146"><para class="po-block e147 e147"><textual class="po-textual">In RNC notation</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e148 e148" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">novel = element novel { 
  element letter {
    element entry {
      ( content |
        transcription )+
    }
  }
}

transcription = chapter+

chapter = element chapter { content }

content = ( element p { text }+ )</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e149 e149"><textual class="po-textual">Sustaining instances like this:</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e150 e150" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">&lt;novel&gt;
  &lt;letter&gt;
    &lt;entry&gt;
      &lt;p/&gt;
    &lt;/entry&gt;
  &lt;/letter&gt;
  &lt;letter&gt;
    &lt;entry&gt;
      &lt;p/&gt;
      &lt;chapter&gt;&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/chapter&gt;
      &lt;chapter&gt;&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/chapter&gt;
      &lt;chapter&gt;&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/chapter&gt;
    &lt;/entry&gt;
  &lt;/letter&gt;
&lt;/novel&gt;</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e151 e151"><textual class="po-textual">Shelley's </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e152 e152" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">Frankenstein</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> does </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e153 e153" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">not</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, quite, fit this model (due to overlap), unless we are willing to make a
        significant editorial adjustment.</textual></para></note><figure class="po-container e154 e154" xml:id="ChaptersOnly"><title class="po-block e155 e155"><textual class="po-textual">Chapter and page hierarchies overlapping (with a gap)</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e156 e156"><imageobject class="po-container e157 e157"><imagedata class="po-meta e158 e158" fileref="../../../vol13/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-004.png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e159 e159"><para class="po-block e160 e160"><textual class="po-textual">Since the chapters of the book begin only on page 18, there is a gap that must be
          accounted for. The contents of the gap constitute the framing narrative, which resumes
          again at the end of the book (not shown in this closeup).</textual></para></caption></figure><figure class="po-container e161 e161" xml:id="StructureMap"><title class="po-block e162 e162"><textual class="po-textual">A more complete map, showing chapters inside Letter IV</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e163 e163"><imageobject class="po-container e164 e164"><imagedata class="po-meta e165 e165" fileref="../../../vol13/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-005.png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject><caption class="po-container e166 e166"><para class="po-block e167 e167"><textual class="po-textual">A more complete accounting for the </textual><quote class="po-inline e168 e168"><textual class="po-textual">content objects</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> of the novel shows
            four letters, one of which (Letter IV) contains several entries, in the midst of which
            the sequence of chapters begins. Letters also appear embedded in the chapters.</textual></para></caption></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e169 e169"><textual class="po-textual">There is, however, another problem. Chapter 24 (the last) starts inside one entry (dated
      August 19) in the last of four letters, but it continues on after this entry ends, to include
      four more (dated August 26 and September 2, 5, 7 and 12). In other words, there is apparently
      an overlap between the hierarchy of chapters, and the hierarchy of letters containing entries.
      This is not a well ordered hierarchy. (See </textual><xref class="po-milestone e170 e170" linkend="Ch24Overlap"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> for a closeup
      view)</textual></para><figure class="po-container e171 e171" xml:id="Ch24Overlap"><title class="po-block e172 e172"><textual class="po-textual">Overlap in Chapter 24</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e173 e173"><imageobject class="po-container e174 e174"><imagedata class="po-meta e175 e175" fileref="../../../vol13/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-006.png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e176 e176"><para class="po-block e177 e177"><textual class="po-textual">This closeup of the map of the novel shows where Chapter 24 overlaps with the framing
          structures (the four letters from the main narrator, Walton, to his sister) and the
          entries in Letter IV.</textual></para></caption></figure><para class="po-block e178 e178"><textual class="po-textual">Yet there is another accounting for this problem. Maybe this overlap is only apparent, if
      the chapter hierarchy is not the </textual><quote class="po-inline e179 e179"><textual class="po-textual">real</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> hierarchy of the book, but merely
      overlaid on top it, like the pages. Maybe the chapter hierarchy and the hierarchy of letters
      and their entries are in fact two different views. Indeed there is another set of ranges we
      might think about, namely the narrative structure as such. The story appears within a story,
      and within the main story are subordinate narratives: three letters and a long narration by
      Frankenstein's creature himself. This hierarchy can be traced, tagged and mapped as well. In
      fact it should include also direct discourse (that is, spans of dialogue) and other
      attributions and sources, which may overlap and conflict with both paragraph and page
      boundaries. A map of the novel showing this hierarchy is shown in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e180 e180" linkend="NarrativeMap"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref></para><figure class="po-container e181 e181" xml:id="NarrativeMap"><title class="po-block e182 e182"><textual class="po-textual">The narrative structure of the novel</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e183 e183"><imageobject class="po-container e184 e184"><imagedata class="po-meta e185 e185" fileref="../../../vol13/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-007.png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject><caption class="po-container e186 e186"><para class="po-block e187 e187"><textual class="po-textual">In this variant, chapters are not shown, and we see only the narrative structure of
            nested stories (letters, stories, dialogue) that constitutes the
              </textual><quote class="po-inline e188 e188"><textual class="po-textual">substance</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> of the book. Direct discourse is noted. Of course, this
            hierarchy still overlaps with the page sequence.</textual></para></caption></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e189 e189"><textual class="po-textual">Mapping out narrative boundaries has always been one of the challenges of OHCO-based
      models, if not because narrative fails at being well structured (typically it does not), then
      because they so often conflict with the </textual><quote class="po-inline e190 e190"><textual class="po-textual">logical</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> structures of paragraphs and
      sections or chapters—the </textual><quote class="po-inline e191 e191"><textual class="po-textual">published view</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. As long as the range space was
      occupied by one and one hierarchy only (that is, as long as the data model recognized only a
      single hierarchy), and as long as the (so-called) logical hierarchy of the published view was
      given pride of place, it has been more or less prohibitively difficult to use XML to mark up
      any hierarchy (or indeed any phenomena at all) that overlapped chapters and paragraphs.
      Paradoxically, the ideology that </textual><quote class="po-inline e192 e192"><textual class="po-textual">descriptive</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> markup should serve multiple
      purposes, and not be limited to presentation (see </textual><xref class="po-milestone e193 e193" linkend="Coombs1987"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">, </textual><xref class="po-milestone e194 e194" linkend="Renear2004"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">), may have hindered this also, since there is at least a presumption
      that one should be able to mark up paragraphs and chapters, and yet also mark up everything
      else one might wish to describe. (Because text, by definition, is an OHCO, there will
        </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e195 e195" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">ipso facto</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> never be a conflict between the so-called
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e196 e196"><textual class="po-textual">logical</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> structure and anything else that is </textual><quote class="po-inline e197 e197"><textual class="po-textual">really there</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">.) In
      other words, the XML data model interferes with the realization of a regime of descriptive
      markup that is fully adequate to the principle's potential. The range model offered by LMNL
      presents no such difficulties: using LMNL syntax, marking these hierarchies together is only
      as difficult as marking each separately.</textual></para><para class="po-block e198 e198"><textual class="po-textual">Yet at the same time, there does seem to be a stress between these hierarchies that we do
      not feel, for example, from the misalignment of either of them with the pagination. We do not
      expect pagination to align with anything, regarding it as an incidental consequence of
      typesetting, not a reflection of </textual><quote class="po-inline e199 e199"><textual class="po-textual">the text</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. Accordingly, we are tempted to set
      aside the pagination structure as merely incidental to anything else (at least until it turns
      out there is some sort of echoing or consonance). Yet between the narrative and the published
      view (the chapters and paragraphs)—most particularly, since the published view must include
      (for this novel) the letters and entries that </textual><quote class="po-inline e200 e200"><textual class="po-textual">wrap</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> the chapter sequence (except
      where they don't)—the reader faces a similar kind of phenomenogical stress as we have observed
      in poetry. Is there an irony here, serving any sort of purpose (or creating any sort of
      effect) like the effect of sentences and phrases in poetry pushing and pulling against verse
      lines? Apparently there is, if we consider how our attention hardly shifts, as readers, across
      the boundary in Chapter 24, back out to the framing narrative in which it is embedded, like
      waking up from a nightmare—only to discover it is not a dream, when the monstrous creature at
      the center of the tale next appears on the scene, no longer only hearsay, but breathing,
      speaking, imprecating. (Or so the story says.)</textual></para><para class="po-block e201 e201"><textual class="po-textual">Thus we are brought back to the text. (Really.) Examining the boundaries between chapters
      (the published view) and the entries in the letters that contain them shows us how we get into
      this trouble in the first place—because the rendering of these transitions in this edition (as
      seen in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e202 e202" linkend="pages1831"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">) leaves it somewhat doubtful that the reader will easily
      construe exactly how things are set up—at least as long as she or he is shaking herself awake.
      Indeed, we are inclined to ask, shouldn't Chapter 24 really end on page 188, with
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e203 e203"><textual class="po-textual">Walton, in continuation</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">? The reader must be the judge. Interestingly, to the
      extent I have been able to determine the question by looking at various editions of this
      frequently-reprinted novel, the 1831 revision by Mary Shelley is actually ambiguous on this
      point, there being no page headers or other indicators to suggest that we are still inside
      Chapter 24 as the framing narrative resumes. Yet in almost every subsequent edition I have
      been able to find, </textual><quote class="po-inline e204 e204"><textual class="po-textual">Chapter 24</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> page headers continue through to the end.</textual><footnote class="po-popup e205 e205"><para class="po-block e206 e206"><textual class="po-textual">The only exceptions I have found are the online edition from Romantic Circles (see
            </textual><link class="po-inline e207 e207" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/frankenstein</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">) and a 1934 edition edited by
          Harrison Smith and Robert Haas (with memorable engravings by Lynd Ward), which has no page
          headers, and does promote the </textual><quote class="po-inline e208 e208"><textual class="po-textual">Walton, in continuation</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> header on the entry
          of August 26 to the level of a chapter heading (thus implicitly ending Chapter 24).</textual></para></footnote></para><figure class="po-container e209 e209" xml:id="pages1831"><title class="po-block e210 e210"><textual class="po-textual">Structural boundaries on two pages from the 1831 edition</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e211 e211"><imageobject class="po-container e212 e212"><imagedata class="po-meta e213 e213" fileref="../../../vol13/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-008.jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><para class="po-block e214 e214"><textual class="po-textual">A few pages later, Frankenstein comes to the end of his narration, and Walton (the
        author of the letters) resumes. In this edition, we might be forgiven for thinking of this
        as tucked within, rather than ending, Chapter 24.</textual></para><mediaobject class="po-container e215 e215"><imageobject class="po-container e216 e216"><imagedata class="po-meta e217 e217" fileref="../../../vol13/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-009.jpg"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e218 e218"><textual class="po-textual">Almost every edition of Frankenstein I have checked ends Chapter 24 not here, with
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e219 e219"><textual class="po-textual">Walton, in continuation</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, but only at the end of the novel as a whole. This
      isn't the case everywhere: indeed, to the extent that they appear to have thought about it at
      all, editors have sometimes been able to </textual><quote class="po-inline e220 e220"><textual class="po-textual">correct</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> it. In effect, these editions
      make the claim at least implicitly that the rendering of the final passages of Walton's letter
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e221 e221"><textual class="po-textual">inside</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> Chapter 24 is an error or lapse, and that the correct form of the
      novel is, in fact, more like an ordered hierarchy of content objects. Chapter 1 begins, and
      Chapter 24 ends, the manuscript that Walton transcribes from Victor.</textual><note class="po-container e222 e222"><para class="po-block e223 e223"><textual class="po-textual">Since this paper was first drafted, I have learned more about the textual transmission
          of Frankenstein, which complicates this picture significantly, without substantially
          challenging the argument here. In the original 1818 edition, indeed, the chapters (along
          with the framing narrative) are grouped into volumes. Yet the same question arises as to
          whether the final passages (entries in Walton's letter from August 26 - September 12)
          should be included within the last chapter (Chapter VII) of Volume III. Considering them
          as external to it does </textual><quote class="po-inline e224 e224"><textual class="po-textual">regularize</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> the shape of the novel along similar
          lines to what I have discussed as applying to the structure of 1831—indeed with an added
          dimension, since the tripartite division into volumes reflects the tripartite division of
          Victor's narrative (while it does not entirely correspond with, inasmuch as it must also
          comprise the leading and trailing sections). Moreover, manuscript evidence that a
          two-volume structure was subsequently recast into three volumes suggests that the eventual
          three-volume structure (which neatly corresponds to the clean nesting of a
            </textual><quote class="po-inline e225 e225"><textual class="po-textual">corrected</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> 1831 text) was a design decision on the part of the author. See
          Robinson (email) 2014, Robinson 1996, SGA [date], and Hindle 1992. Additionally, a set of
          invaluable resources for studying the textual history of the novel is at the Shelley
          Godwin Archive (</textual><link class="po-inline e226 e226" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/</textual></link></para></note></para><para class="po-block e227 e227"><textual class="po-textual">In this reading, the hierarchy of the chapters as published is really subordinate to the
      hierarchy of entries of letters with their contents. (See </textual><xref class="po-milestone e228 e228" linkend="RectifiedMap"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual"> for
      such a </textual><quote class="po-inline e229 e229"><textual class="po-textual">rectified</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> view.) This would indeed have the effect of reconciling the
      form of the novel—its internal form, even if its external form (the chapters as typeset) is
      somewhat misleading—into a single ordered hierarchy. The novel is comprised of four letters,
      one of which has several entries; of these, one contains a transcription of a long narrative
      presented in a sequence of chapters. Chapters (or the contents of letters and entries outside
      the chapters) contain paragraphs or other things such as letters and quotations.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e230 e230" xml:id="RectifiedMap"><title class="po-block e231 e231"><textual class="po-textual">A </textual><quote class="po-inline e232 e232"><textual class="po-textual">rectified</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> view of the narrative and chapter hierarchies
        together</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e233 e233"><imageobject class="po-container e234 e234"><imagedata class="po-meta e235 e235" fileref="../../../vol13/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-010.png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para class="po-block e236 e236"><textual class="po-textual">Thus corrected, the narrative view has the interesting property of aligning with the
      chapter view to a very great extent, if not entirely. The incidences of alignment (or the lack
      thereof) with other factors such as pagination, or quoted dialogue, turn out also to be rather
      interesting, once one starts examining them closely. One can learn a great deal by executing
      queries such as are depicted in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e237 e237" linkend="LuminescentQueries"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">. (For example, there is
      the remarkable fact that chapters starting at Chapter 19 all start on new pages, as if they
      had been copy fit: coincidence, or evidence of something?)</textual><footnote class="po-popup e238 e238"><para class="po-block e239 e239"><textual class="po-textual">On four occasions, dialogue overlaps with paragraphs, but this is not many considering
          there are also 304 marked ranges of directly quoted discourse that do not. Given markup in
          LMNL syntax, a LMNL processor can be used to find these instances (see </textual><xref class="po-milestone e240 e240" linkend="LuminescentQueries"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">).</textual></para></footnote><textual class="po-textual"> In particular, there is the striking alignment between the story that occurs at
      the center of the novel (the narration told by the creature to Victor, who tells it to Walton)
      and the chapter structure, inasmuch as it contains exactly six chapters, and starts and ends
      with them.</textual><note class="po-container e241 e241"><para class="po-block e242 e242"><textual class="po-textual">This is especially interesting in light of the observations of Mary Douglas regarding
            </textual><quote class="po-inline e243 e243"><textual class="po-textual">ring structures</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> in her amazing treatment of such structures in oral and
          written literature (</textual><xref class="po-milestone e244 e244" linkend="Douglas2007"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">). However Mary Shelley came to define
          this structure for the first published edition of Frankenstein—only to revise it or see it
          revised in the subsequent edition of 1831—it certainly </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e245 e245" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">appears</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> to matter that the resulting structure is one that is attested
          elsewhere in imaginative literature.</textual></para></note></para><para class="po-block e246 e246"><textual class="po-textual">One is left with the inescapable conclusion that the ordered hierarchy of content objects
      is a </textual><quote class="po-inline e247 e247"><textual class="po-textual">real</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> thing—but also that it is contingent, not necessary, and the result
      of an evolution in media and forms of expression, and in this case only imperfectly realized
      or expressed in the printed medium. We do not have to regard the relation between the
      narrative structure and the formal chapter/paragraph organization as </textual><quote class="po-inline e248 e248"><textual class="po-textual">ironic</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">;
      instead perhaps other tropes come to mind, perhaps metaphor in this case. Note that here we
      are not speaking of a metaphorical relation between any two levels of any hierarchy, such as
      between Walton's narrative and Victor's contained narrative—which we might also see. Rather,
      it is in the alignment of the structure of the narrative as a set of attested
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e249 e249"><textual class="po-textual">documents</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> (including Walton's letters and his transcript of Victor's story</textual><note class="po-container e250 e250"><para class="po-block e251 e251"><textual class="po-textual">And, intriguingly, perhaps of physical attestation of Victor's veracity in the form of
          transcripts of letters made by the creature and given by him to Victor, who in turn shows
          them to Walton.</textual></para></note><textual class="po-textual">), and the structure of the novel as a published work in conventional
      (chapter/paragraph) form.</textual></para><para class="po-block e252 e252"><textual class="po-textual">Yet to argue that the correct reading is that these must be aligned, with no possibility
      of intentional misarrangement, as a consequence of what it is to be a text, </textual><quote class="po-inline e253 e253"><textual class="po-textual">because ...
        OHCO</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> (which is not, mind you, what was ever proposed for OHCO ... it’s just that
      somehow this coincided with the push for SGML, then to be wired into XML), is to suppose we
      know the answer before we have pondered the question. Instead, alerted to the possibility that
      this novel (and others) might well perturb, if not altogether defy, its own well-ordered
      arrangement—the possibility, that is, of an ironic stress between two or more of its internal
      and presented structures—the fact that we can reconcile them here becomes important. If this
      novel is an ordered hierarchy, an arrangement of nested narratives (that happens incidentally
      to be segmented, in part, into chapters), it is a </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e254 e254" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">particular</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">
      ordered hierarchy of particular content objects. Even the possibility of this reading, that
      is, vindicates the idea that such a model (which indeed is satisfyingly symmetrical in this
      case) was indeed part of the concept of the novel itself. The novel is structured as it is not
      because of some prior rule that texts are always hierarchies, but because Mary Shelley
      designed it like this. (She put the hierarchy there much in the way an XML schema designer
      would have. Except that typesetters subsequently failed to understand her full intent, or the
      implication of it.) At the same time, were the typographer to do a better job representing the
      shift back to the framing story when Frankenstein's narrative ends, it would make it no less
      startling (indeed, maybe more so) when the creature himself appears on the scene—by this
      reading, </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e255 e255" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">outside</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual"> the chapters of the book. A boundary is
      transgressed in either case; indeed in this reading even more strongly, since the separation
      of the framing narrative indicated by a clean ending to Chapter 24 is suddenly broken, and we,
      with the narrator, are brought face to face with something we would prefer never to have
      met.Likewise we can see how our vindication of an OHCO here is only provisional: it applies to
      this novel alone (as long as we take the paginated structure to be incidental, and leave aside
      the occasional misalignment of dialogue speeches with paragraphs), and is liable to slip with
      any new example of a narrative that violates it.</textual></para><para class="po-block e256 e256"><textual class="po-textual">In this respect Frankenstein is not singular among works of literature. Meanwhile, the
      OHCO is alive and well, but not because it is inevitable or the </textual><quote class="po-inline e257 e257"><textual class="po-textual">only correct</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">
      and possible way of representing texts. Its power is not in any generalization regarding
        </textual><quote class="po-inline e258 e258"><textual class="po-textual">texts</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> or some set of artifacts we regard as being </textual><quote class="po-inline e259 e259"><textual class="po-textual">text</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">, as
      much as it is in its own act of </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e260 e260" role="ital"><textual class="po-textual">fiat</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, its description,
      rationalization and legitimization of hierarchical models in systems as we are building
      them.</textual></para></section><appendix class="po-hcontainer e261 e261"><title class="po-block e262 e262"><textual class="po-textual">More sonnets</textual></title><para class="po-block e263 e263"><textual class="po-textual">All these diagrams are generated from poems encoded in LMNL.</textual></para><figure class="po-container e264 e264"><title class="po-block e265 e265"><quote class="po-inline e266 e266"><textual class="po-textual">Leda and the Swan</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> by W. B. Yeats (1924)</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e267 e267"><imageobject class="po-container e268 e268"><imagedata class="po-meta e269 e269" fileref="../../../vol13/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-011.png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject><caption class="po-container e270 e270"><para class="po-block e271 e271"><textual class="po-textual">This example shows phrases overlapping lines (enjambment) in the first quatrain, and
            again at the beginning of the sestet.</textual></para></caption></mediaobject></figure><figure class="po-container e272 e272"><title class="po-block e273 e273"><quote class="po-inline e274 e274"><textual class="po-textual">Correspondences</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> by Charles Baudelaire (1924)</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e275 e275"><imageobject class="po-container e276 e276"><imagedata class="po-meta e277 e277" fileref="../../../vol13/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-012.png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e278 e278"><para class="po-block e279 e279"><textual class="po-textual">In this example, each major division (quatrains and sestet) constitutes a sentence,
          and phrases nest perfectly inside lines, with no overlap.</textual></para></caption></figure><figure class="po-container e280 e280"><title class="po-block e281 e281"><quote class="po-inline e282 e282"><textual class="po-textual">The Silken Tent</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> by Robert Frost (1942)</textual></title><mediaobject class="po-container e283 e283"><imageobject class="po-container e284 e284"><imagedata class="po-meta e285 e285" fileref="../../../vol13/graphics/Piez01/Piez01-013.png"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject><caption class="po-container e286 e286"><para class="po-block e287 e287"><textual class="po-textual">This example shows almost no overlap, except at the beginning of the sestet (i.e., at
          the center), where the language briefly </textual><quote class="po-inline e288 e288"><textual class="po-textual">tugs</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> on the verse.</textual></para></caption></figure></appendix><appendix class="po-hcontainer e289 e289"><title class="po-block e290 e290"><textual class="po-textual">Using LMNL to mark up narrative</textual></title><para class="po-block e291 e291"><textual class="po-textual">Reflecting the lifting, in the LMNL model, of the prohibition against overlap, it becomes
      a comparatively simple exercise to provide a LMNL-syntax description of purely narrative
      structures, aside even from paragraphs. Higher-level narrative structures are marked up as
        </textual><code class="po-atom e292 e292"><textual class="po-textual">story</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> ranges (start or end tags for </textual><code class="po-atom e293 e293"><textual class="po-textual">page</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> ranges may also
      appear):</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e294 e294" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">[page [n}86{] [ed}1831{]}or denial of this opinion. For the first
time, also, I felt what the duties of a creator towards his creature were, and
that I ought to render him happy before I complained of his wickedness. These
motives urged me to comply with his demand. We crossed the ice, therefore, and
ascended the opposite rock. The air was cold, and the rain again began to
descend; we entered the hut, the fiend with an air of exultation, I with a
heavy heart and depressed spirits. But I consented to listen, and seating
myself by the fire which my odious companion had lighted, he thus began his
tale.{p]{chapter]
[story [who}The creature{]}[chapter [n}11{]}
[head}Chapter 11{head]
[p}It is with considerable difficulty that I remember the original era of my
being...</textual></programlisting><para class="po-block e295 e295"><textual class="po-textual">Similarly, dialogue may be marked up as </textual><code class="po-atom e296 e296"><textual class="po-textual">said</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">, as per TEI, without worrying
      about boundaries of paragraphs (which conflict rarely but not never) or pages (conflicting
      frequently):</textual></para><programlisting class="po-block e297 e297" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">[p}[said [who}Prof Waldman{]}I am happy,{said] said M. Waldman,
[said [who}Prof Waldman{]}to have gained a disciple; and if your application
equals your ability, I have no doubt of your success. Chemistry is that branch
of natural philosophy in which the greatest improvements have been and may be
made; it is on that account that I have made it my peculiar study; but at the
same time, I have not neglected the other branches of science. A man would make
but a very sorry chemist if he attended to that department of human knowledge
alone. If your wish is to become really a man of science and not merely a petty
experimentalist,{page]
[page [n}36{n] [ed}1831{ed]}I should advise you to apply to every
branch of natural philosophy, including mathematics.{said]{p]</textual></programlisting></appendix><appendix class="po-hcontainer e298 e298" xml:id="LuminescentQueries"><title class="po-block e299 e299"><textual class="po-textual">Querying LMNL</textual></title><para class="po-block e300 e300"><textual class="po-textual">One of the capabilities of Luminescent (a LMNL processing framework) is querying over an
      XML </textual><quote class="po-inline e301 e301"><textual class="po-textual">compiled</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> version of a LMNL document. (Luminescent is described in </textual><xref class="po-milestone e302 e302" linkend="Piez2012"><textual class="po-textual">Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao Pippo! Ciao</textual></xref><textual class="po-textual">). For example, here is an XQuery expression that returns the number of
      the page (in the 1831 edition) on which </textual><quote class="po-inline e303 e303"><textual class="po-textual">Volney</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual"> is mentioned. (Functions named
      with the </textual><code class="po-atom e304 e304"><textual class="po-textual">lm</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> prefix are defined by
      Luminescent.)</textual><programlisting class="po-block e305 e305" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">let $novel  := db:open('LMNL-library','Frankenstein.xlmnl')/*
return lm:ranges('page',$novel)[contains(lm:range-value(.),'Volney')]
  /lm:annotations('n',.)/lm:annotation-value(.)</textual></programlisting><textual class="po-textual">This
      returns </textual><quote class="po-inline e306 e306"><textual class="po-textual">102</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">. (If Volney were mentioned more than once, more than one page
      number would be returned.)</textual></para><para class="po-block e307 e307"><textual class="po-textual">Here is a query for distinct values of annotations indicating speakers (</textual><code class="po-atom e308 e308"><textual class="po-textual">who</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
      annotations on </textual><code class="po-atom e309 e309"><textual class="po-textual">said</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
      ranges):</textual><programlisting class="po-block e310 e310" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">let $novel  := db:open('LMNL-library','Frankenstein.xlmnl')/*
return distinct-values(
  lm:ranges('said',$novel)/
  lm:annotations('who',.)/lm:annotation-value(.) )</textual></programlisting><textual class="po-textual">26
      strings are returned, including</textual><quote class="po-inline e311 e311"><textual class="po-textual">the Creature</textual></quote><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></para><para class="po-block e312 e312"><textual class="po-textual">Here is a query that returns all the speeches attributed to the Creature (or substitute
      any
      character):</textual><programlisting class="po-block e313 e313" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">let $novel  := db:open('LMNL-library','Frankenstein.xlmnl')/*
let $who    := 'The creature'
return lm:ranges('said',$novel)[lm:annotations('who',.) = $who]
  /lm:range-value-ws-trim(.)</textual></programlisting><textual class="po-textual">48
      speeches are returned.</textual></para><para class="po-block e314 e314"><textual class="po-textual">Count the ranges overlapping </textual><code class="po-atom e315 e315"><textual class="po-textual">said</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> ranges, excluding </textual><code class="po-atom e316 e316"><textual class="po-textual">page</textual></code><textual class="po-textual">
      ranges:</textual><programlisting class="po-block e317 e317" xml:space="preserve"><textual class="po-textual">let $novel  := db:open('LMNL-library','Frankenstein.xlmnl')/*
return count(
  lm:ranges('said',$novel)/lm:overlapping-ranges(.)[not(lm:named('page',.))] )</textual></programlisting><textual class="po-textual">We
      get 4. (Another query shows they are all </textual><code class="po-atom e318 e318"><textual class="po-textual">p</textual></code><textual class="po-textual"> ranges.)</textual></para></appendix><bibliography class="po-hcontainer e319 e319"><title class="po-block e320 e320"><textual class="po-textual">Bibliography</textual></title><bibliomixed class="po-block e321 e321" xml:id="Barnard1995" xreflabel="Barnard et al. 1995"><textual class="po-textual">Barnard, David, Lou Burnard,
      Jean-Pierre Gaspart, Lynne A. Price, C. M. Sperberg-McQueen and Giovanni Battista Varile.
      1995. Hierarchical Encoding of Text: Technical Problems and SGML Solutions. Computers and the
      Humanities, Vol. 29, No. 3, The Text Encoding Initiative: Background and Context (1995), pp.
      211-231.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e322 e322" xml:id="Coombs1987" xreflabel="Coombs et al. 1987"><textual class="po-textual">James H. Coombs, Allen H.
      Renear, and Steven J. DeRose. 1987. “Markup Systems and The Future of Scholarly Text
      Processing.” Communications of the ACM, 30:11 933-947 (1987).</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e323 e323" xml:id="Douglas2007" xreflabel="Douglas 2007"><textual class="po-textual">Douglas, Mary. </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e324 e324"><textual class="po-textual">Thinking in
        Circles: An Essay in Ring Composition</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">. New Haven: Yale University Press, 2007. </textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e325 e325" xml:id="FRBR" xreflabel="FRBR"><textual class="po-textual">Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records.
      See
        </textual><link class="po-inline e326 e326" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.ifla.org/publications/functional-requirements-for-bibliographic-records</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e327 e327" xml:id="Hindle1992"><textual class="po-textual">Hindle, Maurice, ed. Introduction.
        </textual><emphasis class="po-inline e328 e328"><textual class="po-textual">Frankenstein</textual></emphasis><textual class="po-textual">, by Mary Shelley. Penguin Books, 1992.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e329 e329" xml:id="Piez2001" xreflabel="Piez 2001"><textual class="po-textual">Piez, Wendell. “Beyond the ‘Descriptive vs.
      Procedural’ Distinction.” Extreme Markup Languages 2001. See
        </textual><link class="po-inline e330 e330" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://conferences.idealliance.org/extreme/html/2001/Piez01/EML2001Piez01.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e331 e331" xml:id="Piez2012" xreflabel="Piez 2012"><textual class="po-textual">Piez, Wendell. “Luminescent: parsing LMNL
      by XSLT upconversion.” Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada,
      August 7 - 10, 2012. In Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012. Balisage Series
      on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:</textual><biblioid class="po-atom e332 doi e332"><textual class="po-textual">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Piez01</textual></biblioid><textual class="po-textual">. See
        </textual><link class="po-inline e333 e333" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://balisage.net/Proceedings/vol8/html/Piez01/BalisageVol8-Piez01.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e334 e334" xml:id="Renear1990" xreflabel="Renear et al., 1990"><textual class="po-textual">DeRose, Stephen J., David
      Durand, Elli Mylonas, and Allen Renear. “What is Text, Really?” Journal of Computing in Higher
      Education. Winter 1990, Vol. I (2), 3-26.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e335 e335" xml:id="Robinson1996"><textual class="po-textual">Robinson, Charles E. Introduction. In The Frankenstein
      Notebooks (Garland, 1996). Republished by the Shelley-Godwin Archive </textual><link class="po-inline e336 e336" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/contents/frankenstein/the-frankenstein-notebooks-introduction" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/contents/frankenstein/the-frankenstein-notebooks-introduction</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e337 e337" xml:id="Robinson2014"><textual class="po-textual">Robinson, Charles E. Email with the author. July 2014.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e338 e338" xml:id="Renear1993" xreflabel="Renear et al., 1993"><textual class="po-textual">Renear, Allen, Elli Mylonas,
      and David Durand. “Refining our Notion of What Text Really Is: The Problem of Overlapping
      Hierarchies.” See
      </textual><link class="po-inline e339 e339" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://cds.library.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e340 e340" xml:id="Renear2004" xreflabel="Renear 2004"><textual class="po-textual">Renear, Allen. “Text Encoding”. In A Companion to Digital Humanities, ed. Susan Schreibman, Ray Siemens, John Unsworth. Oxford: Blackwell, 2004.  
      </textual><link class="po-inline e341 e341" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion/</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed><bibliomixed class="po-block e342 e342" xml:id="TEIch20" xreflabel="TEI, chapter 20"><textual class="po-textual">Text Encoding Initiative (TEI). P5:
      Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange, chapter 20, Non-hierarchical
      Structures. See
      </textual><link class="po-inline e343 e343" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple"><textual class="po-textual">http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/NH.html</textual></link><textual class="po-textual">.</textual></bibliomixed></bibliography></article></classedDocument>