<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3"><title>Musical Variants: Encoding, Analysis and Visualization</title><info><confgroup><conftitle>Balisage: The Markup Conference 2013</conftitle><confdates>August 6 - 9, 2013</confdates></confgroup><abstract><para>The following paper proposes a model for the encoding of variance in music that is
                based on traditional models and implemented using the data framework offered by the
                Music Encoding Initiative (MEI). It introduces concepts derived from the Functional
                Requirements for Bibliographic Records (FRBR) to music editing. This combination is
                then used to auto-generate proposals for the filiation of sources and to illustrate
                the relationships between the encoded sources. The purpose of this system is to
                structure the editorial process, provide a better overview of the material, and to
                inform the editor's findings. It will be developed and used by the <emphasis role="ital">Freischütz Digital</emphasis> project, the goal of which is to
                create a digital scholarly edition of Carl Maria von Weber's opera <emphasis role="ital">Der Freischütz</emphasis> based on complete encodings of all
                relevant sources. The edition will be completed by Summer 2015.</para></abstract><author><personname><firstname>Johannes</firstname><surname>Kepper</surname></personname><personblurb><para>Dr. Johannes Kepper is Musicologist at the University of Paderborn. He works
                    in the <emphasis role="ital">Freischütz Digital</emphasis> project and
                    participates actively in the development of MEI.</para><para>Johannes holds a Magister Artium in Musicology and a Diploma in Media
                    Informatics from the University of Paderborn. He finished his dissertation in
                    2009 on the topic of <quote>Music editions in the era of new
                    media</quote>.</para></personblurb><affiliation><orgname>University of Paderborn, Germany</orgname></affiliation><email>kepper@edirom.de</email></author><author><personname><firstname>Perry</firstname><surname>Roland</surname></personname><personblurb><para>Perry Roland is Music Metadata Librarian at the University of Virginia Music
                    Library where he participates in the creation of new digital resources and their
                    metadata.</para><para>Perry holds a Bachelor of Science in Music Education from Concord College,
                    Athens, West Virginia; a Master of Arts in Music Composition from the University
                    of Virginia, Charlottesville; and a Master of Science in Library and Information
                    Science from the University of North Carolina at Greensboro. He is the
                    originator of MEI.</para></personblurb><affiliation><orgname>University of Virginia Library, USA</orgname></affiliation><email>pdr4h@eservices.virginia.edu</email></author><author><personname><firstname>Daniel</firstname><surname>Röwenstrunk</surname></personname><personblurb><para>Daniel Röwenstrunk is Computer Scientist and the Project Director of <emphasis role="ital">Freischütz Digital</emphasis> at the University of
                    Paderborn.</para><para>Daniel holds a Diploma in Business Computing with a focus on Decision Support
                    and Operations Research from the University of Paderborn. He has worked in
                    humanities projects since 2006 and has strong interests in digital editions and
                    modeling of music.</para></personblurb><affiliation><orgname>University of Paderborn, Germany</orgname></affiliation><email>roewenstrunk@edirom.de</email></author><legalnotice><para>This work is made available under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommerical-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License (<link xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</link>).</para></legalnotice></info><section><title>Introduction</title><para>The core tasks of a scholarly edition of music are the investigation, documentation,
            and explanation of the transmission of the work. In traditional textual criticism, this
            is done by examining all available sources, comparing the textual version(s) they
            contain, tracing the filiation of sources, selecting a main (or "base") source, and
            providing an edited text that resembles the main source as closely as is reasonably
            possible. The textual variation recorded in this process is traditionally documented in
            a separate list that identifies readings by movement, measure, and (sometimes) beat
            within the measure and voice. In contrast to traditional print publications, which
            restrict themselves to a single base text because of pragmatic and/or financial
            considerations, in the digital medium one may include all pertinent sources without
            regard to their relevance to filiation. In addition, the determination of a base source,
            and thus a listing of variants compared only to it, is not necessary. The edition can
            therefore document all readings, not just a single edited version of the text [<xref linkend="bohl2011"/>]. In fact, it is now possible to provide all historically
            legitimate alternative versions of the text simultaneously.</para></section><section><title>Musical Variants</title><para>Based on earlier literature [<xref linkend="feder1987"/>], German musicologist
            Bernhard R. Appel proposed a systematic model for variants in his article
                <quote>Variatio delectat – Variatio perturbat</quote> [<xref linkend="appel2005"/>,
            pp. 7–24]. He identifies four main types of local variation between sources: <emphasis role="ital">additions</emphasis> (<quote>Ergänzung</quote>), <emphasis role="ital">deletions</emphasis> (<quote>Streichung</quote>), <emphasis role="ital">substitutions</emphasis> (<quote>Ersetzungen</quote>) and <emphasis role="ital">rearrangements</emphasis> (<quote>Umstellungen</quote>). An <emphasis role="ital">addition</emphasis> denotes the introduction of new material to the musical text,
            as compared with an older version (AB ⇒ AXB). In contrast, a <emphasis role="ital">deletion</emphasis> is characterized by leaving out parts of the text (ABC ⇒ AC). A
            variant where a portion of the musical text is replaced by another is identified as a
                <emphasis role="ital">substitution</emphasis> (ABC ⇒ AXC). In this case, the
            original portion and its replacement may differ in length. In the last species of
            variant, <emphasis role="ital">rearrangements</emphasis>, the musical text itself is not
            changed, but portions are reordered (ABC ⇒ ACB). With regard to their effect on the
            musical text, Appel points out that all variants can be assigned to one of these four
            types.</para><para>However, considering the fact that the actual filiation of sources is very often all
            but clear [<xref linkend="feder1987"/>, p. 64], <emphasis role="ital">additions</emphasis> and <emphasis role="ital">deletions</emphasis> may be
            consolidated into a larger category. That is, when it is not possible to establish the
            direction of dependency between two sources, the only possible observation in both cases
            is that one source holds text not present in the other. Therefore, considering both
                <emphasis role="ital">additions</emphasis> and <emphasis role="ital">deletions</emphasis> as the exchange of <quote>something</quote> with
                <quote>nothing</quote>, and thus special cases of <emphasis role="ital">substitution</emphasis>, the number of types may be reduced. A <emphasis role="ital">rearrangement</emphasis> may be thought of as two <emphasis role="ital">substitutions</emphasis> at different positions. What would be lost when taking
            this perspective, though, is the identity of the material omitted in one place and
            inserted at another, so that a <emphasis role="ital">rearrangement</emphasis> requires
            an additional pairing of two atomic <emphasis role="ital">substitutions</emphasis>.
            Therefore, the number of variant types may be reduced to only two—<emphasis role="ital">substitutions</emphasis> and <emphasis role="ital">rearrangements</emphasis>.</para><para>When comparing more than two sources, variants amongst them may also be classified by
            another taxonomy. German philology offers the terms <emphasis role="ital">Bindefehler</emphasis> and <emphasis role="ital">Trennfehler</emphasis>. A
                <emphasis role="ital">Bindefehler</emphasis> is a variant reading shared by two or
            more, but not all, sources. By sharing a particular variant, the sources are logically
            connected and therefore have a closer filial relationship than sources that do not share
            this material. A <emphasis role="ital">Trennfehler</emphasis> describes the opposite
            case. It denotes a variant that distinguishes two sources that have been subjected to
            either a <emphasis role="ital">substitution</emphasis> (in the broad sense mentioned
            above) or a <emphasis role="ital">rearrangement</emphasis>. A <emphasis role="ital">Trennfehler</emphasis> argues for a distant relationship between sources. A variant
            in the musical text transmitted in at least three sources is therefore always a
                <emphasis role="ital">Bindefehler</emphasis> for some of these sources, and a
                <emphasis role="ital">Trennfehler</emphasis> for others at the same time.<footnote><para>Additional explanation of this concept is available in <xref linkend="maas1960"/>.</para></footnote></para><para>Textual variation may appear at various levels—from single notes with a different
            pitch to revised melody lines of almost any length and from the <emphasis role="ital">addition</emphasis> of measures and measure groups to the <emphasis role="ital">rearrangement</emphasis> of entire movements. It is also important to keep in mind
            that, while common music notation (CMN) features a very clear structure of measures and
            staves, the visual structure of music notation does not limit the musical content in any
            way and must not be confused with the semantics of the musical content. Composers and
            copyists alike have never restricted themselves to changes that do not cross this
            structure. When a melody line is replaced by another, changes to several measures may be
            required, without affecting the place of these measures in the context of the notation
            as a whole. Like the conventions of line, paragraph, and page breaks in literary text,
            the visual structures of CMN are simply conventions that facilitate reading and
            writing—no more, no less.</para></section><section><title>Encoding Variants in MEI</title><para>In the case of editorial markup, MEI implements the same concepts and mechanisms as
            TEI (Text Encoding Initiative). Those familiar with TEI can therefore safely assume the
            same concepts behind the elements of the same name in MEI. Thus, encoding variance in
            MEI is based on use of the <code>&lt;app&gt;</code> element, which is allowed at almost
            every level. It identifies a portion of the musical text that varies among different
            sources. Each distinct reading drawn from the available witnesses is held in a
                <code>&lt;rdg&gt;</code> element that identifies its source or sources using its
                <code>@source</code> attribute. This model matches the concept of <emphasis role="ital">Bindefehler</emphasis> and <emphasis role="ital">Trennfehler</emphasis>
            almost perfectly. For sources sharing a reading, an <code>&lt;app&gt;</code> element
            acts as a <emphasis role="ital">Bindefehler</emphasis>, while in the case of sources
            with different readings, it acts as a <emphasis role="ital">Trennfehler</emphasis>.</para><para>However, the <code>&lt;app&gt;</code> element is not capable of adequately dealing
            with all of the species of variance described earlier. MEI does offer a mechanism for
                <emphasis role="ital">additions</emphasis>, <emphasis role="ital">deletions</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="ital">substitutions</emphasis>; that is,
                <code>&lt;add&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;del&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;subst&gt;</code>
            elements. However, these elements are intended to describe scribal processes within a
            given witness, not variation across multiple sources. The more generic
                <code>&lt;app&gt;</code> element could be used, which is designated to describe
            variance of this kind as shown in the following encoding:
            <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
            &lt;app&gt;
	           &lt;rdg xml:id="rdgA" source="#A"/&gt;
	           &lt;rdg xml:id="rdgB" source="#B"&gt;
		       &lt;!-- additional content --&gt;
	           &lt;/rdg&gt;
            &lt;/app&gt;
        </programlisting>
            A complete example of an additional measure in source <emphasis role="ital">B</emphasis>
            including musical content might look like this:
            <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
            &lt;section&gt;
                &lt;measure n="26"&gt;...&lt;/measure&gt;
                &lt;app&gt;
                    &lt;rdg xml:id="rdgA" source="#A"/&gt;
                    &lt;rdg xml:id="rdgB" source="#B"&gt;
                        &lt;measure n="26b"&gt;
                            &lt;staff&gt;
                                &lt;layer n="1"&gt;
                                    &lt;note pname="c" oct="5" dur="4" dots="1"/&gt;
                                    &lt;note pname="b" oct="4" dur="8"/&gt;
                                    &lt;note pname="d" oct="5" dur="4"/&gt;
                                    &lt;rest dur="4"/&gt;
                                &lt;/layer&gt;
                            &lt;/staff&gt;
                        &lt;/measure&gt;
                    &lt;/rdg&gt;
                &lt;/app&gt;
                &lt;measure n="27"/&gt;
            &lt;/section&gt;
        </programlisting>
            This approach works for <emphasis role="ital">substitutions</emphasis> but it falls
            short on <emphasis role="ital">rearrangements</emphasis>. Here, it can only capture two
            seemingly separate operations (<emphasis role="ital">deletion</emphasis> and subsequent
                <emphasis role="ital">addition</emphasis>) in separate <code>&lt;app&gt;</code>
            elements. To circumvent this restriction, additional markup is necessary.</para><para>Because the identification of a <emphasis role="ital">rearrangement</emphasis>
            requires an additional step of interpretation, which may be made by the editor at any
            time in the editorial process, the encoding can begin with the use of two separate
                <code>&lt;app&gt;</code> elements, but allow for enrichment of the basic markup
            later. The simplest, and thus most useful, solution is to employ the
                <code>@corresp</code> attribute to cross-link the corresponding
                <code>&lt;rdg&gt;</code> elements:
            <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
            &lt;app&gt;
	           &lt;rdg xml:id="oldPos" source="#A #B" corresp="#newPos"&gt;
	           &lt;!-- content at old position --&gt;
	           &lt;/rdg&gt;
	           &lt;rdg source="#C"/&gt;
            &lt;/app&gt;
            ...
            &lt;app&gt;
	           &lt;rdg source="#A #B"/&gt;
	           &lt;rdg xml:id="newPos" source="#C" corresp="#oldPos"&gt;
	           &lt;!-- content at new position --&gt;
	           &lt;/rdg&gt;
            &lt;/app&gt;
            </programlisting>
            Using these mechanisms clearly shows that the parallel segmentation method of
                <code>&lt;app&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;rdg&gt;</code> suffices to address musical
            variants occurring inside musical structures.</para><figure xml:id="example1" xreflabel="Example 1"><title>Substitution over two measures</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="png" fileref="../../../vol10/graphics/Kepper01/Kepper01-001.png" width="100%"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para>However, as mentioned earlier, <emphasis role="ital">substitutions</emphasis> (of
            melodies, for example) often ignore the structural features of music notation like
            measures and staves (see <xref linkend="example1"/>). In the given scenario, the musical
            notation, as encoded in MEI, requires splitting the description of variance into two
            separate <code>&lt;app&gt;</code> elements. This separation does not resemble a
                <quote>Befund</quote>, which obviously permits only one difference between the two
            sources. The fact that the change crosses the bar line results in a typical example of
            overlapping hierarchy issues confronted by any XML-based encoding system. For the
            encoding of the musical text, MEI is well prepared to handle such overlaps. For
            instance, slurs, one of the most common features of CMN that interfere with measure and
            staff structures, can be captured using various markup possibilities, including
            attribute-based milestone techniques and standoff markup.</para><para>For <quote>overlapping</quote> variants that interfere with the notational structure
            by crossing barlines, staves or similar boundaries, a mechanism like that proposed for
                <emphasis role="ital">rearrangements</emphasis> may be used. The difference here is
            that instead of relating the descendant <code>&lt;rdg&gt;</code> elements, the
                <code>&lt;app&gt;</code> elements themselves should be connected. Capturing cross
            references with <code>@xml:id</code> and <code>@corresp</code> attributes is less than
            ideal, however, as double-ended references can result in largely redundant pointers
            requiring careful maintenance. For example, consider that even a small change in a
            measure may affect a large number of staves.</para><para>A milestone approach, using elements such as TEI’s <quote>span</quote> elements
                (<code>&lt;addSpan&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;delSpan&gt;</code>, etc.) is of no help
            here, as CMN is a two-dimensional notation, making it impossible to describe an affected
            region of the text with just one start and one end point. Instead, a standoff approach
            allowing only single-direction pointers is more appropriate. The obvious solution would
            be to use the <code>&lt;annot&gt;</code> element (the MEI equivalent to TEI’s
                <code>&lt;note&gt;</code>), which offers a <code>@plist</code> (participant list)
            attribute. The <code>&lt;annot&gt;</code> element could be used to point to all related
                <code>&lt;app&gt;</code> elements, and its <code>@type</code> attribute could be
            used to identify its purpose. However, this solution also falls short with regard to
            explicitness. A standoff methodology explicitly identifying all relevant components is
            clearly the best strategy. But using generic <code>&lt;annot&gt;</code> elements,
            distinguished only by simple typing, for all these specific cases, overloads its
            semantics.</para><para>As an alternative, the authors propose adding specific grouping elements to MEI that
            identify isolated members of a feature group. In the case of multiple
                <code>&lt;app&gt;</code> elements, an <code>&lt;appGrp&gt;</code> element would be
            appropriate. The <code>&lt;appGrp&gt;</code> element could use its own
                <code>@plist</code> attribute to refer to a number of logically connected
                <code>&lt;app&gt;</code> elements that, taken together, represent a specific
            variant:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
            &lt;app xml:id="app1"&gt;
	           &lt;rdg xml:id="rdgA1" source="#A"/&gt;
	           &lt;rdg xml:id="rdgB1" source="#B"/&gt;
            &lt;/app&gt;
            ...
            &lt;app xml:id="app2"&gt;
	           &lt;rdg xml:id="rdgA2" source="#A"/&gt;
	           &lt;rdg xml:id="rdgB2" source="#B"/&gt;
            &lt;/app&gt;
            ...
            &lt;appGrp plist="#app1 #app2"/&gt;
        </programlisting><para>On a related topic, MEI currently lacks grouping mechanisms for the elements intended
            for capturing simple editorial changes, such as <emphasis role="ital">additions</emphasis> (<code>&lt;add&gt;</code>) and <emphasis role="ital">deletions</emphasis> (<code>&lt;del&gt;</code>). Like the variation in source
            material represented by <code>&lt;app&gt;</code>, these elements are also not bound to
            notational structures. They too require a grouping mechanism that helps encoders to
            overcome the hierarchical conflicts arising from a strict XML structure.</para><para>With the proposed models in place, it will be possible to encode all the types of
            variants identified by Appel and their scope. The intention is to allow representation
            of textual variation in stages or layers, from no interpretation to the capture of
            complex relationships, in way that permits the editor to make informed decisions about
            the filiation of the sources of the text.</para></section><section><title>Qualitative Analysis based on Encoding</title><para>The <emphasis role="ital">Functional Requirements for Bibliographical
                Records</emphasis> (FRBR) conceptual model was proposed by the <emphasis role="ital">International Federation of Library Associations and Institutions</emphasis> (IFLA)
            in 1998. It does not offer a ready-to-use data format, but rather generic concepts that
            help to create cataloging formats that address advanced user needs. As the FRBR
            terminology is also applicable to music philology, especially with regard to the
            filiation of sources, it has been adopted by MEI for its 2013 release.</para><para>FRBR is organized into three separate but related entity groups. Only the first group,
            which provides work, expression, manifestation and item entities, has been adopted by
            MEI so far. These four so-called <quote>Group 1</quote> entities provide a clear
            terminology for dealing with the transmission of a work in manuscripts and prints alike.
            While a work entity represents only the conceptual idea of a musical piece, independent
            from the details of its composition, such as its instrumentation, an expression
            identifies a slightly less abstract entity that does include these details. In other
            words, it also denotes a specific version of the text, even though this requires a
            manifestation (MEI uses its pre-existing <code>&lt;source&gt;</code> element for this
            entity) for its materialization. An item is a distinct physical instantiation of a
            manifestation, for example, a copy of a certain print.</para><para>FRBR also allows specification of the relationships between the basic entities. In
            MEI, some of the hierarchical relations are implicitly encoded using inheritance (an
            expression for example is a child element of a work) while others, such as those between
            expressions and manifestations, are dealt with using pointers. This change in approach
            is necessitated by the many-to-many relationships that can exist between expressions and
            sources. For example, a single expression of a work may be transmitted by many sources
            or a single source may contain multiple expressions of one or more works. FRBR offers a
            number of relation types, which establish an entity-relationship-model for bibliographic
            and editorial needs. For example, an expression may be described as a translation or
                <emphasis role="ital">rearrangement</emphasis> of another and a print may be
            identified as a copy of a manuscript source. These relations, however, clearly denote
            the overall relation between two affected entities—they are not operating at the level
            of individual variants, but on the global level of complete objects.</para><para>We believe the recommended types for relationships identified and provided by FRBR are
            also useful to describe processes behind textual variation at more granular levels. For
            example, <quote>isSupplementOf</quote> may be used for <emphasis role="ital">additions</emphasis>, <quote>isAbridgementOf</quote> for <emphasis role="ital">deletions</emphasis>, <quote>isRevisionOf</quote> for substitions and
                <quote>isReconfigurationOf</quote> for <emphasis role="ital">rearrangements</emphasis>. Adding such relations to individual textual variants is
            required to give a better overview of the arguments for a specific filiation of sources.
            The suggested implementation mostly relies on existing MEI models. The only important
            change is to allow the <code>@rel</code> attribute, which is currently only available on
            the <code>&lt;relation&gt;</code> element to describe full-entity relations stored in
            the header, to be used on <code>&lt;rdg&gt;</code> elements. In this implementation,
            material added in a later and derived version of the text would be encoded so:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
            &lt;app&gt;
	           &lt;rdg xml:id="rdgA" source="#A"/&gt;
	           &lt;rdg xml:id="rdgB" source="#B" rel="isSupplementOf" target="#rdgA"&gt;
		       &lt;!-- additional content --&gt;
	           &lt;/rdg&gt;
            &lt;/app&gt;
        </programlisting><para>The example shows how one reading is identified as an <emphasis role="ital">addition</emphasis> to another. The empty reading serves as a placeholder for the
                <quote>base text</quote>. By adding <code>@cert</code> and <code>@evidence</code>
            attributes to <code>&lt;rdg&gt;</code>, the editor may also state the reliability of his
            assessment. While at some point in the future it may be necessary to allow an alternate
            encoding method that employs dedicated elements in order to capture divergent
            interpretation from multiple editors, the simple approach described here will
            suffice.</para><para>The purpose of filiation is to identify the relations (and their directionalities)
            between sources and to create a stemma that illustrates these relations. The results may
            be expressed with FRBR, but they are based on the evaluation of individual variants as
            described above. This evaluation, stored in a FRBR-compliant way, can be used to provide
            a better overview of all arguments and to inform the editor's interpretation of the
            overall connection. It may also help to better explore the filiation of sources with
            multiple intermingled ancestors and other complex situations often overlooked in
            traditional filiation [<xref linkend="feder1987"/>]. However, a fully automated analysis
            of those variants seems impossible; simply quantifying the number of variants indicating
            a filiation from A to B vs. arguments for B to A is not particularly helpful, as some
            arguments are more convincing than others [<xref linkend="feder1987"/>, p. 58]. The
            swapping of two pitches has nearly no persuasiveness with regard to the derivation,
            whereas a missing note in a manuscript is an almost unquestionable argument that it was
            copied from the source to which it is compared. To make full use of the encoding, it is
            therefore important to assess the impact of a particular variant based on the content of
            the readings it holds. Following this reasoning, a variant holding an additional staff
            in one source and no corresponding material in another should be given more weight than
            a variant where the sources differ only on the pitch of a single note. Likewise, a
            variant affecting substantial information of the text is more compelling than a
            variation in the accidental layer of the text [<xref linkend="greg1950"/>]. Accurately
            judging the impact of a variant by an automated examination is clearly a large-scale
            project of its own, but it is fairly easy to get a first suggestion from less ambitious
            algorithms. When considering the fact that the final evaluation must be based on the
            editor's experience and judgment, it seems unnecessary to get a perfect analysis—it just
            needs to be good enough to be a helpful starting point. Under these circumstances, it
            seems logical not to hard-wire the weight given to each category of argument, but
            instead to let the editor balance them according to his expertise.</para><para>An automated analysis of the variation across multiple sources must start with a
            listing of all <emphasis role="ital">Trennfehler</emphasis> and <emphasis role="ital">Bindefehler</emphasis> for every combination of two sources. At this stage, the
            variants do not require further argumentation and stand on their own. An initial graph
            grouping the sources by their level of conformance with each other is already possible.
            However, in order to assess the edges of this graph, the content of these variants must
            be evaluated. Simple pitch changes (which may be nothing more than mere copying errors),
            will be treated differently than larger groups of non-corresponding measures. After
            measuring the strength of these arguments, the next step is to identify their
            directions. This process is also based on an evaluation of the content—is it more likely
            that the textual difference is a later addition to a formerly shorter text, or is it
            more likely that something has been canceled from a formerly richer text? Again, these
            arguments will differ in their persuasiveness, but here the situation is much better, as
            additional information can be used to inform the determination of direction. For
            example, if both sources can be precisely dated, the direction is already clear.
            Likewise, the identification of scribal hands may help to determine filiation when more
            information about the scribe, such as birth and death dates or work locations, is
            available.</para><para>Even when the general relationship between two sources seems to be clear, based on a
            number of arguments regarded as indisputable, it is important that all contradictory
            variants remain available to the editor, as they may hint at a possible contamination of
            sources. Accordingly, the graphical interface for this analysis needs to differentiate
            between parts of these sources and provide hints if there is a significant variation in
            the likely directionality of filiation amongst them. Very often, editors will be able to
            identify the filiation of sources very quickly. The purpose of an automated analysis
            like this is to ensure that editors do not overlook possible alternatives or mixed
            relationships, resulting in oversimplification of the filiations. Having the editor's
            judgment explicitly recorded in <code>@rel</code> attributes on <code>&lt;rdg&gt;</code>
            and a determination of a level of certainty for the assertion in <code>@cert</code>
            attributes, permits better decision-making, ultimately making the edition more
            transparent for the user.</para></section><section><title>Visualization and Analysis of Variants</title><para>As the purpose of the proposed encoding and analysis methodology is both to support
            the editor and to better illustrate the editorial process to the user, an adequate
            visualization is very important. Even though the encoding itself is designed to be as
            legible as possible, the vast amount of data requires provision of a condensed
            view—without which the resulting information would likely be unusable.</para><para>Following the order of steps given above, a first visualization will provide an
            overview of the variance of two or more sources under comparison.</para><figure xml:id="example2" xreflabel="Example 2"><title>Visualization of Variance with a kind of piano roll notation</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="png" fileref="../../../vol10/graphics/Kepper01/Kepper01-002.png" width="100%"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><figure xml:id="example3" xreflabel="Example 3"><title>Visualization of Variance in multiple voices</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="png" fileref="../../../vol10/graphics/Kepper01/Kepper01-003.png" width="100%"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para>This visualization draws on the concept of piano roll notation (see <xref linkend="example2"/> and <xref linkend="example3"/>), but compared to regular piano
            roll notation, it is scaled down to a barely legible size, similar to Edward Tufte's
            sparklines concept [<xref linkend="tufte2008"/>]. The idea is to provide an overview of
            large segments of the source. Every source is assigned a distinct color. Everything
            shown in black is shared amongst all sources, whereas the colored parts show the
            differences between them. Piano roll notation represents only the substantial parts of
            the score, ignoring accidental components like articulation, dynamics, etc. In a proper
            visualization, this kind of information is provided in a separate stream for every
            staff. This stream could also be reduced, showing only a dot for each accidental sign
            (not visible in the examples). Separation into multiple streams helps to distinguish the
            kind of variance even at this high-level overview stage. In the future, scaling may also
            be provided in this view, allowing the user to zoom into more and more detail,
            terminating in the actual notation. Until then, this visualization provides an excellent
            overview of the level of variance between the compared sources. It is also possible to
            highlight variants acting as <emphasis role="ital">Bindefehler</emphasis> between two
            sources by putting them on a differently colored background.<footnote><para>The piano roll doesn't differ in this case and is therefore not capable of
                    delivering this information.</para></footnote></para><para>The next step is to make use of the FRBR-compatible classification of individual
            variants. This is possible by making the interface customizable, allowing the user to
            highlight specific types of variants. The project intends to provide yet another
            perspective on the data that resembles traditional stemmata more closely.</para><para>In the projected interface, there will be a stemma-like graph on the left side of the
            screen, paired with a list of all variants on the right side. These variants can be
            ordered by their type, ascribed FRBR-relations, the editor's certainty, the estimated
            relevance (following customizable categories), and the affected sources and their
            position in the document. Manipulating this list will influence the stemma on the left.
            If, for instance, the editor (or user) decides to focus on a single movement of the
            work, it will reflect only relations in that movement.</para></section><section><title>Conclusion</title><para>The system described in this paper can only operate on fully encoded sources. The
                <emphasis role="ital">Freischütz Digital</emphasis> project will provide data of the
            required verbosity for the first time. The amount of data contained in encodings of
            music notation is already large and providing the additional details described in this
            paper will increase their complexity even further. However, the end result of doing
            so—detailed insight into the transmission and transformation of musical works—is highly
            desirable. While it has not been possible before, by leveraging the potentials of both
            MEI and FRBR it is possible to create intuitive tools that permit the exploration and
            communication of relations among sources containing notated music.</para></section><bibliography><title>Bibliography</title><bibliomixed xml:id="appel2005" xreflabel="Appel 2005">Appel, Bernhard R.: <quote>Variatio
                delectat – Variatio perturbat</quote>, in: Varianten – Variants – Varientes
            (Beihefte zu editio 22), edited by Christa Jansohn and Bodo Plachta, Tübingen
            2005, doi:<biblioid class="doi">10.1515/9783110926941.7</biblioid></bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="bohl2011" xreflabel="Bohl et al. 2011">Bohl, Benjamin/Kepper,
            Johannes/Röwenstrunk, Daniel: <quote>Perspektiven digitaler Musikeditionen aus der Sicht
                des Edirom-Projekts</quote> in: DIE TONKUNST, July 2011, No. 3, Vol. 5 (2011), pp.
            270–276</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="feder1987" xreflabel="Feder 1987">Feder, Georg:
                <quote>Musikphilologie</quote>, Darmstadt 1987</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="greg1950" xreflabel="Greg 1950">Greg, Walter Wilson: <quote>The
                Rationale of Copy-Text</quote>, Studies in Bibliography Vol. 3, (1950/1951), pp.
            19-36, Published by: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="maas1960" xreflabel="Maas 1960">Maas, Paul: <quote>Leitfehler und
                stemmatische Varianten</quote>, in: Textkritik, Leipzig 1960</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="tufte2008" xreflabel="Tufte 2008">Tufte, Edward: <quote>Sparklines:
                theory and practice</quote>, Retrieved September 13 (2004), 2008</bibliomixed></bibliography></article>