<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3"><title>Content, Format, and Interpretation</title><info><confgroup><conftitle>Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</conftitle><confdates>August 2 - 5, 2011</confdates></confgroup><abstract><para>The connection between notation and the content it
expresses is always contingent, and mediated through complex layers of
interpretation. Some content bears directly on the encoder's intention
to convey a particular meaning, while other content concerns the
structures in and through which that meaning is expressed and
organized. <emphasis>Interpretive frames</emphasis> are abstractions
that serve as context for symbolic expressions. They form a backdrop
of dependencies for data management and preservation strategies.
Situation semantics offers a theoretical grounding for interpretive
frames that integrates them into a general theory of communication
through markup and other notational structures.</para></abstract><author><personname><firstname>David</firstname><surname>Dubin</surname></personname><personblurb><para>David Dubin is a Research Associate Professor at the
University of Illinois Graduate School of Library and Information
Science in Champaign, IL. David conducts research on foundational
issues of information representation and description.</para></personblurb><affiliation><jobtitle>Research Associate Professor</jobtitle><orgname>University of Illinois</orgname></affiliation><email>ddubin@illinois.edu</email></author><author><personname><firstname>Karen</firstname><surname>Wickett</surname></personname><personblurb><para>Karen M. Wickett is a doctoral student at the Graduate School of Library and
          Information Science, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. </para></personblurb><affiliation><orgname>University of Illinois</orgname></affiliation><email>wickett2@illinois.edu</email></author><author><personname><firstname>Simone</firstname><surname>Sacchi</surname></personname><personblurb><para>Simone Sacchi is a Doctoral Student at the Graduate School of Library and Information
          Science and research assistant at the Center for Informatics Research in Science and
          Scholarship under the NSF granted Data Conservancy Project. His research interests are in
          conceptual foundation of digital curation and knowledge representation.</para></personblurb><affiliation><orgname>University of Illinois</orgname></affiliation><email>sacchi1@illinois.edu</email></author><legalnotice><para>Copyright © 2011 by the authors.  Used with permission.</para></legalnotice><keywordset role="author"><keyword>Semantics</keyword><keyword>Situation Theory</keyword><keyword>Digital Preservation</keyword></keywordset></info><section><title>Introduction</title><para>The distinction between a digital resource's content and its
expressive format is usually described in different terms than the
content/presentation distinction familiar to markup researchers and
practitioners. In both cases one understands that the same content can
be formatted or presented in different ways. But the word
“format” typically connotes a discrete symbolic
notation—one that might encode conceptual content, structural
information, presentational instructions, or all three.
“Presentation” is usually understood as patterns of
energy or matter that visually or audibly communicate (via shared
graphical or auditory interpretive conventions) resource structure and
content to human minds. Standardized and proprietary digital file
formats are the most familiar of these notations.</para><para>Proposals for semantic enrichment or digital preservation
often focus on methods for transforming resources from one format into
another. Colloquial XML can be transformed into RDF via XSLT 
<xref linkend="sperberg-mcqueen04"/>, or into horn clause assertions
through a Prolog application <xref linkend="dubin03"/>. But although
notations like RDF and first order logic may admit more expressive
distinctions than colloquial XML, such transformations at best merely
re-express resource semantics in a more convenient form for drawing
inferences or some other purpose“those semantics aren't inherent
in the notation. The connection between resource and content (i.e., a
symbol structure and the content it expresses) is always contingent:
the same symbols might just as easily express different content, or no
content at all <xref linkend="renear07"/>. In the context of some particular
assertion event, correct interpretation of encoded content is typically mediated
through  many expressive layers. In the following sections,
we discuss the relationships among content, structure, and
presentation, and situate them with respect to our ongoing research in
scientific data management.</para></section><section><title>Background</title><para>This work is part of the Data Conservancy, an ongoing
scientific data management project funded by the National Science
Foundation's Office of Cyberinfrastructure 
<xref linkend="choudhury09"/>. Our aims are to develop formal
terminology and identity conditions for concepts of general importance
to the management and use of scientific datasets (e.g., observation,
data content, version, format, etc.). Our proposed formalizations are
expressed as terminological axioms in the Description Logic ALC 
<xref linkend="schmidt-schauss91"/> <xref linkend="baader03"/>.
Although these may later base ontologies that can direct automated
reasoning over data set descriptions, our current aims are merely
analytic: we propose, challenge, and revise the models in the context
of reviewing and informing data curation practices and system design
decisions. For example, we suggest that a model separating abstract
propositional content of a scientific assertion from the observation
event justifying that assertion may ease data integration across a
series of related studies (e.g., replication of findings): </para><figure><itemizedlist><listitem><equation><mathphrase>Proposition ⊑ AbstractThing</mathphrase></equation></listitem><listitem><equation><mathphrase>SimpleProposition ⊑ Proposition</mathphrase></equation></listitem><listitem><equation><mathphrase>ComplexProposition ⊑ Proposition</mathphrase></equation></listitem><listitem><equation><mathphrase>Conjunction ⊑ ComplexProposition</mathphrase></equation></listitem><listitem><equation><mathphrase>Observation ⊑ Event</mathphrase></equation></listitem><listitem><equation><mathphrase>Computation ⊑ Event</mathphrase></equation></listitem><listitem><equation><mathphrase>Assertion ⊑ Event</mathphrase></equation></listitem><listitem><equation><mathphrase>SystematicAssertion ≡ Assertion ⊓
              ∃warrantedBy.(Observation ⊔ Computation)</mathphrase></equation></listitem><listitem><equation><mathphrase>(Proposition ⊓ ∃substanceOf.SystematicAssertion) ⊑
              DataContent</mathphrase></equation></listitem><listitem><equation><mathphrase>(Proposition ⊓ ∃conjunctOf.DataContent) ⊑
              DataContent</mathphrase></equation></listitem></itemizedlist></figure><para>The reader is invited to imagine simple propositions as
standing (as reified RDF statements do) in subject, predicate, and
object relations to entities and properties in a scientific domain
like chemistry or ecology. But unlike reified RDF, our simple
propositions are completely abstract, requiring no concrete
expression. <xref linkend="hayes04"/>. Propositions standing in the
same subject, predicate, and object relations are strictly identical.
On this understanding, different data sets might have exactly the same
propositional content, but differ in the observations or computations
that justify their assertions. Similarly, two scientists might appeal
to exactly the same observation events as justification for very
different (or even contradictory) assertions.
</para></section><section><title>On the content of digital resources</title><para>In the context of our research on scientific data, we view
resource “content” as propositional in nature.  A
<emphasis>proposition</emphasis> is an abstract thing which can be the
object of propositional attitudes (such as belief or doubt) and the
bearer of truth values. We consider propositions to be the language
independent entities that are the meanings of
those sentences (or other symbol structures) that express them.
Artistic and literary resources may have forms of non-propositional
content that are inseparable from the expressive choices of their
creators, but artistic and literary content are not our focus in this
study.</para><para>Specifically, we are concerned with two kinds of propositional content:</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term>Conceptual Content</term><listitem><para>Conceptual content is the distinct intellectual
contribution supplied by the digital resource, which in our study
concerns entities, properties, and relations in a scientific domain.
This type of content corresponds, roughly, to the “work”
entity type in the FRBR model <xref linkend="ifla98"/>, or, with a
slightly different connotation, the “Deliverable Unit” in
the PLANETS model <xref linkend="sharpe09"/>. Conceptual content is
typically considered the main preservation target, though on our
account such content, being abstract, is not subject to corruption
and so isn't literally preserved.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Structural Content</term><listitem><para>The second kind of propositional content concerns
abstract structures in and through which conceptual content is
expressed and organized. The paragraphs, chapters, and footnotes of
conventional documentation are among these structures, as well as
database relations, spreadsheet rows, and lines and arcs of vector
graphics. Examples of structural content would include the fact that a
particular text string is a paragraph, or that an arc has particular
coordinates in an abstract display plane.</para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist><para>The digital data resources that concern us are encoded
symbol structures that express scientists' claims, with our analysis
aimed at supporting format migration, digital preservation and data
integration. Abstract symbol structures and propositions do not
undergo changes of state <xref linkend="renearwickett09"/>, and so the
problem is one of maintaining a connection between conceptual content
and the structures that express it. This is easier when structural
content is directly encoded within a digital resource as, for
example, with XML declarations, PostScript prologues, and other forms
of metadata. In the following sections we consider the connections
between the propositions expressed through these technologies, and the
chain that links the bit level to the conceptual level.</para></section><section><title>Data Expression and Interpretive Frames</title><para>By the account in the earlier section, data content are a
subset of abstract propositions, obtaining their status in virtue of
their systematic assertion by a researcher. But the digital data
resources that concern us are encoded symbol structures that express
data content. Our problem is the contingent nature of this connection:
data express their conceptual content not simply in virtue of their
arrangement and structure, but always with reference to what we call
<emphasis>interpretive frames</emphasis>. These are abstractions that
frame the interpretive context for symbolic expressions: </para><figure><itemizedlist><listitem><equation><mathphrase>SymbolStructure ⊑ AbstractThing</mathphrase></equation></listitem><listitem><equation><mathphrase>InterpretiveFrame ≡ (AbstractThing ⊓
              ∃interpretiveContextFor.SystematicAssertion)</mathphrase></equation></listitem><listitem><equation><mathphrase>Data ≡ SymbolStructure ⊓
              ∃primaryExpressionFor.SystematicAssertion)</mathphrase></equation></listitem></itemizedlist></figure><para>At the risk of understating their complexity, one can think
of interpretive frames as functions or mappings between structural
propositions at different expressive levels, or from structural
propositions to conceptual propositions. Examples of interpretive
frames include the grammatical rules expressed by an XML Schema, coded
character sets such as ASCII, the convention of writing numbers as
strings of Arabic numerals with ten as the implied numerical base, the
Hierarchical Data Format standard, and all dialects of the English
language as they are spoken today. Interpretive frames also include
any systematic expressive choices that may be local to a particular
digital resource, such as a correspondence between successive rows of
a spreadsheet and the order of transactions in a scientific
experiment.</para><para>In pointing to contingent interpretations as “our
problem,” we don't mean that to suggest encoding standards,
markup technologies, or even common data management practices are
seriously flawed. While we're motivated by practical problems,
such as under-documented spreadsheets, in highlighting the
complexities of interpretation we don't mean to suggest that effective
tools and solutions are lacking. But discussions of these methods tend
to foreground regularity in a resource's primary expressive structure,
and neglect the interrelationships among interpretive frames at
different levels of abstraction.
    </para></section><section><title>Working Example</title><para>The following digital image can serve as an example of the
distinctions we wish to draw. The resource Fisher5 is an Encapsulated
PostScript file <xref linkend="adobe90"/> Its prologue consists of reusable
functions, written to draw box-and-whisker plots from frequency distribution
parameters. The final lines of the file lay out the parameters for the
single plot:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
/outliers 1 2.0 1 4.2 1 4.4 1 4.1 4
/left 2.2 /loq 2.8 /med 3 /upq 3.3 /right 4.0 /min 2.0 /max 4.4
/label (Anderson/Fisher Sepal Width Data) box

showpage
</programlisting><para>Displayed in an appropriate document viewing application,
the file's presentation looks like this:</para><figure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Dubin01/Dubin01-001.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para>The following propositions comprise Fisher5's conceptual content:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>A certain frequency distribution is called “Anderson/Fisher Sepal Width
          Data.”</para></listitem><listitem><para>The minimum value of that distribution is 2.0.</para></listitem><listitem><para>The maximum value is 4.4.</para></listitem><listitem><para>The median of that distribution is 3.</para></listitem><listitem><para>The upper and lower hinges are 3.3 and 2.8, respectively.</para></listitem><listitem><para>The distribution has four outliers, one each at values 2.0, 4.2, 4.1 and 4.4.</para></listitem><listitem><para>2.2 and 4.0 are (respectively) the lowest and highest values that lie within 1.5
          midspreads of the hinges.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>Structural content would include (among other things):</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Fisher5 is an Encapsulated PostScript File</para></listitem><listitem><para>The bounding box coordinates for this resource are 175,655 and 487,745.</para></listitem><listitem><para>the octet 0x6d at offset 0x622 is a Latin lower case letter m.</para></listitem><listitem><para>“/med” is a PostScript label</para><para>“/med” names a parameter to the function “box.”</para><para>“/med” identifies the median of a distribution.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>ASCII, PostScript, John Tukey's graphical convention for
distribution summaries, and a special-purpose language for encoding
box plots are among the interpretive frames that connect the listing
above to the conceptual propositions it expresses.</para><para>Among the format migration options to be considered for
Fisher5 in a preservation scenario are keeping the resource in its
original PostScript expression, transformation into vector PDF, or
conversion into a raster PNG file. Strictly speaking, all three
options preserve the conceptual content for human beings able to
display the file using viewing software, provided that those viewers
have an understanding of Tukey's box plot conventions. The current
PostScript file encodes conceptual content in a declarative notation:
median, range, hinges, and outliers are expressed in the scale of the
original data, not the PS/PDF display plane coordinates. Those
declarations would disappear in a translation from PS to PDF (usually
understood as a lossless transformation). On the other hand,
syntactically correct PostScript offers no guarantee of page
independence (or, for that matter, halting). This PostScript file uses
a non-embedded font that may not be as commonly available in the
future as it is today. And the undocumented Postscript-based box plot
markup language will be unfamiliar to people who might have an
interest in extracting the data.</para><para>It would be relatively easy to transform box plot markup
language into RDF, preserving all of the conceptual propositions
listed above, and avoiding the shortcomings of PostScript, PDF, and
PNG. Such an RDF re-expression could also include structural
information, such as that Fisher5 is a box-and-whisker plot. But
unlike a PDF or PNG translation, the resulting RDF would not express a
box plot, and the advantages Tukey's notation offers for rapid visual
assessment and comparison would not be available. We don't mean to
suggest that this is a dilemma, or that no better migration options
than these four are available (SVG might offer the best of all of
them, for example). But interpretive frames would form a backdrop of
dependencies for any such solution.</para></section><section><title>Situation Semantics and Interpretive Frames</title><para>The usefulness of frameworks based situation semantics <xref linkend="barwise83"/> for understanding the assignment of
meaning to XML structures has been argued for by Wrightson
        <xref linkend="wrightson01"/>
      <xref linkend="wrightson05"/> and Wickett <xref linkend="wickett10"/>. Barwise and Perry use situation
semantics to model the meaning of indicative sentences as a relation
between a situation<footnote><para> The technical notion of a situation is close to our
intuitive one: a situation occurs at a space-time location and
involves individuals participating in certain roles and standing in
relations. It also closely corresponds to the notion of a state of
affairs, especially since situations are abstract objects that may or
may not obtain.</para></footnote> in which the sentence was uttered (the <emphasis role="ital">discourse situation</emphasis>) and a situation that the
sentence describes (the <emphasis role="ital">described
situation</emphasis>). The framework proposed by Wickett focuses on
treating metadata records encoded in XML as a kind of utterance and,
following Barwise and Perry, examining how specific elements of XML
documents contribute to inform consumers of the resource situations
that were used assign meaning to the document as a whole. Situation
semantics can be used here to give a theoretical grounding for
interpretive frames that integrates them into a general theory of
communication through markup and other notational structures.</para><para>In the case of data encoded in XML documents, we can also
consider the document to be a series of indicative statements. In
general a discourse situation gives an assignment for a speaker, an
addressee, a (space-time) discourse location, and an expression. In
terms of the framework (axioms) for encoding presented above, the
speaker is the agent that commits to an expression, the discourse
location is partially given by the assertion event, and the expression
is the symbol structure that is the primary expression for the
systematic assertion indicated in an assertion event. The role of the
addressee and the end-point of the discourse location are left open
until the document is viewed by some consumer of the data, only at
this point will we have a complete discourse situation. </para><para>The described situation for data is a situation in which the
real-world entities referred to by the symbol structures have the
properties indicated by the relevant set of claims. In other words,
the described situation is one in which the propositions that are the
substance of the assertions (and therefore are data content) are all
true. Since the described situation may not come to pass, we allow for
data that is in error, by referring to things that do not exist or
assigning properties to things incorrectly.</para><para>In Situations and Attitudes, Barwise and Perry discuss
<emphasis role="ital">resource situations</emphasis>, the situations
that the actors participating in a discourse situation have access to
and use to identify and assign referents for the expressions that make
up an utterance. Interpretive frames, as presented above, are a
particular kind of resource situation. One kind of interpretive frame
is the resource situation that govern the mappings between symbol
structures and the things they refer to. This mapping was discussed by
Barwise and Perry (and Wickett) as the speaker's <emphasis role="ital">connections</emphasis>. This interpretive frame assigns
things like identifiers to individual plants in laboratory study, or
assigns one column of a spreadsheet to a particular property of those
plants. The preservation of meaning (in translation or simply within a
single discourse situation) requires that the connections established
by the addressee of an utterance are the same as those intended by the
speaker.</para><para>XML documents, and digital objects in general, operate as
communicative artifacts in virtue of a chain of computational
structures that provide a background in which bitstreams can be
understood as encoding symbolic structures. These interpretive frames
are pointed to by things like standards for character encoding and by
the various standards and specifications for hardware and software
that allow us to create files and share them across systems. Barwise
and Perry discuss how in natural language utterances, expressions that
occur at one point in a discourse situation can supply a <emphasis role="ital">setting</emphasis> that influences how expressions that
occur at another point in the discourse situation are understood. We
can understand the interpretive frames that govern things like
character encodings as resource situations that supply the necessary
settings under which bitstreams can be interpreted as characters.
</para></section><section><title>Discussion and Implications</title><para>One of the goals of the Data Conservancy project is to
support interoperability of scientific data products. An interoperable
data product is one for which given any addressee (consumer of the
data product), the set of connections that link the symbol structures
to referents (objects of study, properties, values, etc.) are the same
as those intended by the agent that indicated those symbol structures
in the original assertion event. Representing structural propositions
directly, either by asserting them (as with metadata annotations) or
expressing them via encoding technologies like XML is one part of our
strategy for helping to achieve this goal. Documentation of
interpretive frames that connect propositions at different abstraction
levels is another part of that same strategy. </para><para>We can see an application of these ideas in the OAIS
Reference Model, which requires the inclusion of
“representation information” as part of an Archival
Information Package. This representation information is intended to
give “information necessary to render and understand the bit
sequences constituting the Content Data Object” 
<xref linkend="lavoie04"/>. However, it is important to draw a
distinction between an interpretive frame and documentation of the
frame. While OAIS representation information is necessary and can
provide documentation of important aspects of the interpretive frames
against which some data object is created, it must itself be in the
form of a symbolic structure. On our view, interpretive frames
are abstract mappings that correspond roughly to a 
<emphasis role="ital">situation</emphasis> <xref linkend="barwise83"/>. 
Therefore documentation can express
elements of an interpretive frame, but a document cannot, by itself,
<emphasis role="ital">be</emphasis> an interpretive frame. </para></section><section><title>Conclusions</title><para>Document markup solutions already do a better job than other
notations in explicating structural content, and connecting it to
appropriate interpretive frames. XML documents begin by declaring what
they are, which encoding governs the interpretation of bit patterns,
and (typically) what schema provides a syntax for the document. XML
metadata applications offer numerous other forms of documentation and
linking to bridge interpretive gaps. Most of the observations we offer
here can be found stated either directly or indirectly by proponents
of semantic documentation and enrichment frameworks like Formal Tag
Set Definition and Intertextual Semantics
<xref linkend="marcoux09"/>. But professional and research literature
on markup semantics tends to foreground the role of markup itself in
licensing inferences <xref linkend="sperberg-mcqueen02"/>
      <xref linkend="sperberg-mcqueen04"/>
      <xref linkend="sperberg-mcqueen11"/>. Archiving standards like
OAIS give an impression that “representation
information” can supply needed interpretations, rather than
simply document encoding choices. We recommend a different
emphasis.</para><para>In our work with scientific data, the author/researcher's
assertion event—rather than the resulting expression
structure—seems to us the locus at which key identities are
established. According to our axioms, it is these assertions that make
propositions into data content, and supply symbol structures with
their contingent meanings. The encoder of a data set can be likened
(as Wendell Piez has suggested) to the player in a nomic game <xref linkend="piez09"/>, accepting some responsibility for creating
the constitutive rules that govern his or her choices.</para></section><section><title>Acknowledgments</title><para>This research was supported by NSF Grant OCI-0830976. The authors wish to thank Allen
      Renear, the GSLIS Research Writing Group, and the anonymous reviewers of a prior Balisage
      submission for suggestions that have improved this paper. </para></section><bibliography><title>Bibliography</title><bibliomixed xml:id="adobe90" xreflabel="Adobe Systems,   1990">Adobe Systems Incorporated. <emphasis role="ital">PostScript Language Reference
        Manual, Second Edition</emphasis>. Addison-Wesley, Reading, MA, 1990.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="baader03" xreflabel="Baader et al.,   2003">F. Baader, D. Calvanese, D. McGuinness,
D. Nardi, and P. Patel-Schneider. <emphasis role="ital">The description logic handbook: theory, implementation,
and applications</emphasis>. Cambridge Univ Press, New York,
2003.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="barwise83" xreflabel="Barwise and Perry,   1983">J. Barwise and
      J. Perry. <emphasis role="ital">Situations and Attitudes. A Bradford Book</emphasis>.
      The MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, 1983.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="carlyle06" xreflabel="Carlyle,   2006">A. Carlyle. Understanding
      FRBR as a conceptual model FRBR and the bibliographic universe. <emphasis role="ital">Library
        Resources and Technical Services</emphasis>, 50(4):264–273, 2006.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="choudhury09" xreflabel="Choudhury and Hanisch,   2009">S. Choudhury
      and R. Hanisch. Data conservancy: Building a sustainable system for interdisciplinary
      scientific data curation and preservation. In <emphasis role="ital">Ensuring Long-Term
        Preservation and Adding Value to Scientific and Technical Data (PV) Conference, Madrid,
        Spain</emphasis>, 2009.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="dubin03" xreflabel="Dubin, 2003">D. Dubin. Object mapping for markup
      semantics. In B. T Usdin, editor, <emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of Extreme Markup
        Languages 2003</emphasis>, Montréal, Canada, August 2003.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="hayes04" xreflabel="Hayes, 2004">P. Hayes. RDF semantics. Published by
      the World Wide Web Consortium at url <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-mt/</link>, February 2004. </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="holdsworth00" xreflabel="Holdsworth and Sergeant,   2000">D. Holdsworth and D. M Sergeant. A blueprint for representation information in
      the OAIS model. In B. Kobler and P. C. Harihan, editors, <emphasis role="ital">Eighth Goddard Conference on Mass Storage Systems and Technologies: In cooperation with the
        17th IEEE Symposium on Mass Storage Systems</emphasis>, pages 413–428, Greenbelt, MD,
      2000. NASA.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="ifla98" xreflabel="IFLA, 1998">International Federation of Library
      Associations (IFLA). <emphasis role="ital">Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records:
        Final Report</emphasis>. UBCIM Publications-New Series. Vol. 19, München: K.G.Saur,
      1998.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="lavoie04" xreflabel="Lavoie, 2004">B. F Lavoie. The open archival
      information system reference model: Introductory guide. <emphasis role="ital">Microform and
        imaging review</emphasis>, 33(2):68–81, 2004.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="marcoux09" xreflabel="Marcoux et al., 2009">Y. Marcoux, C. M.
      Sperberg-McQueen, and C. Huitfeldt. Formal and informal meaning from documents through
      skeleton sentences. In <emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference
        2009</emphasis>, volume 4 of <emphasis role="ital">Balisage Series on Markup
        Technologies</emphasis>, Montréal, Canada, August 2009.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="piez09" xreflabel="Piez, 2009">W. Piez. How to play XML: Markup
      technologies as nomic game. In <emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup
        Conference 2009</emphasis>, volume 4 of <emphasis role="ital">Balisage Series on
        Markup Technologies</emphasis>, Montréal, Canada, August 2009.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="renear07" xreflabel="Renear and Dubin,   2007">A. H. Renear and David Dubin. Three of the four FRBR
group 1 entity types are roles, not types. In Andrew Grove, editor,
<emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of the 70th Annual Meeting of the
American Society for Information Science and Technology</emphasis>,
Medford, NJ, 2007. Information Today, Inc.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="renearwickett09" xreflabel="Renear and Wickett,   2009">A. H. Renear and K. M. Wickett. Documents Cannot
Be Edited. In <emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The
Markup Conference 2009</emphasis>, volume 3 of <emphasis role="ital">Balisage Series on Markup Technologies</emphasis>,
Montréal, Canada, August 2009.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="schmidt-schauss91" xreflabel="Schmidt-Schauß and Smolka,   1991">M. Schmidt-Schauß and G. Smolka.
Attributive concept descriptions with complements. <emphasis role="ital">Artificial Intelligence</emphasis>, 48(1):1–26,
1991.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="sharpe09" xreflabel="Sharpe,   2009">R. Sharpe. PLANETS data model
      overview. Technical Report IF8-D1, Planets Consortium, 2009. please request from
      info@planets-project.eu.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="sperberg-mcqueen04" xreflabel="Sperberg-McQueen   and Miller, 2004">C. M. Sperberg-McQueen and E. Miller. On mapping from colloquial XML to RDF using
      XSLT. In <emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages</emphasis>,
      Montréal, Canada, August 2004.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="sperberg-mcqueen02" xreflabel="Sperberg-McQueen   et al., 2002">C. M. Sperberg-McQueen, D. Dubin, C. Huitfeldt, and A. Renear. Drawing
      inferences on the basis of markup. In B. T Usdin and S. R. Newcomb, editors,
        <emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages 2002</emphasis>,
      Montréal, Canada, August 2002.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="sperberg-mcqueen11" xreflabel="Sperberg-McQueen,   2011">C. M.
      Sperberg-McQueen. What constitutes successful format conversion? towards a formalization of
      'Intellectual content'. <emphasis role="ital">International Journal of Digital
        Curation</emphasis>, 6(1), 2011.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="wickett10" xreflabel="Wickett,   2010">K. M. Wickett. Discourse
      situations and markup interoperability. In <emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The
        Markup Conference 2010</emphasis>, volume 5 of <emphasis role="ital">Balisage Series
        on Markup Technologies</emphasis>, Montréal, Canada, August 2010.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="wrightson01" xreflabel="Wrightson,   2001">A. Wrightson. Some
      semantics for structured documents, topic maps and topic map queries. In <emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages</emphasis>, Montréal, Canada,
      2001.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="wrightson05" xreflabel="Wrightson,   2005">A. Wrightson. Semantics
      of well formed XML as a human and machine readable language: Why is some XML so difficult to
      read. In <emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages</emphasis>, pages
      1–11, Montréal, Canada, 2005.</bibliomixed></bibliography></article>