<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3"><title>Customizing a general purpose XML editor: oXygen's authoring environment</title><info><confgroup><conftitle>International Symposium on Native XML User Interfaces</conftitle><confdates>August 5, 2013</confdates></confgroup><abstract><para>oXygen started in 2001 as an IDE for XML and XML related technologies but after some
        years our users wanted to be able to edit XML documents not only as text, in the source
        mode, but also in a way that will be non-intimidating for non-technical people. As a result
        of that, we introduced in 2007 support for visually editing XML documents. The rendering is
        based on CSS and we allow also custom actions to be defined through configuration or through
        Java coding, XSLT or XQuery scripts, etc. With CSS extensions we introduced also form based
        controls and actions directly in the user interface, thus making possible to quickly create
        interfaces for editing XML documents that completely hide the underlying XML structure and
        allow people to edit XML without seeing any of the XML markup.</para></abstract><author><personname><firstname>George</firstname><surname>Bina</surname></personname><personblurb><para>George Bina is one of the founders of Syncro Soft, the company that develops oXygen
          XML Editor. He worked with XML since 1998, initially using XML for different projects and,
          starting with 2001, on the development of oXygen XML Editor, a tool for XML authoring and
          development. George is actively involved in the XML related projects contributing to XML
          related open source projects: Jing (the validation engine for Relax NG, NVDL)</para></personblurb><affiliation><orgname>Syncro Soft</orgname></affiliation></author><legalnotice><para>Copyright ©  2013 Syncro Soft SRL</para></legalnotice></info><section><title>XML and CSS</title><para>CSS is a W3C standard that can be used to provide styling information to a document. While
      CSS is used mainly with HTML there is no such restriction to the standard itself and it can be
      used also with any XML document. </para><para>The <emphasis>advantage</emphasis> of using CSS for XML editing was the fact that we were
      able to use the XML tree itself as the model and just compute the styles for rendering each
      node, there is no transformation and mapping between an output format and the XML tree. This
      allows to provide feedback to the user on the editing context at the caret position in the
      document and to combine that with the schema information to compute the DTD/schema valid
      markup that can be inserted at that location in the document.</para><section><title>Simple editing concepts</title><para>As the position in the visual editing environment matches the position in the XML tree
        it is possible to have only 2 simple concepts that an author needs to learn in order to edit
        any XML document. The user needs to go to the position where he want to change the document
        and then:<itemizedlist><listitem><para>type to change the content</para></listitem><listitem><para>press "Enter" to enter markup</para></listitem></itemizedlist>With these simple concepts an author can change any XML document.</para><para>To help locate the current position in the document when the XML tags are not displayed
        oXygen provides a number of helpers<itemizedlist><listitem><para>location tooltip</para></listitem><listitem><para>breadcrumb</para></listitem><listitem><para>synchronized views: Outline, Model, Attributes, etc.</para></listitem><listitem><para>highlight the elements at caret position</para></listitem><listitem><para>element range marker</para></listitem></itemizedlist>All these help the user understand what is the current location in the
        document and then the user can perform content and markup changes at that position.</para></section><section><title>Alternate CSS stylesheets</title><para>The specification for associating a CSS with an XML document allows to specify multiple
        CSS stylesheets as alternate stylesheets - thus it is possible to switch between different
        renderings of the XML documents and create specific CSS stylesheets focused on different
        tasks that need to be performed on the XML document.</para><para>Elements can be also completely removed from the visual interface using a <code>display
          : none;</code> property on that element - thus an alternate stylesheet can provide also a
        reduced view on the document. </para><para>As en example we provide for DocBook 3 CSS stylesheets<itemizedlist><listitem><para>the default stylesheet</para></listitem><listitem><para>a stylesheet that hides column specifications for tables</para></listitem><listitem><para>a stylesheet that highlights the content marked with DocBook specific revision
              markup</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section><title>CSS support </title><para>The CSS support covers CSS version 1, 2 and 3. </para><para>From CSS 3 we absolutely needed support for <emphasis>namespaces</emphasis> and the
          <code>attr</code> function to provide access to attribute values and thus be able to
        provide links or to present attribute information in the visual editor. We support also the
        additional attribute type parameter for the <code>attr</code> function that makes this
        function usable to provide dynamic values for CSS properties, values taken from the XML
        document itself.</para><note><para>The <code>attr</code> function gives the attribute information as read only in the
            <code>content</code> property - to be able to edit that we needed to add an
          extension.</para></note><para>Other CSS 3 functionality supported covers transparent colors and support for custom
        fonts using the <code>@font-face</code> at-rule.</para></section></section><section><title>Show/hide XML tag information</title><para>By default the XML tags are not visible but sometimes it is useful to have them visible in
      the visual editing interface. oXygen provides 6 different levels of showing markup information
      in the visual editing interface, from no tags at all to full tags with attributes:<itemizedlist><listitem><para>no tags - no tags are visible</para></listitem><listitem><para>partial tags - inline elements are presented with small tag markers that just signal
            the presence of a tag</para></listitem><listitem><para>inline tags - the tags are visible for inline elements</para></listitem><listitem><para>block tags - the tags are visible for block elements</para></listitem><listitem><para>full tags - the tags are visible for all elements</para></listitem><listitem><para>full tags with attributes - both tags and attributes are visible for all
            elements</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></section><section><title>Custom actions</title><para>Custom actions are part of the editing experience as they provide easy access to inserting
      comment fragments in XML documents. People are used with using similar actions in word
      processing applications and they expect similar support from XML authoring tools. </para><para>In oXygen we developed an architecture that allows defining custom actions mainly through
      configuration. We offer a library of common operations that should cover most of the
      processing needs, but user defined operations can also be added. Then, in order to define a
      custom action one can specify it like </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">     if (condition1) then operation1 
else if (condition2) then operation2 
else if (condition3) then operation3
... </programlisting><para>Where <code>condition1</code>, <code>condition2</code>, etc. are XPath expressions
      evaluated in the current editing context and <code>operation1</code>, <code>operation2</code>,
      etc. are custom operations configured by setting values to their parameters.</para><para>Example of common operations are <code>InsertFragmentOperation</code>,
        <code>ChangeAttributeOperation</code>, "UnwrapTagsOperation" etc. and even
        <code>XSLTOperation</code> and <code>XQueryOperation</code> - these last two allowing to use
      XSLT or XQuery scripts to define the logic of the action.</para></section><section><title>Form controls and inline actions</title><para>This makes possible to create a unified editing area where the user has access to all XML
      content, markup and attributes as well as to document specific actions added in the context
      they should be used from - no need for additional side views or toolbars.</para><para>The CSS styles allow the XML document to be nicely rendered and the users can easily
      change the content and the structure. The attribute information however it is not accessible
      in a similar way - it can go only into read-only labels and in order to change attributes the
      user needs to access them though a side panel or invoking the in-place attribute editor. </para><para>Similarly, the custom actions are generally available on the toolbar, together with all
      the other actions, or added to a menu or to a contextual menu. </para><para>In order to improve the editing of attribute values and to allow easier access to custom
      actions we added a few extension functions that can be used to bind an attribute value to a
      form control or to bind a button to a custom action and then put these directly in the
      authoring interface. These allow creating simple user interfaces that combine the visual CSS
      based authoring useful for mixed content editing with the simplicity of form controls and
      custom actions put directly in the authoring view. </para></section><section><title>Sample user interfaces</title><para>Here you can see a few sample user interfaces.</para><section><title>A DocBook document</title><para>All the specific support for an XML vocabulary is just a configuration and a set of
        resources that are packaged together is a document type or framework. oXygen provides such
        frameworks for many popular XML vocabularies and DocBook is one of them. You can see in the
        following figure the rendering of a fragment of a DocBook article.</para><figure><title>The visual rendering of a DocBook document</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol11/graphics/Bina01/Bina01-001.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></section><section><title>A I-90 form fragment</title><para>Here it is a standard I-90 form fragment, implemented in XML.</para><figure><title>The XML that represents the form data</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol11/graphics/Bina01/Bina01-002.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><figure><title>The rendered form</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol11/graphics/Bina01/Bina01-003.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></section><section><title>A travel guide</title><para>These user interfaces, if carefully designed, allow non technical users to encode
        information in XML without actually knowing anything about the underlying XML format - they
        surely need to know the subject domain of the information they encode.</para><figure><title>The XML source for a point of interest in a travel guide</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol11/graphics/Bina01/Bina01-004.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><figure><title>The visual rendering of the point of interest from the travel guide</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol11/graphics/Bina01/Bina01-005.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></section></section></article>