<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3"><title>How to survive the coming namespace winter</title><info><confgroup><conftitle>Balisage: The Markup Conference 2014</conftitle><confdates>August 5 - 8, 2014</confdates></confgroup><abstract><para>Is XML condemned to be an orphaned syntax with a dimly lit future within the Web
            browser? What can information providers with rich sources of XML do, other than
            down-translate to HTML? The evolving Web Components environment may provide a solution!
            With some simple translations, stylesheets and scripts, it will be possible to wrap
            custom XML in a minimum amount of HTML and serve it over the Web. The browsers will
            never know they’re being tricked into delivering XML.</para></abstract><author><personname><firstname>R. Alexander</firstname><surname>Miłowski</surname></personname><personblurb><para/></personblurb><affiliation><orgname>University of Edinburgh, School of Informatics</orgname></affiliation><email>alex@milowski.com</email></author><author><personname><firstname>Norman</firstname><surname>Walsh</surname></personname><personblurb><para/></personblurb><affiliation><orgname>MarkLogic Corporation</orgname></affiliation><email>norman.walsh@marklogic.com</email></author><legalnotice><para>Copyright © 2014 R. Alexander Miłowski and Norman Walsh</para></legalnotice></info><blockquote><para>It was a late night, again, at XML Prague, and Norm Walsh,
         John Snelson, Charles Greer, and I were walking along attempting
         to find dinner. We had been discussing the Web Components
         session that had occurred earlier in the day. We expressed our
         dismay and depression that we couldn't just have XML. Then it
         occurred to us, like a light being turned on (or being
         whacked on the back of the head with a ruler), Web Components
         are just markup and pretty close to XML. All we needed to do was
         use a hypen rather than a colon, and all was well. It is a
         compromise and likely the best we will get anytime soon. We get
         to put our own pointy brackets into the browser and give it
         semantics—accept it and move on.</para><attribution>Alex Miłowski recounting XML Prague 2014</attribution></blockquote><section><title>Forward from Failure</title><para>A publisher that has a large amount of information in XML documents has little
         recourse in today's world but to transform this information into HTML for delivery on the
         Web or within EPUB ebooks. The ability for the common Web browser to load and process XML
         information, with similar processing semantics to HTML, isn't available; links will not be
         identified, styles and local transformations are fraught with problems, media will not be
         loaded or rendered, and scripts will not execute to provide extensible behaviors.</para><para>At the 2009 Balisage Conference, in <emphasis role="ital">XML in the Browser: the Next
            Decade</emphasis>
         <citation>balisage-2009</citation>, Miłowski enumerated the issues with delivering XML to
         the browser and many, if not all, of those issues remain unsolved in 2014. The various
         browser vendors have since all but abandoned processing XML except as a legacy format. In
         many ways, it only remains as a serialization format for HTML5 <citation>html5</citation>
         and as a mechanism for receiving data within a Web application.</para><para>It was argued that there are intrinsic and non-intrinsic formats for the Web.  In terms
         of markup languages, HTML, SVG, and MathML were identified as the triad of intrinsic markup
         languages.  This assessment is somewhat validated by the integration of SVG and MathML into
         the HTML5 specification.</para><para>This leaves generic XML as an orphaned syntax with dimly lit future within the Web
         browser. If the writings on the walls of various mailing lists are any indication, there is
         a strong desire for less or complete removal of the native XML processing that remains
         within the browser. While current applications and backlash have prevented such removal,
         the days of XML in the browser feel numbered.</para><para>Meanwhile, XML has served a purpose for many information publishers. Tag sets, both
         custom and standardized, have been developed to encode enormous amounts of data. Within
         enterprises, processing pipelines that produce, validate, manipulate, and otherwise consume
         this data have had their benefits. It has become <emphasis>very normal</emphasis> to
         transform these documents into the appropriate HTML markup for delivery to whatever
         consumer is on the other end of that HTTP connection.</para><para>Yet, as Web developers and browser vendors seem to be moving away from custom markup,
         they seem to realize they are missing something.  Making the <emphasis role="ital">Open Web
            Platform</emphasis> extensible means that behaviors that need to accompany information
         need to packaged as reusable components.  That is, information needs to have markup that
         identifies it as a specific kind of information whose scripts, templates, and styling are
         identifiable and loadable over the Web.</para></section><section><title>Hyphens to the Rescue</title><para>Once the desire for extensible markup, outside of the direct control of either the W3C
         or browser vendors, was recognized, the concept of custom elements was introduced and
         eventually formalized <citation>custom-elements</citation>. For HTML parsing purposes, the
         essential distinction is that a custom element's name contains a hyphen—not a colon. This
         allows custom element names to be distinguished from those within HTML itself and the only
         notable exceptions are the handful of element names in SVG and MathML that contain a
         hyphen.</para><para>In common usage, custom elements of the same origin share a common
            <emphasis>prefix</emphasis> followed by a hyphen (see <xref linkend="custom-ex"/>). That
         prefix currently has no registration or association with any URI. As such, it is unlike XML
         namespace prefixes which must be declared before being used.</para><figure xml:id="custom-ex"><title>Custom Element Example</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">&lt;html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;...&lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;db-article version="5.0"&gt;</emphasis>
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;db-title&gt;</emphasis>Foreshadowing<emphasis role="bold">&lt;/db-title&gt;</emphasis>
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;db-section&gt;</emphasis>
      <emphasis role="bold">&lt;db-title&gt;</emphasis>Wondering<emphasis role="bold">&lt;/db-title&gt;</emphasis>
      <emphasis role="bold">&lt;db-para&gt;</emphasis>I wonder where is this paper is going?<emphasis role="bold">&lt;/db-para&gt;</emphasis>
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;/db-section&gt;</emphasis>
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;/db-article&gt;</emphasis>
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt; </programlisting></figure><para>The use of custom elements goes beyond just syntax as it also provides an API for
         registering behaviors with the browser for the markup. During parsing, the DOM construction
         process assigns certain classes to recognized markup (e.g.
            <code>HTMLParagraphElement</code> is used for the <code>p</code> element). When an
         unrecognized element is encountered (i.e. a custom element), it is initially constructed as
            <code>HTMLUnknownElement</code>.</para><para>A script can register with the document a prototype that defines a new behavior or
         assigns an existing HTML behavior to a custom element. For example, the
            <code>db-para</code> could simply be registered as an HTML paragraph as shown in <xref linkend="register-ex"/>. The DOM object for the element is subsequently replaced with a
         new instance of the appropriate type and the behaviors of that element are now
         accessible.</para><figure xml:id="register-ex"><title>Registering a Custom Element</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">document.register("db-para",{ prototype: HTMLParagraphElement.prototype });
document.register("db-title",{ prototype: HTMLHeadingElement.prototype });
document.register("db-programlisting",{ prototype: HTMLPreElement.prototype });</programlisting></figure><para>In simple cases, an element registered as a custom element with one of the available
         HTML prototypes inherits some of the custom behaviors. In testing, it is unlikely that
         default styling will automatically be applied (e.g. using
            <code>HTMLPreElement.prototype</code> doesn't guarantee <code>pre</code> element
         styling). Yet, in some cases, styling does occur and so the behavior is inconsistent and
         seems to be implementation defined.  One can imagine that a consistent, reliable behavior
         is the goal and this will sort itself with time.</para><para>Moreover, registration can go far beyond such simple associations of name to pre-defined
         prototypes. A script can register a custom prototype to provide specific behaviors. The
         prototype provided must contain a function via a <code>createdCallback</code> property that
         will perform any additional initialization of the element. Other similar mechanism are
         available for maintaining the element throughout its life cycle.</para><para>For example, in <xref linkend="highlight-ex"/>, the callback applies a JavaScript-based
         syntax highlighter (<emphasis role="ital">highlight.js</emphasis>
         <citation>highlightjs</citation>) to the contents of the element. Once the element is
         re-created within the DOM with this prototype, the callback function executes with the
         value of <code>this</code> assigned to the element. In this particular example, this means
         the <code>db-programlisting</code> element is constructed with the prototype and the
         callback adds the syntax highlighting.</para><figure xml:id="highlight-ex"><title>Auto-highlighting Code</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">document.registerElement(
   "db-programlisting",
   { prototype:  
       Object.create(HTMLPreElement.prototype, {
          createdCallback: {
             value: function() {
                hljs.highlightBlock(this);
             }
          }
       })
   }
);</programlisting></figure><para>Often, the structured information of an element doesn't directly match the desired
         rendering.  The use of HTML Templates (part of the HTML5 specification) provides the
         ability to package and use structured layouts for the display of custom elements. A
         template is a portion of markup that is wrapped by a <code>template</code> element that can
         be used to construct new content programmatically. One main use for templating is to avoid
         manual construction of elements by either parsing or direct DOM method calls.</para><para>For example, in <xref linkend="reordering-ex"/>, the template for a figure is listed.
         The <code>content</code> element specifies where contained content should be placed. In
         this example, the <code>select</code> attribute is used to specify which child elements
         should be used. The result of this example is reordering the children of
            <code>db-figure</code> so that the title is last.</para><figure xml:id="reordering-ex"><title>Reordering via Templates</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">&lt;template id="db-figure"&gt;
  &lt;content select="db-mediaobject"&gt;&lt;/content&gt;
  &lt;content select="db-title"&gt;&lt;/content&gt;
&lt;/template&gt;</programlisting></figure><para>The registered prototype must use the template and the <emphasis role="ital">Shadow DOM</emphasis>
         <citation>shadowdom</citation> to affect the rendering of the element. The Shadow DOM
         provides the ability to create a rendering based on elements not shown to the user. When
         the user inspects the displayed element (or its source), they will only see the custom
         element. Inside the browser, a "shadow element" is used to structure and render the same
         information where the shadow element is only accessible via scripting or styling embedded
         within the template.</para><para>An example of using a template for the <code>db-figure</code> element is shown in <xref linkend="using-templates"/>. The callback constructs a Shadow DOM for the current
         element and appends content. The content is structured via the template shown in <xref linkend="reordering-ex"/>. The consequence is the current sub-tree for
            <code>db-figure</code> is rendered using the newly constructed Shadow DOM.</para><figure xml:id="using-templates"><title>Using Templates</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">var componentDocument = document.currentScript.ownerDocument;
document.registerElement(
   "db-figure",
   { prototype:  
       Object.create(HTMLDivElement.prototype, {
          createdCallback: {
             value: function() {
                var t = componentDocument.getElementById("db-figure");
                var clone = document.importNode(t.content, true);
                this.createShadowRoot().appendChild(clone);
             }
          }
      })
   }
);</programlisting></figure><para>Finally, we can package our script, templates, and any styling via <emphasis role="ital">HTML
            Imports</emphasis>
         <citation>html-imports</citation>.  The imported document is simply another HTML document
         whose scripts, styles, and templates become available to the current document.  The import
         is invoked by a simple <code>link</code> element with <code>rel</code> attribute value of
               <quote><code>import</code></quote> in the importing document (see <xref linkend="import-ex"/>).</para><para>The imported document packages the Web Component by linking to the necessary scripts and
         stylesheets while containing any templates that are used by those scripts. The example in
            <xref linkend="packaged-ex"/> shows the structure used to package the previous examples.
         The scripts and stylesheets for the highlighter are included using the same mechanism
         already known to Web developers.</para><para>As a nuance, the script registering the custom elements and the templates are in
         collusion within this imported document.  At the very start of the example in <xref linkend="using-templates"/>, the expression
            <code>document.currentScript.ownerDocument</code> is used to obtain the correct document
         for retrieving the templates.  If the component is packaged differently, retrieving the
         template might be more difficult or impossible.</para><figure xml:id="import-ex"><title>Importing a Document</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">&lt;html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
     &lt;link rel="import" href="db-component.xhtml"/&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
  ...
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting></figure><figure xml:id="packaged-ex"><title>Packaged Component</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">&lt;html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;DocBook Component&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="db-component.css"/&gt;
    &lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="http://yandex.st/highlightjs/8.0/styles/default.min.css"/&gt;
    &lt;script type="text/javascript" 
            src="http://yandex.st/highlightjs/8.0/highlight.min.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
     &lt;template id="db-article"&gt;
     ...
     &lt;/template&gt;
     ...
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting></figure><para>In summary, Web Components relies on four essential features:</para><orderedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Custom Elements</emphasis> — a specification that is in <quote>Last
                  Call</quote> and may enter CR in 2014.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">HTML Templates</emphasis> — part of HTML5 (see <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html/scripting-1.html#the-template-element" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">§4.12.3 The template element</link>) that is in CR as of February 04,
               2014.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Shadow DOM</emphasis> — a specification that is a working
               draft.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">HTML Imports</emphasis> — a specification that is a working draft and
               volatile.</para></listitem></orderedlist></section><section><title>Pandora's Box?</title><para>As the features of Web Components coalesce and become part of the commonly deployed
         browser, there is little anyone can do to prevent their use. An author can simply import a
         Web Component of their choice, custom or shared, and the browser can do little more than
         execute the associated semantics within the bounds of the Open Web Platform. That allows
         anyone to develop custom markup to encapsulate their information in much the same way was
         hoped for with XML.</para><para>There are two notable differences between now (2014) and 1998:</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>The browser, as a component of the Open Web Platform, is much more stable,
               technologically advanced, and well understood.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Web Components utilize the Open Web Platform to package semantics in a much more
               extensive way that is compatible with <emphasis>how browsers actually
               work</emphasis>.</para></listitem></orderedlist><para>An unscientific look at the current opinions of the use of Web Components indicates it
         may become hugely popular. While only time will actually determine the outcome, the Shadow
         DOM and HTML Templates are very useful. Accessing them within Custom Elements provides
         needed encapsulation to Web applications and so their intended use in that context makes a
         lot of sense.</para><para>Yet, we don't have to use Web Components to package semantics for custom markup that is
         limited to specialized uses. That is, with relative ease, we can transliterate whole XML
         documents into custom elements, wrap them with a few lines of HTML markup, and the browser
         will load and process the custom elements as specified. Is this abuse, a practice that
         isn't recommended, or should a thousand custom elements bloom?</para><para>Let's open Pandora's box and see whether what is inside is truly evil. We will take
         DocBook, a known vocabulary for documents (books, articles, etc.), and turn the markup into
         a set of Web Components. We will demonstrate how easy the transliteration is to perform and
         show a few interesting results.</para></section><section><title>The DocBook Web Component</title><para>Turning any arbitrary XML document into an HTML document as a Web Component requires on
         three essential steps:</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>Prefix every element with a constant prefix and hyphen that can be associated with
               the element's namespace.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Develop stylesheets, templates, and scripts that encapsulate the desired
               behavior.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Wrap the document in the minimum amount of HTML bootstrapping necessary to deliver
               the Web Component to the browser.</para></listitem></orderedlist><figure xml:id="transform-xproc"><title>Transformation Pipeline</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">&lt;p:declare-step xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
   xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
   version="1.0"
   name="top"&gt;

   &lt;p:input port="source"/&gt;
   &lt;p:output port="result"/&gt;

   &lt;!-- directly process the wrapper and replace the content
        element with the translated DocBook elements --&gt;
   &lt;p:viewport <emphasis>match="h:content"</emphasis>&gt;
      &lt;p:viewport-source&gt;
         &lt;p:document <emphasis>href="wrapper.xhtml"</emphasis>/&gt;
      &lt;/p:viewport-source&gt;

      &lt;!-- transliterate the DocBook elements --&gt;
      &lt;p:xslt&gt;
         &lt;p:input port="source"&gt;
            &lt;p:pipe port="source" step="top"/&gt;
         &lt;/p:input&gt;
         &lt;p:input port="parameters"&gt;&lt;p:empty/&gt;&lt;/p:input&gt;
         &lt;p:input port="stylesheet"&gt;
            &lt;p:document <emphasis>href="db-content.xsl"</emphasis>/&gt;
         &lt;/p:input&gt;
      &lt;/p:xslt&gt;

   &lt;/p:viewport&gt;
    
&lt;/p:declare-step&gt;</programlisting></figure><para>For example, in the specific case of DocBook, we would do the follow:</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>Transform the document by changing every DocBook element name to a name with
                     <quote><code>db-</code></quote> prefix with no namespace. Also, copy any MathML
               or SVG to the output and pay specific attention to the serialization (HTML without a
               namespace or XHTML with a namespace). </para></listitem><listitem><para>Implement Web Components for common constructions like xref,
               mediaobject/imageobject/imagedata, link, etc. and develop CSS stylesheets for the
               rest. Package this component as a single document (see <xref linkend="packaged-ex"/>).</para></listitem><listitem><para>Wrap the document in the minimum markup (see <xref linkend="import-ex"/>).</para></listitem></orderedlist><para>In addition, we'd like to retain some aspect of identity of the namespace from the
         original XML. To do so, we will add an RDFa <citation>rdfa</citation>
         <code>typeof</code> attribute on the root element whose value is the namespace URI. This
         will allow a consuming application to identify the custom element by type rather than a
         fixed prefix. Hence, on the root custom element for DocBook (e.g. <code>db-article</code>),
         a <code>typeof</code> attribute will contain the value
               <quote><code>http://docbook.org/ns/docbook</code></quote>.</para><para>This process was implemented using the simple XProc <citation>xproc</citation> pipeline
         shown in <xref linkend="transform-xproc"/> where the transformed document is inserted in
         the wrapper (see <xref linkend="wrapper"/>) as a replacement for the <code>content</code>
         element. The transformation is simply a set of renaming rules with the main two rules shown
         in <xref linkend="main-xslt"/>.</para><figure xml:id="wrapper"><title>Wrapper Document</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">&lt;html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
     &lt;link rel="import" href="db-component.xhtml"/&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;content/&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting></figure><figure xml:id="main-xslt"><title>Main XSLT Rules</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">&lt;xsl:template match="/db:*"&gt;
   &lt;xsl:element name="db-{local-name()}" namespace="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;
      &lt;xsl:attribute name="typeof"&gt;&lt;xsl:value-of select="namespace-uri()"/&gt;&lt;/xsl:attribute&gt;
      &lt;xsl:apply-templates select="@*|node()"/&gt;
   &lt;/xsl:element&gt;
&lt;/xsl:template&gt;
   
&lt;xsl:template match="db:*"&gt;
   &lt;xsl:element name="db-{local-name()}" namespace="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;
      &lt;xsl:apply-templates select="@*|node()"/&gt;
   &lt;/xsl:element&gt;
&lt;/xsl:template&gt;</programlisting></figure><para>In terms of what these custom elements might provide to a user, some behaviors for
         DocBook that require scripting are:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Links (e.g. link or xref).</para></listitem><listitem><para>Auto-numbering of sections, figures, etc.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Display of media objects (e.g. imageobject/imagedata).</para></listitem><listitem><para>Generated text for cross references (e.g. turn xref into "Figure 2.1 ...").</para></listitem><listitem><para>Auto-generation of a table of contents and other navigation.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Syntax highlighting in programlistings and other code.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>These features were implemented<footnote xml:id="github-fn"><para>The implementation is available at <link xlink:href="https://github.com/alexmilowski/db-component" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">github / alexmilowski /
                  db-component</link>.</para></footnote> and tested in Chrome (the only browser currently implementing Web
            Components<footnote xml:id="flags-fn"><para>It is necessary to turn on experimental features in Chrome to use Web Components.
               The flags that need to be enabled are: <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Enable experimental Web Platform
                           features</emphasis> - required for Custom Elements and the Shadow
                        DOM.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Enable HTML Imports</emphasis> - required to use
                        imports for importing the component definitions and various code or
                        stylesheets.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></footnote>). In total, the implementation was 235 lines of JavaScript, 76 lines of CSS,
         and a 67 line HTML document with none of these resources having been compressed or
         otherwise optimized. The implementation also includes <code>highlight.js</code> via the
         HTML import and programmatically adds MathJax <citation>mathjax</citation> for rendering
         MathML.</para><para>At present, there are some notable issues implementing a set of Web Components and using
         HTML Imports:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>MathJax was not able to be included via the import. The method it uses to
               determine the base URI cannot find the script reference in the imported document.
               MathJax isn't <quote>HTML import aware</quote> at this point in time. As such,
               MathJax added scripts and stylesheets aren't hidden in the imported document but,
               instead, are programmatically added to the importing document.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Implementing links was harder than expected. Just associating the prototype
                  <code>HTMLAnchorElement</code> with the element does not induce some minimal
               linking behavior. Further, using a template that wraps the content with an HTML
               anchor in the Shadow DOM is more complicate as there is no way to automatically copy
               attributes (e.g. the URI in the <code>href</code> attribute) and some default
               behaviors (e.g. a mouse pointer) aren't automatic. Further, clicking had no effect
               and a custom event handler had to be added.</para></listitem><listitem><para>The division between the stylesheet within each template and the overall
               stylesheet is a bit tricky.</para></listitem><listitem><para>There is a lot more to be done to handle the full life cycle of the elements. That
               is, if other scripts manipulate the custom elements <emphasis role="ital">in
                  situ</emphasis>, the components (e.g. the auto-generated navigation) may need
               to update themselves.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>Web components can also be used within other browsers by using the Polymer Platform
            <quote>polyfill</quote>
         <citation>platform</citation>. This JavaScript library provides implementations of various
         Web Components specifications for the Firefox, Safari, and IE browsers. Unfortunately, at
         this time (July 2014), this library fails to work with the DocBook example:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Firefox crashes almost immediately.  This seems to have something to do with the
               generation of the table of contents navigation.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Safari fails with an JavaScript error.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></section><section><title>The Evolving Web</title><para>Web Components is a promising technology for delivering packaged semantics for general
         markup.  It succeeds in many places where previous attempts with XML in the browser have
         failed.  That it is somewhat of a reality today is ever more exciting.</para><para>Yet, the mechanisms for which a browser or resource consumer can recognize the use of a
         particular set of custom elements is fraught with problems. The inability to identify the
         prefix used in constructing the element names, associate that prefix with some URI, or to
         protect content from collisions with other custom elements is going to be an immediately
         painful experience. Authors and publishers will want to mix content from different sources
         outside of their control and custom elements will make that increasingly harder.</para><para>XML has a partial solution for identifying and uniquely naming elements to avoid
         collisions. Yet, that solution allows arbitrary complexity without sufficient gains in
         functionality and was rejected by many in the various Web developer communities. Yet, one
         can't help but feel like a colon was swapped for a hyphen and we lost something in the
         exchange.</para><para>In the end, Web Components lets us deliver XML documents, transliterated, and packaged
         with their semantics. The mechanisms of the Shadow DOM and scripting allow the markup used
         for rendering to have a interactive and integrated mechanism for live manipulation within
         the browser. HTML imports and templates enabling packaging of these semantics into a single
         resource.</para><para>Even though Web Components, HTML5, and scripting isn't necessarily how we all may have
         imagined XML on the Web in 1998, their combination is sufficient to accomplish real work
         with markup within the Open Web Platform. The Web has evolved and XML may be evolving along
         with it. It is a reality that we affectionately call the <quote>Prague
         Compromise</quote>.</para><blockquote><para>He put on his skis, straightened himself up, and remained standing there for some
            time; as he pulled on his mittens he took one glance homeward. He could just make out
            the house in the dim distance. Then the whiteness all around it thickened—rose up in a
            cloud—seemed to be piling in. ... Perhaps it wasn't so dangerous, after all. The wind
            had been steady all day, had held in the same quarter, and would probably keep on ...
            Oh, well—here goes!</para><para>...</para><para>On one of the hillsides stood an old haystack which a settler had left there when he
            found out that the coarse bottom hay wasn't much good for fodder. One day during the
            spring after Hans Olsa had died, a troop of young boys were ranging the prairies, in
            search of some yearling cattle that had gone astray. They came upon the haystack, and
            stood transfixed. On the west side of the stack sat a man, with his back to the
            mouldering hay. This was in the middle of a warm day in May, yet the man had two pairs
            of skis along with him; one pair lay beside him on the ground, the other was tied to his
            back. He had a heavy stocking cap pulled well down over his forehead, and large mittens
            on his hands; in each hand he clutched a staff ... To the boys, it looked as though the
            man were sitting there resting while he waited for better skiing ... His face was ashen
            and drawn. His eyes were set toward the west.</para><attribution>Giants in the Earth: A Saga of the Prairie, O. E. Rölvaag (1924)</attribution></blockquote></section><bibliography><title>Bibliography</title><bibliomixed xml:id="balisage-2009">
         <quote>XML in the Browser: the Next Decade</quote>, R. Alexander Milowski, Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, 2009-08; see also <link xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Milowski01/BalisageVol3-Milowski01.html" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Milowski01/BalisageVol3-Milowski01.html</link>. doi:<biblioid class="doi">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Milowski01</biblioid>
      </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="html5">
         <quote>HTML5</quote>, W3C, 2013-09-06, Robin Berjon, Steve Faulkner, Travis Leithead, Erika Doyle Navara, Edward O'Connor, Silvia Pfeiffer, and Ian Hickson; see also <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.w3.org/TR/html/</link>
      </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="custom-elements">
         <quote>Custom Elements</quote>, W3C, 2014-04-28, Dimitri Glazkov; see also <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/custom-elements/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.w3.org/TR/custom-elements/</link>
      </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="highlightjs">
         <quote>highlight.js</quote>, Ivan Sagalaev, Jeremy Hull, Oleg Efimov; see also <link xlink:href="http://highlightjs.org" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://highlightjs.org</link>
      </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="shadowdom">
         <quote>Shadow DOM</quote>, W3C, 2014-04-25, Dimitri Glazkov; see also <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/shadow-dom/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.w3.org/TR/shadow-dom/</link>
      </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="html-imports">
         <quote>HTML Imports</quote>, W3C, 2014-03-11, Dimitri Glazkov and Hajime Morrita; see also <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html-imports/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.w3.org/TR/html-imports/</link>
      </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="rdfa">
         <quote>RDFa Core 1.1</quote>, W3C, 2012-06-07, Ben Adida, Mark Birbeck, Shane McCarron, and Ivan Herman; see also <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdfa-core/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.w3.org/TR/rdfa-core/</link>
      </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="xproc">
         <quote>XProc: An XML Pipeline Language</quote>, W3C, 2010-05-11, Norman Walsh, Alex Miłowski, and Henry S. Thompson; see also <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xproc/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.w3.org/TR/xproc/</link>
      </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="mathjax">
         <quote>MathJax</quote>, Davide Cervone, Christian Perfect, and Peter Krautzberger; see also <link xlink:href="http://www.mathjax.org/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.mathjax.org/</link>
      </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="platform">
         <quote>Polymer Project</quote>; see also <link xlink:href="https://github.com/polymer" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://github.com/polymer</link>
      </bibliomixed></bibliography></article>