<div id="mainContainerTOC">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTOC" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTOC').toggle('1000');">Table of Content</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTOC" style="display:none;">
      <div class="headedContainerTOC">
         <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#SometimesaquestionofscaleANCHOR" name="SometimesaquestionofscaleTOC">Sometimes a question of scale</a></div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ReferencesANCHOR" name="ReferencesTOC">References</a></div>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerTERMS">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTERMS" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTERMS').toggle('1000')">Index of Terms</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTERMS" style="display:none;">
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">a</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">August 11 - 14, 2009</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">b</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Baghdad</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">c</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">core</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">capable</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">call things by the names you give them</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">C. M.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">d</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">DestroyBaghdad</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">DestroyCity</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">e</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">f</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">g</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">h</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">i</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">j</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">k</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">l</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">m</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">mostly streamable</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Mindlessness</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">n</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">new</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Nathan der Weise</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">o</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">over the wall</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">p</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">q</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">r</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">s</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">SCALE</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">streamability</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Sperberg-McQueen</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">t</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">u</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">v</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">x</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">y</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Yeah, they happen. Deal with it.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">you</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">z</div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerIML"><a name="SometimesaquestionofscaleANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="article e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2">
      <div class="title e1">Sometimes a question of scale</div>
      <div class="info e2">
         <div class="confgroup e3">
            <div class="conftitle e4">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>
            <div class="confdates e5">August 11 - 14, 2009</div>
         </div>
         <div class="abstract e6">
            <div class="para e7">Reflections on size, scale, scaleability, and value.</div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e8">
            <div class="personname e9">
               <div class="firstname e10">C. M.</div>
               <div class="surname e11">Sperberg-McQueen</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e12">
               <div class="para e13">C. M. Sperberg-McQueen is a consultant specializing in the 
                  use of XML and related technologies to help preserve public information (especially
                  
                  cultural heritage data) and make it accessible.  He has served as co-editor of the
                  
                  XML 1.0 specification, the Guidelines of the Text Encoding Initiative, and the XML
                  
                  Schema Definition Language (XSDL) 1.1 specification.  He holds a doctorate in 
                  comparative literature.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e14">
               <div class="orgname e15">Black Mesa Technologies LLC</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="legalnotice e16">
            <div class="para e17">Copyright © 2009 by the author.  Used with
               permission.
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div class="para e18">My friend David Ezell, the chair of the World Wide Web Consortium’s
         XML Schema Working Group, wrote me recently: 
         <div class="quote e19">Best laid plans, and
            careful designs, often degenerate into unintended consequences in the
            face of 
            <div class="emphasis e20" role="ital">SCALE</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="popupBox e21">
            <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e35').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e35').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
            <div id="d1e35" style="display: none;">
               <div class="footnote">
                  <div class="para e22">This version 
                     of these remarks was prepared by consulting both the notes from which I
                     spoke and a recording of what I said, but I have taken the opportunity
                     to recast a few passages here and there and to correct (silently) some
                     errors made during the presentation.
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         
      </div>
      <div class="para e23">I have been thinking a lot about that, lately.</div>
      <div class="para e24">When we scale up from a prototype or experimental system to production
         work, or when we scale up from a niche product to a mass product, things can 
         go wrong in a number of ways:
         
         <div class="itemizedlist e25">
            <div class="listitem e26">
               <div class="para e27">Maybe things don’t run fast enough, so they can’t keep up
                  with the volume of data that it takes to run something in production.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="listitem e28">
               <div class="para e29">Maybe we failed to foresee that when usage grows,
                  or the quantity of some particular resource grows (changes in scale),
                  that some other resource is going to become scarce, and we’ve neglected 
                  to take steps to conserve it.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="listitem e30">
               <div class="para e31">Maybe we’ve failed to remember that the successful delivery 
                  of the first part of a multi-part solution can change the environment within which
                  and in terms of which the problem was identified, in such a way that the second 
                  and third parts of the proposed solution no longer fit because the problem has 
                  changed shape. Or more generally: we may have failed to see that the
                  salient properties of today’s situations are not necessarily permanent. And 
                  although we are trying to plan for the long term, we end up deciding (for example),
                  that namespaces cannot possibly be declared using processing instructions, 
                  because Netscape 3 would do the wrong thing with them. And it’s essential that 
                  namespaces be deployable in the browser. Neither of those constraints seems to 
                  have quite the same force today that it did when the namespace technology was 
                  being designed. Netscape 3 is no longer the standard browser in at least many
                  organizations [laughter], and the people responsible for HTML and W3C’s interface
                  
                  to the browser seem to have changed their minds about how essential it is that 
                  namespaces be deployed in the browser in the first place.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="listitem e32">
               <div class="para e33">Or we could simply fail to predict the true complexity of the
                  environment within which our system will be asked to operate, or the true 
                  difficulty of the problems it’s going to be asked to help solve.
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         Thinking about it this way I have begun to think that in one way or another almost
         every paper at this conference has touched, directly or indirectly, on some problem
         
         relating to scale.
      </div>
      <div class="para e34">First, of course, there’s the problem of speed and streamability.</div>
      <div class="para e35">We’ve heard a lot this week about the problems of speeding
         up XML processing and constraining its memory requirements
         in order to allow users to process larger and larger streams of data.
      </div>
      <div class="para e36">On Monday we had a full day on the topic. starting with extremely clever 
         work first on a chip intended to accelerate XML processing in the software 
         running in the hardware containing the chip [
         <div class="xref e37" linkend="Leventhal"></div>],
         or an entire XML system on the chip, with parser and XSLT processor and 
         schema validator and XML signature processor, and so on [
         <div class="xref e38" linkend="Salz"></div>].
         And the team from Simon Fraser University led by Rob Cameron told us about an 
         extremely ingenious use of the parallel instructions on newer chips intended to 
         support multi-media, to support instead parallel parsing of XML [
         <div class="xref e39" linkend="Cameron"></div>].
         I take a certain pleasure now in recollecting that one of the problems Charles
         Babbage struggled with for a long time was to improve the behavior and
         performance of his mechanisms for carrying digits from one column to another, 
         because of course one carry could lead to another carry, could lead to another 
         carry. And making that happen fast was a serious problem for Babbage.
         It gives me particular pleasure to recollect that, because Rob Cameron 
         has observed that his team have been able to simplify and refine their 
         technique to the point where the entire technique revolves around this one 
         problem of making a carry bit go from one context to another when needed:  
         everything can be reduced to that one problem. It’s nice how much continuity 
         there can be in technological history.
      </div>
      <div class="para e40">Layered above those low-level problems, there are similarly
         complex problems at higher levels.
      </div>
      <div class="para e41">On Monday, David Lee demonstrated that XML processing is
         no exception to what some old-timers have described to me as
         an eternal law of data processing:  context switches are really expensive.
         and you really want to avoid them [
         <div class="xref e42" linkend="Lee"></div>]. Why does the 
         flagship Oracle database ship with its own programming language, instead 
         of just using the techniques which are the core of the SQL standard to allow 
         users to call SQL from C or Cobol or Fortran or whatever programming 
         language they  want to use? A grayhaired researcher from Oracle once 
         told me, no, it was not because they had hot-shot programmers who just
         couldn’t rest until they had invented yet another programming language 
         with yet another syntax and yet another function library and yet another 
         set of quirks. It was because every time the database system threw control 
         
         <div class="quote e43">over the wall</div> to the application and then the application 
         threw control back over the wall to the database system, they lost several 
         hundred milliseconds.  A hundred milliseconds here, a few hundred there. 
         It begins to mount up.
      </div>
      <div class="para e44">Mohammed Zergaoui illustrated that these are not simple problems 
         [
         <div class="xref e45" linkend="Zergaoui"></div>].  Even defining what 
         <div class="emphasis e46" role="ital">streamability</div> 
         means, and what the rules for streamability ought to be, is not simple. What are 
         the tradeoffs among pure streamability, something that’s not strictly streamable 
         because its memory requirements grow without bound, but grow only very 
         slowly, so it’s sort of 
         <div class="quote e47">mostly streamable</div>, and rules that allow 
         a process to be kinda sorta streamable, on a good day, if the wind doesn’t 
         change? It’s more complicated than you might think at first.
      </div>
      <div class="para e48">Maybe that’s why David Birnbaum found, when he ran into his XPath 
         quicksand [
         <div class="xref e49" linkend="Birnbaum"></div>], that the system he was using wasn’t 
         in much of a position to explain to him why his query was painfully slow.  It 
         took careful experimentation by systematically changing first one part of 
         the program, then another, in the carefully calibrated process known to
         professional programmers as random guesswork, to find the bottleneck. And 
         then it took human eyes to examine that part of the query and explain why it 
         was so slow.  It then took more random, er, systematic, experimentation to 
         find alternative formulations of the problem that would behave better in that
         particular implementation.
      </div>
      <div class="para e50">David concluded by observing that the best performance of all on the 
         problem was achieved when the developers changed the behavior of the 
         implementation on that kind of query, under the hood. But I draw a slightly
         different moral from his experience escaping from that quicksand:  those of 
         us on the user side of the keyboard are not powerless; with application and 
         determination and a little luck we can help ourselves to better performance, 
         even if we can’t get much help from the developers.  Work on scalability is 
         not an exclusive club:  anybody can play the game, if they are willing to do 
         the work.
      </div>
      <div class="para e51">Norm Walsh gave hope to those who really would prefer that other
         people do that work, by observing that as far as we can tell, based on our 
         minimal understanding of what the usage patterns will be for an extremely 
         new language, most typical XProc pipelines will be streamable, so that an 
         aggressively optimizing processor can hope to provide good performance 
         even if the user does nothing [
         <div class="xref e52" linkend="Walsh"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e53">Michael Kay gave us an enlightening discussion of the push/pull 
         duality in pipelines, and illustrated a surprising point about the way things 
         scale over time [
         <div class="xref e54" linkend="Kay"></div>]. When one part of a problem or 
         system changes scale dramatically, the character of the problem changes, 
         and we often need new algorithms.  So if you look at textbooks published in 
         the 1980s, their description of sorting doesn’t look like the same thing as the 
         descriptions of sorting published in textbooks in the 1970s. Why? Because 
         the kinds of things people needed to sort had changed — or rather, 
         the kinds of things people needed to sort were much the same, but the 
         underlying hardware was so different that you could have an entirely new set 
         of algorithms that performed much better. Over time it can happen that the 
         other factors in the system catch up, and the system regains something like 
         its original overall proportions, the problem changes again, and we may find 
         that techniques developed in the 1970s for program inversion are practially 
         relevant again. Knuth’s discussion of tape sorting has never lost its purely 
         mathematical interest and beauty.  But nowadays, programmers may be reading 
         it not for the sake of its mathematical beauty but to help them optimize current 
         systems, which aren’t using tapes but are using storage which, like tapes, is 
         slower than core.  (Do I date myself if I call it 
         <div class="quote e55">core</div>? I guess I 
         do.  Sorry; I never learned to call it anything else.)
      </div>
      <div class="para e56">Tomasz Müldner’s work on queryable compression for XML shows 
         that, as with time, so also with space:  if you apply enough ingenuity you may 
         find ways to reduce space requirements without impairing usability (at least, if we
         
         take queryability as a reasonably good proxy for usability) [
         <div class="xref e57" linkend="Müldner"></div>].
         
      </div>
      <div class="para e58">There’s another sense in which we speak of things scaling up. Some 
         people are interested in any technology only to the extent that it has large 
         numbers of users.
      </div>
      <div class="para e59">If you want a large number of users, the World Wide Web appears to 
         be an inescapable model, or object of contemplation.
      </div>
      <div class="para e60">How did that happen?</div>
      <div class="para e61">Why did the World Wide Web become quasi-universal? In the early 
         1990s it was one of several hypertext systems. HTML and HTTP were not 
         better developed that Guide or System G.  In fact, everybody I know who 
         actually knows all of those systems tells me that Guide and System G were 
         much more impressive than the first HTML browsers.
      </div>
      <div class="para e62">Why was it that the World Wide Web spread, and became quasi-universal, 
         and not Guide or System G?
      </div>
      <div class="para e63">There’s a story that people tell, that in the early ’90s, this guy at 
         CERN, Tim Berners-Lee, proposed a paper to the European Conference on 
         Hypertext (ECHT). In it, he described a system he wanted to build, which would 
         provide essentially a world-wide hypertext. The paper, famously, was rejected.
      </div>
      <div class="para e64">How the rejection is interpreted, and thus the next part of the story, 
         depends on who is telling it. I have heard people associated with the World 
         Wide Web Consortium tell it as a story of reviewers who were essentially blind. 
         They were fixed in their ways, they understood how existing systems did things, 
         and the Web wasn’t going to do things that way.  So the reviewers said, 
         
         <div class="quote e65">It’s impossible; hypertext systems will never scale to those dimensions.  
            It can’t be done; the paper is technically naive.
         </div> The story illustrates, 
         in this telling, how new ideas are often misunderstood.
      </div>
      <div class="para e66">I talked once with someone who had a number of friends among the 
         program committee of the European Conference on Hypertext.  From that 
         person, I heard a slightly different version of the story.  The reviewers read 
         the paper and said 
         <div class="quote e67">yes, you can build a system like that.  We’ve all 
            built toy hypertext systems, systems that don’t do anything to ensure link 
            integrity and don’t care about findability.  We’ve built them; but they are not 
            interesting. They are not 
            <div class="emphasis e68" role="ital">capable</div>; we are interested
            in better systems than that. The paper would be interesting if it had some new 
            method of dealing with link rot or discoverability, but there’s nothing here about
            
            either topic.
         </div>  So the paper offered nothing 
         <div class="emphasis e69" role="ital">new</div>,
         and was rejected on that ground.
      </div>
      <div class="para e70">Actually, the reviewers did miss something. Maybe Tim didn’t explain 
         it in the clearest possible way, but the technical innovation in the World 
         Wide Web’s treatment of broken links is to say 
         <div class="quote e71">Yeah, they happen. 
            Deal with it.
         </div>  The mechanism that runs fastest and scales best is 
         the mechanism you don’t have to build at all. By just saying that we won’t 
         have any mechanism at all to deal with those problems, Tim was able to 
         achieve what I believe must have been his primary technical design goal for 
         the World Wide Web:  he made it scaleable. It’s decentralized; at least initially
         
         Web browsers and Web servers could be relatively simple (I don’t think that
         modern Web browsers are dramatically simpler than Guide, but the initial 
         ones certainly were); and it encourages low expectations on the part of the 
         user. Those are all recipes for good scaleability.
      </div>
      <div class="para e72">But those properties don’t explain why the Web became universal;
         at most, they explain why, when it became universal, it was able to survive 
         the transition.
      </div>
      <div class="para e73">I think the reason the Web became universal was that it provided 
         an advantageous cost/benefit ratio to huge numbers of people.  Lots of 
         people found it worth their while to set up a Web server and start serving
         pages.  It was easy enough to set up the server or to write HTML that even 
         the relatively modest payback in kudos or visibility or convenience was 
         enough to justify the expenditure of effort to make it happen. Of course, 
         the initial Web site hosts were typically technical people interested in doing 
         fun things, or interested in disseminating information, not necessarily people 
         seeking to make a buck. but it illustrates what I have come to call the Paoli
         Principle, named for Jean Paoli, one of the co-editors of the XML 1.0 
         specification, who is probably more responsible than any other single 
         human being for getting many different product groups within Microsoft to
         take an interest in XML, and therefore probably more responsible than any 
         other single person for the ubiquity of XML as an infrastructure in today’s
         commercial IT environment.
      </div>
      <div class="para e74">Jean has frequently said 
         <div class="quote e75">If you ask people to expend five 
            cents worth of effort, then you need to give them five cents worth of benefit, 
            very quickly.
         </div> Ideally, you’d like to give them ten cents worth of 
         benefit, but at the very least they have to make back their effort. And if 
         you don’t manage that, then it’s only some who is already suffering severe 
         pain owing to other causes who will persevere with your technology.
      </div>
      <div class="para e76">This leads me to think about Alex Milowski’s talk and the state of
         XML on the Web [
         <div class="xref e77" linkend="Milowski"></div>]. Is XML on the Web a failure? 
         or a success?  Good question; sometimes I think, yes, and sometimes I think, 
         no, to each of those questions in turn, and sometimes vice versa. If what you 
         want is for everybody to use XML, then it’s not a success.  Manifestly, not 
         everyone in the world is using XML, and if that’s the goal then the only question
         
         left is whether we should keep trying, or accept defeat and move on to do
         something else with our lives.
      </div>
      <div class="para e78">If on the other hand your goal, as Murray Maloney was saying this
         morning in one of the discussions, was to do things the way 
         <div class="emphasis e79" role="ital">you</div> 
         want to do them, and not the way some program wants to try to force you to 
         do them, and if like some people (including me) what you want to do is to
         
         <div class="emphasis e80" role="ital">call things by the names you give them</div>, and not by 
         the names some program tries to make you call them by, then XML on the 
         Web is a huge success.  I can do what I wanted to do: I can publish, in XML, 
         on the Web, and browsers will display it appropriately. I can publish XML on 
         the Web and treat HTML purely as a page description language for certain 
         kinds of interactive pages, exactly as I treat PDF as a page description 
         language for paper pages.
         <div class="popupBox e81">
            <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e165').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e165').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
            <div id="d1e165" style="display: none;">
               <div class="footnote">
                  <div class="para e82">It should be noted that PDF 
                     readers do have some interactive features; I just don’t use them very 
                     often.
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div> I don’t think about the page description language, 
         except when I’m trying to design and describe the page.  When I’m editing, 
         I can deal with the ontology I choose.
      </div>
      <div class="para e83">Some of us only ever wanted to be able to publish on the web in 
         SGML. We probably expected some others, particularly large organizations 
         that had valuable data with valuable semantics, to want to do the same. My
         memory may be faulty, but I don’t remember anyone in the SGML on the
         Web WG claiming that the criterion for success should be that the large 
         body of HTML users should throw down their HTML and take up XML.
         I’m sure everyone thought that would be a wonderful thing if it happened,
         but I don’t remember anyone saying that that should be the criterion of 
         success. Others, not necessarily members of that working group, who
         took it as axiomatic that for any technology the only definition of success 
         is universal uptake, naturally assumed that universal uptake was the criterion 
         of XML’s success. They gave it a one- or two-year deadline (we are speaking 
         after all about Web time!) and now ten years later they more or less
         naturally conclude that the experiment has been a failure, that XML has 
         failed to live up to their expectations, and that we should forget about it.
      </div>
      <div class="para e84">How do we make XML scale up? Do we need to? Do we wish to?</div>
      <div class="para e85">Perhaps XML’s natural niche is simply a smaller one, in which it is 
         used by many people (beneath the hood), but invisible to most of them 
         (except for a small number of people, like perhaps many in this room, who 
         habitually want to pop the hood and look at what’s happening underneath).
         
      </div>
      <div class="para e86">Wide usage can mean having lots of users. But it can also mean wide 
         applicability, ubiquity, applications in many areas, and openness to the wider 
         community, or at least smooth interoperation with the rest of the world.
      </div>
      <div class="para e87">I’m happy to see papers about work that pushes XML into new and 
         interesting areas of application, and illustrates the problems and opportunities 
         in XML’s coexistence with the non-XML part of the universe (yes, I’m told 
         there is one).
      </div>
      <div class="para e88">The work reported on at the U.S. National Archives [
         <div class="xref e89" linkend="Nguyen"></div>],
         the work on health care data in several papers [
         <div class="xref e90" linkend="Beuchelt"></div>],
         [
         <div class="xref e91" linkend="McCay"></div>], Zoe Borovsky’s illustration that yes, you can take
         XML data and use network analysis tools to visualize it [
         <div class="xref e92" linkend="Borovsky"></div>].
         Even if it does typically mean stripping out all the markup so the network 
         analysis tools will read it, still, you can get there.
      </div>
      <div class="para e93">Mohamed Zergaoui’s illustration that modeling tools don’t necessarily 
         have to put angle brackets into the users’ eyes [
         <div class="xref e94" linkend="Zergaoui-bis"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e95">Peter Flynn’s paper on XML editors helps show us what openness 
         to the rest of the world may entail in practice [
         <div class="xref e96" linkend="Flynn"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e97">Related to this topic are efforts to push XML into the infrastructure, 
         like those reported by Slava Zholudev and Michael Kohlhase, with the goal 
         of making an XML-aware versioned storage system [
         <div class="xref e98" linkend="Zholudev"></div>]. 
      </div>
      <div class="para e99">And on the more general topic of our interactions with and our 
         responsibilities to the wider community, of course, the memorable talk by 
         Kurt Cagle this morning [
         <div class="xref e100" linkend="Cagle"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e101">As Patrick Durusau and Kurt Cagle agreed this morning, it is not 
         necessarily our mission to teach others what justice and transparency are.  
         But we can, and I think some of us will choose to, try to develop descriptive 
         markup and its technologies in such a way as to make it easier for 
         technology to support appropriate kinds of transparency and appropriate 
         kinds of responsibility.
      </div>
      <div class="para e102">Now, this is kind of an idealistic line of thought, about our ethical 
         responsibility as professionals, and it’s not hard to make fun of it. During 
         the first Gulf War a wit [
         <div class="xref e103" linkend="Borenstein"></div>] wrote
         
         <div class="popupBox e104">
            <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e212').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e212').hide('1000');">[ blockquote ]</div>
            <div id="d1e212" style="display: none;">
               <div class="blockquote">
                  <div class="para e105">It should be noted that no ethically-trained software engineer 
                     would ever consent to write a 
                     <div class="quote e106">DestroyBaghdad</div> procedure. 
                     Basic professional ethics would instead require him to write a
                     
                     <div class="quote e107">DestroyCity</div> procedure, to which 
                     <div class="quote e108">Baghdad</div> 
                     could be given as a parameter.
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div class="para e109">We are not the sole repositories of truth.  And what we do to 
         benefit the causes which we believe to be right, may also — indeed,
         it almost certainly 
         <div class="emphasis e110" role="ital">will</div> also — prove useful
         to those doing what we believe to be wrong.  The Web was built for fine 
         and noble reasons, but it does provide communication and support for
         racists, and terrorists, and enemies of all the things we may believe to be 
         fine and noble, as well as providing support for those we may agree with. 
         The consequences of our actions as technologists are as likely to be mixed 
         as are the consequences of any other people’s actions.
      </div>
      <div class="para e111">And yet I can’t quite bring myself to agree with Patrick Durusau’s
         proposal, this morning, that none of us does anything because we think
         it will make the world a better place, but only because someone pays
         us to do it. A former colleague with whom I disagreed about practically 
         everything once hit the nail on the head when he said (to the visible 
         dismay of management, who were disconcerted by this independence 
         of thought) that he chose to work for our common employer because it 
         helped him achieve a specific set of goals for the Web and the world, and 
         that the moment he concluded that further employment with that employer 
         was not helping him and the world achieve the goals he was working toward, 
         he would be gone. Whether we work for employers or for clients, we have 
         the choice:  either to work in a particular way so as to have clients, or to 
         have clients in order to allow us to work in the ways that we choose.  Or, 
         as a character in Lessing’s play 
         <div class="emphasis e112" role="ital">Nathan der Weise</div>
         put it:  Kein Mensch muß müssen.  No one can be compelled
         to be compelled.
      </div>
      <div class="para e113">The Web shows us that one way to scale up is to make things easy,
         to allow faults, to make the system robust in the face of error.
      </div>
      <div class="para e114">But there is another time-honored method of scaling things up, and 
         that is to control error, to mechanize and automate operations, so as to
         control complexity and minimize the number of things we have to keep in
         our heads at any one point while we’re trying to do  things.
      </div>
      <div class="para e115">Arithmetic, algebra, symbolic logic are all examples of this approach 
         to scalability. They provide mechanical rules for manipulating formulas, so 
         that we can think about other things than how to preserve the truth of the 
         formula. Formalizations of all kind follow the same pattern, modeling languages
         among them.
      </div>
      <div class="para e116">So it was good to see the papers of Dennis Pagano and Anne 
         Brueggeman-Klein [
         <div class="xref e117" linkend="Pagano"></div>], and Bruce Bauman 
         [
         <div class="xref e118" linkend="Bauman"></div>], about interfacing with and interacting with
         modeling languages.  There is a long way to go from where we are now 
         to really good and comfortable control over semantics and modeling,
         but the way to make that long journey is to keep moving.
      </div>
      <div class="para e119">I’m similarly happy to have heard the papers by Jacques Durand 
         [
         <div class="xref e120" linkend="Durand"></div>] and Josh Lubell [
         <div class="xref e121" linkend="Lubell"></div>] about 
         better validation, and of course, I have a soft spot in my heart for the 
         philosophers who tell us whether documents can be edited or not, or how 
         to formalize their meaning [
         <div class="xref e122" linkend="Renear"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e123">There is yet another sense in which a given set of tools can be said
         to scale, or not to scale. They can scale to harder problems, or they can fail 
         to address harder problems.
      </div>
      <div class="para e124">Jens Stegmann and Andreas Witt’s paper [
         <div class="xref e125" linkend="Stegmann"></div>],
         and the paper by Fabio Vitali’s group in Bologna [
         <div class="xref e126" linkend="Peroni"></div>],
         the work by Maik Stührenberg and Daniel Jettka [
         <div class="xref e127" linkend="Stührenberg"></div>] 
         on stand-off markup, and the work reported by  Pierre Edouard Portier and 
         Sylvie Calabretto [
         <div class="xref e128" linkend="Portier"></div>] — all of these people 
         working on complex annotations and complex problems help ensure that 
         the technologies we are building will scale in that direction.
      </div>
      <div class="para e129">And I for one will be forever grateful for the ingenious demonstration
         by Desmond Schmidt  [
         <div class="xref e130" linkend="Schmidt"></div>]of an application of an
         indexing technique based on semi-infinite strings, first developed for the 
         New Oxford English Dictionary,
         <div class="popupBox e131">
            <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e271').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e271').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
            <div id="d1e271" style="display: none;">
               <div class="footnote">
                  <div class="para e132">See [
                     <div class="xref e133" linkend="Gonnet"></div>] 
                     for the indexing technique, which formed the basis of the commercial search 
                     tool Pat.
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div> to the problem of manuscript collation. I certainly 
         never expected to see that application; it’s a beautiful one, and if you didn’t 
         hear the talk I encourage you to read the paper.
      </div>
      <div class="para e134">Of course, the attempt to scale up can be pushed too far. As Tommie
         Usdin pointed out in her opening remarks on Tuesday morning [
         <div class="xref e135" linkend="Usdin"></div>], 
         standards can be and often are pushed on people who have no pressing 
         need for them. This results, perhaps, from people determined to increase 
         the number of adherents to the standard they themselves have declared 
         allegiance to.
      </div>
      <div class="para e136">But sometimes the right scale for a standard or technology, the right
         number of users or application areas, is not large.  Some problems are 
         unusual; some requirements are special.  Some communities can be small. 
         Some standards meet the needs not of a large community but of a small 
         one; there is no need to make the community forcibly larger, in the interests
         of standards compliance.
      </div>
      <div class="para e137">In the same way, technologies have suitable fields of application
         which may be large or small, broad or narrow.  For any technology, there 
         are things it is not suited some for, areas where it should not be applied.
      </div>
      <div class="para e138">Of course, when it comes to descriptive markup I don’t really believe 
         this for an instant.  If there are applications within IT to which descriptive 
         markup really should not be applied, I am not at all sure I’ve seen them.  
         But I’ve been told on good authority that this is a theoretical possibility, or 
         at least some smart people think so.  Perhaps I’ve just been carrying this 
         hammer for too long, but you know, it’s hard to put down the hammer once 
         you have discovered that pretty much everything turns out to be a nail if 
         you look at it long and intently enough.
      </div>
      <div class="para e139">It is not standards in themselves that are harmful, but mindless 
         adherence to standards that is harmful.
      </div>
      <div class="para e140">And similarly scale in itself may cause fewer problems than a mindless 
         devotion to working at a particular scale of things, an unthinking reflexive 
         conviction that to be worthwhile, a thing must be large scale, or small scale, 
         or any particular scale.
      </div>
      <div class="para e141">
         <div class="emphasis e142" role="ital">Mindlessness</div> is harmful.
      </div>
      <div class="para e143">Don’t be mindless.  Don’t build systems that encourage mindlessness.  
         Let us go out from here, when this conference ends, to work on better ways 
         to use descriptive markup to support mindfulness, to enhnace it, to augment 
         it. Nous réaliserons ainsi les vrais avantages du balisage. In that way, 
         we will bring to reality the real benefits of markup, and of Balisage.
      </div><a name="ReferencesANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="bibliography e144">
         <div class="title e145">References</div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e146" xml:id="Bauman" xreflabel="Bauman 2009">
            Bauman, Bruce Todd. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e147" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Bauman01/BalisageVol3-Bauman01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Prying Apart Semantics and Implementation: Generating XML Schemata directly from
               ontologically sound conceptual models.”
            </div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e148" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e149">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Bauman01</div>. 
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e150" xml:id="Beuchelt" xreflabel="Beuchelt et al. 2009">
            Beuchelt, Gerald, Harry Sleeper, Andrew Gregorowicz and Robert Dingwell. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e151" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Beuchelt01/BalisageVol3-Beuchelt01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“hData - A Simple XML Framework for Health Data Exchange.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e152" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e153">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Beuchelt01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e154" xml:id="Birnbaum" xreflabel="Birnbaum 2009">
            Birnbaum, David J. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e155" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Birnbaum01/BalisageVol3-Birnbaum01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“An XML user steps into, and escapes from, XPath quicksand.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e156" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e157">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Birnbaum01</div>. 
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e158" xml:id="Borenstein" xreflabel="Borenstein 1992">
            Borenstein, Nathaniel S. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e159" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.guppylake.com/~nsb/CSCW-ATOMICMAIL.txt" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Computational mail as network infrastructure for computer-supported cooperative work.”</div> Presented at 1992 ACM Conference on Computer-supported Cooperative Work, Toronto,
            Canada, November 1 - 4, 1992. (Apparently a draft of what was later published in 
            <div class="emphasis e160" role="ital">Proceedings of the 1992 ACM Conference on Computer-supported Cooperative Work</div>. The proceedings 
            version lacks the material quoted in the text.)
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e161" xml:id="Borovsky" xreflabel="Borovsky et al. 2009">
            Borovsky, Zoe, David J. Birnbaum, Lewis R. Lancaster and James A. Danowski. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e162" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Borovsky01/BalisageVol3-Borovsky01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“The Graphic Visualization of XML Documents.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e163" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e164">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Borovsky01</div>. 
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e165" xml:id="Cagle" xreflabel="Cagle 2009">
            Cagle, Kurt. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e166" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Cagle01/BalisageVol3-Cagle01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Open data and the XML community.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e167" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e168">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Cagle01</div>. 
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e169" xml:id="Cameron" xreflabel="Cameron / Herdy / Amiri 2009">
            Cameron, Rob, Ken Herdy and Ehsan Amiri. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e170" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol4/html/Cameron01/BalisageVol4-Cameron01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Parallel Bit Stream Technology as a Foundation for XML Parsing Performance.”</div> Presented at International Symposium on Processing XML Efficiently: Overcoming Limits
            on Space, Time, or Bandwidth, Montréal, Canada, August 10, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e171" role="ital">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Processing XML Efficiently: Overcoming
               Limits on Space, Time, or Bandwidth
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 4 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e172">10.4242/BalisageVol4.Cameron01</div>. 
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e173" xml:id="Zergaoui-bis" xreflabel="Cau / Zergaoui 2009">
            Cau, Jean Michel, and Mohamed Zergaoui. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e174" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Zergaoui01/BalisageVol3-Zergaoui01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Visual Designers: Those XML tools with no angle bracket at all!”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e175" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e176">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Zergaoui01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e177" xml:id="Peroni" xreflabel="Di Iorio / Peroni / Vitali 2009">
            Di Iorio, Angelo, Silvio Peroni and Fabio Vitali. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e178" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Peroni01/BalisageVol3-Peroni01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Towards markup support for full GODDAGs and beyond: the EARMARK approach.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e179" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e180">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Peroni01</div>. 
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e181" xml:id="Durand" xreflabel="Durand et al. 2009">
            Durand, Jacques, Stephen Green, Serm Kulvatunyou and Tom Rutt. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e182" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Durand01/BalisageVol3-Durand01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Test Assertions on steroids for XML artifacts.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e183" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e184">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Durand01</div>. 
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e185" xml:id="Flynn" xreflabel="Flynn 2009">
            Flynn, Peter. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e186" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Flynn01/BalisageVol3-Flynn01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Why writers don’t use XML: The usability of editing software for structured documents.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e187" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e188">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Flynn01</div>. 
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e189" xml:id="Gonnet" xreflabel="Gonnet / Baeza-Yates / Snider 1992">
            Gonnet, Gaston H., Ricardo A. Baeza-Yates and Tim Snider. “New indices for text: 
            Pat trees and Pat arrays.” Chap. 5 in 
            
            <div class="emphasis e190" role="ital">Information Retrieval: Algorithms and Data Structures</div>, edited by W. Frakes and R. Baeza-Yates, 66-82. New York: Prentice-Hall, 1992.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e191" xml:id="Kay" xreflabel="Kay 2009">
            Kay, Michael. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e192" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Kay01/BalisageVol3-Kay01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“You Pull, I’ll Push: on the Polarity of Pipelines.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e193" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e194">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Kay01</div>. 
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e195" xml:id="Lee" xreflabel="Lee / Walsh 2009">
            Lee, David, and Norman Walsh. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e196" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol4/html/Lee01/BalisageVol4-Lee01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Efficient scripting.”</div> Presented at International Symposium on Processing XML Efficiently: Overcoming Limits
            on Space, Time, or Bandwidth, Montréal, Canada, August 10, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e197" role="ital">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Processing XML Efficiently: Overcoming
               Limits on Space, Time, or Bandwidth
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 4 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e198">10.4242/BalisageVol4.Lee01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e199" xml:id="Leventhal" xreflabel="Leventhal / Lemoine 2009">
            Leventhal, Michael, and Eric Lemoine. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e200" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol4/html/Leventhal01/BalisageVol4-Leventhal01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“The XML Chip at 6 Years.”</div> Presented at International Symposium on Processing XML Efficiently: Overcoming Limits
            on Space, Time, or Bandwidth, Montréal, Canada, August 10, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e201" role="ital">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Processing XML Efficiently: Overcoming
               Limits on Space, Time, or Bandwidth
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 4 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e202">10.4242/BalisageVol4.Leventhal01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e203" xml:id="Lubell" xreflabel="Lubell 2009">
            Lubell, Joshua. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e204" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Lubell01/BalisageVol3-Lubell01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Documenting and Implementing Guidelines with Schematron.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e205" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e206">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Lubell01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e207" xml:id="McCay" xreflabel="McCay et al. 2009">
            McCay, Charlie, Michael Odling-Smee, Joseph Waller and Ann Wrightson. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e208" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Wrightson01/BalisageVol3-Wrightson01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Graciously handling a level of change in a complex specification: Configuration management
               for community-scale implementation of an HL7v3 messaging specification.”
            </div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e209" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e210">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Wrightson01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e211" xml:id="Milowski" xreflabel="Milowski 2009">
            Milowski, R. Alexander. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e212" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Milowski01/BalisageVol3-Milowski01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“XML in the Browser: the Next Decade.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e213" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e214">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Milowski01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e215" xml:id="Müldner" xreflabel="Müldner et al.  2009">
            Müldner, Tomasz, Christopher Fry, Jan Krzysztof Miziołek and Scott Durno. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e216" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Muldner01/BalisageVol3-Muldner01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“XSAQCT: XML Queryable Compressor.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e217" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e218">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Muldner01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e219" xml:id="Nguyen" xreflabel="Nguyen / Harvey 2009">
            Nguyen, Quyen L., and Betty Harvey. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e220" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Harvey01/BalisageVol3-Harvey01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Agile Business Objects Management Application for Electronic Records Archive Transfer
               Process.”
            </div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e221" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e222">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Harvey01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e223" xml:id="Pagano" xreflabel="Pagano / Brüggemann-Klein 2009">
            Pagano, Dennis, and Anne Brüggemann-Klein. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e224" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Bruggemann-Klein01/BalisageVol3-Bruggemann-Klein01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Engineering Document Applications&nbsp;—&nbsp;From UML Models to XML Schemas.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e225" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e226">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Bruggemann-Klein01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e227" xml:id="Portier" xreflabel="Portier / Calabretto 2009">
            Portier, Pierre-Edouard, and Sylvie Calabretto. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e228" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Portier01/BalisageVol3-Portier01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Methodology for the construction of multi-structured documents.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e229" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e230">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Portier01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e231" xml:id="Renear" xreflabel="Renear / Wickett 2009">
            Renear, Allen H., and Karen M. Wickett. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e232" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Renear01/BalisageVol3-Renear01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Documents Cannot Be Edited.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e233" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e234">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Renear01</div>.  
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e235" xml:id="Salz" xreflabel="Salz / Achilles / Maze 2009">
            Salz, Richard, Heather Achilles and David Maze. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e236" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol4/html/Salz01/BalisageVol4-Salz01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Hardware and software trade-offs in the IBM DataPower XML XG4 processor card.”</div> Presented at International Symposium on Processing XML Efficiently: Overcoming Limits
            on Space, Time, or Bandwidth, Montréal, Canada, August 10, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e237" role="ital">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Processing XML Efficiently: Overcoming
               Limits on Space, Time, or Bandwidth
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 4 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e238">10.4242/BalisageVol4.Salz01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e239" xml:id="Schmidt" xreflabel="Schmidt 2009">
            Schmidt, Desmond. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e240" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Schmidt01/BalisageVol3-Schmidt01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Merging Multi-Version Texts: a Generic Solution to the Overlap Problem.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e241" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e242">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Schmidt01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e243" xml:id="Stegmann" xreflabel="Stegmann / Witt 2009">
            Stegmann, Jens, and Andreas Witt. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e244" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Stegmann01/BalisageVol3-Stegmann01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“TEI Feature Structures as a Representation Format for Multiple Annotation and Generic
               XML Documents.”
            </div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e245" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e246">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Stegmann01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e247" xml:id="Stührenberg" xreflabel="Stührenberg / Jettka 2009">
            Stührenberg, Maik, and Daniel Jettka. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e248" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Stuhrenberg01/BalisageVol3-Stuhrenberg01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“A toolkit for multi-dimensional markup: The development of SGF to XStandoff.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e249" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e250">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Stuhrenberg01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e251" xml:id="Usdin" xreflabel="Usdin 2009">
            Usdin, B. Tommie. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e252" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Usdin01/BalisageVol3-Usdin01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Standards considered harmful.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e253" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e254">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Usdin01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e255" xml:id="Walsh" xreflabel="Walsh 2009">
            Walsh, Norman. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e256" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Walsh01/BalisageVol3-Walsh01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Investigating the streamability of XProc pipelines.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e257" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e258">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Walsh01</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e259" xml:id="Zergaoui" xreflabel="Zergaoui 2009">
            Zergaoui, Mohamed. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e260" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol4/html/Zergaoui02/BalisageVol4-Zergaoui02.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“Memory management in streaming: Buffering, lookahead, or none. Which to choose?”</div> Presented at International Symposium on Processing XML Efficiently: Overcoming Limits
            on Space, Time, or Bandwidth, Montréal, Canada, August 10, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e261" role="ital">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Processing XML Efficiently: Overcoming
               Limits on Space, Time, or Bandwidth
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 4 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e262">10.4242/BalisageVol4.Zergaoui02</div>.   
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e263" xml:id="Zholudev" xreflabel="Zholudev / Kohlhase 2009">
            Zholudev, Vyacheslav, and Michael Kohlhase. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e264" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Zholudev01/BalisageVol3-Zholudev01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">“TNTBase: Versioned Storage for XML.”</div> Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 -
            14, 2009. In 
            <div class="emphasis e265" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e266">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Zholudev01</div>.   
            
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>