<div id="mainContainerTOC">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTOC" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTOC').toggle('1000');">Table of Content</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTOC" style="display:none;">
      <div class="headedContainerTOC">
         <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#StandardsconsideredharmfulANCHOR" name="StandardsconsideredharmfulTOC">Standards considered harmful</a></div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#StandardsBullyingANCHOR" name="StandardsBullyingTOC">Standards Bullying</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#KnowYourGoalsandSticktoThemANCHOR" name="KnowYourGoalsandSticktoThemTOC">Know Your Goals and Stick to Them</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#PeerPressureinAcademiaANCHOR" name="PeerPressureinAcademiaTOC">Peer Pressure in Academia</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#InappropriateStandardsApplicationintheCommercialWorldANCHOR" name="InappropriateStandardsApplicationintheCommercialWorldTOC">Inappropriate Standards Application in the Commercial World</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#UnderspecificationHurtsTooANCHOR" name="UnderspecificationHurtsTooTOC">Underspecification Hurts, Too</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ConclusionANCHOR" name="ConclusionTOC">Conclusion</a></div>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerTERMS">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTERMS" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTERMS').toggle('1000')">Index of Terms</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTERMS" style="display:none;">
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">a</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">all future humans,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">And it is best practice</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">all</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">and</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">August 11 - 14, 2009</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">b</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Best practice</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">best practices</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">But,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">best practice</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">best</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">beautiful</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">best practice</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">B. Tommie</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">c</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">cool</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Cool.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">class</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">corn</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">cleaner,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">charitable contributions</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">d</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Does everybody else have to use them?</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">display name,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">did</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">e</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">f</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">g</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">good</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Give me ten examples of searches you want to do,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Grrr,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Good was good.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">good,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Good XML</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">h</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">harmful</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">high,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">How are you going to identify your documents?</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">i</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">I found some cool data. Give me some money.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">It is best practice to …</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">if</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">j</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">k</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">l</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">low,</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">m</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">medium,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Most people now …</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">most people</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">most people now</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Markup Languages: Theory &amp; Practice</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">n</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">not</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">no</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">o</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Oh, you can’t do that! It’s best practice to ….</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Oh. I don’t know anything about it.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Okay, how do you love it so quickly?</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Oh, @$&amp;#*, we’re in trouble.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">p</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">primary</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">q</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">r</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">reminded</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">requirements</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">referencing string</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">real</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">s</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Standards considered harmful.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Standards bullying</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">sophisticated</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Sophisticated</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Sophisticated searching,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">standards compliance budget</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">t</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Typical,</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">u</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">use</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">user</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">useful.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Usdin</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">v</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">x</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">XYZ considered harmful</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">y</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Yeah, but is it a good idea?</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">You need XYZ in order to ABC.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">z</div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerIML"><a name="StandardsconsideredharmfulANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="article e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2">
      <div class="title e1">Standards considered harmful</div>
      <div class="info e2">
         <div class="confgroup e3">
            <div class="conftitle e4">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009</div>
            <div class="confdates e5">August 11 - 14, 2009</div>
         </div>
         <div class="abstract e6">
            <div class="para e7">Standards and shared specifications allow us to share data, build general purpose
               tools, and significantly reduce training and customization costs and startup time.
               That is, the use of appropriate specifications can help us reduce costs, reduce startup
               time, and increase quality, usability, and reusability of content. Some vigorous standards
               proponents insist that the more standards used the better. To them I say 
               <div class="quote e8">mind your own business and let me mind my own store</div>. They argue that using standards is always the right thing to do, because it enables
               re-use and interchange. Maybe so. But adoption of a standard that supports an activity
               that is not central to your mission is a distraction, an unwarranted expense, a bad
               idea.
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e9">
            <div class="personname e10">
               <div class="firstname e11">B. Tommie</div>
               <div class="surname e12">Usdin</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e13">
               <div class="para e14">B. Tommie Usdin is President of Mulberry Technologies, Inc., a consultancy specializing
                  in XML and SGML. Ms. Usdin has been working with SGML since 1985 and has been a supporter
                  of XML since 1996. She chairs the Balisage conference and was co-editor of 
                  <div class="emphasis e15">Markup Languages: Theory &amp; Practice</div> published by the MIT Press. Ms. Usdin has developed DTDs, Schemas, and XML/SGML application
                  frameworks for applications in government and industry. Projects include reference
                  materials in medicine, science, engineering, and law; semiconductor documentation;
                  historical and archival materials. Distribution formats have included print books,
                  magazines, and journals, and both web- and media-based electronic publications. You
                  can read more about her at 
                  <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e16" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.mulberrytech.com/people/usdin/index.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mulberrytech.com/people/usdin/index.html</div>.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e17">
               <div class="orgname e18">Mulberry Technologies, Inc.</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="legalnotice e19">
            <div class="para e20">Copyright © 2009 by the author.  Used with
               permission.
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div class="note e21">
         <div class="title e22">Editor‘s Note</div>
         <div class="para e23">This talk was given in the opening session of “Balisage: The Markup Conference” 2009.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="para e24">
         <div class="quote e25">Standards considered harmful.</div> Actually, when it occurred to me that I might want to call a talk that, it occurred
         to me that 
         <div class="quote e26">XYZ considered harmful</div> talks were probably harmful.  I thought about that, and I did a little browsing around,
         and learned that actually several  people have given conference talks or written essays
         about 
         <div class="quote e27">harmful</div> essays being harmful. And I  decided that proves it’s a cliché, and there’s nothing
         wrong with clichés, so here I am talking about standards considered harmful. And as
         in most 
         <div class="quote e28">harmful</div>-considered papers, what I’m really saying is:  Reflexive or mindless use of standards
         or mindless application of standards that are not applicable is harmful.
      </div><a name="StandardsBullyingANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e29">
         <div class="title e30">Standards Bullying</div>
         <div class="para e31">We have, unfortunately I think, reached a stage in the evolution of markup and markup
            specifications and standards where we not only have a multitude of them, if not an
            excess, but we also have generated ourselves some religious fanatics about them. I
            am not really fond of fanatics of any sort — I think political fanatics make me even
            crazier than religious fanatics — but in either case application without reason or
            encouragement of application without reason is harmful. And it’s easier to fall into
            than you would think.
         </div>
         <div class="para e32">
            <div class="quote e33">Standards bullying</div> often comes in innocuous and helpful-sounding guises. 
            <div class="quote e34">Best practice</div> is one that frequently makes my skin crawl. 
            <div class="quote e35">Oh, you can’t do that! It’s best practice to ….</div> I’m going to talk about that some more in a minute, and we have a [conference] panel
            talking about 
            <div class="quote e36">best practices</div> tomorrow.
         </div>
         <div class="para e37">
            <div class="quote e38">It would be more standards-compliant if you did this instead of that.</div> How many times have people outside your projects 
            <div class="quote e39">reminded</div> you of requirements you must meet? Those are the people who really make me anxious.
            A lot of these 
            <div class="quote e40">requirements</div> translate to 
            <div class="quote e41">You should spend a lot of your money and your time and your energy doing something
               that will be of no value to you, but that might someday be useful to me or to someone
               I can imagine.
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e42">Or worse, in my opinion: 
            <div class="quote e43">You should spend a lot of your money and make everything you are doing harder so that
               
               <div class="emphasis e44" role="ital">if</div>, in the future I, or someone like me, wants to re-use your content, it will be easy
               for us.
            </div> Often the people who are helpfully pushing you toward standards or best practices
            or shared recommendations are not only not involved in funding your project, their
            goals are not your primary mission, or, for that matter your secondary, or tertiary,
            or quaternary mission. They are sidetracking you. And in many cases they don’t even
            know it.
         </div>
         <div class="para e45">These self-styled standards evangelists are of good will. They think it would be really
            wonderful if everyone could just get along, and if everyone could just share all of
            their information. And, of course, they are right; it would be really wonderful. But
            that doesn’t make sharing information, especially with unknown future users with unspecified
            and unknowable requirements, the primary goal for each and every information project.
            In fact, I would venture to say that it is not the 
            <div class="emphasis e46" role="bold">primary</div> goal of any funded project that has the money to create a substantial body of marked
            up documents. (It may be the primary goal of projects or activities to enhance information
            sharing, but those projects rarely (never?) have the funding to prepare the documents.
            They assume that they will write guidelines and others will use those guidelines.)
         </div>
         <div class="para e47">The projects and activities that actually seem to have the money to mark up a substantial
            body of documents generally have as their missions things like: Create print and electronic
            publications that follow our house style for display, are searchable using our organization’s
            favorite search engine, and that will help make the next update easier and cheaper
            than the last one was. It is possible that the mission also includes being a basis
            for creation of unknown future electronic publications and possible mix-n-match print.
            But there’s usually a 
            <div class="quote e48">use</div> scenario and a 
            <div class="quote e49">user</div> scenario in mind at the point when the funding is available to do the work. I think
            we need to stop forgetting that.
         </div>
      </div><a name="KnowYourGoalsandSticktoThemANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e50">
         <div class="title e51">Know Your Goals and Stick to Them</div>
         <div class="para e52">When you start a project — practically any project — there are some basic management
            tasks that we all ought to do. These tasks help us stay on track by making the track
            explicit, to ourselves and others. In addition, they allow us to know what we are
            
            <div class="emphasis e53" role="bold">not</div> trying to do, so we can focus on what we are trying to do.
         </div>
         <div class="itemizedlist e54">
            <div class="listitem e55">
               <div class="para e56">Identify the stakeholders. That is, who are you doing this for? Be specific. You are
                  
                  <div class="emphasis e57" role="bold">not</div> creating a document collection for 
                  <div class="quote e58">all future humans,</div> or at least I doubt that you are. Your stakeholders are more likely to include the
                  people who will read, use, or buy your electronic product (are they students, teachers,
                  railroad switch engineers, managers of non-profit associations, art historians, or
                  … some other group), and the people funding your project, and the managers of your
                  organization, and the printer with whom you have a contract.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="listitem e59">
               <div class="para e60">Identify your project goals. What do you have to do to be a success? Project goals
                  are probably a mixture of technical, educational, financial, scheduling, and budgetary.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="listitem e61">
               <div class="para e62">Identify your non-goals. That is, things that perhaps somebody else might want to
                  do and therefore assume that you are setting out to do, but that you are not doing.
                  It is my opinion that explicitly recording your non-goals is the best safety measure
                  you can take in starting any funded project. 
                  <div class="quote e63">I didn’t forget to make a Spanish translation of this content. That wasn’t a goal
                     of my project.
                  </div> 
                  <div class="quote e64">I didn’t forget to make an RDF-access tool for my data; that’s not what I was doing.</div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="listitem e65">
               <div class="para e66">Prioritize your project goals. If you prioritize your project goals into 
                  <div class="quote e67">high,</div> 
                  <div class="quote e68">medium,</div> and 
                  <div class="quote e69">low,</div> and all your project goals end up as 
                  <div class="quote e70">high,</div> prioritize again. Everything can’t be top priority. It’s not possible. If you’ve
                  done that, what you’ve done is — I don’t want to say, lied to yourself — you just
                  haven’t done the hard work of figuring out what is the most important thing and what
                  are secondary things. Now, you can say, 
                  <div class="quote e71">Here’s a list of eight things that my project has to do. All of them must be done
                     for me to be a success.
                  </div> But that doesn’t mean that all of them have to be the most important thing because
                  all of them can’t be. Your project goals may be a mixture of technical goals, educational
                  goals, financial goals, scheduling goals, and budget goals. Without explicit goals
                  you can't know if you are getting where you want to go, and you are wandering about
                  witout your primary weapon against being forever sidetracked before you accomplish
                  anything.
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e72">At that point, I think you probably also want to start thinking about a distinction
            I talk about a lot when 
            we’re talking about document modeling:  what is true versus what is useful. When you
            start looking at a set of
            documents, you can find a lot of things that are true about them and that you could
            identify and spend an awful 
            lot of money on. The question is how many of those things are useful. It would be
            possible, for example, when 
            marking up business documents for a subject retrieval system to identify the parts
            of the document on your 
            subject taxonomy and to identify the documents themselves and the chapters of them
            and the sections of them and 
            the paragraphs and the sentences and the words and what was the language of origin
            of each of the verbs in each 
            of the sentences. Is this likely to be useful? Is it conceivable that there might
            be somebody someplace who would 
            find that useful? Yes. If your goal is to make a corporate procedure library easily
            available to the telephone 
            help desk, is it likely that knowing which word is a verb is going to be helpful?
            Probably 
            not. So, if you’re supporting a telephone help desk, maybe you don’t need to get into
            the linguistic analysis of the sentences. That’s what I’m talking about:  about not
            supplying, not spending money to 
            do something that it is possible that some unknown future person might want. Stick
            to what you’re supposed 
            to be doing. There may be a text markup standard that specifies how to mark the parts
            of speech of each word in documents and their language of origins. If there is, and
            knowing or manipulating this information is related to 
            one of your project goals, then and only then, is that standard relevant to your project.
         </div>
         <div class="para e73">I think in this talk I should also talk about 
            <div class="quote e74">good</div> versus 
            <div class="quote e75">useful.</div> It may be good to know — I’m trying to think of a good example about these same help
            desk documents — how many times it’s been used, who read it, and what language it
            was originally written in (if you’re in a multi-lingual environment). There may be
            a whole lot of other things that it might be 
            <div class="quote e76">cool</div> to know but that are irrelevant to the users and the uses of this data. Maybe you
            don’t need to keep track of that. Even if there is a document describing standard
            markup for tracking such information.
         </div>
      </div><a name="PeerPressureinAcademiaANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e77">
         <div class="title e78">Peer Pressure in Academia</div>
         <div class="para e79">Some of you are probably thinking that maybe this is true in the business environment,
            but not in the academic world. Right? I mean, we know that in the academic world being
            a good team player is the route to gaining respect, admiration, and support, right?
            Or at least that’s what people say. (It doesn’t actually look like that sometimes,
            but that’s what they say.)
         </div>
         <div class="para e80">So, when we get our hands on a new set of data in the academic environment, we should
            work with the expectation that we’re going to share it with others, right? That’s
            what data is for.
         </div>
         <div class="para e81">Let’s imagine a scenario. We have an eager, young cultural anthropologist — I like
            cultural anthropologists because they seem to be interested in everything — and he
            wanders into a little library in a farming town in the middle of who-cares-what-country
            (it doesn’t matter). Some little town somewhere. Little tiny town library. And he
            discovers literally hundreds of diaries of the farmers and the townspeople for the
            last 150 years. It’s a treasure trove. Wow! What a find! It just made his career,
            right? He’s going to study these, he’s going to publish about them, he’s got it. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e82">The town is losing population fast, the library is underfunded, its roof is leaking,
            and the diaries may be destroyed by water and mold the next time there’s a big summer
            storm. But the librarian says, 
            <div class="quote e83">You can’t have my diaries. You can take pictures of them, but you can’t have them.</div> What does our young researcher go out and do? He needs a grant, so he needs to write
            a proposal. He can’t just go home to the university and say 
            <div class="quote e84">I found some cool data. Give me some money.</div> So, he starts planning. He’s going to have to scan them; he’s going to have to clean
            up the pages; he’s going to have to transcribe them, analyze them, and start publishing
            about all the things he’s learned about the history of this farming community and
            the history of farmers and all these wonderful things.
         </div>
         <div class="para e85">How to transcribe it? Well, his professors when he was in school got their source
            materials and sat down at typewriters and transcribed them into typescript. That’s
            probably not the — it’s probably going to be 2010 before he gets his money — 2010
            way to do it. Among other things, he knows he’s going to want to put bits of these
            on the web with his analysis of them, besides which, he wants to do 
            <div class="quote e86">sophisticated</div> searching of his documents.
         </div>
         <div class="para e87">[Aside:] How many of you have had users who said they wanted to do 
            <div class="quote e88">sophisticated</div> searching? How many of you think they knew what they were talking about? I have an
            opinion. I know what 
            <div class="quote e89">sophisticated</div> searching means. 
            <div class="quote e90">Sophisticated</div> searching means you can show it off at a cocktail party, and people will say, 
            <div class="quote e91">Cool.</div> When a user says 
            <div class="quote e92">Sophisticated searching,</div> and then you say, 
            <div class="quote e93">Give me ten examples of searches you want to do,</div> and they can’t give you any, what they want is a 
            <div class="quote e94">wow.</div> That’s what our mythical cultural anthropologist wants: a 
            <div class="quote e95">wow.</div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e96">He’s going to want to flag the things he finds most interesting in these documents:
            crops, harvests, the weather, the health of the people, the names of the people, the
            names of places, the stuff that he’s going to be wanting to find amongst this data
            set so he can do his analysis. Now, this is going to be a little tricky, but fortunately
            our young cultural anthropologist is an expert on HTML. How did he get to be an expert
            on HTML? He has a 64-page book about it, and he read it. Well, he looked at it. Well,
            he has it, anyway. So, he’s an expert. He knows how to do this. He’s going to have
            an army of students read the copies of the pages of these diaries and transcribe them
            into HTML which is pretty easy, and he can afford a whole lot more copies of the 64-page
            book so he can teach them, too. This is going to be easy. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e97">He thinks about the information he really cares about in these documents, and how
            to flag it so he can find it and analyze it later; he read about it in his HTML book.
            There’s this, there’s this, there’s this — there’s a way to say that something is
            about a class — he can add 
            <div class="quote e98">class</div> attributes to stuff so he’s going to be able to find the stuff about the crops and
            the weather and the people’s health. He’s got it all figured out. He’s got his budget,
            he’s got his proposal ready to submit to his funding agency, he’s telling his friends
            about it, and a colleague with several years of experience in creating collections
            of historical documents says, 
            <div class="quote e99">Nah, nah, nah. You don’t want to do this HTML stuff. The difference between HTML and
               XML is that in XML you can make up your own tags. XML is make-up-your-own-tag-HTML.
               And it’s going to be much easier for you to use XML than HTML because you don’t have
               to say 
               <div class="code e100">&lt;span class="crop"&gt;</div> to mark your crops; you can have a tag called 
               <div class="code e101">&lt;crop&gt;</div> and just surround it. It’s much easier, and you’re going to be much happier.
            </div> So, at the last minute he makes a change:  He’s not going to mark the data up in
            HTML; he’s going to mark it up in XML.
         </div>
         <div class="para e102">He sends in his grant proposal, chews on his fingers for a few months, and gets funded.
            Cool. Two years’ of funding — it’s time to get started. He celebrates, he hires an
            army of students, and he starts getting organized. 
            <div class="quote e103">Wait, wait,</div> says another member of his departmental coffee-klatch, 
            <div class="quote e104">How are you going to identify your documents?</div> 
            <div class="quote e105">What do you mean, how am I going to identify my documents? We’re going to put in the
               file name, we’re going to have the name of the person who wrote the diary in which
               volume it is and which page it is, and we’re going to transcribe it. What’s the big
               deal?
            </div> 
            <div class="quote e106">You never heard of Dublin Core? What’s the matter with you? How anti-social are you?
               You have to use the standard.
            </div> 
            <div class="quote e107">Oh. I don’t know anything about it.</div> 
            <div class="quote e108">Well, you better learn ’cause it’s the right way to do it.</div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e109">Okay. So he goes and reads up on Dublin Core. And actually that doesn’t look so hard;
            he agrees to make little Dublin Core headers.
         </div>
         <div class="para e110">He sends the teams out to go and scan the documents, and he starts marking up his
            little XML documents that have HTML tags for all the sort of normal things like paragraphs,
            and he makes up tags for the things like weather and crops that HTML doesn’t have
            a tag for. This should work, because, after all, XML is add-a-tag-HTML. And he’s chatting
            about his cool new project at a conference, when a well-respected expert on documentary
            projects says: 
            <div class="quote e111">Wait, wait. You can’t do that.</div> 
            <div class="quote e112">What do you mean I can’t do that? The sample document I have been working on looks
               OK to me, and I’m in the middle of writing guidelines so we can do this consistently.
               Look, he says, I have a 
               <div class="code e113">&lt;p&gt;</div> tag around my paragraphs, and I have 
               <div class="code e114">&lt;crop&gt;</div> tags around each mention of a crop. 
               <div class="code e115">&lt;crop&gt;</div> seems much easier to deal with than 
               <div class="code e116">&lt;span class="crop"&gt;</div>.
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e117">
            <div class="quote e118">But,</div> the expert says, 
            <div class="quote e119">XML is more complicated than that. Go and get an XML book.</div> So he takes himself off to the little local library to look for the 64-page book
            all about XML, and there aren’t any. There are books — way more than 64 books — none
            of them are as short as 64 pages.  (This XML stuff is complicated! Did you know they
            have conferences about XML? There’s enough that you can have a conference?? It’s ridiculous.)
            
         </div>
         <div class="para e120">So, he comes back, and he starts talking to his friends and saying, 
            <div class="quote e121">Okay, which of these books do I buy? And do I really have to read all of it? These
               books are big.
            </div> 
            <div class="quote e122">No, you don’t have to buy a book about XML, and you don’t have to read one. You just
               have to go and read about the Text Encoding Initiative because that is the one and
               only right way to tag your scholarly XML documents so other scholars can use them.
            </div> 
            <div class="quote e123">Does everybody else have to use them?</div> 
            <div class="quote e124">Yes. How anti-social are you going to be? You’ve got to use this standard.</div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e125">So, okay, he’s going to go and read about the Text Encoding Initiative. Do you know
            how big that sucker is? [Laughter.]  You know, they don’t have a 64-page book about
            it either. So, he settles down, and he does some reading, and then he takes a class,
            and he goes to a workshop, and  gets a consultant in to help him cut the TEI tag set
            down to something that is merely daunting. And his budget is flying out the window.
         </div>
         <div class="para e126">So, he does this, he does that, and he’s finally got himself a subset of the TEI with
            Dublin Core metadata because how can you not do that, and he’s got some sample documents
            he can show to his student-workers, and he’s got a few scanned pages that he can mark
            up, and he starts marking them up. And now, instead of HTML’s 
            <div class="code e127">&lt;span class="crop"&gt;</div> or the XML he made up for himself 
            <div class="code e128">&lt;crop&gt;</div>, he has the infinitely better 
            <div class="code e129">&lt;rs type="crop"&gt;</div> (making the word 
            <div class="quote e130">corn</div> into a 
            <div class="quote e131">referencing string</div> of type crop). Well, that’s an improvement, isn’t it.
         </div>
         <div class="para e132">And what does our young researcher want to do now? He wants to look at his sample
            tagged documents. That is, he wants to do what he set out to do in the first place
            which is to be able to look at his text on the screen with the crops in yellow and
            the weather in blue. And he finds that he can’t do it with off-the-shelf tools. (Not
            even the tools promulgated by the TEI), He has to find a programmer to write some
            code to render his documents readable and searchable, so he can start doing his analysis.
            So, he finds somebody who knows some Perl to do this for him.
         </div>
         <div class="para e133">
            <div class="quote e134">Wait, wait, wait, wait,</div> says the standards do-gooder, 
            <div class="quote e135">You’re going to write some throw-away Perl to do that. You can’t do that. That’s anti-social.
               Respectable people don’t do throw-away Perl. We do XSLT. Well-documented and properly
               parameterized so that when somebody wants to go and re-use it, they don’t have it
               tied to your tags and your subjects; they can plug theirs in and their colors.
            </div> And, all of a sudden, we’re not talking about an afternoon of work anymore, are we?
            So, he gets somebody to write this thing and document it.
         </div>
         <div class="para e136">And now he’s out of money. He now needs to go back to his funding agency and say,
            
            <div class="quote e137">You gave me the money to be able to get the first of these things up, searched, and
               analyzed, but I was busy being socially helpful. And I have learned a bunch of tag
               sets, I have learned a bunch of specs, I have had some code written that can be re-used,
               and I have no documents and no analyses to show for it. Can I have some more money?
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e138">How does that story sound to you? [Answer from audience: 
            <div class="quote e139">Typical,</div>  to which Tommie responds, 
            <div class="quote e140">Yeah, but is it a good idea?</div>] And how likely is our young researcher to get more money with so little to show
            for the funds he already spent? Even if this is par for the course, how much easier
            would it be for him to get additional money if he 
            <div class="emphasis e141" role="ital">did</div> have something to show for his previous funding?
         </div>
      </div><a name="InappropriateStandardsApplicationintheCommercialWorldANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e142">
         <div class="title e143">Inappropriate Standards Application in the Commercial World</div>
         <div class="para e144">So, does this only happen in the academic world? Not a chance.</div>
         <div class="para e145">We don’t have time to go into details on this one, so I will simply tell you that
            I know of a very, very large commercial publisher who has a database intended to be
            the font from which vast riches, in the form of re-used content, will flow. All content
            published after the start date for the re-use project must be either produced in or
            converted to the XML format for this database and the content stored in the database.
            Then, editors or marketers looking for existing material they can incorporate in new
            products can simply search this database, find the bits they want to re-use, copy
            them out, and combine them with other resources from the database to make new targeted
            products. This means that the budget for every single publication needs to include
            making this XML, either from the XML they may need to produce the product-specific
            electronic product they are going to sell or from the typesetting files used to create
            their print publication. Now, for some of their content this makes sense; they have
            a lot of text books and reference books on the same subject matter, and specialty
            volumes can often be created by combining the portions of several text books and sections
            of reference volumes that address a specialized topic. However, there are publications
            that everyone knows cannot be so re-purposed, and they must participate anyway. Because
            it is a corporate standard, and for no other reason.
         </div>
      </div><a name="UnderspecificationHurtsTooANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e146">
         <div class="title e147">Underspecification Hurts, Too</div>
         <div class="para e148">The folks at Mulberry recently wrote a tag set — actually, we revised a public tag
            set, customized it — for a publisher who wanted to move from their old SGML-based
            document model to a new XML-based one. They said that they wanted this new model to
            last as long and be as flexible as the model it was replacing, which had been in use
            for over 20 years. They wanted a really good model of their documents; highly semantic,
            rich enough to support typesetting as they typeset now (meaning they needed to be
            able to override the formatting manually in many places), vendor and technology neutral,
            and adopting all of the appropriate standards. Oh, yeah. And they wanted it to be
            as compatible as possible with their existing model for a related type of materials.
            By that they meant that paragraphs should have the same tag, and sections should be
            recursive, as they were in the other documents. You know, stuff like that. Use the
            same list and table tagging. We sat with them for quite a while, learning about their
            documents, their plans for the future of their documents, the functionality they could
            imagine supporting in future electronic versions of their documents, the variations
            in their documents historically, and even how they might want to market their documents,
            and thus what information their marketing people might want from the documents to
            support marketing. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e149">We built them a 
            <div class="emphasis e150" role="bital">beautiful</div> document model, if I say so myself. It met 
            <div class="emphasis e151" role="bital">all</div> of the functional requirements we discussed, and it was graceful. We sent them a
            draft, with draft user documentation and some guideline on how to evaluate it. And
            the day after they received it, we got a phone call saying, 
            <div class="quote e152">We love it.</div> 
            <div class="quote e153">Okay, how do you love it so quickly?</div> 
            <div class="quote e154">We love it because we just slid it into the editing application we’re using for our
               other documents, and it works really well.
            </div> 
         </div>
         <div class="para e155">At that moment I should have said, 
            <div class="quote e156">Oh, @$&amp;#*, we’re in trouble.</div> But I didn’t, because I was busy being happy that my client was happy. I hadn’t realized
            at that point that using their old editing application was 
            <div class="emphasis e157" role="bold">not</div> one of the functional requirements, and they loved it for doing something they’d
            never said they wanted it to do. I would have been right if I had started to worry
            then. Three or four days later I got email from the project manager — who knows the
            organization, and the documents, and their end users, but is as technical as my left
            shoe. This email said essentially 
            <div class="quote e158">It’s a really nice tag set, but there are a few things in it that you should modify
               for current best practice.
            </div> Now, I expected and wanted a set of comments and suggestions, but these suggestions
            were really odd. They were phrased as 
            <div class="quote e159">Most people now …</div> or 
            <div class="quote e160">It is best practice to …</div> or 
            <div class="quote e161">You need XYZ in order to be able to do ABC with your documents.</div> Now 
            <div class="quote e162">most people</div> and 
            <div class="quote e163">best practice</div> are pretty soft, so I let them go, and started with the 
            <div class="quote e164">You need XYZ in order to ABC.</div> The email suggested that since there were elements in common in the metadata for
            the documents and in citations (that is, the document would have a title, an author,
            a publication date) 
            <div class="emphasis e165" role="bold">and</div> the documents cited in the document might have titles, authors, and publication dates),
            we should 
            <div class="quote e166">put all of the citation-related content into its own namespace.</div> 
            <div class="quote e167">Grrr,</div> I said, at least to myself. That may be convenient for this particular application,
            but it is a really revolting thing to do in general. It is a sneaky underhanded way
            to make the names of the same information in different contexts different, and in
            a way that may surprise future users. You can simply look up the tree to see what
            the context is of that author, or title, or … Sigh. 
            <div class="quote e168">And it is best practice</div> continued this email, 
            <div class="quote e169">to have not only tagged in your data all of the parts of the names of the people,
               but also to store the full display name, including all punctuation.
            </div> 
            <div class="quote e170">And it is best practice to store in addition to the titles and all of the subtitles
               of which there may be none or multiples, a combined title which is, for example, the
               display title.
            </div> Since when is it 
            <div class="emphasis e171" role="bital">best practice</div> to do this? Best practice according to whom? It does not seem to me to be 
            <div class="quote e172">best</div> practice, or even 
            <div class="quote e173">good</div> practice to store the same content twice, nor does it seem like even acceptable practice
            to store computable data in the same XML file as the source from which it could be
            computed.
         </div>
         <div class="para e174">So I pushed back a little, and I discovered that they not only had selected a database
            in which this stuff was going to reside, they had already customized the database
            product and written the searches, before bringing us in to design the tag set. And
            they needed a tag set that was going to work with this database product in this particular
            database with these already canned searches. So now I know what 
            <div class="quote e175">best practice</div> means in this environment. 
            <div class="quote e176">Best practice</div> means works in the database they already have. This also tells me what 
            <div class="quote e177">most people now</div> means; it means that since I have been working pushing a product that requires this,
            most of the applications I see do it that way. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e178">I suggested that they create two XML formats: one generic format, in which information
            was stored only once (instead of, for example, as the parts of each name as fine granules
            and as combined names for sorting), and in which context was used to identify what
            sort of date, author, heading, etc. each was. And then a second format, which could
            be automatically created from the first, which was optimized for their database. This
            would allow them to create, quality control, and manage for the long term documents
            that were smaller and 
            <div class="quote e179">cleaner,</div> in that they didn’t contain duplicate content. They rejected this suggestion; they
            didn’t want the complication, and they had apparently been assured by their database
            vendor that the database was XML, so they would have all of the advantages of XML
            when they used this database.
         </div>
         <div class="para e180">They were quite disappointed in the design we sent them. And they were right to be
            disappointed; it didn’t meet their 
            <div class="emphasis e181" role="ital">real</div> requirement. What did the really want? Well, they had just made a major investment
            in a tool and were spending a small fortune building a system around that tool. They
            needed a mode for their XML that would work gracefully with that tool. That was their
            top priority, and the model we had designed was not optimized for the tool. We had
            not met their real needs.
         </div>
         <div class="para e182">How did this happen? I think it happened because they have heard what XML is good
            for, and they thought, 
            <div class="quote e183">Good was good.</div> If they told us that they wanted a model that was 
            <div class="quote e184">good,</div> it would work in their 
            <div class="quote e185">good</div> tool. 
            <div class="quote e186">Good XML</div> is vendor neutral. 
            <div class="quote e187">Good XML</div> uses all appropriate standards. 
            <div class="quote e188">Good XML</div> enables as much semantic tagging as possible. They thought that if they wanted all
            of those good things they would end up with good XML, and that would work well in
            their new 
            <div class="quote e189">good</div> tool.
         </div>
         <div class="para e190">They needed a model that would support the tool in which they had made a major investment.
            This tool and the application built on top of it would make or break their business.
            That, actually, was their top priority. And in a half-day discussing their functional
            requirements and several days discussing the details of their model, they never mentioned
            it. Because they assumed that a 
            <div class="quote e191">good</div> XML model would be good for their chosen tool.
         </div>
         <div class="para e192">So, we modified the model to accommodate the tool. Did we compromise our principles?
            I don’t think so. Is the model they are using less elegant than the draft we sent
            them? Yes. It has some unnecessary namespaces, for example. Why? Because either the
            tool or the application designer (I don’t know which, and it doesn’t really matter)
            can’t cope with context. They want (need?) to have a different namespace for 
            <div class="code e193">&lt;author&gt;</div> in 
            <div class="code e194">&lt;citation&gt;</div> than for 
            <div class="code e195">&lt;author&gt;</div> in the document metadata. From a strictly XML design point of view, this is silly;
            any application can know what the context of that 
            <div class="code e196">&lt;author&gt;</div> is. However, it does no harm in the long run; all the information we modeled is still
            there, and if they switch to a different application that doesn’t need these namespaces,
            and perhaps that doesn’t want to deal with all these namespaces they can remove them.
            The context is still there, after all. Similarly, the XML files contain some things
            that are completely derived from other things in the file: Those same author names
            are not only stored as first name, middle initial, and surname, they are also stored
            in the XML file as 
            <div class="quote e197">display name,</div> meaning all the parts of the name, in one element, with spaces as needed. Is this
            harmful? No, it’s clutter. (Well, it isn’n harmful unless/until they someone updates
            one but not the other copy of the same information @mdash; that’s the danger of storing
            information twice in any format).  But apparently either the tool or the application
            finds it unacceptable or inefficient to concatenate the parts of the name and spaces
            on display. This sets my teeth on edge; it shouldn’t be in the long-term storage XML
            file; they are paying conversion vendors to create the same data twice (or, preferably,
            to put it the programmatically and charge them as if they had created it twice). Worse,
            they are going to ask their editors to create the same data twice, and are either
            going to add a validation step to ensure that the data is the same or deal with the
            inconsistencies that storing the same data twice creates. (If you need to store information
            like that in your database …) But if having it pre-assembled really makes the database
            or the application more efficient, or even if it simply caters to the limitations
            of the application developer, then it needs to be there.
         </div>
         <div class="para e198">The Mulberry pig got passed around a few times during the process, but now everybody
            is happy. Do you know about the Mulberry pig? We have a trophy at Mulberry; it’s got
            a big, fancy, gold color base and a big pseudo-malachite column and a little gold
            color pig on the top. When you grump creatively or excessively, especially about a
            project or client, the pig it sits on your desk until the next person earns it. Well,
            the pig passed around quite a bit for a few weeks.
         </div>
      </div><a name="ConclusionANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e199">
         <div class="title e200">Conclusion</div>
         <div class="para e201">I don’t want to tell you not to use standards. I don’t want to tell you that standards
            are bad. I don’t want to tell you to ignore advice given to you by your friends and
            colleagues. I think I want to suggest that you treat suggestions to use a standard
            the way I treat solicitations from charities.
         </div>
         <div class="para e202">My guess is that I get an average of ten solicitations from charitable organizations
            a week. Some of them are from organizations promoting a position I find abhorrent,
            and these are easy to deal with: into the recycle bin they go! Most of them are from
            organizations doing work or promoting causes with which I have some sympathy. (There
            are 
            <div class="emphasis e203" role="ital">no</div> diseases for which I think a cure would be a bad thing.) And a few are solicitations
            for something that will be of immediate use to me as well as perhaps helping the world;
            for example membership in my local zoo not only supports the zoo, it gets me free
            parking at the zoo. Similarly, use of some XML application standards not only increases
            the chances that unplanned and unknown users will find your data useable, it may well
            enable you to interchange data with your business partners. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e204">There is no question about contributing to those charities for which I see immediate
            personal benefit; I send them money every year. As for the rest: I have a budget,
            and I try to help as many worthy causes as I can within that charitable contribution
            budget. I do not even try to donate to every worth cause that asks for money, nor
            do I even try to donate as much to any of them as they ask. I simply can’t.
         </div>
         <div class="para e205">I suggest that you might want to consider the various XML specifications, standards,
            and applications that vie for your time and money in the same way. Set a 
            <div class="quote e206">standards compliance budget</div> and stay within it, both in terms of time and money. Of course, if there is an immediate
            win to your project from using a specific specification, use it. If there might be
            a benefit to the world in general, or to some unknown future users of you data if
            you add some metadata, or use an existing tag set, or some such, decide if this additional
            effort is within your 
            <div class="quote e207">charitable contributions</div> budget.
         </div>
         <div class="para e208">So, as you participate in Balisage this year I charge you to consider the relevance
            of the various technologies, specifications, and applications you are hearing about.
            Learn as much as you can. Add as many tools to your toolbox as possible. Consider
            as many points of view as your mind can manage. And when you go home, remember than
            you don’t have to use your shiny new hammer on every task. Think carefully about which
            of the specifications and standards you know of should be used in what situation,
            and to what benefit.
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>