<div id="mainContainerTOC">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTOC" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTOC').toggle('1000');">Table of Content</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTOC" style="display:none;">
      <div class="headedContainerTOC">
         <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#DocumentsasTimedAbstractObjectsANCHOR" name="DocumentsasTimedAbstractObjectsTOC">Documents as Timed Abstract Objects</a></div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#BackgroundANCHOR" name="BackgroundTOC">Background </a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#TheInconsistentTriadANCHOR" name="TheInconsistentTriadTOC">The Inconsistent Triad </a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ResponsestotheInconsistencyANCHOR" name="ResponsestotheInconsistencyTOC">Responses to the Inconsistency </a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#TimedAbstractObjectsANCHOR" name="TimedAbstractObjectsTOC">Timed Abstract Objects </a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#TimedAbstractObjectsandFRBRANCHOR" name="TimedAbstractObjectsandFRBRTOC">Timed Abstract Objects and FRBR </a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ProblemswithTimedAbstractObjectsANCHOR" name="ProblemswithTimedAbstractObjectsTOC">Problems with Timed Abstract Objects </a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ConclusionANCHOR" name="ConclusionTOC">Conclusion </a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ReferencesANCHOR" name="ReferencesTOC">References</a></div>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerTERMS">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTERMS" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTERMS').toggle('1000')">Index of Terms</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTERMS" style="display:none;">
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">a</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">August 7 - 10, 2012</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Associate Professor</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">b</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">becoming</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">c</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">change</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Contemporary Debates in Metaphysics</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">claus.huitfeldt@uib.no</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Claus</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">d</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Documents Cannot Be Edited.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">e</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">f</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">fabio@cs.unibo.it</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Fabio</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">g</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">h</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Huitfeldt</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">i</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">j</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">k</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">l</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">m</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">n</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">o</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">p</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Parts. A Study in Ontology.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Peroni</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">q</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">r</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">s</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">speroni@cs.unibo.it</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Silvio</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">t</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Turtle, Terse RDF Triple Language</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">There are No Documents.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">u</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">v</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Vitali</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">x</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">y</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">z</div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerIML"><a name="DocumentsasTimedAbstractObjectsANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="article e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3">
      <div class="title e1">Documents as Timed Abstract Objects</div>
      <div class="info e2">
         <div class="confgroup e3">
            <div class="conftitle e4">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>
            <div class="confdates e5">August 7 - 10, 2012</div>
         </div>
         <div class="abstract e6">
            <div class="para e7">At Balisage 2009 and 2010 Renear and Wickett discussed problems in reconciling the
               view that documents are abstract objects with the fact that they can undergo change.
               In this paper we present an account of documents which we believe is quite common,
               but which was not discussed by Renear and Wickett. 
            </div>
            <div class="para e8">According to this account documents are indeed abstract objects, but this is
               easily reconciled with the fact that they are created and can undergo change. We
               then point to a similarity between this account and the notion of so-called
               space-time slices. We argue that the proposed account of documents as timed abstract
               objects may be subject to the same kind of criticism that has been raised against
               the notion of space-time slices. 
            </div>
            <div class="para e9">We believe that our account fares no worse than the other accounts given of
               documents as abstract objects. But it still fails, and we remain agnostic about the
               ontological status of documents and their relation to abstract objects, as well as
               about the nature of abstract objects. We conclude that either documents are not (or
               not related to) abstract objects, or they are (or are related to) abstract objects
               of a kind which does not correspond to the standard definition of what an abstract
               object is.
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e10">
            <div class="personname e11">
               <div class="firstname e12">Claus</div>
               <div class="surname e13">Huitfeldt</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e14">
               <div class="para e15">Claus Huitfeldt is Associate Professor at the Department of Philosophy of the
                  University of Bergen, Norway. He was founding Director (1990-2000) of the
                  Wittgenstein Archives at the University of Bergen, for which he developed the
                  text encoding system MECS as well as the editorial methods for the publication
                  of Wittgenstein's Nachlass — The Bergen Electronic Edition (Oxford University
                  Press, 2000).
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e16">
               <div class="jobtitle e17">Associate Professor </div>
               <div class="orgname e18">Department of Philosophy, University of Bergen, Norway</div>
            </div>
            <div class="email e19">claus.huitfeldt@uib.no</div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e20">
            <div class="personname e21">
               <div class="firstname e22">Fabio</div>
               <div class="surname e23">Vitali</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e24">
               <div class="para e25">Fabio Vitali is Associate Professor in Computer Science at the University of
                  Bologna, where he teaches Web Technologies and Human-Computer Interaction. His
                  interests lie in models and languages for document management and hypertext
                  support, and has published more than 60 papers in national and international
                  venues. He is member of the W3C Working Group on XML Schema, and member of the
                  scientific committee of several conferences and journals in Web engineering and
                  technologies. He is author of important standards in the legislative XML Domain,
                  and work on issues related to digital publishing, Web technologies and Semantic
                  Web technologies. 
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e26">
               <div class="orgname e27">Department of Computer Science, University of Bologna, Bologna,
                  Italy
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="email e28">fabio@cs.unibo.it </div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e29">
            <div class="personname e30">
               <div class="firstname e31">Silvio</div>
               <div class="surname e32">Peroni</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e33">
               <div class="para e34">Silvio Peroni holds a degree in Computer Science at the University of Bologna.
                  The main research interests in his current Ph.D. career include Semantic Web
                  technologies, markup languages for complex documents, design patterns for
                  digital documents and automatic processes of analysis and segmentation. He has
                  published 9 scientific papers about these subjects. 
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e35">
               <div class="orgname e36">Department of Computer Science, University of Bologna, Bologna, Italy
                  
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="email e37">speroni@cs.unibo.it </div>
         </div>
         <div class="legalnotice e38">
            <div class="para e39">Copyright © 2012 by the authors</div>
         </div>
      </div><a name="BackgroundANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e40" xml:id="Background">
         <div class="title e41">Background </div>
         <div class="para e42">Cultural objects like literary or musical works and other repeatable forms of
            expression occupy an ambiguous and philosophically interesting position between the
            concrete and the abstract. On the one hand, they become known to us only in the form
            of
            concrete physical objects like books, scores or performances. On the other hand, it
            seems unnatural to identify the works with their manifestations: A literary work is
            not
            identical with any sum of physical manifestations, and a musical work is identical
            neither with its score nor with its performances. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e43">Questions concerning the ontological status of literary or musical works fall within
            the wider domain of questions concerning the ontological status of other cultural
            or
            artistic expressions such as for example sculpture or painting, and also within the
            even
            wider domain of questions concerning the status of cultural artifacts in general.
            Our
            discussion in this paper is limited to the realm of writing. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e44">Following Goodman [
            <div class="xref e45" linkend="Goodman76"></div>], we may distinguish what may be called
            "unique" from "multiple" art forms by appeal to his definitions of autographic and
            allographic works.
            .
            Roughly, and limiting ourselves to modern Western culture, literary and musical works
            are based on notations and are therefore allographic, whereas sculptures and paintings
            are non-notational, and therefore autographic. No copy of Mona Lisa or replica of
            David
            is an authentic manifestation of Mona Lisa or David, whereas any edition of Hamlet
            or
            performance of Bolero is a manifestation of Hamlet and Bolero, respectively. In the
            former case, the authenticity of a manifestation is a question of physical identity.
            In
            the latter case, no question of authenticity in terms of physical identity applies.
            Whether a copy is a manifestation of a literary or musical work is only a question
            of
            correctness of reproduction within certain constraints. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e46">Thus, the identity criteria for autographic works are similar to the identity criteria
            for physical objects. The identity criteria for allographic works are slightly more
            difficult to specify. What is it that makes two physical objects manifestations of
            the
            same document? 
            <div class="popupBox e47">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e79').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e79').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e79" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e48">So far, we have talked about musical and literary "works". From this point on,
                        we will talk mainly about "documents": This may be slightly confusing, as many
                        writers on this subject use the term "document" to refer to the physical aspect
                        of the matter, while "text" or "work" refer precisely to the abstract aspect.
                        For the sake of this discussion, however, we stick to Renear and Wickett's
                        terminology.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div> And, considering the fact that a physical manifestation of a document may
            undergo change: How do we decide whether or not it is still a manifestation of the
            same
            document? 
         </div>
         <div class="para e49">One way of accounting for the identity of documents through multiplicity and change
            among physical manifestations is to say that the document is an abstract object, and
            that its manifestations are instantiations of that abstract object. So what two physical
            objects must have in common in order to be manifestations of the same document is
            that
            they must both instantiate the same abstract object. 
            <div class="popupBox e50">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e85').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e85').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e85" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e51">At this point we have already departed completely from Goodman, who had little
                        patience with any talk of abstract objects.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="para e52">In philosophy this kind of explanation by reference to abstract objects is perhaps
            contentious, but not uncommon. We observe that it is perhaps more common, and certainly
            regarded as less contentious, in domains outside philosophy. In the library professions
            and library and information science, for example, one of the currently important
            standards is Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records [
            <div class="xref e53" linkend="frbr"></div>],
            distinguishes between bibliographic objects in terms of different abstraction levels
            such as item, manifestation, expression and work. 
         </div>
      </div><a name="TheInconsistentTriadANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e54" xml:id="Triad">
         <div class="title e55">The Inconsistent Triad </div>
         <div class="para e56">Renear and Wickett point out that the view that documents are abstract objects leads
            to the following inconsistent triad: 
            <div class="itemizedlist e57">
               <div class="listitem e58">
                  <div class="para e59">Documents are strings.</div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e60">
                  <div class="para e61">Strings cannot be modified. </div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e62">
                  <div class="para e63">Documents can be modified.</div>
               </div>
            </div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="para e64"> The authors argue that all the three statements seem to have some initial
            plausibility, yet any two of them implies the negation of the remaining statement.
         </div>
         <div class="para e65">In the example as quoted, the explicit reference is to "strings", not to abstract
            objects. The authors make it very clear, however, not only that they regard strings
            as
            abstract objects, but also that they believe their argument to be valid irrespective
            of
            which particular kind of abstract object documents are thought to constitute. They
            take
            care to make explicit that the inconsistency cannot be seen to trade on any ambiguity
            in
            the way that the three statements are phrased. 
            <div class="popupBox e66">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e113').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e113').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e113" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e67">In [
                        <div class="xref e68" linkend="RenWick09"></div>], they offer the following formalisation: 
                        <div class="itemizedlist e69">
                           <div class="listitem e70">
                              <div class="para e71"> (x)[(isaDocument(x) -&gt; isaString(x)] </div>
                           </div>
                           <div class="listitem e72">
                              <div class="para e73"> (x)[(isaString(x) -&gt; ~isModifiable(x)] </div>
                           </div>
                           <div class="listitem e74">
                              <div class="para e75"> (Ex)[(isaDocument(x) &amp; isModifiable(x)] </div>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div> In [
            <div class="xref e76" linkend="RenWick10"></div>] they observe that the inconsistency does
            not arise if the last of the three statements is read not as an existence claim, but
            only as a universal generalisation. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e77">For purposes of terminology and generality, we may therefore reformulate the
            inconsistent triad as follows: 
            <div class="itemizedlist e78">
               <div class="listitem e79">
                  <div class="para e80">1. All documents are abstract objects </div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e81">
                  <div class="para e82">2. No abstract object can change. </div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e83">
                  <div class="para e84">3. Documents exist, and they can change 
                     <div class="popupBox e85">
                        <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e144').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e144').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
                        <div id="d1e144" style="display: none;">
                           <div class="footnote">
                              <div class="para e86">Since this is a conjunction of two statements, the inconsistent
                                 "triad" might actually be said to consist of four statements, rather
                                 than three.
                              </div>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </div> .
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            
         </div>
      </div><a name="ResponsestotheInconsistencyANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e87" xml:id="Responses">
         <div class="title e88">Responses to the Inconsistency </div>
         <div class="para e89">It is not hard to agree with Renear and Wickett that the third of the three
            statements, that documents exist and that they can change, has "initial plausibility",
            as it seems to be implied in all our talk and all our dealings with documents as objects
            of our everyday world. The first statement may seem less obvious, but the authors
            argue
            forcefully, and in our eyes they are right, that it is an underlying assumption in
            much
            or most of the theoretical disciplines and technologies involved in document processing
            and management that documents are abstract objects. The second, i.e. the claim that
            abstract objects cannot change, is in accordance with the standard modern definition
            of
            abstract objects as non-spatial, atemporal and causally inefficient. 
            <div class="popupBox e90">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e154').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e154').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e154" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e91">See for example [
                        <div class="xref e92" linkend="rosen2012"></div>] and [
                        <div class="xref e93" linkend="swoyer2008"></div>]. If everybody agrees that abstract objects cannot change and that documents
                        can change, it may seem futile to discuss whether documents are abstract
                        objects. However, it does not follow from these two claims alone that documents,
                        or our conceptions of them, do not presuppose or are not in some other sense
                        basically related to abstract objects. Moreover, the notions that abstract
                        objects are atemporal, non-spatial, and causally inefficient, and that documents
                        are in some sense abstract, are so deep-rooted in modern science and culture
                        that it seems reasonable to take the discussion seriously, futile or not.
                     </div>
                     <div class="para e94">Even so, to the authors of this paper (and probably to many of its readers) it
                        often seems awkward to use the term "object" (including "abstract object") about
                        abstract topics of scientific discourse, where we would often be inclined to
                        talk about concepts rather than objects. If we agree that a chair is an object
                        and freedom is a concept, for example, it seems more plausible to liken
                        documents, strings, and mathematical structures (say π) to freedom than to the
                        chair. The relation between concepts and objects as technical terms in this
                        context is a complex one, however, 
                        and far too far-reaching for this paper. For purposes of the present discussion,
                        therefore, we try to keep with the "object" terminology, but the reader may
                        notice that we have sometimes, when this has seemed too strained, allowed
                        ourselves to use the term "concept". 
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div> We have nothing to say against the plausibility of the three statements at
            this stage, though we will come back to the point about abstract objects towards the
            end. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e95">When the three statements form an inconsistent triad, and the inconsistency does not
            rest on some ambiguity, the natural question to ask is which of the statements to
            reject
            or modify. Renear and Wickett go through and argue against a considerable number of
            possible responses. Rejection of the statement that documents are abstract objects
            (in
            the form of "materialist" or "social object" strategies) as well as the rejection
            of the
            statement that documents can change (in the form of "new document" or "selection"
            strategies) are considered in 
            <div class="xref e96" linkend="RenWick09"></div>. Rejection of the statement
            that documents exist is considered in 
            <div class="xref e97" linkend="RenWick10"></div>. As a more acceptable
            alternative, they propose a "string-in-a-role" strategy, which partly denies the
            statement that documents can be modified and partly denies the statement that documents
            are abstract objects, by redefining the notion of a document. Although we do not think
            that all their arguments in favour of their own and against the other strategies are
            equally convincing 
            <div class="popupBox e98">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e172').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e172').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e172" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e99">For example, some views are simply dismissed as "difficult to reconcile with a
                        naturalistic view of the world", without further argument.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>, we will not pursue these matters here, but rather point to yet another
            alternative. 
         </div>
      </div><a name="TimedAbstractObjectsANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e100" xml:id="TAO">
         <div class="title e101">Timed Abstract Objects </div>
         <div class="para e102">Science is not unfamiliar with the problems involved in describing time-related events
            and processes in physical reality in terms of time-independent mathematical concepts.
            A
            whole subfield of physics, dynamical systems, is devoted to the formal study of the
            mathematics of things that change. Poincaré (1854-1912) and Gibbs (1839-1903) provided
            the basic tools used today to study anything from the evolution of chemical reactions
            to
            the trajectories of celestial bodies. The basic approach of dynamical systems is to
            use
            functions of time to model the evolution of a point in a manifold. The set of points
            of
            the manifold represent all the potential states, the phase space, and each function
            draws a plot or a trajectory within the phase space. The evolution function is often
            defined as an iterative function that determines the state of the system in the future,
            given its conditions at the present. The study of the dynamical system is meant to
            determine the state of the system at any point in the future by solving the equations
            of
            the evolution function. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e103"> In computer science, the theory of automata studies the behavior of abstract machines
            that change their internal state upon receiving some input. More specifically, an
            automaton is an abstract machine that passes from a single initial state through several
            intermediate states to one of many final states (e.g., Success) depending on the input
            received. In this model, the automaton is a quintuple (Q, Ʃ, ∂, q0, F), where Q is
            the
            set of states (the state space) of the machine, Ʃ is the alphabet of the potential
            inputs, ∂ is a transition function from one state to another depending on elements
            of
            the alphabet Ʃ, q0 is the initial state, and F is the subset of Q that constitute
            the
            acceptable final states. An automaton succeeds on input X (a string of items of the
            alphabet Ʃ) if the machine transits from the initial state through intermediate states
            up to a final state while receiving input X, and fails if it remains in an intermediate
            state. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e104">Automata are more useful than dynamic systems in our discussion: Dynamic systems
            analysis is well suited for modelling change in manifolds, i.e. continuous state spaces.
            Automata theory, however, is better suited to deal with discrete structures, such
            as
            strings. We may regard strings as the state space of the content of a document.
         </div>
         <div class="para e105">On this conception, strings are still immutable concepts that do not change over time.
            The number 2 is an immutable object. The string “To be or not to be” is also an
            immutable object. The set of all strings, past, future or potential, each one of them
            an
            immutable object, is also an immutable object. We could now proceed in two different,
            but ultimately equivalent, directions: On the one hand we could go the dynamical system
            way, introducing a change function for each document. This function is associated
            with
            the ordered independent variable similar to “time”, which we will call *time. 
            <div class="popupBox e106">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e187').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e187').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e187" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e107">One may need to make further restrictive hypothesis about the *time points, if
                        he/she were inclined to over-analyze this theory, but for the moment we let it
                        stand that *time may not be time but behaves like time.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div> On the other hand, we could introduce an edit function, associated with an
            independent variable called “edit session”. In both cases, the function selects a
            specific string for each value of time t or edit session s. For instance, it will
            select
            string s1 for time t1, and string s2 for time t2, etc. Given a change function c or
            an
            edit function e, we can now define a document as the sequence of strings sc that are
            selected for each value in time or edit session. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e108"> Still, documents, like strings, are immutable concepts that do not change over time.
            But documents are not strings. While not changing in time, documents change in *time,
            because the function change associates different strings with different *time points.
            
            
            This allows us to provide a time-dependent view of documents that is not affected
            by the
            immutableness of the basic mathematical concepts under it: we just select different
            strings at different *times and regard them as the state of the document at that *time.
            
         </div>
      </div><a name="TimedAbstractObjectsandFRBRANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e109" xml:id="Application">
         <div class="title e110">Timed Abstract Objects and FRBR </div>
         <div class="para e111">When we refer to a document, we can mean to refer to several different objects
            depending on our backgrounds and social roles (e.g., reader, archivist, author,
            publisher, etc.). In fact, as [
            <div class="xref e112" linkend="tillett04"></div>] puts it, when we speak about
            a document, we may refer to a physical object in our bookcase, to a particular
            publication (i.e., an edition) identified through an ISBN, to its content (or part
            of
            it) identified through a DOI and, finally, to the abstract conceptualisation, i.e.,
            «the
            conceptual content that underlies all of the linguistic versions, the story being
            told
            in the book, the ideas in a person’s head for the book» [Tillett 2004]. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e113">The Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records (FRBR) [
            <div class="xref e114" linkend="ifla09"></div>] is a general model, proposed by the International Federation of Library Associations
            and Institutions (IFLA),
            <div class="popupBox e115">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e208').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e208').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e208" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e116">
                        
                        <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e117" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ifla.org/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ifla.org/</div>
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div> for the description of documents and their evolution according to the
            aforementioned perspectives. To describe FRBR,
            <div class="popupBox e118">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e215').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e215').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e215" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e119">... or, rather, our own understanding of the FRBR levels. We do not claim we
                        have the correct interpretation of the model, but only of having a consistent
                        model which may or may not be the same as the one intended by IFLA.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div> we start from physical objects and work upwards toward more abstract
            concepts. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e120">Let us consider a physical book. We can identify some of its properties: weight, size,
            number of pages, color of the cover, quantity and shape of the ink on the 15th page,
            and
            so on. If we partake to a culture that recognizes the book as a cultural object, a
            *book, may be able to identify more properties: a title, an author, a publication
            date,
            a content, and so on. Now let us consider another book. We notice that it has the
            same
            physical properties as the first one (same weight, size, color, disposition of the
            ink
            in each page etc.) and, by interpreting the underlying *book, we notice it has the
            same
            title, author, content, etc. We need a concept to collect and describe these
            similarities against the fundamental difference that they are, in fact, numerically
            different objects. Thus we define each physical object as an Item of the same *book,
            and
            allow this *book to be perceivable as one through many different books, each having
            the
            same values for most cultural and physical properties, except for physical sameness.
            
         </div>
         <div class="para e121">Now let us consider a PDF file, which we are told is the source of the physical books
            seen before: it is physically completely different, being a computer structure rather
            than a physical object. Yet, somehow the culturally relevant concept of “content”
            is the
            same, and a number of culturally relevant related concepts (e.g., the author, the
            title,
            and so on) are identical. We have two different forms of book, but we interpret both
            forms as representing the same *book. We call them individual Manifestations of the
            same
            *book, and allow the *book to be perceivable as one through many different forms,
            each
            having the same values for a number of cultural properties, but many different physical
            properties. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e122">Let us next consider another book, (either electronic or physical, it does not
            matter), which we are told is a different version of the same *book. This book is
            different from all the others, even in content: it may be a slight difference, a few
            words here and there, or a complete difference, as in having close to no similar content.
            <div class="popupBox e123">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e225').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e225').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e225" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e124">Consider for instance the translation of a Norwegian book into Italian, where
                        the two contents have practically no words in common.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div> Possibly, a number of cultural properties are the same: same author, same
            title (which does not mean the same string for the title property, but same conceptual
            value for the title concept), etc, and somehow we recognize that these two books are
            related, that they are one, in some more abstract way than by sharing the same content.
            We may have some properties that have the same values, but we may also have no sameness
            whatsoever, except only for some culturally shared and accepted, yet vague and
            approximate, sameness. We call the content of the two books, and the properties that
            are
            specific of each content, two Expressions of the same *book, and allow the *book to
            be
            perceivable as one through many different contents, each different in most or all
            properties except for some vague but culturally accepted sameness. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e125">We call Work whatever is left, composed of any property we agree is still associated
            with the *book regardless of the Item, Manifestation and Expression it is perceivable
            through, or nothing but the above-mentioned indistinct sameness, if no property is
            left.
            The Work is characterized by those properties that are shared by all Expressions,
            and in
            turn all Manifestations and all Items of a *book. On the other hand, each of its
            Expressions and Manifestations exist in a multiplicity of instances. At different
            points
            of *time we may access the same *book and find different contents, different forms,
            even
            different physical properties (a corner is torn, a stain appears on the cover, the
            book
            is physically replaced by the bookstore due to a misprint, etc.). Thus Expressions,
            Manifestations and Items change in *time and are, by definition, changeable and
            modifiable. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e126">The FRBR model has been used in different contexts: for the publishing domain [
            <div class="xref e127" linkend="peroni12"></div>], in open-government contexts [
            <div class="xref e128" linkend="cifuentes11"></div>],
            for the description of the musical publishing process [
            <div class="xref e129" linkend="raimond07"></div>] and
            for the legal domain [
            <div class="xref e130" linkend="barabucci2009"></div>]. For instance, Akoma Ntoso
            <div class="popupBox e131">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e241').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e241').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e241" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e132">
                        
                        <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e133" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.akomantoso.org" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.akomantoso.org</div>
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div> – a set of simple technology-neutral XML formats for parliamentary,
            legislative and judiciary documents – makes wide use of the FRBR hierarchy. It
            re-interprets parts of the FRBR endeavours so as to clearly and unambiguously identify
            the core attributes that characterise legislative documents. The entity Work is
            associated with the concept of identity, the Expression and Manifestation layers relate
            respectively to the content and the format of a such a document, and Item is used
            to
            indicate the particular location in which a concrete document is available. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e134"> In [
            <div class="xref e135" linkend="RenWick10"></div>] the authors explain that although «[t]he word
            "document" has ... many senses», their own «informal characterization of the sense
            ...[is]... more or less the same sense implied in the XML specification, which defines
            "XML Document" as a string that matches certain formal constraints [
            <div class="xref e136" linkend="Bray08"></div>]», and also that it «corresponds closely to the concept of an
            "expression" in the "Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records" (FRBR) [
            <div class="xref e137" linkend="frbr"></div>]». 
         </div>
         <div class="para e138">Yet on the one hand, the definition of XML documents seems more related to the
            Manifestation layer than to the Expression layer of FRBR: we read in 
            <div class="xref e139" linkend="Bray08"></div> that «an XML document may consist of one or many storage units.
            These are called entities; they all have content and are all (except for the document
            entity and the external DTD subset) identified by entity name». Thus, XML seems to
            be a
            vehicle to store document contents in a particular format by means of entities, which
            seems closer to the FRBR definition of Manifestation than that of Expression. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e140">On the other hand, however, the association of XML documents with only one of the
            various abstraction layers of FRBR is in our eyes unfortunate, be it the Expression,
            the
            Manifestation or the Item layer. We believe that FRBR defines a specific endeavour
            to
            model the time-dependency of documents, i.e., the fact that the Work is associated
            in
            time with a number of different Expressions. It is only by allowing XML documents
            to be
            considered, depending on context, either as Items, as Manifestations, as Expressions
            or
            even as Works in their own right, that the full potential of applying FRBR also to
            electronic documents can be exploited. 
            <div class="popupBox e141">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e262').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e262').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e262" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e142">At least one of the authors of 
                        <div class="xref e143" linkend="RenWick10"></div> has discussed and
                        criticized both the FRBR hierarchy and its relation to XML in a number of
                        earlier publications, so perhaps their association of XML documents with FRBR
                        Expressions is just a simplification made for the sake of their argument.
                        However, their argument does seem to rely at least to some extent on this
                        simplification.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="para e144"> The FRBR-aligned Bibliographic Ontology (FaBiO)
            <div class="popupBox e145">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e271').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e271').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e271" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e146">
                        
                        <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e147" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://purl.org/spar/fabio" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.org/spar/fabio</div>
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div> provides an example of how changes to a document may be tracked. For
            instance, we may summarise the steps of the creation of a particular research paper
            (class fabio:ResearchPaper, a subclass of frbr:Work). Let us assume that this particular
            Work has three authors, as shown in the following excerpt (in Turtle syntax [
            <div class="xref e148" linkend="prudhommeaux11"></div>]):
            
            <div class="programlisting e149" xml:space="preserve">           
               :paper a fabio:ResearchPaper
               ; frbr:creator :author1 , :author2, :author3 .
               
            </div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="para e150"> The very first (incomplete) draft content of this Work (i.e., an Expression) is
            written by one author only (let us suppose :author1). In FaBiO, this particular scenario
            can be described by referring to a particular realisation of the Work, an individual
            of
            fabio:ConferencePaper (i.e., a subclass of frbr:Expression), as follows:
            
            <div class="programlisting e151" xml:space="preserve">:paper frbr:realization :first-content-draft .
               :first-content-draft a fabio:ConferencePaper
               ; frbr:realizer :author1 .
               
            </div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="para e152">In this way, we can record both that there are three authors of the paper and that
            :author1 was responsible for writing the first draft of that paper. Similarly, the
            writing process can proceed with :author2, who wrote, for instance, a revised version
            of
            the content written previously by :author1:
            
            <div class="programlisting e153" xml:space="preserve">:paper frbr:realization :revised-content-draft .
               :first-content-draft frbr:revision :revised-content-draft .
               :revised-content-draft a fabio:ConferencePaper
               ; frbr:realizer :author2 .
               
            </div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="para e154">This process can be repeated until the authors produce the final version of the paper
            to be submitted to a venue. Has the document changed in time? If one considers each
            expression as a separate document (as suggested by Renear &amp; Wickett [Renear
            &amp; Wickett 2010]), then the answer is surely «no, none of the documents have
            changed». However, none of the previous documents record both author1, author2 and
            author3 as its authors . Thus, none of those documents fully represents the paper
            we are
            talking about, since it should record three people as its authors. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e155">Everything changes if we take the Work :paper, rather then its various Expressions,
            into account. In this case, the author is clearly specified – i.e., all the people
            involved in the realisation of each Expression are authors of :paper. The Work in
            consideration has changed during *time, since it has been realised in several revised
            expressions that differ in content and in *time of creation. 
         </div>
      </div><a name="ProblemswithTimedAbstractObjectsANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e156" xml:id="Problems">
         <div class="title e157">Problems with Timed Abstract Objects </div>
         <div class="para e158">We believe that this account of documents as Timed Abstract Objects has a number of
            strengths, and that it gives a coherent explanation of document change as well as
            our
            practices of identifying documents at different levels of abstraction. Notwithstanding
            its attractiveness, however, it also has some weak points. One of its consequences
            is
            that two documents which would perhaps on other accounts be regarded as identical
            would
            have to be regarded as different if they have different histories.
            <div class="popupBox e159">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e302').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e302').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e302" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e160">One may be reminded of Luis Borges' short story "Pierre Menard, Author of the
                        Quixote", where an (invented) XX century French writer re-writes word for word
                        Cervante's Don Quixote (a XVI century Spanish writer), not by copying it, nor by
                        imitating Cervantes, but by 
                        <div class="emphasis e161" role="ital">becoming</div> a XX
                        century French writer that through his own conceptual and philosophical growth
                        generates the Quixote (in XVI century Spanish, of course). We guess that most
                        reader's intuitions do not provide a clear answer whether we are dealing with
                        one or two documents in such a case. On the Timed Abstract Object account,
                        however, the answer is clear enough: They are two different documents.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div> In other words, two series of identical changes to "the same" document at
            slightly different times will constitute two different documents. But perhaps this
            is
            just a minor quirk, perhaps we simply don't have clear intuitions in such cases. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e162">However, the fact that its change history becomes so to speak a constitutive part
            of
            the document itself also implies that documents are not really accounted for as
            changeable objects, but as "events". Events, though they do take time, don't change.
            This attempt to account for document change has the seemingly paradoxical consequence
            that documents do not really change at all. (A poker may exemplify change by being
            first
            cold, and then warm. But a poker which is cold at the one end and warm at the other
            does
            not exemplify change.) 
            <div class="popupBox e163">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e311').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e311').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e311" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e164">The example is taken from [
                        <div class="xref e165" linkend="simons87"></div>], p. 126.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="para e166"> It is interesting, and may be instructive, to notice the parallel to the notion of
            space-time slices proposed by so-called "four-dimensionalism" in ontology, and some
            of
            the criticisms of that notion. The notion of space-time slices was introduced by
            philosophers like Quine and Goodman in an attempt to salvage the claim that concrete
            physical objects (or more generally, individuals) are identical with the sum of their
            parts (the claim that "the whole is nothing over and above its parts"), yet can undergo
            change. If an object is identical to the sum of its parts, then how can it lose a
            part,
            and yet remain the same object? One favoured example in the discussion is a cat losing
            its tail. After the loss of its tail, the cat is still the same cat, but clearly not
            the
            same sum of parts.
         </div>
         <div class="para e167"> The answer proposed by four-dimensionalism is that the cat, correctly considered,
            is
            not the sum of its parts at any single moment, but the sum of all its temporal as
            well
            as its spatial parts. And when the cat is considered as the sum of all its
            spatio-temporal parts, there is no difficulty explaining how references to the cat
            before and after the loss of its tail can be references to the same cat: they refer
            to
            two spatio-temporal parts of the very same cat. What we have before us at any particular
            moment when we consider the cat is not the whole cat, but a temporal part, a time-slice,
            of the cat.
         </div>
         <div class="para e168"> One of the critics of this conception, Peter Simons, points out that on the
            four-dimensional account, the cat losing its tail does not really 
            <div class="emphasis e169" role="ital">change</div>: The loss of its tail is so to speak baked into the cat as such.
            Simons' complaint "is not that the four-dimensional ontology is inconsistent (if it
            is
            inconsistent, this is far from obvious), but that no one has begun to do the work
            required to make it understandable to we users of a continuant/occurent ontology".
            
            <div class="popupBox e170">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e326').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e326').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e326" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e171">[
                        <div class="xref e172" linkend="simons87"></div>], p. 123. The "continuant/occurent" distinction is
                        (roughly) a distinction between things, substances or individuals on the one
                        hand, and events, processes etc. on the other. Simons contends that adherents of
                        four-dimensionalism are "cheating", i.e. they are relying on the ordinary
                        distinction between continuants and occurents in all their claims that the
                        former can be reduced to the latter. He does not argue that a language where all
                        references to continuants were consistently translated to references to
                        four-dimensional objects and their spatio-temporal parts is impossible, but that
                        it is hard to see how it would be comprehensible, and that no one has even begun
                        the task of constructing such a language. 
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="para e173">It may be conceded that a proposal to consider documents as Timed Abstract Objects
            is
            not quite as drastic as the analogous attempt to account for continuants in general
            as
            four-dimensional objects. But, as suggested above, we do think that the proposal has
            similar, counter-intuitive implications. Finally, the account may have counter-intuitive
            consequences when applied to the actual handling of documents in every-day contexts,
            especially involving digital documents. When deciding whether two document files
            instantiate the same document we do not normally, and would normally not be in the
            position to, decide whether or not they have been brought about by the same
            string-modifying operations at the same points of time, nor is it easy to think of
            examples where such information would be considered relevant. 
            <div class="popupBox e174">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e334').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e334').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e334" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e175">It may of course be argued that this is only because such information is in
                        fact rarely available.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="para e176">More importantly, however, we believe that the difficulties with this and the other
            proposals to deal with the inconsistent triad may be rooted in the concept of abstract
            object presupposed by all of them. Renear and Wickett explicitly exclude from
            consideration "responses that deny the second assertion", i.e. (in our rephrasing)
            that
            abstract objects cannot change. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e177"> We have come to believe that as long as abstract objects are defined as atemporal,
            non-spatial and causally ineffective, none of the above accounts can explain the perhaps
            most important distinctive feature of documents: That they can carry information,
            be
            written and read by human beings, and thus serve the transmission of knowledge, culture
            and value.
         </div>
         <div class="para e178">Admittedly, Renear and Wickett's proposal is not that documents themselves are
            abstract objects, but that they are abstract objects in a particular role. Similarly,
            on
            the Timed Abstract Object account the claim is not that documents themselves are
            abstract objects, but that they are functions from time sequences to abstract objects.
            On both accounts, however, documents are defined in relation to abstract objects.
            
            <div class="popupBox e179">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e344').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e344').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e344" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e180">It may be objected that a function is not an object, but a relation. This may
                        be true, but is hardly relevant for the argument presented here.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="para e181">The problem of explaining how we can have epistemic access to abstract objects is
            well
            known. For example, Swoyer, a realist about abstract objects, says:
            <div class="popupBox e182">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e350').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e350').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e350" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e183"> [
                        <div class="xref e184" linkend="swoyer2008"></div>], p. 27. See also [
                        <div class="xref e185" linkend="rosen2012"></div>]
                        and [
                        <div class="xref e186" linkend="dorr2008"></div>]) 
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            
            <div class="popupBox e187">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e360').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e360').hide('1000');">[ blockquote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e360" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="blockquote">
                     <div class="para e188">Epistemology is the Achilles' heel of realism about abstracta. We are
                        biological organisms thoroughly ensconced in the natural, spatio-temporal causal
                        order. Abstract entities, by contrast are atemporal, non-spatial, and causally
                        inert, so they cannot affect our senses, our brains, or our instruments for
                        measuring and detecting.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div> It may very well be that atemporal, non-spatial and causally ineffective
            abstract objects exist. Perhaps mathematical objects like numbers or sets are of this
            kind (even though similar problems concerning epistemic access apply here). But we
            seem
            forced to conclude not only that documents are not themselves abstract objects, but
            also
            that any account of documents that relies on our epistemic access to abstract objects
            remains unsatisfactory unless the definition of abstract objects on which it relies
            differs from the standard one. 
         </div>
      </div><a name="ConclusionANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e189" xml:id="Conclusion">
         <div class="title e190">Conclusion </div>
         <div class="para e191">Among the considered accounts of documents in terms of abstract objects, we believe
            that the Timed Abstract Object account is the best. However, the failure of all accounts
            of documents in terms of abstract objects to explain how we can have epistemic access
            to
            them is a major drawback. The fact remains that documents exist, that they are created
            and can be changed by human beings, and that they can go out of existence. We remain
            agnostic about their ontological status, but we conclude that either documents are
            not
            abstract objects after all, or they are abstract objects of a kind which does not
            correspond to the standard definition of what an abstract object is.
         </div>
      </div><a name="ReferencesANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="bibliography e192">
         <div class="title e193">References</div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e194" xml:id="barabucci2009" xreflabel="Barabucci et al. 2009"> Barabucci, G.,
            Cervone, L., Palmirani, M., Peroni, S., Vitali, F. (2009). "Multi-layer markup and
            ontological structures in Akoma Ntoso". In 
            <div class="emphasis e195" role="ital">Proceeding of the
               International Workshop on AI approaches to the complexity of legal systems
               II
            </div> (AICOL-II). Rotterdam, The Netherlands. 
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e196" xml:id="barabucci2010" xreflabel="Barabucci et al. 2010">Barabucci, G.,
            Cervone, L., Di Iorio, A., Palmirani, M., Peroni, S., Vitali, F. (2010). "Managing
            semantics in XML vocabularies: an experience in the legal and legislative domain".
            In
            
            <div class="emphasis e197" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference</div>
            2010. Montreal, Canada. doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e198">10.4242/BalisageVol5.Barabucci01</div>.
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e199" xml:id="Bray08" xreflabel="Bray et al. 2008">Bray, T., Paoli, J.,
            Sperberg-McQueen, C. M., Maler, E., Yergeau, F. (2008). 
            <div class="emphasis e200" role="ital">Extensible
               Markup Language (XML) 1.0
            </div> (Fifth Edition). W3C Recommendation 26 November
            2008. World Wide Web Consortium. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e201" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e202" xml:id="cifuentes11" xreflabel="Cifuentes Silva et al. 2011">Cifuentes Silva,
            F. A., Sifaqui, C., Labra Gayo, J. E. (2011). "Towards an architecture and adoption
            process for linked data technologies in open government contexts: a case study for
            the
            Library of Congress of Chile". In 
            <div class="emphasis e203" role="ital">Proceedings of the 7th
               International Conference on Semantic Systems (I-SEMANTICS 2011).
            </div> Graz,
            Austria, September 7-9. 
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e204" xml:id="dorr2008" xreflabel="Dorr 2008">Dorr, Cian. "There Are No Abstract
            Objects" in Sider et. al 2008, pp. 32-63. 
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e205" xml:id="frbr" xreflabel="FRBR 98">
            
            <div class="emphasis e206" role="ital">Functional requirements for bibliographic records : final report /
               IFLA Study Group on the Functional Requirements for Bibliographic
               Records
            </div>. — München : K.G. Saur, 1998. — viii, 136 p. — (UBCIM publications ;
            new series, vol. 19). — ISBN 978-3-598-11382-6. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e207" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ifla.org/en/publications/functional-requirements-for-bibliographic-records" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ifla.org/en/publications/functional-requirements-for-bibliographic-records</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e208" xml:id="ifla09" xreflabel="IFLA 2009"> International Federation of Library
            Associations and Institutions Study Group on the Functional Requirements for
            Bibliographic Records (2009). Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records Final
            Report. International Federation of Library Associations and Institutions.
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e209" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ifla.org/files/cataloguing/frbr/frbr_2008.pdf" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ifla.org/files/cataloguing/frbr/frbr_2008.pdf</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e210" xml:id="Goodman76" xreflabel="Goodman 1976">Goodman, Nelson. 
            <div class="emphasis e211" role="ital">Languages of art: An approach to the theory of symbols</div>.
            Indianapolis, Cambridge: Hackett, 1976.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e212" xml:id="peroni12" xreflabel="Peroni &amp; Shotton 2012">Peroni, S.,
            Shotton, D. (2012). 
            <div class="emphasis e213" role="ital">FaBiO and CiTO: ontologies for describing
               bibliographic resources and citation
            </div>s. Submitted for publication in the
            Journal of Web Semantics. 
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e214" xml:id="prudhommeaux11" xreflabel="Prud'hommeaux &amp; Carothers 2011">Prud'hommeaux, E., Carothers G. (2011). 
            <div class="emphasis e215" role="ital">Turtle, Terse RDF Triple
               Language
            </div>. W3C Working Draft 09 August 2011, World Wide Web Consortium.
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e216" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/turtle" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.w3.org/TR/turtle</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e217" xml:id="raimond07" xreflabel="Raimond et al. 2007"> Raimond, Y., Abdallah, S.,
            Sandler, M., Giasson, F. (2007). "The Music Ontology". In 
            <div class="emphasis e218" role="ital">Proceedings of the 8th International Conference on Music Information Retrieval
               (ISMIR 2007).
            </div> Vienna, Austria, September 23-27. 
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e219" xml:id="RenWick09" xreflabel="Renear &amp; Wickett 2009">Renear, Allen H.
            and Karen M. Wickett 
            <div class="emphasis e220" role="ital">Documents Cannot Be Edited. </div>
            Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 - 14,
            2009. In Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009. Balisage Series on Markup
            Technologies, vol. 3 (2009). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e221">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Renear01</div>. Downloadable from
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e222" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Renear01/BalisageVol3-Renear01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://balisage.net/Proceedings/vol3/html/Renear01/BalisageVol3-Renear01.html</div>
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e223" xml:id="RenWick10" xreflabel="Renear &amp; Wickett 2010">Renear, Allen H.
            and Karen M. Wickett 
            <div class="emphasis e224" role="ital">There are No Documents.</div> Presented
            at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2010, Montréal, Canada, August 3 - 6, 2010. In
            Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2010. Balisage Series on Markup
            Technologies, vol. 5 (2010). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e225">10.4242/BalisageVol5.Renear01</div>. Downloadable from
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e226" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://balisage.net/Proceedings/vol5/html/Renear01/BalisageVol5-Renear01.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://balisage.net/Proceedings/vol5/html/Renear01/BalisageVol5-Renear01.html</div>
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e227" xml:id="rosen2012" xreflabel="Rosen 2012">Rosen, Gideon. "Abstract Objects"
            
            <div class="emphasis e228" role="ital">The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</div> (Spring
            2012 Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.).
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e229" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://plato.stanford.edu/archives/spr2012/entries/abstract-objects" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://plato.stanford.edu/archives/spr2012/entries/abstract-objects</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e230" xml:id="simons87" xreflabel="Simons 1987">Peter Simons. 
            <div class="emphasis e231" role="ital">Parts. A Study in Ontology.</div> Oxford University Press 1987.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e232" xml:id="Sider2008" xreflabel="Sider et. al 2008">Theodore Sider, John
            Hawthorne, and Dean W. Zimmerman (eds.): 
            <div class="emphasis e233" role="ital">Contemporary Debates in
               Metaphysics
            </div>. Blackwell 2008. 
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e234" xml:id="swoyer2008" xreflabel="Swoyer 2008">Swoyer, Chris. "Abstract Entities"
            in Sider et. al 2008, pp. 11-31.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e235" xml:id="tillett04" xreflabel="Tillett 2004">Tillett, B. (2004). "What is FRBR?
            A conceptual model for the bibliographic universe". 
            <div class="emphasis e236" role="ital">Library of
               Congress Cataloguing and Distribution service.
            </div>
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e237" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/cds/downloads/FRBR.PDF" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.loc.gov/cds/downloads/FRBR.PDF</div>
            
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>