<div id="mainContainerTOC">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTOC" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTOC').toggle('1000');">Table of Content</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTOC" style="display:none;">
      <div class="headedContainerTOC">
         <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#AstandardsrelatedwebbasedinformationsystemANCHOR" name="AstandardsrelatedwebbasedinformationsystemTOC">A standards-related web-based information system</a></div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#IntroductionANCHOR" name="IntroductionTOC">Introduction</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#TheproblemwithstandardsANCHOR" name="TheproblemwithstandardsTOC">The problem with standards</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ProvidingguidanceANCHOR" name="ProvidingguidanceTOC">Providing guidance</a></div>
            <div class="headedContainerTOC">
               <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#InformationstructureANCHOR" name="InformationstructureTOC">Information structure</a></div>
            </div>
            <div class="headedContainerTOC">
               <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#RepresentationANCHOR" name="RepresentationTOC">Representation</a></div>
            </div>
            <div class="headedContainerTOC">
               <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#CurrentstateandfutureworkANCHOR" name="CurrentstateandfutureworkTOC">Current state and future work</a></div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ReferencesANCHOR" name="ReferencesTOC">References</a></div>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerTERMS">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTERMS" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTERMS').toggle('1000')">Index of Terms</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTERMS" style="display:none;">
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">a</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">August 7 - 10, 2012</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Andreas</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">b</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">c</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">CLARIN</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Constraint Language</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">d</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">e</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">f</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">g</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Generic Corpus Annotation</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">h</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">HL7</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">i</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">ISO</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">j</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">k</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">l</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Language Resources Management</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">m</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Meta Language</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Metadata</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">maik.stuehrenberg@uni-bielefeld.de</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Maik</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">n</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">o</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">OASIS</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Oliver</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">p</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">q</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">r</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">s</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">schonefeld@ids-mannheim.de</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Stührenberg</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Schonefeld</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">t</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">u</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">v</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">x</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">y</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">z</div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerIML"><a name="AstandardsrelatedwebbasedinformationsystemANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="article e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3">
      <div class="title e1">A standards-related web-based information system</div>
      <div class="info e2">
         <div class="confgroup e3">
            <div class="conftitle e4">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>
            <div class="confdates e5">August 7 - 10, 2012</div>
         </div>
         <div class="abstract e6">
            <div class="para e7">This late breaking proposal introduces the prototype of a web-based information system
               dealing with standards in the field of annotation.
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e8">
            <div class="personname e9">
               <div class="firstname e10">Maik</div>
               <div class="surname e11">Stührenberg</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e12">
               <div class="para e13">Maik Stührenberg received his Ph.D. in Computational Linguistics and Text Technology
                  from Bielefeld University in 2012. After graduating in 2001 he worked four years as
                  research assistant at Giessen University in different text-technological projects
                  together
                  with Henning Lobin and Georg Rehm. Afterwards, he worked together with Andreas Witt,
                  Dieter Metzing, Daniela Goecke and Daniel Jettka in the Sekimo project of the Research
                  Group 437 Text-technological Modelling of Information funded by the German Research
                  Foundation. During 2011 and 2012 he was employed at the Institut für Deutsche Sprache
                  (IDS, Institute for the German Language) in Mannheim as member of the CLARIN-D project
                  group and is currently employed as research assistant at Bielefeld University.
               </div>
               <div class="para e14"> His main research interests include specifications for structuring multiple annotated
                  data, query languages, and query processing.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e15">
               <div class="orgname e16">Institut für Deutsche Sprache (IDS) Mannheim</div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e17">
               <div class="orgname e18">Universität Bielefeld</div>
            </div>
            <div class="email e19">maik.stuehrenberg@uni-bielefeld.de</div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e20">
            <div class="personname e21">
               <div class="firstname e22">Oliver</div>
               <div class="surname e23">Schonefeld</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e24">
               <div class="para e25">Oliver Schonefeld works at the Institut für Deutsche Sprache (Institute for the German
                  Language) in Mannheim and is involved in the projects CLARIN and TextGrid. He studied
                  computer science with specialization in text technology at Bielefeld University until
                  2005. After graduating he worked as a researcher at Bielefeld University and later
                  at
                  Tübingen University's collaborative research center Linguistic Data Structures. His
                  major
                  research interests are the limitations of markup languages (especially overlapping
                  markup)
                  and the use of markup languages in linguistic description of language data.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e26">
               <div class="orgname e27">Institut für Deutsche Sprache (IDS) Mannheim</div>
            </div>
            <div class="email e28">schonefeld@ids-mannheim.de</div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e29">
            <div class="personname e30">
               <div class="firstname e31">Andreas</div>
               <div class="surname e32">Witt</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e33">
               <div class="para e34">Witt received his Ph.D. in Computational Linguistics and Text Technology from the
                  Bielefeld University in 2002 (dissertation title: “Multiple Informationsstrukturierung
                  mit
                  Auszeichnungssprachen. XML-basierte Methoden und deren Nutzen für die Sprachtechnologie”).
                  After graduating in 1996, he started as a researcher and instructor in Computational
                  Linguistics and Text Technology. He was heavily involved in the establishment of the
                  minor
                  subject Text Technology in Bielefeld University's Magister and B.A. program in 1999
                  and
                  2002 respectively. After his Ph.D. in 2002 he became an assistant lecturer, still
                  at the
                  Text Technology group in Bielefeld. In 2006 he moved to Tübingen University, where
                  he was
                  involved in a project on “Sustainability of Linguistic Resources” and in projects
                  on the
                  interoperability of language data. Since 2009 he is senior researcher at Institut
                  für
                  Deutsche Sprache (Institute for the German Language) in Mannheim. Witt is and was
                  a member
                  of several research organizations, amongst them the TEI Special Interest Group on
                  overlapping markup, for which he was involved in the writing of the latest version
                  of the
                  chapter “Multiple Hierarchies”, which is included in TEI-Guidelines P5.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e35">
               <div class="orgname e36">Institut für Deutsche Sprache (IDS) Mannheim</div>
            </div>
            <div class="email e37">witt@ids-mannheim.de</div>
         </div>
         <div class="legalnotice e38">
            <div class="para e39">Copyright © 2012 by the authors. Used with permission.</div>
         </div>
      </div><a name="IntroductionANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e40">
         <div class="title e41">Introduction</div>
         <div class="para e42">This late breaking proposal is based on an ongoing effort started in the CLARIN project
            and which was presented briefly at the LREC 2012 Workshop on Collaborative Resource
            Development and Delivery. Initial point was the development of an easy to use information
            system for the description of standards developed in ISO/IEC TC37/SC4 
            <div class="emphasis e43">Language
               Resources Management
            </div>. Since these standards are heavily related to each other it
            is usually not feasible to adopt only a single standard for one's work but to dive
            into the
            standards jungle in full. Because of positive feedback after the presentation of the
            prototype
            at the Istanbul Workshop we decided to broaden the information accessible by the system
            to
            markup language related standards.
         </div>
      </div><a name="TheproblemwithstandardsANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e44">
         <div class="title e45">The problem with standards</div>
         <div class="para e46">Every year at Balisage's markup game or quiz difficult questions regarding markup
            have to
            be answered. Even the participants of this very special conference have sometimes
            problems to
            find the correct answer. An some of the younger generation have never heard terms
            like
            'sosofo' or 'DSSSL' before. At current, an unmanageable number of standards is available
            for
            annotating data of various kinds. These standards can be divided into several groups,
            according to such different features such as standard body (W3C, ISO, OASIS, HL7,
            to name just
            a few), basic or derivative work (i. e., standards that are built upon basic specifications),
            the state (de jure vs. de facto standard), or the topic. 
            <div class="xref e47" linkend="fig1"></div> gives a very
            rough overview about some of the named aspects. Other divisions would deal with a
            temporal
            aspect of standardization: specifications change over the time of development, some
            (almost)
            historical standards have been abandoned and have been replaced by other
            specifications.
         </div>
         <div class="figure e48" xml:id="fig1">
            <div class="title e49">A rough overview about the complexity in the fields of standardization.</div>
            <div class="mediaobject e50">
               <div class="imageobject e51">
                  <div class="metaBox e52"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e83').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e83" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e52'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol8/graphics/Stuhrenberg01/Stuhrenberg01-001.png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='png'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e53">Missing in the aforementioned list is another interesting aspect: the relationships
            between different standards. For example, meta languages such as SGML or XML are used
            to
            define (that is, syntax and possibly a schema formalism) markup languages. A given
            markup
            language is defined by a schema which in turn is defined by using a schema language
            (either a
            grammar-based or rule-based constraint language), and so on. Apart from these relations
            between basic standards and those that are built upon these, are other relations between
            members of the first group and of the second group. Some of the formal restrictions
            of XML
            instances and XML DTDs (and even XSD) are based on faits accomplis created during
            the
            development of SGML, DSSSL and HyTime &amp;#8211; standards that are decades old. Features
            that were already present in DSSSL, have been improved and adapted for current W3C
            standards
            such as XPath, XSLT and XSL-FO. XPath is usually used via a host language such as
            XSLT. The
            Corpus Encoding Standard (CES) is an application of the SGML-based version of the
            TEI, P3. The
            are dozens of similar relations, some are only good for get bonus points at Balisage
            Bingo but
            others really help in understanding specific issues one may have when working with
            a given
            specification. At least the knowledge about these older standards and the decisions
            that were
            made during their design process and which still impact current technologies such
            as XML
            schema or XSLT runs the risk of being forgotten just because of the amount of time
            already
            passed.
         </div>
         <div class="para e54">This holds especially when dealing with non-basic standards, for example with markup
            languages for annotating linguistic data. During the last couple of years a large
            number of
            specifications have been developed in ISO/IEC TC 37/SC 4 Language Resources Management.
            These
            standards are often released to the public during their various stages of the standardization
            process (either as publicly available specialisations, such as Draft International
            Standard or
            as topic of a research paper). However, these version may substantially differ from
            the final
            version of the standard which is usually not available without charge. In addition,
            the
            relations between these specifications are numerous which complicates their correct
            use.
         </div>
         <div class="para e55">Another problem is the fact, that often scholars and researchers are not even aware
            that
            standardized formats and models exist.
         </div>
      </div><a name="ProvidingguidanceANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e56">
         <div class="title e57">Providing guidance</div>
         <div class="para e58">We propose a community project to build up a platform providing guidance through the
            jungle that has been grown around the XML world. Starting with a very small set of
            standards
            and specifications and constructed as an XRX (XForms, Rest, XQuery) application we
            offer the
            starting point for a platform that allows Balisage's experts to share their knowledge
            with
            others. During the last months we have developed a prototypical web-based information
            system
            that serves as a starting point in providing guidance through the standards jungle
            as part of
            the 
            <div class="emphasis e59">CLARIN</div> distributed project group.
            <div class="popupBox e60">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e98').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e98').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e98" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e61">The system was presented in May 2012 at the LREC 2012 Workshop on Collaborative
                        Resource Development and Delivery and is described in more detail in 
                        <div class="xref e62" linkend="Stuehrenberg2012"></div>.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div> Up to now, it contains a collection of topics such as 
            <div class="emphasis e63">Meta
               Language
            </div>, 
            <div class="emphasis e64">Metadata</div>, 
            <div class="emphasis e65">Generic Corpus
               Annotation
            </div>, or 
            <div class="emphasis e66">Constraint Language</div>, amongst others, standard
            bodies such as 
            <div class="emphasis e67">ISO</div>, 
            <div class="emphasis e68">W3C</div>, 
            <div class="emphasis e69">OASIS</div>,
            and 
            <div class="emphasis e70">HL7</div>, and 25 specifications at the time of writing. 
            <div class="xref e71" linkend="fig2"></div> shows a partial screenshot of the current state. Relations between
            specifications (in this case between TEI P3 and SGML and P3 and CES) are described
            both in a
            textual and graphical way.
         </div>
         <div class="figure e72" xml:id="fig2">
            <div class="title e73">A screenshot of the current state of the information system (showing TEI's
               entry).
            </div>
            <div class="mediaobject e74">
               <div class="imageobject e75">
                  <div class="metaBox e76"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e136').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e136" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e76'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol8/graphics/Stuhrenberg01/Stuhrenberg01-002.png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='png'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div><a name="InformationstructureANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e77">
            <div class="title e78">Information structure</div>
            <div class="para e79">The information system itself is based on standards as well. We have developed a
               lightweight format for structuring information about specifications, topics, and standard
               setting bodies defined by an XSD. Although it seems to be at least questionable to
               invent
               yet another annotation format especially for this kind of project we tried to stick
               as close
               to existing annotation formats such as the TEI as possible while streamlining the
               format and
               therefore keeping it small and simple. 
               <div class="xref e80" linkend="lst.format"></div> shows an excerpt of the
               storage format.
            </div>
            <div class="figure e81" xml:id="lst.format">
               <div class="title e82">An excerpt of the storage format</div>
               <div class="programlisting e83" xml:space="preserve">
                  &lt;spec xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:id="SpecXML"
                  standardSettingBody="W3C" topicRef="TopicMetaLanguage"
                  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://localhost:8080/exist/apps/clarin/xsd/spec.xsd"&gt;
                  &lt;titleStmt&gt;
                  &lt;title&gt;Extensible Markup Language (XML)&lt;/title&gt;
                  &lt;abbr&gt;XML&lt;/abbr&gt;
                  &lt;/titleStmt&gt;
                  &lt;scope&gt;Meta language for Creating Markup Languages&lt;/scope&gt;
                  &lt;description&gt;
                  &lt;p&gt;The Extensible Markup Language (XML) is a meta language specified by a W3C recommendation,
                  containing both a syntax for describing and serializing data objects called XML documents
                  (or
                  XML instances) and a formalism for describing document grammars (DTD)
                  &lt;!-- [...] --&gt;    
                  &lt;/p&gt;
                  &lt;/description&gt;
                  &lt;version xml:id="SpecXML1"&gt;
                  &lt;versionNumber type="major"&gt;1.0&lt;/versionNumber&gt;
                  &lt;date&gt;1998-02-10&lt;/date&gt;
                  &lt;respStmt&gt;
                  &lt;resp&gt;Editor&lt;/resp&gt;
                  &lt;name type="person"&gt;Tim Bray&lt;/name&gt;
                  &lt;name type="person"&gt;Jean Paoli&lt;/name&gt;
                  &lt;name type="person"&gt;C. M. Sperberg-McQueen&lt;/name&gt;
                  &lt;/respStmt&gt;
                  &lt;address type="URL"&gt;http://www.w3.org/TR/1998/REC-xml-19980210&lt;/address&gt;
                  &lt;relation target="SpecSGML" type="isSubclassOf"&gt;
                  &lt;p&gt;XML 1.0 is a subset of SGML.&lt;/p&gt;
                  &lt;/relation&gt;
                  &lt;/version&gt;
                  &lt;version xml:id="SpecXML1-SE"&gt;
                  &lt;versionNumber type="major"&gt;1.0&lt;/versionNumber&gt;
                  &lt;versionNumber type="minor"&gt;Second Edition&lt;/versionNumber&gt;
                  &lt;date&gt;2000-10-06&lt;/date&gt;
                  &lt;!-- [...] --&gt;
                  &lt;/version&gt;
                  &lt;version xml:id="SpecXML1.1"&gt;
                  &lt;versionNumber type="major"&gt;1.1&lt;/versionNumber&gt;
                  &lt;date&gt;2004-02-04&lt;/date&gt;
                  &lt;description&gt;
                  &lt;p&gt;XML 1.1 differs from XML 1.0 in terms of naming conventions for elements and attributes
                  
                  (generic identifier) with respect to current and future version of Unicode. Whereas
                  XML 
                  1.0 provided a rigid definition of names, wherein everything that was not permitted
                  was 
                  forbidden, XML 1.1 names are designed so that everything that is not forbidden (for
                  a 
                  specific reason) is permitted. &lt;/p&gt;
                  &lt;/description&gt;
                  &lt;respStmt&gt;
                  &lt;resp&gt;Editor&lt;/resp&gt;
                  &lt;name type="person"&gt;Tim Bray&lt;/name&gt;
                  &lt;name type="person"&gt;Jean Paoli&lt;/name&gt;
                  &lt;name type="person"&gt;C. M. Sperberg-McQueen&lt;/name&gt;
                  &lt;name type="person"&gt;Eve Maler&lt;/name&gt;
                  &lt;name type="person"&gt;François Yergeau&lt;/name&gt;
                  &lt;name type="person"&gt;John Cowan&lt;/name&gt;
                  &lt;/respStmt&gt;
                  &lt;address type="URL"&gt;http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xml11-20040204/&lt;/address&gt;
                  &lt;relation target="SpecXML1" type="isVersionOf"&gt;
                  &lt;p&gt;XML 1.1 is a refined version of XML 1.0.&lt;/p&gt;
                  &lt;/relation&gt;
                  &lt;/version&gt;
                  &lt;version xml:id="SpecXML1.1-SE"&gt;
                  &lt;!-- [...] --&gt;
                  &lt;/version&gt;
                  &lt;/spec&gt;
                  
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="para e84">The information is stored in a native XML database system (we have chosen the Open
               Source eXist database as starting point but try to do not use any application-dependant
               features). Queries on the data are performed via XQuery scripts and forms will be
               implemented by XForms (which in turn will be processed by XSLTForms supported by eXist).
               The
               goal of the information system is not to replicate information that is already available
               (but may not be traceable anymore), but to connect pieces of information and enrich
               these
               pieces with small amounts of additional data. In the example above (
               <div class="xref e85" linkend="lst.format"></div>) we only refer to the information available at the W3C (and
               respective places). Information about standard bodies and topics is stored in a similar
               way.
            </div>
         </div><a name="RepresentationANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e86">
            <div class="title e87">Representation</div>
            <div class="para e88">The output of the information system is based on HTML5's XML syntax. Although the
               textual representation is feasible for providing detailed information about a given
               standard, our plan is to establish an additional graphical representation format.
               This
               second representation should provide a better overview of the relations between a
               large
               number of standards at once. Minor demonstrations have been done with D3 
               <div class="xref e89" linkend="Bostock2011"></div>, an Open Source JavaScript library that directly manipulates
               objects in the DOM tree to interactively visualize data
               <div class="popupBox e90">
                  <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e160').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e160').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
                  <div id="d1e160" style="display: none;">
                     <div class="footnote">
                        <div class="para e91">Additional information and downloads are available at 
                           <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e92" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://d3js.org/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://d3js.org/</div>.
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>. However, since JavaScript and XQuery share some syntax elements (e.g. the curly
               brackets) there are some minor traps to avoid. In the current prototype we therefore
               only
               use the non-interactive SVG graphics that are included in the standard's description
               page
               (see 
               <div class="xref e93" linkend="fig2"></div>). Since browser support for interactive 2- and 3-dimensional
               graphics is getting stronger and stronger, other options such as WebGL-based representations
               are possible as well (see 
               <div class="xref e94" linkend="Jettka2011"></div> for example).
            </div>
         </div><a name="CurrentstateandfutureworkANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e95">
            <div class="title e96">Current state and future work</div>
            <div class="para e97">The current state of the information system is still quite rough. What we want to
               propose is allow Balisage's participants to get involved in the process of collecting
               and
               sharing information about the standards they work with and have knowledge of. In addition,
               Balisage is the place to find experts in SVG (which is used to display relations between
               two
               or more specialisations), XQuery and XForms. If we manage to bring these people together
               to
               establish a community that is willing to share its knowledge the final product could
               be of
               much use to scholars and researchers around the world. As a first starting point we
               will
               publish the XML schema defining the annotation format to receive comments and add
               further
               enhancements. After a stable format has been established, interesting parties could
               create
               specification sheets and upload them into the platform. In addition, we will open
               the
               platform for reading access for other people to give feedback on a less technical
               way. The
               current prototype is made available at 
               <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e98" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://clarin.ids-mannheim.de/standards/index.xq" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://clarin.ids-mannheim.de/standards/index.xq</div>.
            </div>
         </div>
      </div><a name="ReferencesANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="bibliography e99">
         <div class="title e100">References</div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e101" xml:id="Bostock2011" xreflabel="Bostock et al., 2011">Michael Bostock, Vadim
            Ogievetsky, and Jeffrey Heer. D3: Data-driven documents. IEEE Trans. Visualization
            &amp; Comp.
            Graphics (Proc. InfoVis), 2011.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e102" xml:id="Jettka2011" xreflabel="Jettka and Stührenberg, 2011">Daniel Jettka, and
            Maik Stührenberg. Visualization of concurrent markup: From trees to graphs, from 2d
            to 3d. In
            Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference, volume 7 of Balisage Series on Markup
            Technologies, Montreal, 2011. doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e103">10.4242/BalisageVol7.Jettka01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e104" xml:id="Stuehrenberg2012" xreflabel="Stührenberg et al., 2012">Maik Stührenberg,
            Antonina Werthmann, and Andreas Witt. Guidance through the standards jungle for linguistic
            resources. In Nancy M. Ide, Collin Baker, Christiane Fellbaum, and Rebecca Passonneau,
            editors, Proceedings of the LREC 2012 Workshop on Collaborative Resource Development
            and
            Delivery, pages 9–13, 2012.
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>