<div id="mainContainerTOC">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTOC" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTOC').toggle('1000');">Table of Content</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTOC" style="display:none;">
      <div class="headedContainerTOC">
         <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ThingsstaythesameortherealmeaningoftechnicalworkANCHOR" name="ThingsstaythesameortherealmeaningoftechnicalworkTOC">Things stay the same, or, the real meaning of technical work</a></div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ReferencesANCHOR" name="ReferencesTOC">References</a></div>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerTERMS">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTERMS" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTERMS').toggle('1000')">Index of Terms</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTERMS" style="display:none;">
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">a</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">A bachelor is an unmarried man,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">a spinster is an unmarried woman.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">ACS Publications — Ensuring XML Quality.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">A standards-related web-based information system.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">about</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">a priori</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">August 7 - 10, 2012</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">b</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">bachelor</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">c</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Call things what they are,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Computer Standards &amp; Interfaces</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">C. M.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">d</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Developing Low-Cost Functional Class 3 IETM.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Documents as Timed Abstract Objects.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">e</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">f</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Fleshing the XDM chimera.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">From a Logical Point of View</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">g</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">gesture</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">h</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">i</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">is</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">I need a summary. Now.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">is</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">j</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Joe is a bachelor</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Joe</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">k</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">l</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Leveraging XML Technology for Web Applications.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Luminescent: parsing LMNL by XSLT upconversion.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">m</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Moving sands: Adventures in XML e-book-land.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">MicroXML: Who, What, Where, When, Why.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">n</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">not P.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">not P,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">natural representation,</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">o</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">On XML Languages….</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">our</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">p</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">P.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">q</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Quality Control of PMC Content: A Case Study.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">r</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">s</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Serialisation, abstraction, and XML applications.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Sperberg-McQueen</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">t</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Things stay the same,</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">The machine changes state</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">The structure of content.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Type Introspection in XQuery.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">The MLCD Overlap Corpus (MOC): Project report.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Two dogmas of empiricism.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">this</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">that other</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">that</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">The Philosophical Review</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">u</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">us versus them.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">v</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">x</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">XML Entropy Study.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">XML instances to validate XML schemas.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">y</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">z</div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerIML"><a name="ThingsstaythesameortherealmeaningoftechnicalworkANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="article e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3">
      <div class="title e1">Things stay the same, or, the real meaning of technical work</div>
      <div class="info e2">
         <div class="confgroup e3">
            <div class="conftitle e4">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>
            <div class="confdates e5">August 7 - 10, 2012</div>
         </div>
         <div class="abstract e6">
            <div class="para e7">What does not change when things change.</div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e8">
            <div class="personname e9">
               <div class="firstname e10">C. M.</div>
               <div class="surname e11">Sperberg-McQueen</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e12">
               <div class="para e13">C. M. Sperberg-McQueen is the founder of Black Mesa Technologies LLC,
                  a consultancy specializing in the use of descriptive markup to help
                  memory institutions preserve cultural heritage information for the
                  long haul.  He has served as co-editor of the XML 1.0 specification,
                  the Guidelines of the Text Encoding Initiative, and the XML Schema
                  Definition Language (XSD) 1.1 specification.  He holds a doctorate in
                  comparative literature.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e14">
               <div class="orgname e15">Black Mesa Technologies LLC</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="legalnotice e16">
            <div class="para e17">Copyright © 2012 by the author</div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div class="para e18">Murray Maloney just called my attention to a
         recently case horoscope which covers the next couple 
         of hours.  It seems to be describing at least the title of my talk, 
         <div class="quote e19">Things stay the same,</div> but is perhaps
         describing the conference as a whole.  It says:
         
         <div class="popupBox e20">
            <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e33').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e33').hide('1000');">[ blockquote ]</div>
            <div id="d1e33" style="display: none;">
               <div class="blockquote">
                  <div class="para e21">Attempts to change things fail. Others resist your suggestions and stand in your way.</div>
                  <div class="para e22">Comforts are a bother.</div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         I wasn’t quite sure at first what to make of that last bit, but now I think it’s telling
         us there’s no conference lunch today.
      </div>
      <div class="para e23">As the horoscope suggests, as people — as human beings — we seem to have trouble with
         change.
      </div>
      <div class="para e24">At one level, we run into difficulties when the meanings of technical terms shift.
         That’s part of language history, but it leads to complications, as Tommie Usdin told
         us in her opening on Tuesday [
         <div class="xref e25" linkend="t915p"></div>].  It can lead to resentment if people re-use old terms with new meanings; it can
         lead to resentment if they coin new terms when we think they could have used old ones
         or the terms that we coined before they coined theirs.
      </div>
      <div class="para e26">That low-level problem is matched by similar problems at higher levels of abstraction
         or system complexity.  We’re all familiar with the problems of building systems to
         accommodate change and with the challenges that come with trying to accommodate the
         changes that actually happen even after you have built a system to accommodate change
         because you discover that you built it to accommodate 
         <div class="emphasis e27">this</div> kind of change [
         <div class="emphasis e28">gesture</div>], and if people would only make that kind of change instead of 
         <div class="emphasis e29">that other</div> kind of change [
         <div class="emphasis e30">gesture</div>], our system would be fine.  But people don’t always change in the way that we want
         them to.  Keeping track of things is complicated.  Keeping track of how things got
         the way they are is an important topic; without that, we have no memories. Ashley
         Clark’s paper on meta-stylesheets and the provenance of XSL transformations addresses
         a key problem for every process undertaken by any institution that hopes to have any
         form of institutional memory [
         <div class="xref e31" linkend="w1100l"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e32">The difficulty of change isn’t peculiar to technical
         areas.
      </div>
      <div class="para e33">The challenge of dealing with change has been with us for a long
         time. We have a long history of efforts to deal with change. 
         Centuries of stoic and neo-stoic philosophy teach us to discipline
         our emotions and not to allow ourselves to come to care for things
         that may change.
      </div>
      <div class="para e34">The neo-stoic approach somehow feels like an attempt to deal
         with the emotional side — the emotional difficulties —
         of change. One of the reasons we are uncomfortable with change is it
         reminds us that time is passing.  Not just time in general, but
         
         <div class="emphasis e35">our</div> time is passing; our mortality is nearing.
         Many of us have some difficulty, at least some of the time,
         contemplating our mortality with complete equanimity. But even in less
         emotional contexts, change and time are hard.  A lot of us here
         — a lot of people in IT generally — began in other
         fields and got into IT through specific application domains, so I
         can’t be the only person here who has trained in another field
         but occasionally reads computer science textbooks.  And so I doubt
         that I’m the only one who has been struck by the contortions
         that formal descriptions of Turing machines go through to explain the
         change of state in a Turing machine or even a finite state automaton.
         A completely informal introduction to Turing machines has no problem
         with this topic at all, 
         but any skilled mathematician trying to provide a more
         careful description will bend over backwards to
         avoid talking about time or change of any kind.  They will begin
         with an
         elaborate description, completely static, of the state of a Turing
         machine.  They will then develop an elaborate 
         rule for comparing
         two Turing machine states so as to determine 
         where they differ and where they resemble each
         other.  And finally they will describe the construction of
         sequences of Turing machine states, each adjacent pair
         of states related by a similarity relation based on
         the rule for comparison, to ensure that any two 
         adjacent states are similar in all but exactly one way.  
         They may spend pages and pages
         — or worse only half a page, in compressed
         and laconic form, with no explanation,
         motivation, or guidance — all in order
         to avoid saying 
         <div class="quote e36">The machine changes state</div>.
         Why?
         Because our formal systems just don’t deal well with 
         change.
         <div class="popupBox e37">
            <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e74').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e74').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
            <div id="d1e74" style="display: none;">
               <div class="footnote">
                  <div class="para e38">Or,
                     at least, some of our formal systems don't, 
                     logic and philosophy prominent among them.  
                     Oddly enough, mathematics
                     has no particular trouble with this, or at least hasn’t since
                     Newton showed how to do describe change mathematically; 
                     before Newton, it was apparently just as bad for
                     straight math as for logic today.
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         I submit to you that at least
         some of the difficulties Claus Huitfeldt reported on,
         some of the objections philosophers have raised against 
         viewing documents as timed
         abstract objects (or against timed abstract objects
         more generally) stem from to
         this weakness in our formal systems:  their inability to accept change
         [
         <div class="xref e39" linkend="h900p"></div>]. 
      </div>
      <div class="para e40">Unfortunately, the difference between change and stability is
         one we cannot get away with ignoring, because the difference between
         change and stability, and the relation between them, are in some sense
         at the heart of the idea of descriptive markup. Years ago, computer
         scientists at the University of Waterloo wrote a paper that was
         distributed in manuscript — distributed fairly widely but never
         published in this form — that said among other things the
         critique of SGML and the critique in particular of the ontological
         pretensions of SGML theorists. And in that draft, the author, Darrell
         Raymond said:
      </div>
      <div class="popupBox e41">
         <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e84').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e84').hide('1000');">[ blockquote ]</div>
         <div id="d1e84" style="display: none;">
            <div class="blockquote">
               <div class="para e42">Yes, descriptive markup rescues authors from the frying pan of typography only to
                  hurl them headlong into the hellfire of ontology.
               </div>
               <div class="attribution e43">[
                  <div class="xref e44" linkend="Raymond"></div>]
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div class="para e45">We might well ask how that happened. Why did ontology suddenly
         break out as an area of concern in the slightly unexpected province of
         technical publication? And I would like to suggest a possible answer
         to you.
         <div class="popupBox e46">
            <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e93').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e93').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
            <div id="d1e93" style="display: none;">
               <div class="footnote">
                  <div class="para e47">I should point out that the discussion of the
                     change and stability in technical publishing offered
                     here is a kind of Just-So story about the origins
                     of descriptive markup intended to illustrate the
                     relevance of change and stability to descriptive markup,
                     and vice versa.  It is not intended and should not be 
                     taken as a full historical account of all the issues
                     on the minds of those who developed the idea of
                     descriptive markup or the SGML specification.
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         Put yourself in the position of the tech publishing managers
         who were struggling to develop the concepts which we now know as
         descriptive markup and which became SGML — generic coding and
         then SGML and then XML. They are perfectly aware that when they print
         manuals this week or this month for this year’s release of the
         operating system, chapter titles will be in a particular font-face
         — they will be Garamond 16 point on 18 demi-bold with a 7 quad
         vertical jump and a horizontal rule and so forth. But they are also
         acutely aware that that’s not essential. That that’s not
         a permanent part of the document. They’re acutely aware because
         they are involved in the design decisions, and they know perfectly
         well that some people really hate Garamond, and it may change. And
         they are also acutely aware that changing that kind of thing manually
         is extremely expensive, so they want a way to encode the document that
         won’t require manual change every time the style changes
         because style is part of their professional identity. They know
         perfectly well that style changes. They know perfectly well that when
         the big new version of the operating system comes out eighteen months
         from now, they’re going to have a ground up redesign of the
         entire technical library. There will be a new look; they don’t
         what it’s going to be because the contact hasn’t been issued yet, but etc., etc.
      </div>
      <div class="para e48">So we want a way to represent a document that will work for the
         styles we’ve got now and for the styles we’re going to
         have in eighteen months with the new big release. How do we do that?
         Well, we need to find some aspect of the document to call out that can
         be related to the styling and that’s not going to change. The
         style is going to change, and the kind of processing we’re
         going to do with the document may change. (In the early 80’s
         not everybody had a well-developed expectation of being able to do
         full-text searching and build things other than printed pages from
         documents, but a lot of people knew it was possible even if they
         didn’t have software to do it themselves, and they had fond
         hopes.) The one thing that’s not going to change between now
         and eighteen months from now is the structure of the sentence:
         
         <div class="quote e49">we want it to be 16 on 18 Garamond demi-bold because
            it’s a chapter title.
         </div> Everything in that sentence is
         going to change except 
         <div class="quote e50">We want it to be [styled in a certain
            way] because it’s a chapter title.
         </div> Our ideas about what
         we think this part of the document 
         <div class="emphasis e51">is</div> are going
         to change more slowly, maybe not at all. But at least they’re
         going to change more slowly than what we do with this piece of the
         document. It is natural, then that any effort to produce reusable
         document representations is going to push us a little bit toward
         ontology, toward a statement of what the thing is and not what we want
         to do with it.
      </div>
      <div class="para e52">Now, it’s possible to over-emphasize the ontological
         pretensions of descriptive markup, and I’m sure that many of us
         who got enthusiastic about SGML in the 1980’s did so. But there
         are philosophers who tell us almost no statements are really permanent in the way
         I have just described.
         The American philosopher W.V.O. Quine spent much of his
         career attacking what is called the analytic/synthetic
         distinction.  That is the common philosophical doctrine that some
         sentences are true by virtue of the definition of the terms [
         <div class="xref e53" linkend="Quine1951"></div>]. For example, consider the sentences
         
         <div class="quote e54">A bachelor is an unmarried man,</div>
         or 
         <div class="quote e55">a spinster is an unmarried woman.</div> The
         standard analysis in terms of the analytic/synthetic
         distinction says that these sentences say nothing at all
         abut the real world, and so no empirical observation of
         the real world can possibly render them true or false.
         They are not 
         <div class="emphasis e56">about</div> the real world;
         they are about the definitions of terms in our language. 
         Sentences like these are true or false because 
         of the meanings of their words and not because of any
         state of affairs in the real world.
         By contrast, the sentence 
         <div class="quote e57">Joe is a bachelor</div> is an
         empirical or synthetic statement and is true or false 
         depending not just on the meanings of the words 
         
         <div class="quote e58">Joe</div> and 
         <div class="quote e59">is</div> and 
         <div class="quote e60">bachelor</div>
         but on whether in fact Joe is or is not married.
         Quine said, No, no, no, no. There’s no such bright line
         between analytic statements and synthetic statements; there is only a
         spectrum between sentences whose truth values we are ready to revise
         at a moment’s notice, and sentences whose truth values we are
         not so ready to revise.  Our beliefs about the
         world, Quine argued,
         do not face the tribunal of experience singly, but as a
         corporate body. This is 
         certainly true in every
         formalization of logic I’ve ever seen; if you have a
         contradiction in a set of statements, you don’t know which
         statement to remove in order to remove the contradiction, and quite
         often you have a choice. Just take the simple case: 
         <div class="quote e61">P</div>
         and 
         <div class="quote e62">not P.</div> Well, we can make that set consistent by
         dropping 
         <div class="quote e63">not P,</div> or we can make it consistent by
         dropping 
         <div class="quote e64">P.</div> There’s no 
         <div class="emphasis e65" role="ital">a
            priori
         </div> distinction.
      </div>
      <div class="para e66">Quine said what we call the truths of logic are just the
         sentences that we are going to throw to the wolves last. 
         If, one fine morning in the physics lab, the data 
         from our physical measurements don't
         match the expected values, we are prepared to accept 
         the proposition that we must have
         misread the dial on the instrument.
         We resolve to be more careful.
         If it happens again the next day and the next,
         however, then it becomes harder and harder to believe 
         that we have misread the dial so consistently, 
         and we begin to think the machine may be out of calibration.
         And if the evidence mounts up, we may be willing to consider the
         possibility that the machine is actually not measuring what we thought
         it was measuring, it’s broken completely, or it’s based
         on a wrong physical theory, and it never measured anything. Those are
         progressively harder and harder to accept because they involve the
         revision of more and more of our world view, but on
         Quine's account nothing is sacred, and no part of our
         belief system is immune to revision. 
         Perhaps that’s the level of ontological commitment that
         we can safely make for good descriptive markup: 
         It’s not sacred, but it's one of the
         parts of our worldview we are least likely to 
         change in the normal course of events.
         It’s 
         useful to say 
         <div class="quote e67">Call things what they are,</div> but
         it’s also easy to tie ourselves in knots over the philosophical
         questions of what things really are and what things do we believe
         really exist. You can build a lot of good practical systems by
         dialing that back a little bit and asking instead 
         
         <div class="quote e68">What do we think
            we’re going to think this is, over the course
            of the next five
            years?
         </div>
      </div>
      <div class="para e69">Steven Pemberton showed us the other day that such conceptual
         change is not unique to documents. The same problem arises in other
         areas. He told us, remember, about an abstraction error in early C
         and Unix — the conflation of the notion of character with the
         fundamental unit of storage [
         <div class="xref e70" linkend="t245p"></div>]. Why is that an
         abstraction error? It’s an abstraction error because our
         concept of character changes at a different rate from our
         implementation of character representation. Implementations, we
         know, are going to change a lot, and our concepts change much more
         slowly. It’s not that our concepts never change, but they change much
         more slowly. It’s an abstraction error to conflate things that
         have different rates of change; ultimately, they shear apart, giving
         us the technological or conceptual equivalent of
         Africa on the one side and South America on the other, 
         and like continents our concepts can
         drift pretty far apart as time goes by.
      </div>
      <div class="para e71">What won’t change in the short term are the things we
         care about. And what some of us care about may not be what other
         people care about. That’s one of the reasons we want
         user-definable vocabularies. Sometimes those of us who 
         drank the descriptive markup Kool-aid
         in the 1980’s may find it extremely counterintuitive
         to see that what some people care about is not the logical
         structure of the document but the design.
         Dianne Kennedy talked to us early in the conference
         about the PRISM Source Vocabulary [
         <div class="xref e72" linkend="t1145p"></div>],
         which demonstrates conclusively that a sufficiently 
         general idea like descriptive markup can be applied in
         ways that go well beyond what the original designers
         may have had in mind.
      </div>
      <div class="para e73">Some papers at this conference provide striking illustrations of
         just how far we’ve come as a community towards being able to
         build whole systems based on standards and descriptive
         markup, like Anne Brüggemann-Klein’s paper yesterday about
         leveraging XML technology for web applications [
         <div class="xref e74" linkend="h445r"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e75">Even after we relativize the idea in the way 
         I’m suggesting, any emphasis on saying what things
         are and on data longevity will lead directly to a 
         consequent emphasis on getting things
         right in the first place. We have to get this right because these
         documents are going to be around for a long time.
         We’re constructing documents and document
         systems for longevity, and if we succeed we are going to
         have to live with what we say for a long time. Quality assurance
         takes on even more importance in this context than it might
         otherwise do. This year's program has had a remarkable 
         emphasis on quality
         assurance — not just in the pre-conference
         symposium on Monday about quality assurance,
         but also throughout the conference proper. 
         On Monday morning, Dale Waldt gave a general overview 
         of the issues, stressing among other things
         that you don’t do quality assurance last if you want to have
         good quality assurance; you need to push it up-stream as far as
         possible [
         <div class="xref e76" linkend="m910"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e77">Wei Zhao and Jeff Beck and their colleagues provided wonderful
         descriptions of QA practices in large aggregators like the Ontario
         Scholars Portal or PubMed Central. Such aggregators are constrained to
         accept input from a wide variety of sources with wide variations in
         quality, but they try to produce unified interfaces. So the
         aggregators need to try to level the quality by bringing up the lower
         bound [
         <div class="xref e78" linkend="m1100"></div>, 
         <div class="xref e79" linkend="m1140"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e80">Keith Rose and Tamara Stoker provided an
         inspiring view of what can be done inside a publishing organization when it sets its
         mind to improve the quality of its data [
         <div class="xref e81" linkend="m1220"></div>].  They were talking about the American Chemical Society, but a lot of what they
         said could be applied anywhere.
      </div>
      <div class="para e82">Also on Monday, Charlie Halpern-Hamu gave us a wonderful synoptic overview of a whole
         sampler of techniques for quality assurance in document projects. 
         <div class="xref e83" linkend="m245"></div>].  At least one person was overheard leaving the room saying, 
         <div class="quote e84">Well, 
            <div class="emphasis e85" role="ital">that</div> changes my schedule for next week; that project is going to be redesigned because
            those techniques will work better for us thatn what we are doing now.
         </div>
      </div>
      <div class="para e86">If you want to take quality seriously, you need quality
         assurance not just on your data but on other parts of your system.
         Eric van der Vlist spoke to us Monday morning about applying quality
         assurance not to documents, but using documents to apply quality
         assurance to the schemas that we use to validate the documents [
         <div class="xref e87" linkend="m950"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e88">Sheila Morrissey and her colleagues at Portico showed how they extend their focus
         from the data that they are preserving to the systems they are using to preserve the
         data [
         <div class="xref e89" linkend="m200"></div>], and Jorge Williams, in the conference itself, pointed our tools in yet another
         direction, to validate not deployment packages, but whole RESTful services [
         <div class="xref e90" linkend="w900r"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e91">historically, one of the most important tools in quality
         assurance for descriptive markup has been the document grammar and
         validation against a schema. The great promise of syntactic validation
         both in SGML DTDs and before it in things like the invention of BNF in
         the definition of Algol 60 is that it enables the automatic detection
         of certain classes of errors. It’s easy to forget that careful
         people never promised that automatic detection based on clean syntax
         definitions would detect all errors. The value proposition has always
         been: when a large class of errors can be detected automatically, it
         becomes possible to concentrate expensive, human eyeball resources on
         the class of errors that cannot be detected automatically. It’s
         easy to think 
         <div class="quote e92">Oh, gosh, if validation doesn’t catch all
            errors, so you still have to have eyeballs, then surely automatic
            validation is pointless.
         </div> I think if experience shows that
         it’s better to find things automatically if possible, because
         it’s cheaper, but that no organization that cares about data
         quality can plan to do without human eyeballs entirely. And, of
         course, if you don’t actually plan to have any humans looking
         at your data, ever, why are you working with it in the first
         place?
      </div>
      <div class="para e93">When thinking about automatic validation, it’s always
         tempting to go for more power, but like all error detection,
         validation involves a trade-off between power or completeness of
         checking and cost. More power in a validation language is not always
         an improvement, because the more powerful the validation language is,
         the harder it is going to be to reason about the class of documents
         accepted as valid. Turing completeness is not necessarily a
         recommendation in a validation language, but it’s always
         interesting to see just how far you can go in validation while keeping
         things tractable. Jakub Malý’s
         talk about applying OCL constraints to documents by means of
         translation into Schematron shows an interesting
         approach in this area [
         <div class="xref e94" linkend="h1100p"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e95">Sometimes the challenge is the complexity of the validity
         function that you’re calculating, and sometimes the complexity
         lies in figuring out just what the validation function is and where we
         are expected to be drawing the line between okay input and not okay
         input. And sometimes the challenge is figuring out which of those is
         the problem that we face: is it hard because we have a complex
         validation function or because we can’t figure out what the
         validation function is, and how do we tell when we have solved that
         problem?  Those not working in healthcare informatice might
         not be able to relate to or follow all the details in 
         what Kate Hamilton and Lauren Wood were telling us the other day
         [
         <div class="xref e96" linkend="h1145p"></div>], but almost everyone can look at the 
         complexity of the situation they described and suddenly feel
         better about the degree of complexity in the problems we 
         face in our own work.
      </div>
      <div class="para e97">As soon as we decide we want to check things not just for
         structural correctness but for veracity or at least verisimilitude, we
         find ourselves skating onto the sometimes thin ice of semantics and
         ontologies. As Kurt Cagle described in his paper, we will need
         mechanisms for managing controlled vocabularies and developing
         semantics [
         <div class="xref e98" linkend="w945r"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e99">Predefinition of ontologies is not the only way to achieve
         better semantic control of our data. Sometimes we can work bottom up;
         Steve DeRose’s talk on text analytics on Monday suggested a lot
         of opportunities for plausibility checking using probabilistic, or
         stochastic and non-symbolic methods. 
         <div class="xref e100" linkend="m345"></div>].
         I’m always nervous about purely stochastic methods because
         I’m never sure I understand what it is they’re telling
         me, and I’m always afraid I’m going to make a fool of
         myself by assuming that they’ve passed the Turing test when
         actually I’m just talking to a modern version of Eliza. But
         text analytics may help us with plausibility checking.
      </div>
      <div class="para e101">If you’re in the realm of stochastic methods, then
         you’re in the realm of sampling and exploratory data analysis
         and the techniques that Micah Dubinko talked about, using XQuery to
         get an overview of unfamiliar data [
         <div class="xref e102" linkend="h245p"></div>]. Someone
         hands you a USB stick and says, 
         <div class="quote e103">I need a summary. Now.</div>
         Quick! What do you do? Well, hopefully you’ve internalized the
         techniques Micah Dubink described, because they will help you in that
         situation.
      </div>
      <div class="para e104">Charlie Halpern-Hamu gave a very illuminating talk on a way of
         constructing a  sample to get essentially
         similar kinds of results but in the form of a particular test document
         that you can use so that you have
         a small sample to develop against, but it’s a good sample to
         develop against because it exercises as much of your code as can
         conveniently be managed, a lot more of your code than you are
         otherwise going to get in a single sample [
         <div class="xref e105" linkend="w945l"></div>].
         
      </div>
      <div class="para e106">The topic of testing reminds us of the ongoing, never-ending
         discussion between those who wish to prove software correctness by
         testing (which cannot be done because tests can never prove the
         absence of bugs; they can only prove the presence of bugs) and those
         who would like to prove things correct by reasoning. You know,
         I’m always more comfortable with code if it can be proven
         correct, but I’m also uncomfortably aware that the literature
         is littered with articles about people who took code that had been
         proven correct and translated it to running code and ran test cases
         against it. And particularly, the usual way to bring a program like
         that to its knees is to hand it input that doesn’t obey the
         contract you made. Yes, of course, Dijkstra’s algorithm for
         calculating the greatest common denominator of two integers is going
         to fail if you hand it two inputs that are not integers or not
         integers within the acceptable range. But, you know, that’s what our users do: they
         give us stuff that’s out of range. That’s one of the
         reasons why I got interested in validation to begin with.
      </div>
      <div class="para e107">Sometimes, as Michel Biezunski explained to us yesterday, having valid input and valid
         output is not enough because there is plenty of valid data that the software doesn’t
         actually support.  And if you want to publish e-books, take a deep breath and be prepared
         for the fact that you’re going to have to test e-book readers one by one [
         <div class="xref e108" linkend="h400l"></div>].  That’s a rude awakening for some of us, but it confronts us with the real world.
      </div>
      <div class="para e109">Sometimes the confrontation with the real world is not quite as depressing as it was
         during parts of Michel’s talk.  I was very heartened by Liam Quin’s discovery that
         the percentage of ill-formed XML is not nearly as high as some people have suggested
         [
         <div class="xref e110" linkend="f1145p"></div>].  That made me feel better, but it’s still a reality check.  13%?  Gee, I would
         have hoped for better than that, even in RSS.
      </div>
      <div class="para e111">And Betty Harvey’s talk — talk about rubber
         meeting the road! I hope that the specs we’re involved in
         writing now are as functional and implementable twenty and twenty-five
         years and thirty years from now as the specs that she showed us
         implementing today [
         <div class="xref e112" linkend="f1100p"></div>]. Yes, they look kinda
         dated and quaint, but, by golly, they do still work. By golly, maybe
         all the work done in the 1980s for future-proofing data did
         effectively future-proof some data. That’s a really heartening
         thought; I’m very grateful to Betty Harvey for bringing us that
         message.
      </div>
      <div class="para e113">Whenever you have longevity — and we should think about
         this if we’re aiming at longevity — you have
         maintenance issues. I’ve never done research myself, but I have
         been told many times and its seems plausible — it seems
         consistent with everything I’ve ever seen in real life
         organizations — that the main cost of maintenance is not fixing
         errors, even though fixing errors after a program is deployed is very
         expensive. The main cost of maintenance is adjusting the program to
         run in new environments.
      </div>
      <div class="para e114">Now, if my thumbnail sketch of history holds any water, one of
         the points of SGML and XML was to help information longevity by
         recording the properties of the information that don’t change
         or don’t change as fast as our processing needs. So, we might
         expect that SGML and XML themselves by focusing attention on what
         doesn’t change may themselves have a long life. But what we
         really care about is not, in the last analysis, a long life for our
         technology, but a long life for our information, and that may involve
         changing the technology as we go along. Several people have mentioned
         in other contexts the example of our grandfather’s ax or
         Theseus’ ship; is it still the same ship after we have replaced
         each plank? Is it the same ax if it's had three new handles and seven
         new heads? In a passage popular among philosophers, W.V.O. Quine
         describes with approval a suggestion of the philosopher Otto Neurath.
         Quine says:
      </div>
      <div class="popupBox e115">
         <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e264').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e264').hide('1000');">[ blockquote ]</div>
         <div id="d1e264" style="display: none;">
            <div class="blockquote">
               <div class="para e116">Neurath has likened science to a boat which, if we are to rebuild it, we must rebuild
                  plank by plank while staying afloat in it.
               </div>
               <div class="attribution e117">[
                  <div class="xref e118" linkend="Quine1960"></div>]
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div class="para e119">I haven’t thought of a better analogy for the situation
         of our technology adopters, or a better explanation for their aversion
         to change and risk. Many people have observed that users of technology
         (as opposed to technologists and evangelists, like many of us in this
         room) are famously relunctant to adopt new technology even if it is
         clearly better. Why? Partly because change is painful, and partly
         because change involves risk. They’re at sea in a boat, and
         we’re suggesting that they take out a plank and replace it with
         a better plank. That’s going to be risky. But those of us who
         are afloat in SGML or XML are in that situation; if we want the ship
         to stay afloat, we are going to have to replace some planks, or at
         least that’s a possibility we are going to have to face.
      </div>
      <div class="para e120">One way for technology to grow, of course, in one dimension is to become smaller in
         another dimension.  So, we must occasionally ask ourselves which dimensions we care
         about and which aspects of our technology we want to preserve, and which we’re willing
         to jettison.  The logic of John Cowan’s MicroXML is that by making the syntax and
         the spec of XML smaller, we can appeal to a larger audience; that’s a trade-off we
         have to consider [
         <div class="xref e121" linkend="f900p"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e122">The more traditional way to grow a technology is to add
         functionality, and there the challenge is to add functionality in a
         way that feels like an organic development, feels like growth, and
         doesn’t feel to the technology adopters like a risky change.
         The organic development of XQuery in Mary
         Holstege’s talk on type introspection [
         <div class="xref e123" linkend="t945p"></div>] exemplifies the kind of new functionality
         that will feel intuitively right to most users of the technology. 
         I was similarly heartened to hear Abel Braaksma’s
         discussion of higher-order functions and other functional technologies
         in XSLT 3.0 [
         <div class="xref e124" linkend="f945p"></div>]. Hervé Ruellan’s
         discussion of XML entropy seems to suggest ways to develop and
         evaluate compression mechanisms for marked-up documents [
         <div class="xref e125" linkend="h400r"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e126">Sometimes the way to find new ways to do things in language is
         not just to add new things, but to push what you’ve got a
         little harder than some of us would otherwise have pushed it.
         That’s the lesson I took from Wendell Piez’s talk on
         using XSLT to parse not XML, but LMNL data [
         <div class="xref e127" linkend="w1145r"></div>].
         If you are pushing your infrstructure hard enough, the accumulators of
         XSLT 3.0 will make some things more convenient, but you don’t
         always have to wait for the language developers; sometimes you can
         just do it yourself.
      </div>
      <div class="para e128">The most challenging growth path we are facing is the potential of modifying the XDM.
         And I think when we look back on this year’s Balisage, many of us will remember the
         sequence of talks by Eric van der Vlist, Jonathan Robie, and Hans-Jürgen Rennau on
         different ways of adapting XDM and, with it, the specs that rely on XDM to the advent
         of JSON [
         <div class="xref e129" linkend="t200p"></div>, 
         <div class="xref e130" linkend="t400p"></div>, 
         <div class="xref e131" linkend="t445p"></div>].  One reason to do that is to say, 
         <div class="quote e132">Well, we’re in the situation of anybody doing maintenance.  The context has changed.
            There are people out there who want to use JSON; we need to be able to interoperate
            with them.
         </div>
      </div>
      <div class="para e133">But it’s not always a question of 
         <div class="quote e134">us versus them.</div>  Sometimes within the same institution, there will be those who want to work with
         XML or C++ or C-sharp, and others who want to work with different notations.  So,
         Ari Nordström’s example of finding ways to do things in the notation of your choice
         as a way of helping keep the peace within an organization is a message we can all
         take to heart. 
         <div class="xref e135" linkend="t1100p"></div>].  Remember:  good fences make good neighbors.
      </div>
      <div class="para e136">The problem is not always even other people in the same
         institution. Sometimes it’s we ourselves. We ourselves will
         want sometimes to use one notation and sometimes to use another. There
         are a million opportunities and a million choices to make; we will
         need guidance in the wilderness of standards. Even if we restrict
         ourselves to standards and recommendations, we’ll need guidance
         of the kind that Maik Stührenberg and Oliver Schonefeld talked
         about the other day with their web-based information system about
         standards [
         <div class="xref e137" linkend="h945p"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e138">Sometimes the right form for some of our information will use the RDF model.  And
         we will have hybrid systems like the one described by Anna Jordanous, Alan Stanley,
         and Charlotte Tupman for their ancient documents [
         <div class="xref e139" linkend="w900l"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e140">Sometimes the structure of information we want to manage fits neatly into a tree,
         and those of us with long memories are still so impressed with how much more powerful
         and interesting trees are than the one-damn-thing-after-another model of documents
         that preceded SGML that we are astonished that not everybody is happy with trees,
         and we think that everybody really ought to be content with trees.  But, thank God,
         some of us are professional malcontents.  So we should be grateful to those who continue
         pushing on the issue of overlap and finding the right way to represent our information,
         even when it has overlapping structures [
         <div class="xref e141" linkend="w1100r"></div>].
      </div>
      <div class="para e142">Some of the most challenging areas for us when we are looking for the right way to
         represent our information are those that involve information of multiple kinds for
         different audiences.  Making information for different audiences co-exist is very
         difficult, often because the natural representation varies even if we’re fully aware
         that when we say 
         <div class="quote e143">natural representation,</div> we mean the one we’re most familiar with for that kind of information.
      </div>
      <div class="para e144">That makes literate programming one of the most challenging areas that we face, but
         it is also one of the most important because, going back to that QA symposium on Monday,
         if we really want to preserve our information, it’s not just the documents we have
         to be able to understand and preserve, but the systems that they are built to interact
         with.  And so literate programming as a method of making our programs easier to understand
         and keeping the documentation in sync with the executable code is crucial.  So what
         Sam Wilmott said, yes [
         <div class="xref e145" linkend="w1145l"></div>].  What David Lee and Norm Walsh said, yes [
         <div class="xref e146" linkend="w200p"></div>, 
         <div class="xref e147" linkend="w245p"></div>].  What Matthew McCormick said, absolutely [
         <div class="xref e148" linkend="w400p"></div>].  And Mario Blažević’s efforts to bring back SHORTREF and make it work in an environment
         very different from the SGML environment for which it was originally developed [
         <div class="xref e149" linkend="w445p"></div>]?  If that makes it easier to have natural notations for information, then it will
         help information longevity.
      </div>
      <div class="para e150">Syntax is important.  I’m always a little nervous when people say 
         <div class="quote e151">Syntax isn’t important; it’s only semantics that’s important</div> because I’m acutely aware that if we don’t have agreement on syntax, it’s extremely
         unlikely that we will understand the semantics that the other person is trying to
         tell us about.  So, I think syntax is important.  But it’s not important for itself;
         it’s important because it enables the recording and the exchange of semantic information.
      </div>
      <div class="para e152">In the same way, technology is important, but it’s not important for itself; it’s
         important because it can help us (or, in some cases, hinder us) in the pursuit of
         our goals.  For the technologies that we in this room care about, that often means
         it’s important because it helps us manage our information:  the information that courses
         through the veins of our institutions and societies, the information that our organizations
         care about or that we care about as individuals.  The right technology can help us
         ensure that what changes as time goes by is our technology and not the information
         we manage with the help of that technology.
      </div>
      <div class="para e153">Conferences like this one are important, but they’re not important only in and for
         themselves, and not only for the talks that constitute the official conference program.
         They’re important because they bring us together as people, and they give us the chance
         to engage with each other, both in the official program and in the hallways and afterwards.
         When things work right, conferences help us find solutions to our technical problems.
      </div>
      <div class="para e154">When everything goes well, conferences — or rather, the people we engage with when
         we attend conferences — can help us remember why we care about those technical problems:
         what we care about and why we care about it.  They can help us achieve clarity in
         thinking about how to use our technical skills to serve particular ends, to serve
         the advancement or preservation of a particular technology, or the creation and management
         and preservation of the information that our institutions or our societies or our
         cultures care about, to serve the humanity that has created those institutions, those
         societies, that culture.
      </div>
      <div class="para e155">Every year I learn a lot by listening to the talks at Balisage, and every year I learn
         a lot — or sometimes even more — by engaging with the people who attend and make Balisage
         what it is.  Thank you for being those people.  Thank you for coming to Balisage 2012.
      </div><a name="ReferencesANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="bibliography e156">
         <div class="title e157">References</div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e158" xml:id="h400l" xreflabel="Biezunski">Biezunski, Michel. 
            <div class="quote e159">Moving sands: Adventures in XML e-book-land.</div>  Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e160" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e161">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Biezunski01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e162" xml:id="w445p" xreflabel="Blažević">Blažević, Mario. 
            <div class="quote e163">Extending XML with SHORTREFs specified in RELAX NG.</div>  Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e164" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e165">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Blazevic01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e166" xml:id="f945p" xreflabel="Braaksma">Braaksma, Abel. 
            <div class="quote e167">Simplifying XSLT stylesheet development using higher order functions.</div>  Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e168" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e169">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Braaksma01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e170" xml:id="h445r" xreflabel="Brüggemann-Klein, Hahn and Sayih">Brüggemann-Klein, Anne, Jose Tomas Robles Hahn and Marouane Sayih. 
            <div class="quote e171">Leveraging XML Technology for Web Applications.</div>  Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e172" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e173">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Bruggemann-Klein01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e174" xml:id="w945r" xreflabel="Cagle">Cagle, Kurt. 
            <div class="quote e175">The Ontologist: Controlled Vocabularies and Semantic Wikis.</div>  Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e176" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e177">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Cagle01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e178" xml:id="w1100l" xreflabel="Clark">Clark, Ashley. 
            <div class="quote e179">Meta-stylesheets: Exploring the Provenance of XSL Transformations.</div>  Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e180" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e181">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Clark01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e182" xml:id="f900p" xreflabel="Cowan">Cowan, John. 
            <div class="quote e183">MicroXML: Who, What, Where, When, Why.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e184" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e185">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Cowan01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e186" xml:id="m345" xreflabel="DeRose">DeRose, Steven J. 
            <div class="quote e187">The structure of content.</div>   Presented at International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control in
            XML, Montréal, Canada, August 6, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e188" role="ital">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control
               in XML
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 9 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e189">10.4242/BalisageVol9.DeRose01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e190" xml:id="h245p" xreflabel="Dubinko">Dubinko, Micah. 
            <div class="quote e191">Exploring the Unknown: Understanding and navigating large XML datasets.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e192" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e193">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Dubinko01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e194" xml:id="w400p" xreflabel="Flood, McCormick and Palmer">Flood, Mark D., Matthew McCormick and Nathan Palmer. 
            <div class="quote e195">Encoding Transparency: Literate Programming and Test Generation for Scientific Function
               Libraries.
            </div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e196" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e197">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Flood01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e198" xml:id="m245" xreflabel="Halpern-Hamu">Halpern-Hamu, Charlie. 
            <div class="quote e199">Case study: Quality assurance and quality control techniques in an XML data conversion
               project.
            </div>   Presented at International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control in
            XML, Montréal, Canada, August 6, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e200" role="ital">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control
               in XML
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 9 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e201">10.4242/BalisageVol9.Halpern-Hamu01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e202" xml:id="w945l" xreflabel="Halpern-Hamu">Halpern-Hamu, Charlie. 
            <div class="quote e203">Design considerations in the implementation of a boil-this-corpus-down-to-a-sample-document
               tool.
            </div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e204" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e205">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Halpern-Hamu02</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e206" xml:id="h1145p" xreflabel="Hamilton and Wood">Hamilton, Kate, and Lauren Wood. 
            <div class="quote e207">Schematron in the Context of the Clinical Document Architecture (CDA).</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e208" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e209">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Wood01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e210" xml:id="f1100p" xreflabel="Harvey">Harvey, Betty. 
            <div class="quote e211">Developing Low-Cost Functional Class 3 IETM.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e212" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e213">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Harvey01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e214" xml:id="t945p" xreflabel="Holstege">Holstege, Mary. 
            <div class="quote e215">Type Introspection in XQuery.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e216" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e217">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Holstege01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e218" xml:id="h900p" xreflabel="Huitfeldt, Vitali and Peroni">Huitfeldt, Claus, Fabio Vitali and Silvio Peroni. 
            <div class="quote e219">Documents as Timed Abstract Objects.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e220" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e221">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Huitfeldt01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e222" xml:id="w900l" xreflabel="Jordanous, Stanley and Tupman">Jordanous, Anna, Alan Stanley and Charlotte Tupman. 
            <div class="quote e223">Contemporary transformation of ancient documents for recording and retrieving maximum
               information: when one form of markup is not enough.
            </div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e224" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e225">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Jordanous01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e226" xml:id="m1140" xreflabel="Kelly and Beck">Kelly, Christopher, and Jeff Beck. 
            <div class="quote e227">Quality Control of PMC Content: A Case Study.</div>   Presented at International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control in
            XML, Montréal, Canada, August 6, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e228" role="ital">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control
               in XML
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 9 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e229">10.4242/BalisageVol9.Beck01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e230" xml:id="t1145p" xreflabel="Kennedy">Kennedy, Dianne. 
            <div class="quote e231">Finally — an XML Markup Solution for Design-Based Publishers: Introducing the PRISM
               Source Vocabulary.
            </div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e232" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e233">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Kennedy01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e234" xml:id="w200p" xreflabel="Lee">Lee, David. 
            <div class="quote e235">CodeUp: Marking up Programming Languages and the winding road to an XML Syntax.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e236" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e237">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Lee01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e238" xml:id="h1100p" xreflabel="Malý and Nečaský">Malý, Jakub, and Martin Nečaský. 
            <div class="quote e239">Utilizing new capabilities of XML languages to verify integrity constraints.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e240" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e241">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Maly01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e242" xml:id="w1100r" xreflabel="Marcoux, Huitfeldt and Sperberg-McQueen">Marcoux, Yves, Claus Huitfeldt and C. M. Sperberg-McQueen. 
            <div class="quote e243">The MLCD Overlap Corpus (MOC): Project report.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e244" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e245">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Huitfeldt02</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e246" xml:id="m200" xreflabel="Morrissey et al.">Morrissey, Sheila M., John Meyer, Sushil Bhattarai, Gautham Kalwala, Sachin Kurdikar,
            Jie Ling, Matt Stoeffler and Umadevi Thanneeru. 
            <div class="quote e247">Beyond Well-Formed and Valid: QA for XML Configuration Files.</div>   Presented at International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control in
            XML, Montréal, Canada, August 6, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e248" role="ital">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control
               in XML
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 9 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e249">10.4242/BalisageVol9.Morrissey01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e250" xml:id="t1100p" xreflabel="Nordström">Nordström, Ari. 
            <div class="quote e251">Using XML to Implement XML: Or, Since XProc Is XML, Shouldn’t Everything Else Be,
               Too?
            </div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e252" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e253">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Nordstrom01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e254" xml:id="t245p" xreflabel="Pemberton">Pemberton, Steven. 
            <div class="quote e255">Serialisation, abstraction, and XML applications.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e256" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e257">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Pemberton01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e258" xml:id="w1145r" xreflabel="Piez">Piez, Wendell. 
            <div class="quote e259">Luminescent: parsing LMNL by XSLT upconversion.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e260" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e261">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Piez01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e262" xml:id="f1145p" xreflabel="Quin">Quin, Liam R. E. 
            <div class="quote e263">Characterizing ill-formed XML on the web: An analysis of the Amsterdam Corpus by document
               type.
            </div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e264" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e265">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Quin01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e266" xml:id="Quine1951" xreflabel="Quine">Quine, Willard Van Orgman. 
            <div class="quote e267">Two dogmas of empiricism.</div> 
            <div class="emphasis e268" role="ital">The Philosophical Review</div> 60 (1951):20-43. Reprinted in W.V.O. Quine. 
            <div class="emphasis e269" role="ital">From a Logical Point of View</div>. Harvard University Press, 1953; second, revised, edition 1961.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e270" xml:id="Quine1960" xreflabel="Quine">Quine, Willard Van Orgman. 
            <div class="emphasis e271" role="ital">Word and Object</div>. Cambridge, MA:  MITS Press, 1960 [pages 3-5].
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e272" xml:id="Raymond" xreflabel="Raymond, Tompa and Wood">Raymond, Darrell, Frank Tompa and Derick Wood. 
            <div class="quote e273">From Data Representation to Data Model: Meta-Semantic Issues in the Evolution of SGML.</div> 
            <div class="emphasis e274" role="ital">Computer Standards &amp; Interfaces</div> 18 (1996): 25-36.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e275" xml:id="t445p" xreflabel="Rennau">Rennau, Hans-Jürgen. 
            <div class="quote e276">From XML to UDL: a unified document language, supporting multiple markup languages.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e277" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e278">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Rennau01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e279" xml:id="t400p" xreflabel="Robie">Robie, Jonathan. 
            <div class="quote e280">XQuery, XSLT and JSON: Adapting the XML stack for a world of XML, HTML, JSON and JavaScript.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e281" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e282">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Robie01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e283" xml:id="h400r" xreflabel="Ruellan">Ruellan, Hervé. 
            <div class="quote e284">XML Entropy Study.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e285" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e286">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Ruellan01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e287" xml:id="m1220" xreflabel="Stoker and Rose">Stoker, Tamara, and Keith Rose. 
            <div class="quote e288">ACS Publications — Ensuring XML Quality.</div>   Presented at International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control in
            XML, Montréal, Canada, August 6, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e289" role="ital">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control
               in XML
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 9 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e290">10.4242/BalisageVol9.Rose01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e291" xml:id="h945p" xreflabel="Stührenberg, Schonefeld and Witt">Stührenberg, Maik, Oliver Schonefeld and Andreas Witt. 
            <div class="quote e292">A standards-related web-based information system.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e293" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e294">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Stuhrenberg01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e295" xml:id="t915p" xreflabel="Usdin">Usdin, B. Tommie. 
            <div class="quote e296">Things change, or, the `real meaning’ of technical terms.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e297" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e298">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Usdin01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e299" xml:id="m910" xreflabel="Waldt">Waldt, Dale. 
            <div class="quote e300">Quality assurance in the XML world: Beyond validation.</div>   Presented at International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control in
            XML, Montréal, Canada, August 6, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e301" role="ital">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control
               in XML
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 9 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e302">10.4242/BalisageVol9.Waldt01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e303" xml:id="w245p" xreflabel="Walsh">Walsh, Norman. 
            <div class="quote e304">On XML Languages….</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e305" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e306">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Walsh01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e307" xml:id="w900r" xreflabel="Williams and Cramer">Williams, Jorge Luis, and David Cramer. 
            <div class="quote e308">Using XProc, XSLT 2.0, and XSD 1.1 to validate RESTful services.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e309" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e310">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Williams01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e311" xml:id="w1145l" xreflabel="Wilmott">Wilmott, Sam. 
            <div class="quote e312">Literate Programming: A Case Study and Observations.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e313" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e314">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Wilmott01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e315" xml:id="t200p" xreflabel="van der Vlist">van der Vlist, Eric. 
            <div class="quote e316">Fleshing the XDM chimera.</div>   Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012, Montréal, Canada, August 7 -
            10, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e317" role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 8 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e318">10.4242/BalisageVol8.Vlist01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e319" xml:id="m950" xreflabel="van der Vlist">van der Vlist, Eric. 
            <div class="quote e320">XML instances to validate XML schemas.</div>   Presented at International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control in
            XML, Montréal, Canada, August 6, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e321" role="ital">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control
               in XML
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 9 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e322">10.4242/BalisageVol9.Vlist02</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e323" xml:id="m1100" xreflabel="Zhao, Chengan and Bai">Zhao, Wei, Jayanthy Chengan and Agnes Bai. 
            <div class="quote e324">Quality Control Practice for Scholars Portal, an XML-based E-journals Repository.</div>   Presented at International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control in
            XML, Montréal, Canada, August 6, 2012. In 
            <div class="emphasis e325" role="ital">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control
               in XML
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 9 (2012). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e326">10.4242/BalisageVol9.Zhao01</div>.
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>