<div id="mainContainerTOC">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTOC" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTOC').toggle('1000');">Table of Content</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTOC" style="display:none;">
      <div class="headedContainerTOC">
         <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#AnOnionofDocumentsandMetadataANCHOR" name="AnOnionofDocumentsandMetadataTOC">An Onion of Documents and Metadata</a></div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#BuildingtheUntestable%E2%80%94andDocumentingItANCHOR" name="BuildingtheUntestable%E2%80%94andDocumentingItTOC">Building the Untestable—and Documenting It</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#TheDCRLifeCycleANCHOR" name="TheDCRLifeCycleTOC">The DCR Life Cycle</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ConstructingaDCRinXMLANCHOR" name="ConstructingaDCRinXMLTOC">Constructing a DCR in XML</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#TrackingtheWorkflowANCHOR" name="TrackingtheWorkflowTOC">Tracking the Workflow</a></div>
            <div class="headedContainerTOC">
               <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#FilesLocationsandManagementANCHOR" name="FilesLocationsandManagementTOC">Files, Locations, and Management</a></div>
            </div>
            <div class="headedContainerTOC">
               <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#MetadataFlowANCHOR" name="MetadataFlowTOC">Metadata Flow</a></div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#WorkflowstoComeANCHOR" name="WorkflowstoComeTOC">Workflows to Come</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ReferencesANCHOR" name="ReferencesTOC">References</a></div>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerTERMS">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTERMS" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTERMS').toggle('1000')">Index of Terms</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTERMS" style="display:none;">
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">a</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">August 12 - 15, 2008</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Albert</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">b</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Balisage</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2008</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">c</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">d</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">D.</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">David</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">e</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Extreme Markup Language</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">f</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">g</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Gutenberg Award</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">h</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">i</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">j</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">James</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">J.</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">k</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Knowledge Technologies 2002</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Kelleher</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Klein</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">l</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">m</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Mason</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Matthew</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">n</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">o</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">p</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">q</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">r</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">s</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">SGML 1997</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">t</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Tekkie Award</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">u</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">v</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">x</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">y</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">z</div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerIML"><a name="AnOnionofDocumentsandMetadataANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="article e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2">
      <div class="title e1">An Onion of Documents and Metadata</div>
      <div class="info e2">
         <div class="confgroup e3">
            <div class="conftitle e4">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2008</div>
            <div class="confdates e5">August 12 - 15, 2008</div>
         </div>
         <div class="abstract e6">
            <div class="para e7">When a product cannot be tested as a finished unit, its warranty,
               as it were, depends on extensive testing of its component parts and
               assemblies. The record for products of the Y-12 National Security
               Complex has for many years been in the form of lengthy paper documents.
               Recently we have begun a process to capture some of this information
               in XML documents. However, this is not simply another XML publishing
               project. Because our products have a potentially very long shelf life
               and we cannot foresee the computing environment in their distant future
               existence, we must take extraordinary measures to document not only
               the products themselves but also the environment in which the documentation
               has been prepared. Adding complexity to this documentation challenge
               is a parallel effort to capture the output data of test equipment
               and wrap it in XML. While this project is very much a work in progress,
               we can see that one major component of its possible success will be
               the coordination of complex metadata.
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e8">
            <div class="personname e9">
               <div class="firstname e10">D.</div>
               <div class="othername e11">Matthew</div>
               <div class="surname e12">Kelleher</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e13">
               <div class="para e14">Matthew Kelleher has a B.S. in chemical engineering from Iowa
                  State University and an M.S. in computer science from the University
                  of Tennessee. He works at Y-12 National Security Complex in Oak Ridge,
                  Tennessee, and has worked at Oak Ridge National Laboratory and other
                  Oak Ridge facilities. He has a background in modeling and simulation
                  and data management and is interested in using computing technology
                  to solve real-world problems. 
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e15">
            <div class="personname e16">
               <div class="firstname e17">Albert</div>
               <div class="othername e18">J.</div>
               <div class="surname e19">Klein</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e20">
               <div class="para e21">Albert Klein is a Senior Technical Project Officer for B&amp;W
                  Technical Services, LLC in Oak Ridge, TN, a prime contractor for Department
                  of Energy (DOE) and national Nuclear Security Administration (NNSA).
                  Al is the project manager for the Y-12 Product Realization Integrated
                  Digital Enterprise (PRIDE) Surveillance program, dealing with weapons
                  systems surveillance data storage, access control, and interchange
                  among the nuclear weapons complex (NWC). The PRIDE Surveillance program
                  includes initiatives for shop floor control and paperless operations,
                  XML document standardization, records digitization, and data interchange.
                  He is currently investigating commercial applications for delivery
                  of process plans and electronic work instructions to shop floor operators
                  and coordinates with other NWC sites and NNSA HQ for PRIDE planning
                  and execution.
               </div>
               <div class="para e22">Mr. Klein has over twenty-five years' experience in project
                  management and principal investigation in information technology and
                  knowledge management projects. These include knowledge management,
                  document classification, expert systems, electronic commerce/electronic
                  data interchange (EC/EDI), document imaging, optical storage technology,
                  and enterprise integration. He has an M.B.A. from the University of
                  Illinois, Urbana, an M.S. in physics from the University of Washington,
                  Seattle, and a B.S. in physics from the University of Illinois. He
                  was born in Austria and is fluent in German.    
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e23">
            <div class="personname e24">
               <div class="firstname e25">James</div>
               <div class="othername e26">David</div>
               <div class="surname e27">Mason</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e28">
               <div class="para e29">James D. Mason, originally trained as a mediaevalist and linguist,
                  has been a writer, systems developer, and manufacturing engineer at
                  U.S. Department of Energy facilities in Oak Ridge since the late 1970s.
                  In 1981, he joined the ISO work on standards for document management
                  and           interchange. He chaired ISO/IEC JTC1/SC34, which is
                  responsible for SGML, DSSSL, topic maps, and related standards, 1985–2007.
                  Dr. Mason has been a frequent writer and speaker on standards and
                  their applications. For his work on SGML, he has received the 
                  <div class="emphasis e30" role="ital">Gutenberg Award</div> from Printing Industries of
                  America and the 
                  <div class="emphasis e31" role="ital">Tekkie Award</div> from
                  GCA. Dr. Mason was Chairman of the 
                  <div class="emphasis e32" role="ital">Knowledge
                     Technologies 2002
                  </div> conference, has co-chaired the 
                  <div class="emphasis e33" role="ital">Extreme Markup Language</div> conferences. and is
                  co-chair of 
                  <div class="emphasis e34" role="ital">Balisage</div>. He is currently
                  working on information systems to support the classification and manufacturing
                  communities at DOE's Y-12 National Security Complex in Oak Ridge,
                  Tennessee. He received a B.A. in mathematics and physics and a M.A.
                  in English from Vanderbilt University and a Ph.D. in English and Germanic
                  linguistics and mediaeval literature from the University of Tennessee.
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="legalnotice e35">
            <div class="para e36">The Y-12 National Security Complex is managed for the U.S. Department
               of Energy by B&amp;W Technical Services Y-12, L.L.C. (B&amp;W Y-12),
               under contract DE-AC05-00OR22800.
            </div>
            <div class="para e37">This document was prepared as an account of work sponsored by
               an agency of the U.S. Government. Neither the United States Government
               nor any agency thereof, nor Contractor, nor any of their employees,
               makes any warranty, express or implied, or assumes any legal liability
               or responsibility for the accuracy, completeness, use made, or usefulness
               of any information, apparatus, product, or process disclosed, or represents
               that its use would not infringe privately owned rights. Reference
               herein to any specific commercial product, process, or service by
               trade name, trademark, manufacturer, or otherwise, does not necessarily
               constitute or imply its endorsement, recommendation, or favoring by
               the United States Government or any agency or Contractor thereof.
               The views and opinions of authors expressed herein do not necessarily
               state or reflect those of the United States Government or any agency
               or Contractor thereof. Further, B&amp;W Y-12 is not responsible for
               the contents of any off-site pages referenced.
            </div>
            <div class="para e38">This document was prepared by a contractor of the U.S. Government
               under contract DE-AC05-00OR22800. Accordingly, the U.S. Government
               retains a nonexclusive, royalty-free license to publish or reproduce
               these documents, or to allow others to do so, for U.S. Government
               purposes. These documents may be freely distributed and used for non-commercial,
               scientific and educational purposes.
            </div>
         </div>
      </div><a name="BuildingtheUntestable%E2%80%94andDocumentingItANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e39">
         <div class="title e40">Building the Untestable—and Documenting It</div>
         <div class="para e41">For more than sixty years, the Y-12 National Security Complex
            (Y-12) has made components for the nuclear arsenal of the United States.
            Unlike other industrial products, such as automobiles and computers,
            Y-12's finished work cannot be tested in use. Instead, we must assure
            our customers that the products we send them are made precisely according
            to specifications, using approved procedures. Not only can the products
            not be tested in use, they typically remain in the stockpile inventory
            for some decades, so assurance of what went into an individual unit
            and how all the components were assembled is important for continued
            customer assurance (no mere 5 years/50,000 mile warranty here). And
            when an individual unit comes back to us, either to be refurbished
            for life extension or to be dismantled at the end of its life, we
            need to know exactly what was in it and how the components were assembled.
         </div>
         <div class="para e42">Because we think in long product lifetimes for these products
            that are not easily opened for inspection (you can't just lift the
            hood and check the oil), each individual product is accompanied by
            extensive documentation. A typical component will undergo numerous
            certifications, including tests of the chemical and physical properties
            of its materials and inspections of the part itself for dimensions,
            surface finish, and contaminants. Each step in the assembly process
            is accompanied by more tests and X-rays for alignment of components,
            finished dimensions, and other properties. All the test results, checklists,
            instrument printouts, and other materials gradually accumulate into
            a bulky record that is kept until the individual device is dismantled,
            when it will be compared with a report of what is found in the dismantlement
            process.
         </div>
         <div class="para e43">Dealing with potentially long product life expectancy and  therefore
            also archival retention of product documentation has made the Nuclear
            Weapons Complex (NWC) extremely conservative about introduction of
            new technology to documentation. The devices that Y-12 has recently
            refurbished were first built before the development of the personal
            computer, and their documentation is entirely in paper. It is only
            in the past decade that the NWC has begun to require that the measurement
            data from certification tests be captured in electronic form. In this
            same period, the NWC has also begun to look at formal standards for
            capturing metadata about the documents, if not the actual documents
            themselves, in electronic format [
            <div class="xref e44" linkend="mason97"></div>]. The actual process of certifying parts has for more than sixty
            years continued to be driven by paper procedures and checklists used
            on the shop floor. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e45">As part of a project to move to an electronic process for product
            construction records, we have undertaken to develop an XML-based workflow
            for the Dimensional Certification Report (DCR) and the Nondestructive
            Test Report (NDT). Dimensional certification typically employs templates
            and instruments such as coordinate measuring machines (CMMs). The
            CMMs can perform exceedingly precise tracings of surface contours
            and generate electronic data. At some future phase of this project
            we hope to merge CMM data directly into the DCR, but for the present
            it will be entered into the report by the inspector at a terminal
            beside the machine. (Our CMMs are massive instruments: to achieve
            the necessary precision, their work tables and supporting beams are
            massive blocks of granite because steel I-beams are too flexible,
            Fig. 1.) Typical NDT tests include visual inspection and treatment
            with fluorescent dyes that can help make visible minute cracks in
            welds or metal parts. 
            <div class="xref e46" linkend="boo"></div>
         </div>
         <div class="figure e47" xml:id="boo">
            <div class="mediaobject e48">
               <div class="imageobject e49">
                  <div class="metaBox e50"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e87').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e87" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e50'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol1/graphics/Mason01/Mason01-001.jpg'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='jpg'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='50%'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="caption e51">
                  <div class="para e52">Fig. 1. Coordinate Measuring Machine</div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e53">The DCR is not simply the report of results of a certification
            process; it is also a procedure for carrying out the process, with
            the results captured in forms in the body of the procedure. Thus,
            a potential reader some years in the future can see not only that
            a product has been certified but the steps that were taken in the
            process to certify it. As an XML document, the DCR is not particularly
            exceptional; it has the typical components of technical documents:
            sections, titles, paragraphs, lists, tables, figures. Its most unusual
            feature is the tabular presentation of the steps in the procedure,
            intermixed with spaces to capture user input as the steps are carried
            out. The NDT is simpler than the DCR, but it, too, captures data on
            a form. The procedure for the NDT is a separate document, and the
            form is for data capture only. (Each DCR procedure is unique to an
            individual component, but NDT procedures are generic to many components.)
         </div>
         <div class="para e54">What is more interesting than the forms as examples of XML documents
            is the workflow associated with the creation and use of the these
            procedures/reports and its implications for configuration management.
            In their paper format, DCRs in particular have always been under many
            layers of configuration control. A typical DCR contains one or more
            “Picture Pages” that contain drawings of the component being certified,
            followed by the testing procedure. Both the Picture Page and the procedure
            require sign-offs by a Product Engineer and an Inspection Engineer,
            who are responsible for the manufacture and testing of the component,
            and a configuration control officer, who releases the procedure to
            the certification laboratory under a Product Engineering Transmittal
            (PET). The process of developing, approving, and releasing an individual
            DCR procedure is well established and governed by its own controlled
            procedures. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e55">In developing an electronic workflow, we are constrained by
            the PET process. However, behind it we must develop additional layers
            of configuration control on the components of the XML processing.
            Even though SGML, XML, and related software have been evolving in
            the industrial documentation sector for more than a quarter of a century,
            they are still young in the eyes of those in the NWC. Our configuration
            control must not only account for the requirements of software development,
            they must also meet the requirements of our customers, most of whom
            are not computing specialists, much less XML experts. One consequence
            of the PET process is that we must closely mirror the process for
            paper documents, and the electronic document must capture the metadata
            associated with the paper one that has been accepted by the user community. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e56">Behind that, however, we must also maintain a high level of
            configuration control for the XML and processing components. Because
            the potential lifetime of certification data for a product is longer
            than the past history of structured markup, we must attempt to anticipate
            what will be needed to recall certification data when an individual
            product returns for refurbishment or dismantlement some day in the
            future, when everyone who is working either on the current XML project
            or who participated in the certification on the shop floor has retired.
            Thus the files that record results of certifications must record audit
            trails not only of the certification process but also of the XML and
            its processing behind the creation of the files. Only when we are
            able to integrate all of these processes and data flows into an integrated
            archive will we be able to say that we have implemented an Electronic
            Build History (EBH).
         </div>
         <div class="para e57">The life cycle that we are incorporating into this project is
            only one of the possibilities we examined. We also looked at a system
            for scanning user input on paper forms and a manufacturing execution
            system that would place the entire process under electronic control.
            Scanning, we decided, was actually too difficult: intelligent character
            recognition systems, it seems, place too many constraints on their
            input forms. They fit best in environments where there are large volumes
            of a very few forms, which is the opposite of our situation. A manufacturing
            execution system (MES), we know from our own tests, could be programmed
            for our workflow. Because our current MES is very old and does not
            have good data collection capabilities, Y-12 is looking at replacing
            it. Although the replacement MES will take time to implement, it may
            have appropriate data collection capabilities. Thus a workflow built
            around an XML publishing system with extensive scripting and an attached
            Web server represents a middle path for capability and costs.
         </div>
      </div><a name="TheDCRLifeCycleANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e58">
         <div class="title e59">The DCR Life Cycle</div>
         <div class="para e60">The certification process captured by the DCR is a late step
            in an overall manufacturing workflow that begins with a product specification
            issued by a Design Agency (DA, typically Los Alamos National Laboratory
            or Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory). At Y-12, that specification
            becomes the responsibility of a Product Engineer (PE), who oversees
            its interpretation into manufacturing processes on the shop floor
            and then certification procedures for validating the results of manufacturing.
            The manufacturing process for an individual component may be complex,
            involving many steps, each with its own associated tests. A casting,
            for example, may be turned to a rough shape, then gradually machined
            to a final shape before being submitted for final certification. At
            every step there are additional tests. Certification itself is often
            iterative: a part that is slightly off-tolerance will be returned
            to manufacturing for further refinement, perhaps several times, until
            it is able to meet all requirements of the certification. As each
            test is completed, the results and the reports are audited before
            the manufacturing step is certified. The various test reports, such
            as the DCR and NDT, will accumulate with each part and assembly, being
            accumulated into a build history that forms part of the certification
            documentation of a product.
         </div>
         <div class="para e61">The certification process is overseen by an Inspection Engineer
            (IE), who works with the PE to ensure that the tests are adequate
            to capture the specification of the component. Development of an inspection
            procedure is also iterative; when it is complete, the document must
            be signed by both the PE and the IE, as well as an engineer responsible
            for configuration control. The typical DCR, having both a part drawing
            and a testing procedure, has separate signature records for both.
         </div>
      </div><a name="ConstructingaDCRinXMLANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e62">
         <div class="title e63">Constructing a DCR in XML</div>
         <div class="para e64">Our current practice is for a DCR to be generated in Microsoft
            Word and for the results to be printed. The testing procedure consists
            of steps, each of which describes a test process and lists the tools
            and instruments needed to carry it out. Each step, which appears as
            a row in tabular form, also provides a space to record the results,
            which may include pass/fail indicators, direct observations or measurements
            from test equipment, and comments or even sketches from the inspector.
            Fig. 2 shows sample pages from a typical DCR: a “Picture Page,” a
            page of instructions, and a page from the combined certification procedure
            and data-recording form.
            <div class="figure e65">
               <div class="mediaobject e66">
                  <div class="imageobject e67">
                     <div class="metaBox e68"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e116').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e116" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e68'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol1/graphics/Mason01/Mason01-002.jpg'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='jpg'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='100%'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption e69">
                     <div class="para e70">Fig. 2a. Picture Page from a DCR</div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="mediaobject e71">
                  <div class="imageobject e72">
                     <div class="metaBox e73"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e122').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e122" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e73'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol1/graphics/Mason01/Mason01-003.jpg'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='jpg'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='100%'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption e74">
                     <div class="para e75">Fig. 2b. Instruction Page from a DCR</div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="mediaobject e76">
                  <div class="imageobject e77">
                     <div class="metaBox e78"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e128').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e128" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e78'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol1/graphics/Mason01/Mason01-004.jpg'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='jpg'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='100%'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div class="caption e79">
                     <div class="para e80">Fig. 2c. Procedure Page from a DCR</div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e81">The workflow we envision for a DCR is based on our understanding
            of the workflow already used in Word. In Fig. 3, the development of
            a new procedure and its reporting form begins with the IE, guided
            by the PE, producing an XML document rather than a Word file. The
            resulting document goes through the conventional review process, ending
            with approval and the addition of appropriate signatures and other
            metadata to the XML file. Each dimensional inspection process for
            a given part requires such an XML template file that will guide the
            inspection, record the data collected in the inspection, and become
            the basis for the certification report that accompanies each part.
         </div>
         <div class="figure e82">
            <div class="mediaobject e83">
               <div class="imageobject e84">
                  <div class="metaBox e85"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e137').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e137" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e85'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol1/graphics/Mason01/Mason01-005.jpg'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='jpg'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='100%'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="caption e86">
                  <div class="para e87">Fig. 3. DCR Workflow</div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e88">Once the base document is approved, the workflow diverges from
            past practice, because the information flow forks: The XML document
            is converted to an HTML (actually JSP) procedure and form for online
            delivery to the inspector, while a copy of the file is reserved for
            population with data later in the process. The inspector on the shop
            floor uses a Web browser to enter data into a new instance of the
            online form. At the end of the inspection, the data is collected in
            another XML file that is then merged with the empty copy of the procedure
            to produce the actual certification report. At that point the completed
            procedure is audited. If the part is not approved, it is returned
            to manufacturing for further work, followed by more inspections, until
            the part is either finally approved for this stage or it is “killed”
            and its materials perhaps recycled. If the part is approved, based
            on the data collected, the completed XML report is archived. Our current
            view is that there will actually be at least three objects archived:
            the first is the XML data file collected from the online process,
            the second a merged XML file containing the DCR in the form of the
            template populated with the collected data, and the third a PDF file
            of the completed DCR report created by merging the data file with
            the form. Moreover, until the EBH has been certified as a valid process,
            the DCR report must be produced in paper. For this reason, as well
            as for the comfort of our customers, we have taken special care to
            produce the DCR in a format that closely approximates that of the
            current Word documents. Using a form that looks like their current
            form also makes it easier to meet Y-12's conduct-of-operations requirements.
         </div>
         <div class="para e89">This workflow contains most of the expected components associated
            with XML-based publishing. Behind the XML documents there are, of
            course, DTDs. (We use DTDs and not some other form of schema largely
            for consistency with other local applications.) Conversion to HTML
            forms and merging data collected online back into the XML record is
            handled by XSLT. Because we use the Arbortext publishing system, both
            screen presentation and formatting for PDF are handled by Arbortext's
            proprietary stylesheets, which are, at least, also XML documents.
         </div>
         <div class="para e90">When we started on the project, our early goal was to find out
            whether we could recreate the DCR document in an XML publishing system.
            Having done the document analysis, written a DTD, and created a stylesheet,
            we concluded that the basic document was within our capabilities.
            Then the process expanded into the scripts that create the HTML form
            pages, collect the data from the forms, and populate a completed XML
            document. That being done, and a parallel process for the NDT form
            likewise undertaken, we could have considered our project complete.
            However, these reporting forms do not exist in a vacuum. The data
            recorded on a DCR, in particular, does not all come from human observation;
            it may come from test equipment, though it currently must be entered
            manually. In many cases the component being tested may also be undergoing
            a surface contour trace on a CMM, and the CMM is producing a data
            file. For some years, DOE has been requiring that such data become
            part of an “Electronic Data Capture” (EDC) record. Heretofore, the
            EDC file has probably been in a proprietary format or in a record
            format that does not involve XML. CMM measurements and reports are
            not entered in or handled as DCRs, and current CMM reports have their
            own defined paper and electronic formats. CMM paper reports are placed
            in the build history and electronic versions are saved in the plant
            EDC system. Now, however, we are beginning to look at the potential
            for merging data entered by the inspector with EDC data from test
            gear and creating a complete XML record of the certification process.
            DCRs are used for many kinds of measurements not performed using CMMs
            and for which EDC is not currently performed. Future development of
            an EBH may cause rethinking of the kinds of reports generated, the
            formats of the data, and the relationship between the reports and
            the results of EDC.
         </div>
         <div class="para e91">Building the XML environment for EDC is in only the very earliest
            investigatory stages. We know that some data, such as series of coordinates
            from CMMs, could be recorded as simple XML records. Other data, such
            as signal output from a vibration analyzer, will probably need to
            remain in binary format. Our challenge, then, will be to create a
            layered data/metadata environment that will accommodate a variety
            of test equipment as well as a variety of users and uses for the data
            over the long life span of the product. We are investigating this
            environment with other users of such test equipment, most of them
            outside the NWC. At the innermost layers of the metadata onion, next
            to the core of data from the test gear, will need to be metadata about
            the equipment in use, such as the identification of the device and
            its calibration record. Around that will be layers that describe the
            specific test environment, such as the time, date, and environmental
            conditions in the test shop. Another layer will include the identification
            of the component under test and link the specific test to the record
            being created in the DCR.
         </div>
      </div><a name="TrackingtheWorkflowANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e92">
         <div class="title e93">Tracking the Workflow</div>
         <div class="para e94">Much of the problem of assembling an EBH is a result of the
            need to track both the actual certification data and the metadata
            about the data-collection process and to keep all of this information
            in synchronization. Furthermore, the process must continue to support
            the workflow that has been built up—and certified—around the paper-based
            process. The layers of configuration management that have accumulated
            around the PET process are concerned with tracking paper documents.
            Now we need to embed configuration management into the documents themselves
            and make them as self-documenting as possible. This seems to suggest
            that at each stage of processing the document should accumulate additional
            metadata, so that when the report, which represents the procedure
            completely populated with certification data, is finished, it is also
            fully populated with an audit trail of the processes that allowed
            it to be completed. Thus the metadata will accumulate in layers, one
            of which captures the traditional PET and audit processes and the
            others which track the XML environment.
         </div><a name="FilesLocationsandManagementANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e95">
            <div class="title e96">Files, Locations, and Management</div>
            <div class="para e97">In a conventional XML document-management environment, the goal
               is frequently to get to a final document. In that case, it is the
               document instance that will be archived. It may be of interest to
               archive the DTD or other schema if that will help in further interpretation
               of the document, but for many applications a well-formed document
               may, as some have argued, be sufficient. If a document, such as a
               maintenance manual, is revised iteratively, then continued maintenance
               of its DTD and other supporting structures like stylesheets becomes
               more significant than in cases where the document is a final product.
               In our case, however, the entire processing stack becomes a structure
               subject to audit and thus to archiving. When we face the possibility
               that a generation from now it will be necessary to verify that an
               electronic document is what was intended originally, we need not only
               the document and its graphics but many of the process files that supported
               them.
            </div>
            <div class="para e98">The document-management system for our process is not yet established
               because it will have to be coordinated with other systems outside
               our current scope. Currently a DCR template is created on a local
               PC. For the interim, document processing and storage are on a Web
               server (see below, Table 1). Even after primary storage systems are
               established, copies of the files will continue to appear on that system.
               Processing of a new DCR form begins with loading the DTD, template,
               composition stylesheet, and XSLT stylesheets to the server. The server
               then establishes links for starting certifications using that template.
               The inspector can call forth an online form, enter metadata about
               the part being tested, and walk through the procedure, entering data
               as required. When the procedure is completed, the results can be saved.
               The individual certification run can be reopened for further editing,
               or the results can be composed as a report and sent for auditing and
               approval.
            </div>
            <div class="para e99">At the current stage in the development of the process, we are
               not completely certain of all the items that will be tracked, but
               our current analysis suggests that we have a complex of items in the
               stack. Since our analysis is more advanced for the DCR than for the
               NDT, this list reflects the components required for it.
            </div>
            <div class="itemizedlist e100">
               <div class="listitem e101">
                  <div class="para e102">End-user objects
                     <div class="itemizedlist e103">
                        <div class="listitem e104">
                           <div class="para e105">Blank Procedures/Forms</div>
                           <div class="para e106">Each DCR procedure/form,
                              which represents an individual certification step for a particular
                              component, is represented by this single configuration control item:
                              
                           </div>
                           <div class="itemizedlist e107">
                              <div class="listitem e108">
                                 <div class="para e109">Form XML file, the template for constructing reports
                                    on individual components
                                 </div>
                              </div>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="listitem e110">
                           <div class="para e111">Form Graphics and Supplemental Material</div>
                           <div class="para e112">The graphics and supplemental material can be specific to a single
                              form or shared among forms.
                           </div>
                           <div class="para e113">The “Picture Page” of a DCR procedure contains at least one
                              reference drawing for the certification process. Such graphics are
                              under configuration control with the related forms:
                           </div>
                           <div class="itemizedlist e114">
                              <div class="listitem e115">
                                 <div class="para e116">Part graphics and supplemental material</div>
                              </div>
                              <div class="listitem e117">
                                 <div class="para e118">Common part graphics and supplemental material </div>
                              </div>
                              <div class="listitem e119">
                                 <div class="para e120">Common process graphics and supplemental material </div>
                              </div>
                              <div class="listitem e121">
                                 <div class="para e122">Form graphics used to improve form appearance and
                                    operation
                                 </div>
                              </div>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="listitem e123">
                           <div class="para e124">In-Process Form Data</div>
                           <div class="para e125">In-process form data
                              represent forms that have data entered but have not yet been assigned
                              a disposition.  These data must be managed using an iterative model
                              with all iterations saved:
                           </div>
                           <div class="itemizedlist e126">
                              <div class="listitem e127">
                                 <div class="para e128">XML data file, collected from Web form</div>
                              </div>
                              <div class="listitem e129">
                                 <div class="para e130">PDF file showing data entered in original form, displayed
                                    for review, auditing, and certification
                                 </div>
                              </div>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="listitem e131">
                           <div class="para e132">Record Data</div>
                           <div class="para e133">Forms that are complete become
                              record data and must be stored in a system that complies with records
                              management requirements:
                           </div>
                           <div class="itemizedlist e134">
                              <div class="listitem e135">
                                 <div class="para e136">XML data file</div>
                              </div>
                              <div class="listitem e137">
                                 <div class="para e138">Completed XML DCR with data merged into template</div>
                              </div>
                              <div class="listitem e139">
                                 <div class="para e140">PDF file rendering the XML DCR with entered data in
                                    original blank form
                                 </div>
                              </div>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e141">
                  <div class="para e142">XML control structures
                     <div class="itemizedlist e143">
                        <div class="listitem e144">
                           <div class="para e145">DCR Procedure and Report Form Template</div>
                           <div class="para e146">Each type of form is represented by a DTD that controls its structure
                              and data content:
                           </div>
                           <div class="itemizedlist e147">
                              <div class="listitem e148">
                                 <div class="para e149">DCR XML DTD, which represents all the components of
                                    a generic procedure, along with the framework for data collection
                                    to create a report and the frameworks for metadata
                                 </div>
                              </div>
                              <div class="listitem e150">
                                 <div class="para e151">Data-collection DTD, which defines the structure of
                                    the data collected online during the execution of the certification
                                    process
                                 </div>
                              </div>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e152">
                  <div class="para e153">Supporting software
                     <div class="itemizedlist e154">
                        <div class="listitem e155">
                           <div class="para e156">Form Web Page</div>
                           <div class="para e157">The Web artifacts are displayed
                              to the end users during the execution of the procedure and the collecting
                              of certification data. Because they are secondary documents generated
                              by software, they may be stored and managed separately from their
                              original sources. End users may interact with pages on the Web server,
                              but they have no interaction with the files as files, any more than
                              they interact with the XSLT or Java source code.
                           </div>
                           <div class="itemizedlist e158">
                              <div class="listitem e159">
                                 <div class="para e160">Java Server Pages: Web page form displayed on the
                                    inspector's browser in the certification shop or laboratory 
                                 </div>
                              </div>
                              <div class="listitem e161">
                                 <div class="para e162">Web page graphics and supplemental material, generally
                                    drawn from the graphics associated with the XML form template
                                 </div>
                              </div>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="listitem e163">
                           <div class="para e164">Form Transforms and Style Sheets</div>
                           <div class="para e165">These
                              form transforms can be specific to a single form or shared by several
                              forms; in general, they are specific to a single DTD, such as the
                              DCR:
                           </div>
                           <div class="itemizedlist e166">
                              <div class="listitem e167">
                                 <div class="para e168">XSLT from form XML to JSP</div>
                              </div>
                              <div class="listitem e169">
                                 <div class="para e170">XSLT for merging data XML and form XML into a completed
                                    report
                                 </div>
                              </div>
                              <div class="listitem e171">
                                 <div class="para e172">Arbortext style sheet for rendering XML into PDF</div>
                              </div>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="listitem e173">
                           <div class="para e174">Form Web Page Software</div>
                           <div class="para e175">The Web server
                              software can be specific to a single form but more likely will be
                              shared among forms generated from a single DTD:
                           </div>
                           <div class="itemizedlist e176">
                              <div class="listitem e177">
                                 <div class="para e178">Java Server Faces backing bean that transfers data
                                    between the Web page and the data model
                                 </div>
                              </div>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="listitem e179">
                           <div class="para e180">Data File</div>
                           <div class="para e181">Data file configuration control
                              items consist of:
                           </div>
                           <div class="itemizedlist e182">
                              <div class="listitem e183">
                                 <div class="para e184">Data File Model, a software representation of the
                                    data file that maps form entries to data file entries  
                                 </div>
                              </div>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="para e185">Another way of looking at the complex of files and programs
               is to consider what roles the components play and where they appear
               both during processing and in storage (Table 1).
               <div class="table e186" rules="all">
                  <div class="caption e187">
                     <div class="para e188">DCR form system file types
                        and locations
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div class="thead e189">
                     <div class="tr e190">
                        <div class="th e191" align="center" valign="middle">File Type</div>
                        <div class="th e192" align="center" colspan="3" valign="middle">Component file role</div>
                        <div class="th e193" align="center" colspan="4" valign="middle">File storage locations</div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div class="tbody e194">
                     <div class="tr e195">
                        <div class="td e196" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e197" align="center" valign="middle">Form Creation Template</div>
                        <div class="td e198" align="center" valign="middle">Form Package</div>
                        <div class="td e199" align="center" valign="middle">Data Package</div>
                        <div class="td e200" align="center" valign="middle">Content-management System</div>
                        <div class="td e201" align="center" valign="middle">Web Server</div>
                        <div class="td e202" align="center" valign="middle">Arbortext Publishing Engine Server</div>
                        <div class="td e203" align="center" valign="middle">Data Repository</div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="tr e204">
                        <div class="td e205" align="center" valign="middle">Form DTD </div>
                        <div class="td e206" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e207" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e208" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e209" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e210" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e211" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e212" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="tr e213">
                        <div class="td e214" align="center" valign="middle">Form XML instance</div>
                        <div class="td e215" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e216" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e217" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e218" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e219" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e220" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e221" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="tr e222">
                        <div class="td e223" align="center" valign="middle">Form graphics instances</div>
                        <div class="td e224" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e225" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e226" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e227" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e228" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e229" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e230" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="tr e231">
                        <div class="td e232" align="center" valign="middle">Form PDF stylesheet </div>
                        <div class="td e233" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e234" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e235" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e236" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e237" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e238" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e239" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="tr e240">
                        <div class="td e241" align="center" valign="middle">Form PDF </div>
                        <div class="td e242" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e243" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e244" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e245" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e246" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e247" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e248" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="tr e249">
                        <div class="td e250" align="center" valign="middle">Form-to-JSP XSL transform </div>
                        <div class="td e251" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e252" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e253" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e254" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e255" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e256" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e257" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="tr e258">
                        <div class="td e259" align="center" valign="middle">Form JSP instance</div>
                        <div class="td e260" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e261" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e262" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e263" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e264" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e265" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e266" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="tr e267">
                        <div class="td e268" align="center" valign="middle">Data-collection DTD </div>
                        <div class="td e269" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e270" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e271" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e272" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e273" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e274" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e275" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="tr e276">
                        <div class="td e277" align="center" valign="middle">Data-collection XML instance</div>
                        <div class="td e278" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e279" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e280" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e281" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e282" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e283" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e284" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="tr e285">
                        <div class="td e286" align="center" valign="middle">Form-and-data merge XSL transformation</div>
                        <div class="td e287" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e288" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e289" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e290" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e291" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e292" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e293" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="tr e294">
                        <div class="td e295" align="center" valign="middle">Form XML with merged data </div>
                        <div class="td e296" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e297" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e298" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e299" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e300" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e301" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e302" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="tr e303">
                        <div class="td e304" align="center" valign="middle">Completed report with data merged and rendered to
                           PDF
                        </div>
                        <div class="td e305" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e306" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e307" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e308" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e309" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                        <div class="td e310" align="center" valign="middle"></div>
                        <div class="td e311" align="center" valign="middle">X</div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="para e312">What Table 1 shows is that, just looking at files and not at
               the software behind them, we start with a small number of control
               files, build a form package, and then collect a data package. Source
               files are to be archived in a content-management system and final
               results will be passed to a data repository. Almost all the files
               pass through the Web server, where source XML is rendered into HTML/JSP
               forms, data is collected through the forms, and results are assembled
               in XML and PDF. One auxiliary server hosting composition software
               is called in to manage PDF rendition of XML files. Software source
               code, such as the backing bean module and DOM-based interpreter of
               JSP output, will also be managed, probably on a content-management
               system.
            </div>
            <div class="para e313">Some files in the system are, in effect, transient and so do
               not require archiving. The JSP version of a procedure and form is
               created when an IE creates a new or revised procedure and loads it
               to the Web server. It is displayed to guide the inspector through
               the certification process and collect input from the process, but
               it is not saved with data in place. Creation of a new XML data file
               from what is entered in the online form is hidden from the user until
               that data is merged with the XML form template and displayed as a
               PDF rendition. 
            </div>
         </div><a name="MetadataFlowANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e314">
            <div class="title e315">Metadata Flow</div>
            <div class="para e316">Because the EBH project builds on legacy processes and incorporates
               metadata from both the legacy and the new processes, it incorporates
               a dual flow of metadata.
            </div>
            <div class="para e317">The XML component of the EBH study began with a pilot project
               to capture a DCR as an XML document rather than as a Word file. One
               of the first decisions in the document design was to create specific
               elements to capture metadata already in the paper-based workflow.
               So there are individual elements to both information about the component
               being certified and the engineers involved in developing and approving
               the certification and reporting procedure. The component itself is
               identified on the template form by its part number and name. When
               the certification procedure is executed, the inspector will add to
               these the lot number and serial number of the part. The Picture Page
               also includes the governing drawing number. The approvals include
               elements for the PE, IE, and configuration engineer, along with the
               dates of their approvals and the PET governing the procedure. There
               are separate approvals for the Picture Page and the body of the procedure.
               These elements of the template are simply passed through the entire
               process to the final certification report unchanged. They are rendered
               in both HTML and PDF, but appear in the XML version of the report
               just as they appeared in the template XML created by the IE.
            </div>
            <div class="para e318">The IE will recognize that the new workflow calls out this legacy
               metadata as explicit items for input, rather than finding it simply
               as locations in a Word table to fill in. (We are still developing
               the user interface to be used in the Arbortext editor.) But beyond
               that, these items will not be recognized as metadata by users of the
               process. The information will, for all practical purposes, continue
               to look as it did in the paper-based process. Because the information
               is wrapped in XML, however, it will be available to future processes
               that for the most part have not yet been created.
            </div>
            <div class="programlisting e319" xml:space="preserve"> &lt;DCRbody&gt;
               &lt;DCRInformation&gt;
               &lt;DCRHeader&gt;
               &lt;DCRPET&gt;47691&lt;/DCRPET&gt;
               &lt;DCRArea&gt;9201-1&lt;/DCRArea&gt;
               &lt;DCRtitleblock&gt;
               &lt;DCRPartName&gt;Eyelet&lt;/DCRPartName&gt;
               &lt;DCRPartNumber&gt;B-K-23189&lt;/DCRPartNumber&gt;
               &lt;DCRDrawingNumber&gt;B-K-23189&lt;/DCRDrawingNumber&gt;
               &lt;DCRDrawingRev&gt;L&lt;/DCRDrawingRev&gt;
               &lt;DCRProductID&gt;PP1200-19&lt;/DCRProductID&gt;
               &lt;DCRLotNumber&gt;120019xxxx&lt;/DCRLotNumber&gt;
               &lt;/DCRtitleblock&gt;
               &lt;/DCRHeader&gt;
               &lt;DCRFooter1&gt;
               &lt;DCRdisposition&gt;
               &lt;Disposition&gt;pending&lt;/Disposition&gt;
               &lt;DispositionedBy&gt;mxm&lt;/DispositionedBy&gt;
               &lt;InspectionDate&gt;
               &lt;date&gt;200801281628&lt;/date&gt;
               &lt;/InspectionDate&gt;
               &lt;/DCRdisposition&gt;
               &lt;/DCRFooter1&gt;
               &lt;DCRFooter2&gt;
               &lt;DCRApproval&gt;
               &lt;DCRPEapproval&gt;
               &lt;ProductEngineer&gt;David B. Engineer&lt;/ProductEngineer&gt;
               &lt;date&gt;10/2/03&lt;/date&gt;
               &lt;/DCRPEapproval&gt;
               &lt;DCRIEapproval&gt;
               &lt;InspectionEngineer&gt;Eric E. Inspectionguru &lt;/InspectionEngineer&gt;
               &lt;date&gt;10/1/03&lt;/date&gt;
               &lt;/DCRIEapproval&gt;
               &lt;DCRCCapproval&gt;
               &lt;CCReview&gt;I. M. Incontrol&lt;/CCReview&gt;
               &lt;date&gt;10/2/03&lt;/date&gt;
               &lt;/DCRCCapproval&gt;
               &lt;DCRDocumentNumber&gt;OO-CG-007&lt;/DCRDocumentNumber&gt;
               &lt;DCRRevision&gt;B&lt;/DCRRevision&gt;
               &lt;/DCRApproval&gt;
               &lt;/DCRFooter2&gt;
            </div>
            <div class="para e320">There is a similar block of data for the Picture Page. The information
               collected in this metadata appears in the PDF rendition of the DCR
               in the blocks at the top and bottom of the Picture Page and the first
               page of the DCR body (Figs. 2a and 2b).
            </div>
            <div class="para e321">As we have created a workflow that processes the DCR template,
               we have added the other metadata in ways that are transparent to the
               user. It is not necessary even to display this information, since
               it is not expected on the paper forms we are emulating. Nonetheless,
               we are currently appending it to the merged DCR and rendering it in
               the PDF output, largely as a convenience to ourselves in testing.
               This metadata falls into two categories: information about the version
               of the process and information tracking the application of the process. 
            </div>
            <div class="para e322">Information about the process begins with the versions of the
               DTDs and XSLT stylesheets employed. 
            </div>
            <div class="para e323">In the case of the DTDs, version information begins as a parameter
               entity and is carried by an attribute of the document element. As
               a result, the DCR procedure created by an IE carries its version data,
               and this is in turn recorded in the merged DCRs that result from execution
               of the procedure.
            </div>
            <div class="programlisting e324" xml:space="preserve">&lt;DCR doc_class_level="U" DTD_version="0.9" status="draft"&gt;</div>
            <div class="para e325"> The corresponding version data about the data-collection DTD
               similarly appears in the XML data generated by the online process.
               In the merged DCR, this latter version data can be copied by the XSLT
               into the metadata section appended to the original DCR.
            </div>
            <div class="para e326">Version information about the XSLT begins as variables in the
               stylesheets, and this is written by the transforms into “meta” elements
               in the HTML/JSP files and attributes on the metadata appendix of the
               merged XML DCR. Because the HTML/JSP files are transient generated
               objects and not archival artifacts, their metadata is less important
               than that of the XML files. Nonetheless, we have the information available
               in case we need it. We do write the name of the Web form into the
               data-collection file and copy that into the DCR.
            </div>
            <div class="para e327">In addition to version information, we also capture data about
               each “inspection event.” In traditional processing, each inspection
               of a part is a unique event. If the part passes the inspection (or
               is granted a “deviation” waiver from some portion of the specification
               being tested), a report is completed and sent to auditing. If the
               part fails, it is either “killed” or sent for rework, and the form
               being completed is discarded without becoming a report. Because the
               overall process for electronic histories is still in early phases
               of investigation, we have not constrained ourselves to this model.
               Instead, our process allows for checkpointing a version of the collected
               data and reopening the form for revision, starting with the saved
               inspection data. Even if the future workflow continues the current
               model of each inspection being unique, the ability to reopen a file
               allows the inspector or auditor to correct errors in data entry. In
               any event, we record data from each time the file is opened, including
               the person opening the file, a timestamp, and the disposition of the
               inspection (whether the part has been accepted or has failed). This
               data, together with other metadata from the process flow, is accumulated
               in the “Inspection Record” appended to the DCR.
            </div>
            <div class="programlisting e328" xml:space="preserve"> &lt;LotInspection&gt;
               &lt;InspectionData&gt;
               &lt;FormID formNumber="OO-CG-007" formRevision="A" formType="DCR"/&gt;
               &lt;InspectionID iteration="1" lotNumber="1200-19-0000"
               number="4" time="2008-01-10 07:17:24.015-0500" user="george"/&gt;
               &lt;FormPage&gt;pp1200-19.jspx&lt;/FormPage&gt;
               &lt;/InspectionData&gt;
               &lt;InspectionHistory&gt;
               &lt;InspectionEvent iteration="1" lotNumber="1200-19-0000"
               number="1" time="2008-01-10 07:17:24.015-0500" user="george"/&gt;
               &lt;InspectionEvent iteration="1" lotNumber="1200-19-0000"
               number="2" time="2008-01-10 07:17:24.015-0500" user="george"/&gt;
               &lt;InspectionEvent iteration="1" lotNumber="1200-19-0000"
               number="3" time="2008-01-10 07:17:24.015-0500" user="george"/&gt;
               &lt;InspectionEvent iteration="1" lotNumber="1200-19-0000"
               number="4" time="2008-01-10 07:17:24.015-0500" user="george"/&gt;
               &lt;/InspectionHistory&gt;
               &lt;LotNumber&gt;1200-19-0000&lt;/LotNumber&gt;
               &lt;InspectionDisposition state="pending" time="200801281628" user="jake"/&gt;
               &lt;/LotInspection&gt;
            </div>
            <div class="para e329">The result of this metadata flow is flexible: a completed DCR
               contains a history of its creation, and all the metadata, whether
               from the old or new workflows, can be printed and is accessible to
               further XML processing. Information flows from both the traditional
               approval system and all the steps in online processing, being accumulated
               in a merged XML file and rendered in PDF for paper records (Fig. 4).
               <div class="figure e330">
                  <div class="mediaobject e331">
                     <div class="imageobject e332">
                        <div class="metaBox e333"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e527').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e527" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                              &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e333'
                                 </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol1/graphics/Mason01/Mason01-006.jpg'
                                 </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='jpg'
                                 </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='100%'
                                 </span>
                              &gt;
                              
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="caption e334">
                        <div class="para e335">Fig. 4. Information Flow in document processing.</div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>A certified part is thus wrapped in many layers of data and
               metadata, all of which has the potential for electronic retrieval
               and further processing (Fig. 5).
               <div class="figure e336">
                  <div class="mediaobject e337">
                     <div class="imageobject e338">
                        <div class="metaBox e339"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e535').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e535" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                              &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e339'
                                 </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol1/graphics/Mason01/Mason01-007.jpg'
                                 </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='jpg'
                                 </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='100%'
                                 </span>
                              &gt;
                              
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div class="caption e340">
                        <div class="para e341">Fig. 5. An Onion of Documents and Metadata: a part certified</div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="para e342">The NDT Report is a much simpler document than the DCR. It is
               usually a single page with form metadata at the top and bottom. Onto
               this form several different kinds of body can be put for a variety
               of tests, such as visual inspection of welds, tests with fluorescent
               dyes to reveal cracks, and X-rays. The body information is generally
               simple, to capture the identifiers of the parts being tested and whether
               the parts pass or fail the test. The general workflow mirrors that
               for the DCR, though there is less collecting of approval metadata.
               The flow of metadata through the processing system is nonetheless
               similar to that for the DCR.
            </div>
         </div>
      </div><a name="WorkflowstoComeANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e343">
         <div class="title e344">Workflows to Come</div>
         <div class="para e345">The DCR and NDT are only two of many tests done in the overall
            certification process for Y-12's products. Materials may be sent for
            chemical, isotopic, and metallographic tests. Large assemblies undergo
            extensive X-ray analysis. (We have just installed a 9–MeV linear accelerator
            for examination of large structures.) DOE has mandated that many tests
            perform “electronic data capture” (EDC), though what that means is
            in some cases still evolving. In the case of radiography, we are being
            pushed to new electronic technology simply because of the dwindling
            supply of suitable X-ray film. Early EDC was done in stand-alone processes,
            with data captured in conventional databases. Essentially all machine-measured
            data is now collected in a central plant electronic data collection
            system. The proposed data packaging project will look at storing these
            data in XML-based packages. After years of hesitancy, there is a growing
            awareness that XML will probably turn out to be a way of binding together
            all the disparate processes and collections of data in the certification
            of our processes.
         </div>
         <div class="para e346">We are just now beginning to look at the problems of aligning
            the metadata about XML documents and processes with actual metadata
            about test conditions and pointers to test data from instruments.
            We are looking at HDF (Hierarchical Data Format, http://www.hdfgroup.org/why_hdf/index.html)
            as a means for managing instrument data, and we are looking at extracting
            HDF metadata into XML.
         </div>
         <div class="para e347">This project is still in an early state. We have created XML
            applications for both DCR and NDT, but the planning for the metadata
            is incomplete, particularly metadata about test results. We are just
            beginning to move the applications into the hands of the end users.
            By the time of the Balisage conference, however, we expect to have
            moved our environment from the test system to one that will be available
            in a few actual production areas. At that point, we shall begin working
            with IEs to create pilot inspection forms to be used in parallel with
            paper processing early in the coming fiscal year. If this project
            is successful, we shall expand it to more certification and report
            types, and we hope to move towards fully electronic records of Y-12's
            products.
         </div>
      </div><a name="ReferencesANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="bibliography e348">
         <div class="title e349">References</div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e350" xml:id="mason97" xreflabel="Mason 1997">Mason, James
            David. “SGML Metadata for Nuclear Weapons Information,” presented
            at 
            <div class="emphasis e351" role="ital">SGML 1997</div>, Washington, DC, December
            8, 1997.
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>