<div id="mainContainerTOC">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTOC" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTOC').toggle('1000');">Table of Content</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTOC" style="display:none;">
      <div class="headedContainerTOC">
         <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#SecuredManagementofOnlineXMLDocumentServicesthroughStructurePreservingAsymmetricEncryptionANCHOR" name="SecuredManagementofOnlineXMLDocumentServicesthroughStructurePreservingAsymmetricEncryptionTOC">Secured Management of Online XML Document Services through Structure Preserving Asymmetric
               Encryption</a></div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#IntroductionANCHOR" name="IntroductionTOC">Introduction</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#Donotdecryptdocuments:makeoperatorscompatible!ANCHOR" name="Donotdecryptdocuments:makeoperatorscompatible!TOC">Do not decrypt documents: make operators compatible!</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#EncryptionawaretransformationofXMLoperatorsANCHOR" name="EncryptionawaretransformationofXMLoperatorsTOC">Encryption aware transformation of XML operators</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#NoveltyANCHOR" name="NoveltyTOC">Novelty</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#DiscussionANCHOR" name="DiscussionTOC">Discussion</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#RelatedWorkANCHOR" name="RelatedWorkTOC">Related Work</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ANCHOR" name="TOC"></a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ReferencesANCHOR" name="ReferencesTOC">References</a></div>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerTERMS">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTERMS" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTERMS').toggle('1000')">Index of Terms</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTERMS" style="display:none;">
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">a</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">an encryption aware transformation</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Administration Guide</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">August 2 - 5, 2011</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">b</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">c</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Configuring Database Indexes</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">d</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">doi: 10.1109/IDEAS.2006.39</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">doi: 10.1145/1099554.1099575</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Document Rewriting and Querying</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Document versioning</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Document Indexation</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">e</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">f</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">fully homomorphic encryption</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">g</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">h</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Homomorphic Encryption</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">i</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">j</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">jean-yves.vion-dury@xeroxlabs.com</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Jean-Yves</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">k</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">l</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">m</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">n</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">o</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Optimal Asymmetric Encryption Padding</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">OAEP Reconsidered</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">p</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Public-key Cryptography</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">q</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Querying Encrypted XML Documents</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Queriable Hierarchical Data,</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">r</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">RSA</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">s</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">symmetric keys</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">stricto sensu</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">SCAN</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Symmetric-Key Algorithm</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Senior Scientist</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">t</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">u</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">v</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Validation Engine</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">VaultMate</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Vion-Dury</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">x</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">xmlns</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">xml:base</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">xml:space</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">xml:id</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">XML Encryption Syntax and Processing</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">y</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">z</div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerIML"><a name="SecuredManagementofOnlineXMLDocumentServicesthroughStructurePreservingAsymmetricEncryptionANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="article e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3">
      <div class="title e1">Secured Management of Online XML Document Services through Structure Preserving Asymmetric
         Encryption
      </div>
      <div class="info e2">
         <div class="confgroup e3">
            <div class="conftitle e4">Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</div>
            <div class="confdates e5">August 2 - 5, 2011</div>
         </div>
         <div class="abstract e6">
            <div class="para e7">Externalizing document management is a problem when individual or corporate
               privacy is to be ensured. Provided that the decryption key is not known from service
               side, pure storage/archiving of encrypted documents is highly secure, but of poor
               interest as no operation can be performed on hosted data. Thus, current document
               management systems offer restricted privacy mechanisms, roughly based on secured
               communication channels and sometimes encrypted storage. However, many value-added
               processing operations require decrypting the document, and no formal guaranty is
               granted regarding the safety of system behaviors. As an example of known issue,
               there is the problem of data remanence (persisting information on disk after file
               system deletion), bugs or viruses acting on various level of the software
               architecture. This paper describes a method to allow restricted (but yet
               meaningful) ways of processing encrypted XML documents without needing decryption
               phase. The encryption process we propose allows isomorphic encryption of data (XML
               document owned by customers) and operator transformations (verification and
               transformation operated by the Service Provider) in such a way that full secrecy is
               ensured simply because the decoding key is not known by the Service Provider. Once
               transformed, operators can handle encrypted documents with equivalent results up to
               the decryption operation.
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e8">
            <div class="personname e9">
               <div class="firstname e10">Jean-Yves</div>
               <div class="surname e11">Vion-Dury</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e12">
               <div class="para e13"> Jean-Yves Vion-Dury holds an CS engineering degree from the "Conservatoire
                  National des Arts et Métiers, Paris" (1993) and graduated with a PhD in CS from
                  Université Joseph Fourier, Grenoble in 1999. He has been working at Xerox
                  Research Centre Europe (in Grenoble, France) since 1995, as a research
                  scientist; he has also been on a two year sabbatical with Vincent Quint's team
                  at INRIA in 2002-2004. His research interests relate to various aspect of XML
                  including models, the impact of standards, validation/transformation languages
                  and architectures, with theoretical background in programming languages,
                  compilation, type systems and formal logics. 
               </div>
               <div class="para e14">Jean-Yves was Program Chair of DocEng (ACM Document Engineering Symposium ) in
                  2004, is member of its Program Committee since 2003, and member of its Steering
                  Committee since 2005. 
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e15">
               <div class="jobtitle e16">Senior Scientist</div>
               <div class="orgname e17">Xerox Research Centre Europe</div>
            </div>
            <div class="email e18">jean-yves.vion-dury@xeroxlabs.com</div>
         </div>
         <div class="legalnotice e19">
            <div class="para e20">Copyright © 2011 Xerox.  All rights reserved.</div>
         </div>
      </div><a name="IntroductionANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e21">
         <div class="title e22">Introduction</div>
         <div class="para e23">This paper describes a method to allow restricted (but yet meaningful) ways of
            processing encrypted XML documents without needing decryption phase. The encryption
            process we propose allows isomorphic encryption of data (XML document owned by
            customers) and operator transformations (verification and transformation operated
            by the
            Service Provider) in such a way that full secrecy is ensured simply because the decoding
            key is not known by the Service Provider. Once transformed, operators can handle
            encrypted documents with equivalent results up to the decryption operation.
         </div>
         <div class="para e24">Nowadays, when a customer wants an external service provider to host and manage
            confidential documents, he has to fully trust them, their information system and
            internal policies. The confidential documents may be transmitted to the hosting system
            over a secured channel using encryption to protect the sensitive information from
            any
            spying software potentially able to intercept and interpret the data.
         </div>
         <div class="para e25">However, an XML document, once encrypted using standard approaches , is like an opaque
            and flat bit packet on which only two basic operations can be undertaken: integrity
            checking and decryption 
            <div class="popupBox e26">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e43').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e43').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e43" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e27">The W3C recommendation describes encryption processing
                        
                        <div class="xref e28" linkend="xmlEnc"></div> in a way that preserve compatibility with XML
                        requirement, but doesn't change the fundamental issue we address.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>.
            Therefore, once hosted, the document must be decrypted in order to be able to offer
            some
            more complex processing such as those involved in basic services, e.g. indexation,
            validation and transformation. And in order to decrypt, the service provider must
            share
            the decryption key with the customer, which is a risk against which nobody can guaranty
            full protection (see 
            <div class="xref e29" linkend="SCAN"></div> and 
            <div class="xref e30" linkend="VaultMate"></div> for examples
            of document services in this area today ; note that both use a symmetric ciphering
            method 
            <div class="xref e31" linkend="SKA"></div> which requires for the service provider owning the
            customer's private key, and naturally, performing decryption when needed by the
            system).
         </div>
      </div><a name="Donotdecryptdocuments:makeoperatorscompatible!ANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e32">
         <div class="title e33">Do not decrypt documents: make operators compatible!</div>
         <div class="para e34">Our contribution applies on structured documents (typically XML, but any similar
            approaches could be addressed by this method) where an attributed tree-like structure
            captures the syntax and semantic of the data. In XML, it is commonly understood that
            textual content is mainly stored in the leaves (the so called text nodes) whereas
            meta-information such as presentation style are conveyed by namespaces, tag names
            and
            additional attributes-values pairs.
         </div>
         <div class="para e35">According to this, we propose first to encrypt the content of the document (textual
            leaves) using a private key, only known by the document owner, and to encrypt the
            structural part (tag names, namespaces and attribute-value pairs) through an asymmetric
            encryption mechanism (see 
            <div class="xref e36" linkend="PKC"></div> for a general presentation) in such a
            way that the resulting document still complies with XML lexical constraints (in other
            words, XML wellformedness property remains ensured). Beyond preserving better isolation
            between the two cryptographic subsystems, private key encryption comes with fast,
            possibly stream based, ciphering algorithms, with obvious application in large document
            processing.
         </div>
         <div class="para e37">In asymmetric encryption schemes, a public key allows encryption, whereas decryption
            can only be performed thanks to a secret (private) key.
         </div>
         <div class="para e38">The Service provider may use the public key in order to transform its operators in
            such a way that they can be adapted to operate directly on the encrypted documents.
            The
            central idea of our proposal is here: applying 
            <div class="emphasis e39" role="ital">an encryption
               aware transformation
            </div> on the operators, so that they become compatible
            with the encrypted instances. In other word, rather that decrypting the customer's
            documents in order to process them, we propose to adapt the operators in order to
            make
            it possible for them to operate on encrypted document. More precisely, operators are
            transformed using a public encryption key as parameter. Obviously, not all operators
            can
            be used this way, but only those that do not use textual content but only structural
            information (which still covers a large class of practical applications for structured
            document processing).
         </div>
         <div class="para e40">This way, the customer performs the structure-preserving encryption with a public
            key,
            and the textual content encryption with a private key they will never communicate.
            The
            composite-encryption algorithm is implemented and furnished by the Service Provider,
            and
            is run by the customers in their protected space. The resulting document can be sent
            to
            the Service Provider together with the public key, without particular precaution.
            The
            provider can archive the ciphered document, together with the public key, and moreover,
            will use the latter to transform the relevant operators in order to operate on the
            customer's documents. The customer data privacy/confidentiality is not put at risk
            by
            the provider software, communication channels and systems.
         </div>
         <div class="para e41">When required, the documents resulting from remote operations (validation reports,
            transformation products…) can be sent back to the customer, who will be able to fully
            decrypt them locally through his two private keys.
         </div>
         <div class="para e42">The figure below illustrates the composite encryption process:</div>
         <div class="figure e43">
            <div class="mediaobject e44">
               <div class="imageobject e45">
                  <div class="metaBox e46"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e80').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e80" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e46'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol7/graphics/Vion-Dury01/Vion-Dury01-001.png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='60%'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="itemizedlist e47">
            <div class="listitem e48">
               <div class="para e49">ε
                  <div class="subscript e50">1</div>(β
                  <div class="subscript e51">1</div>) represents an asymmetric
                  encryption process (applied to the structural part of the document) using a
                  public key β
                  <div class="subscript e52">1</div>.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="listitem e53">
               <div class="para e54">ε 
                  <div class="subscript e55">2</div>(α
                  <div class="subscript e56">2</div>) represents the symmetric
                  encryption process (applied to textual content and attribute values) using a
                  private key α
                  <div class="subscript e57">2</div>.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="listitem e58">
               <div class="para e59">ε (β
                  <div class="subscript e60">1</div>, α
                  <div class="subscript e61">2</div>) represents the
                  combined encryption process over an XML document.
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e62">Essentially, this figure expresses the isomorphic properties of our encoding: typing
            properties of the object are preserved by ε
            (β
            <div class="subscript e63">1</div>, α
            <div class="subscript e64">2</div>) , so that some standard
            XML analysis tools can operate before and after encryption as well.
         </div>
         <div class="note e65">
            <div class="para e66">We recall that symmetric encryption ε and decryption
               ε
               <div class="superscript e67">-1</div> obey to the following laws (here 
               <div class="emphasis e68" role="bital">α</div> is the secret
               private key and 
               <div class="emphasis e69" role="bold">x</div> the message):
            </div>
            <div class="table e70">
               <div class="caption e71">
                  <div class="para e72">
                     <div class="emphasis e73" role="bold">symmetric keys</div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="tr e74">
                  <div class="td e75"></div>
                  <div class="td e76"></div>
                  <div class="td e77">ε
                     <div class="superscript e78">-1</div>(
                     <div class="emphasis e79" role="bital">α</div> , ε(
                     <div class="emphasis e80" role="bital">α</div> , 
                     <div class="emphasis e81" role="bold">x</div>)) = 
                     <div class="emphasis e82" role="bold">x</div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="tr e83">
                  <div class="td e84">
                     <div class="emphasis e85" role="bital">α</div> ≠ 
                     <div class="emphasis e86" role="bital">α'</div>
                  </div>
                  <div class="td e87"> ⇒ </div>
                  <div class="td e88"> ε
                     <div class="superscript e89">-1</div>(
                     <div class="emphasis e90" role="bital">α'</div> , ε(
                     <div class="emphasis e91" role="bital">α</div> , 
                     <div class="emphasis e92" role="bold">x</div>)) ≠ 
                     <div class="emphasis e93" role="bold">x</div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="para e94">Similarly, for asymmetric encryption functions where (
               <div class="emphasis e95" role="bital">α</div> is the private key, and 
               <div class="emphasis e96" role="bital">β</div>
               is the public key):
            </div>
            <div class="table e97">
               <div class="tr e98">
                  <div class="td e99"></div>
                  <div class="td e100"></div>
                  <div class="td e101"> ε
                     <div class="superscript e102">-1</div>(
                     <div class="emphasis e103" role="bital">α</div> ,
                     ε(
                     <div class="emphasis e104" role="bital">β</div> , 
                     <div class="emphasis e105" role="bold">x</div>)) = 
                     <div class="emphasis e106" role="bold">x</div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="tr e107">
                  <div class="td e108"> 
                     <div class="emphasis e109" role="bital">α</div> ≠ 
                     <div class="emphasis e110" role="bital">α'</div> 
                  </div>
                  <div class="td e111"> ⇒ </div>
                  <div class="td e112">   ε
                     <div class="superscript e113">-1</div>(
                     <div class="emphasis e114" role="bital">α'</div> , ε(
                     <div class="emphasis e115" role="bital">β</div> , 
                     <div class="emphasis e116" role="bold">x</div>)) ≠ 
                     <div class="emphasis e117" role="bold">x</div> 
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="para e118">Keys 
               <div class="emphasis e119" role="bital">α,β</div>, are integers whose valuation space is so huge, that it is practically extremely
               hard for an attacker to guess their value. These laws just capture in an
               abstract way the reversibility of encryption and the sensitivity of underlying algorithms
               to key
               information.
            </div>
         </div>
      </div><a name="EncryptionawaretransformationofXMLoperatorsANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e120">
         <div class="title e121">Encryption aware transformation of XML operators</div>
         <div class="para e122">The composite encryption we proposed preserves lexical and logical structure. It is
            an
            algorithm that encrypts tag names (and attribute names) in such a way that all XML
            lexical constraints remain satisfied, but do not change the tree structure.
         </div>
         <div class="para e123">We used in our experiments the combination of an RSA based asymmetric encryption
            applied separately to namespace prefix and local tag/attribute names (general purpose
            XML attributes such as 
            <div class="emphasis e124" role="ital">xmlns</div>, 
            <div class="emphasis e125" role="ital">xml:base</div>, 
            
            <div class="emphasis e126" role="ital">xml:space</div>, 
            
            <div class="emphasis e127" role="ital">xml:id</div> are not encrypted, in order to
            allow standard behavior of XML processors) . Then our encryption algorithm translates
            the result into a base16 encoded sequences of ASCII characters and substitutes the
            new
            names to the old ones. The algorithm process all tags and attributes recursively over
            the tree structure.
         </div>
         <div class="para e128">Figure 
            <div class="xref e129" linkend="ex1"></div> is an example of such a transformation (note that content encryption has not
            been applied here for illustration purpose). The image shows the original document
            (the
            specialized DocBook XML schema used for the Balisage conference proceedings...), and
            the
            second one below shows the same document after the structure preserving encryption
            (for
            clarity, textual content was not encrypted using symmetric ciphering algorithm).
         </div>
         <div class="para e130"> We propose now to examine 4 fundamental classes of document operators that
            can be tailored to process structure preserving encrypted documents. 
         </div>
         <div class="orderedlist e131">
            <div class="listitem e132">
               <div class="para e133">
                  <div class="emphasis e134" role="ital">Validation Engine</div>
               </div>
               <div class="para e135">Typically, a tree grammar schema can be automatically modified by changing
                  element names, according to the public encryption key.
               </div>
               <div class="para e136">For instance, the following grammar:</div>
               <div class="table e137">
                  <div class="tr e138">
                     <div class="td e139">Html</div>
                     <div class="td e140">→</div>
                     <div class="td e141">html [ Header Body]</div>
                  </div>
                  <div class="tr e142">
                     <div class="td e143">Header</div>
                     <div class="td e144">→</div>
                     <div class="td e145">header [ Base? Title? Meta* (Link | Script)*]</div>
                  </div>
                  <div class="tr e146">
                     <div class="td e147">Body</div>
                     <div class="td e148">→</div>
                     <div class="td e149">body [ ... ]</div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="para e150">would become</div>
               <div class="table e151">
                  <div class="tr e152">
                     <div class="td e153">Html</div>
                     <div class="td e154">→</div>
                     <div class="td e155">_012A321B839B167C [ Header Body]</div>
                  </div>
                  <div class="tr e156">
                     <div class="td e157">Header</div>
                     <div class="td e158">→</div>
                     <div class="td e159">_2842FA3D2B8317A8 [ Base? Title? Meta* (Link | Script)*]</div>
                  </div>
                  <div class="tr e160">
                     <div class="td e161">Body</div>
                     <div class="td e162">→</div>
                     <div class="td e163">_3A78B91537E65F45 [ ... ]</div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="para e164">provided that, for a given encryption key β , 
                  ε
                  <div class="subscript e165">1</div>(β "html")     = _012A321B839B167C ,
                  ε
                  <div class="subscript e166">1</div>(β "header") = _2842FA3D2B8317A8 and
                  ε
                  <div class="subscript e167">1</div>(β "body") = _3A78B91537E65F45
                  
               </div>
               <div class="para e168">If the new labels comply with the inherent lexical constraints of the
                  formalism (in this case XML), then the corresponding recognition automaton can
                  be derived in the standard way in order to check the validity of the encrypted
                  document. RelaxNG, for instance, is a validation standard focused on structural
                  validation, although some extensions allow dealing with attribute or textual
                  content. In latter cases, the transcription cannot be achieved 
                  <div class="emphasis e169" role="ital">stricto sensu</div> (no access to encrypted textual
                  content), but we argue that it is always feasible to derive from such grammars a
                  more general schema that only captures the structural information (this can even
                  be automated for the general case).
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="listitem e170">
               <div class="para e171">
                  <div class="emphasis e172" role="ital">Document Rewriting and Querying</div>
               </div>
               <div class="para e173">Many such transformations do not have to deal with textual content. As an
                  example, a table of content construction, outline extraction, link extraction,
                  tags reorganization …
               </div>
               <div class="para e174">For instance, the following sample rule from an illustrative tree rewriting system</div>
               <div class="table e175">
                  <div class="tr e176">
                     <div class="td e177">title[ p[X] p[Y] ]</div>
                     <div class="td e178">→</div>
                     <div class="td e179">title[ p[X Y] ]</div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="para e180">Can be transformed like this</div>
               <div class="table e181">
                  <div class="tr e182">
                     <div class="td e183">_123E456A8421F745 [  _164C3812A7945B14 [X] _164C3812A7945B14[Y] ]</div>
                     <div class="td e184">→</div>
                     <div class="td e185">_123E456A8421F745[ _164C3812A7945B14[X Y] ]</div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="para e186">provided that, for a given encryption key β , 
                  ε
                  <div class="subscript e187">1</div>(β "title")     = _123E456A8421F745 ,
                  ε
                  <div class="subscript e188">1</div>(β "p") = _164C3812A7945B14 
                  
               </div>
               <div class="para e189">Regarding standard technologies such as XSLT or XQuery, they are based on
                  XPath to capture structural information. In our prototype, we rewrite structural
                  XPath expressions in order to encrypt tag names and attribute names. Structural
                  XPath expressions do not use tests on attribute and textual values. Figures 
                  <div class="xref e190" linkend="ex3"></div>
                  and 
                  <div class="xref e191" linkend="ex4"></div> show an XSLT stylesheet designed for computing DocBook outlines, before
                  and after transformation. Note that XPath expressions have been rewritten
                  according to tag name ciphering.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="listitem e192">
               <div class="para e193">
                  <div class="emphasis e194" role="ital">Document versioning</div>
               </div>
               <div class="para e195">These services are based of Tree diff algorithms, based on structural analysis
                  of tree node hierarchy and on node comparison. They are therefore compatible
                  with our encoding proposal, since they do not address diff analysis of original textual
                  content.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="listitem e196">
               <div class="para e197">
                  
                  <div class="emphasis e198" role="ital">Document Indexation</div>
                  
               </div>
               <div class="para e199">These algorithms relies on various techniques, most importantly using
                  structural information (see eXist structural indexes 
                  <div class="xref e200" linkend="eXist"></div>, or Apache‟s Xindice
                  
                  <div class="xref e201" linkend="Xindices"></div>) that can be handled using the technique we propose.
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div><a name="NoveltyANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e202">
         <div class="title e203">Novelty</div>
         <div class="para e204">The problem of authorizing general arithmetic computation on ciphered data has been
            coined
            as 
            <div class="emphasis e205" role="ital">fully homomorphic encryption</div> 
            <div class="xref e206" linkend="homoEnc"></div>, and has been the
            holy grail of cryptologists for decades. The area is quite active recently, but is
            certainly not mature enough to find practical applications before a long time especially
            because the operators are of algebraic nature (very low level and generic: addition,
            multiplication, subtraction and division) rather than algorithmic.
         </div>
         <div class="para e207">The related work section below discusses existing approaches in the field of XML
            databases. In the best case, the authors propose very specific index construction
            algorithms that only allows simplified query over encrypted documents (see 
            <div class="xref e208" linkend="surveyQEncrypt"></div>, 
            <div class="xref e209" linkend="semCrypt"></div>). Our approach, much broader
            and simple, enable four major operations: transformation, validation, versioning and
            indexing, by using restricted but standardized technologies (XPath, XSLT, XQuery,
            RelaxNG…). More significantly, all proposals we examined so far in the literature
            made
            use of symmetric encryption. It just means that the provider must share the private
            key
            with the customer (therefore, representing a potential security hole) or that
            encryption/decryption operation can be done exclusively from the client side.
         </div>
      </div><a name="DiscussionANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e210">
         <div class="title e211">Discussion</div>
         <div class="para e212">Encrypting tag names may raise a safety issue due to the low entropy level of XML
            vocabulary, especially when the target namespace is known or guessed by an attacker.
            For
            instance, if the code breaker knows that the document is using the HTML namespace,
            he
            could try breaking the code using “html” as the plaintext input of the encrypted top
            level tag. Indeed, this approach is particularly vulnerable to (so-called) chosen
            plaintext attacks.
            A solution is using optimal asymmetric encryption padding  
            
            <div class="xref e213" linkend="optimalEncPadding"></div> 
            <div class="xref e214" linkend="optimalAssymEnc"></div> and its more recent
            amelioration 
            <div class="xref e215" linkend="OEAP"></div>. We have indeed implemented this latter approach, consisting of using two
            ancillary secure Hash functions (SHA and MD5 in our prototype) and a random pattern
            in
            order to increase the entropy of input message.
         </div>
         <div class="para e216">Our prototype also revealed that, if working with long keys for reaching very high
            level of safety, the tag/attribute names are transformed in very long labels, as
            compared to original ones. However, our prototype did not exhibit any problem with
            respect to this side effect, and runtime and memory performances are almost not
            impacted 
            
            <div class="popupBox e217">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e431').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e431').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e431" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e218">We indeed used a hash table to memorize the encrypted code for recurrent
                        tag/attribute names.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>.
         </div>
         <div class="para e219">During the exchange of documents between the client and the provider, one could
            imagine applying a supplemental global encryption using a symmetric scheme with a
            private key that would be shared between the two parties, thanks to a standard secured
            key exchange protocol. Of course this key would be different than the private key
            used
            by the client to encode the document content, and would provide a supplemental security
            barrier to communication based attacks (this can be done e.g. through the standard
            HTTPS
            protocol and SSL libraries).
         </div>
      </div><a name="RelatedWorkANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e220">
         <div class="title e221">Related Work</div>
         <div class="para e222">In 
            <div class="xref e223" linkend="queriableHD"></div>
            
            <div class="xref e224" linkend="queriableHDpaper"></div>, Mittal and Srivastava propose a somehow similar
            approach. However, the authors clearly encode the hierarchical structure into a
            distinct, specific data structure 
            <div class="popupBox e225">
               <div class="popupLabel" onmouseover="$('#d1e446').show('1000');" onmouseout="$('#d1e446').hide('1000');">[ footnote ]</div>
               <div id="d1e446" style="display: none;">
                  <div class="footnote">
                     <div class="para e226">an RSA encryption (asymmetric scheme 
                        <div class="xref e227" linkend="RSA"></div>) is
                        applied on both the content and the structure with a common key, leading to a
                        less secure protection since cracking the code through attacks on structure will
                        give direct access to the content.
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>. As a consequence, standard XML tools cannot be used, since the links
            between structure and content are managed externally. The document is no longer an
            XML
            document after the encryption and compression operations proposed in this approach.
            Using standard language is an important plus, as the provider may propose to run
            customer made style sheets on customer data. In addition, using standard methodology
            is a major
            advantage to develop transformations and validation schemas, among others.
         </div>
         <div class="para e228">Various approaches have been explored in literature to secure documents hosted by
            an
            outsourcing service, especially in the field of XML databases. Existing proposals
            are
            organized around minimizing decryption operations (for obvious response time and CPU
            cost saving; and also for security reasons too, when minimization is based on document
            partitioning 
            <div class="xref e229" linkend="queryingEnc"></div>) or preparation of specific indexes to allows
            restricted queries on encrypted documents 
            <div class="xref e230" linkend="SecuringXML"></div>
            
            <div class="xref e231" linkend="surveyQEncrypt"></div>. Other studies focused on protecting information during
            encrypted exchanges between the service provider and the client, preventing statistical
            analysis based on expected frequencies of query terms 
            <div class="xref e232" linkend="EfficientSecureQuery"></div>. However, our approach does not need to focus on
            communication, since transformation work is done locally on secured documents.
         </div>
      </div><a name="ANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="appendix e233">
         <div class="title e234"></div>
         <div class="figure e235" xml:id="ex1">
            <div class="mediaobject e236">
               <div class="imageobject e237">
                  <div class="metaBox e238"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e467').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e467" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e238'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol7/graphics/Vion-Dury01/Vion-Dury01-002.png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='80%'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="caption e239">
               <div class="para e240">Input document (excerpt) </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="figure e241" xml:id="ex2">
            <div class="mediaobject e242">
               <div class="imageobject e243">
                  <div class="metaBox e244"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e474').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e474" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e244'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol7/graphics/Vion-Dury01/Vion-Dury01-003.png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='112%'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="caption e245">
               <div class="para e246">Structural encryption: Input document with encrypted tags</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="figure e247" xml:id="ex3">
            <div class="mediaobject e248">
               <div class="imageobject e249">
                  <div class="metaBox e250"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e482').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e482" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e250'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol7/graphics/Vion-Dury01/Vion-Dury01-004.png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='60%'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="caption e251">
               <div class="para e252">Operator: The XSL stylesheet to be applied to input document</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="figure e253" xml:id="ex4">
            <div class="mediaobject e254">
               <div class="imageobject e255">
                  <div class="metaBox e256"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e489').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e489" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e256'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol7/graphics/Vion-Dury01/Vion-Dury01-005.png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='100%'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="caption e257">
               <div class="para e258">Encryption aware Operator: The XSL stylesheet customized thanks to the public
                  encryption key. This transformed style sheet is intended to be run on provider's
                  site.
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="figure e259" xml:id="ex5">
            <div class="mediaobject e260">
               <div class="imageobject e261">
                  <div class="metaBox e262"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e496').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e496" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e262'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol7/graphics/Vion-Dury01/Vion-Dury01-006.png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='85%'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="caption e263">
               <div class="para e264">The result of style sheet application on the fully encrypted input document (sent
                  back by the service provider)
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="figure e265" xml:id="ex6">
            <div class="mediaobject e266">
               <div class="imageobject e267">
                  <div class="metaBox e268"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e504').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e504" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e268'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol7/graphics/Vion-Dury01/Vion-Dury01-007.png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='png'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">width='60%'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="caption e269">
               <div class="para e270">The final result is obtained by decrypting both the structural part and the
                  content part thanks to the two secret keys. This operation is done locally by the
                  customer in a secured environment.
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div><a name="ReferencesANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="bibliography e271">
         <div class="title e272">References</div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e273" xml:id="SCAN" xreflabel="1">
            
            <div class="emphasis e274" role="ital">SCAN</div>, Trusted ICT Security Solution Provider.
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e275" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.scan-associates.net/product_securedoc.htm" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.scan-associates.net/product_securedoc.htm</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e276" xml:id="VaultMate" xreflabel="2">
            
            <div class="emphasis e277" role="ital">VaultMate</div>, Enterprise Privacy Solution.
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e278" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.vaultmate.com/features.php" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.vaultmate.com/features.php</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e279" xml:id="PKC" xreflabel="3">
            
            <div class="emphasis e280" role="ital">Public-key Cryptography</div>, Wikipedia.
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e281" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_key_encryption" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_key_encryption</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e282" xml:id="SKA" xreflabel="4">
            
            <div class="emphasis e283" role="ital">Symmetric-Key Algorithm</div>, Wikipedia.
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e284" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symmetric_key_algorithm" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symmetric_key_algorithm</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e285" xml:id="RSA" xreflabel="5">
            
            <div class="emphasis e286" role="ital">RSA</div>, Wikipedia.
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e287" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSA" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSA</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e288" xml:id="homoEnc" xreflabel="6">
            
            <div class="emphasis e289" role="ital">Homomorphic Encryption</div>, Wikipedia.
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e290" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homomorphic_encryption" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homomorphic_encryption</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e291" xml:id="optimalEncPadding" xreflabel="7">
            
            <div class="emphasis e292" role="ital">Optimal Asymmetric Encryption Padding</div>, Wikipedia.
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e293" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optimal_Asymmetric_Encryption_Padding" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optimal_Asymmetric_Encryption_Padding</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e294" xml:id="optimalAssymEnc" xreflabel="8">
            
            <div class="emphasis e295" role="ital">Optimal Asymmetric Encryption -- How to encrypt with
               RSA
            </div>, M. Bellare, P. Rogaway. Extended abstract in Advances in Cryptology -
            Eurocrypt '94 Proceedings, Lecture Notes in Computer Science Vol. 950, A. De Santis
            ed,
            Springer-Verlag, 1995. 
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e296" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www-cse.ucsd.edu/users/mihir/papers/oae.pdf" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www-cse.ucsd.edu/users/mihir/papers/oae.pdf</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e297" xml:id="OEAP" xreflabel="9">
            
            <div class="emphasis e298" role="ital">OAEP Reconsidered</div>, Victor Shoup. IBM Zurich Research
            Lab, Saumerstr. 4, 8803 Ruschlikon, Switzerland. September 18, 2001.
            (Full length version of the extended abstract in Proc. Crypto 2001)
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e299" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.shoup.net/papers/oaep.pdf" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.shoup.net/papers/oaep.pdf</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e300" xml:id="queryingEnc" xreflabel="10">
            
            <div class="emphasis e301" role="ital">Querying Encrypted XML Documents</div>, Ravi Chandra Jammalamadaka and Sharad Mehrotra.
            Proceedings of the 10th International Database Engineering and Applications Symposium,
            p.129-136, December 11-14, 2006
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e302" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/IDEAS.2006.39" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1109/IDEAS.2006.39</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e303" xml:id="FIPS-180" xreflabel="11">
            
            <div class="emphasis e304" role="ital">The FIPS 180-2 publication on Secure Hash Algorithms</div>, NIST.
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e305" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/fips/fips180-2/fips180-2.pdf" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/fips/fips180-2/fips180-2.pdf</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e306" xml:id="SecuringXML" xreflabel="12">
            
            <div class="emphasis e307" role="ital">Securing XML data in third-party distribution systems</div>,
            Barbara Carminati, Elena Ferrari, and Elisa Bertino. Proceedings of the 14th ACM
            international conference on Information and knowledge management (CIKM '05), New York,
            NY, USA. 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e308" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1099554.1099575" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">doi:
               10.1145/1099554.1099575
            </div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e309" xml:id="EfficientSecureQuery" xreflabel="13">
            
            <div class="emphasis e310" role="ital">Efficient Secure Query Evaluation over Encrypted XML Database</div>, 
            Hui Wang and Laks V.S. Lakshmanan.
            VLDB „06, September 12-15, 2006, Seoul, Korea.
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e311" xml:id="surveyQEncrypt" xreflabel="14">
            
            <div class="emphasis e312" role="ital">A Survey on Querying Encrypted XML Documents for Databases as a Service</div>,
            Ozan Ünay and Taflan Gündem.
            SIGMOD Record, March 2008 (Vol. 37, No. 1)
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e313" xml:id="eXist" xreflabel="15">
            
            <div class="emphasis e314" role="ital">Configuring Database Indexes</div>, eXist Open Source Native Database, 
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e315" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://exist.sourceforge.net/indexing.html#structuralidx" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://exist.sourceforge.net/indexing.html#structuralidx</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e316" xml:id="Xindices" xreflabel="16">
            
            <div class="emphasis e317" role="ital">Administration Guide</div>, Xindices 1.1, The Apache XML project,
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e318" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://xml.apache.org/xindice/1.1/guide-administrator.html#Managing+Indexes" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://xml.apache.org/xindice/1.1/guide-administrator.html#Managing+Indexes</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e319" xml:id="semCrypt" xreflabel="17">
            
            <div class="emphasis e320" role="ital">SemCrypt-Ensuring Privacy of Electronic Documents Through Semantic-Based Encrypted
               Query Processing
            </div>,
            M. Schrefl, K. Grun, and J. Dorn.
            Proceedings of the 21st International conference on Data Engineering Workshop, 2005,
            IEEE computer society.
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e321" xml:id="queriableHD" xreflabel="18">
            
            <div class="emphasis e322" role="ital">Queriable Hierarchical Data,</div>, Sumit Mittal and Biplav Srivastava.
            US patent, US 2008/0071814 A1
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e323" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.google.com/patents/about?id=1WuoAAAAEBAJ" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.google.com/patents/about?id=1WuoAAAAEBAJ</div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e324" xml:id="queriableHDpaper" xreflabel="19">
            
            <div class="emphasis e325" role="ital">Exploring Queriability of Encrypted and Compressed XML Data </div>,
            I. Elgedawy, B. Srivastava, and S. Mittal.
            24th International Symposium on Computer and Information Sciences, 14-16 Sept. 2009
            (ISCIS 2009). 
            doi: 
            <div class="biblioid doi e326">10.1109/ISCIS.2009.5291834</div> 
            
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e327" xml:id="xmlEnc" xreflabel="20">
            
            <div class="emphasis e328" role="ital">XML Encryption Syntax and Processing</div>, W3C recommendation, 
            10 December 2002.
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e329" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlenc-core/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlenc-core/</div>
            
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>