<div id="mainContainerTOC">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTOC" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTOC').toggle('1000');">Table of Content</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTOC" style="display:none;">
      <div class="headedContainerTOC">
         <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ProofExpressANCHOR" name="ProofExpressTOC">ProofExpress</a></div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#IntroductionANCHOR" name="IntroductionTOC">Introduction</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#UserInterfaceANCHOR" name="UserInterfaceTOC">User Interface</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ChangeTrackingANCHOR" name="ChangeTrackingTOC">Change Tracking</a></div>
            <div class="headedContainerTOC">
               <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#TheLimitationsofXMLDifferencingANCHOR" name="TheLimitationsofXMLDifferencingTOC">The Limitations of XML Differencing</a></div>
            </div>
            <div class="headedContainerTOC">
               <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#RuleEngineforChangesAcceptanceandRejectionANCHOR" name="RuleEngineforChangesAcceptanceandRejectionTOC">Rule Engine for Changes Acceptance and Rejection</a></div>
            </div>
            <div class="headedContainerTOC">
               <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#CustomElementsandXMLDenormalizationANCHOR" name="CustomElementsandXMLDenormalizationTOC">Custom Elements and XML Denormalization</a></div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#CustomizationANCHOR" name="CustomizationTOC">Customization</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ConclusionANCHOR" name="ConclusionTOC">Conclusion</a></div>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerTERMS">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTERMS" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTERMS').toggle('1000')">Index of Terms</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTERMS" style="display:none;">
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">a</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">August 5, 2013</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Antony</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">b</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">c</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Charles</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">d</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Director, Technology Strategy</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">e</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">f</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">g</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Gnanapiragasam</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">h</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Hepp</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">i</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">j</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">k</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">l</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">m</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Michael</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">n</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">o</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">O'Connor</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">p</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">pl</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">q</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">r</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">s</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">t</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">u</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">v</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">x</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">y</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">z</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">ze</div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerIML"><a name="ProofExpressANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="article e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3">
      <div class="title e1">ProofExpress</div>
      <div class="subtitle e2">An Online, Browser-Based XML Article Proofing System for STM Journals</div>
      <div class="info e3">
         <div class="confgroup e4">
            <div class="conftitle e5">International Symposium on Native XML User Interfaces</div>
            <div class="confdates e6">August 5, 2013</div>
         </div>
         <div class="abstract e7">
            <div class="para e8">For a browser-based XML article proofing system to function well in a journal
               publishing workflow, it must embody two virtues: It must have a very shallow
               learning curve, because the majority of users will be encountering it for the first
               time, and they may have no knowledge whatsoever of XML. It must also have a
               comprehensive and accurate change-tracking feature that allows editors to accept and
               reject changes without breaking the XML. A system designed for a publication
               services company with many publisher-customers must have the additional virtue of
               being highly customizable to account for wide variations in journal styles and the
               particular needs of online hosts.
            </div>
            <div class="para e9">To achieve usability, we based ProofExpress on LiveContent Create (formerly
               Xopus), a browser-based, WYSIWYG XML editor, and designed form-based tools to guide
               users in the creation of more complex XML structures. Our change-tracking feature
               employs denormalization of nested elements to granularly expose all edits and a rule
               engine that protects the structure of the XML by governing the order of acceptance
               and rejection of edits. XML configuration files control the content of the nodes
               added by the tools, allowing ProofExpress to accommodate the differences in, for
               example, reference, citation, and footnote styles used by journals that publish
               articles in XML that conforms to the JATS 1.0 DTD.
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e10">
            <div class="personname e11">
               <div class="firstname e12">Charles</div>
               <div class="surname e13">O'Connor</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e14">
               <div class="para e15">Charles has a degree in biology and had previous lives as an indexer,
                  copyeditor, and video store clerk before getting involved in this XML
                  thing.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e16">
               <div class="jobtitle e17">Workflow Automation Specialist</div>
               <div class="orgname e18">Dartmouth Journal Services</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e19">
            <div class="personname e20">
               <div class="firstname e21">Antony</div>
               <div class="surname e22">Gnanapiragasam</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e23">
               <div class="para e24">Antony has masters degrees in computer science and public administration and
                  works as a system architect.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e25">
               <div class="jobtitle e26">Workflow Automation Specialist</div>
               <div class="orgname e27">Dartmouth Journal Services</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e28">
            <div class="personname e29">
               <div class="firstname e30">Michael</div>
               <div class="surname e31">Hepp</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e32">
               <div class="para e33">Mike has a bachelor's degree in printing management and sciences and is the
                  project leader for ProofExpress.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e34">
               <div class="jobtitle e35">Director, Technology Strategy</div>
               <div class="orgname e36">Dartmouth Journal Services</div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="legalnotice e37">
            <div class="para e38">Copyright © Dartmouth Journal Services 2013</div>
         </div>
      </div><a name="IntroductionANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e39">
         <div class="title e40">Introduction</div>
         <div class="para e41">The advent of PDFs represented a leap forward for article proofing. No longer did
            proofs need to be printed out and either mailed or faxed to the author for correction.
            The PDF could be delivered instantly over the Internet, and the author could view
            and
            annotate the PDF on a computer in a different environment, using a different operating
            system. (Of course, that does not stop them from printing the pages out, correcting
            them
            by hand, and mailing or faxing them back.) The question then becomes, how can we bank
            the gains that were made in delivery and interoperability and take them to the next
            level? The answer, of course, is online XML editing.
         </div>
         <div class="para e42">The clearest advantage of an online, XML-based proofing system is that everyone
            involved can work on the same document from copyediting through final corrections.
            This
            stands in contrast to PDF-based proofing, where authors and editors may mark up
            different PDFs, which are then given to a typesetter to transfer the corrections.
            Sources of error at this stage include the misinterpretation of sometimes ambiguous
            corrections and the rekeying itself (
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e43" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.councilscienceeditors.org/files/scienceeditor/v27n5p155.pdf" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.councilscienceeditors.org/files/scienceeditor/v27n5p155.pdf</div>). A
            new PDF is then generated, and another review cycle is initiated. PDF proofing is
            thus
            both inefficient and prone to error due to the degree of manual intervention. As
            attractive as an XML-based proofing system can seem from a workflow standpoint, however,
            it will come to nothing unless it is adopted. An online, XML-based article proofing
            system designed for science, technical, and medical (STM) journals must be easy to
            use
            for authors, editors, and publishers and maintain the XML in good shape for the
            typesetting system and the online providers that host the resulting content.
         </div>
         <div class="para e44">Authors of STM journal articles can be many things--researchers, engineers, students,
            doctors. One thing they often are not is readers of instructions. (Many jobs in
            publishing, from copyeditors to developers of editorial software, depend on this fact.)
            In addition, authors may not be especially eager to learn new software. When Dartmouth
            Journal Services (DJS) instituted PDF annotation as our preferred method of proof
            review, many authors pointed out that they had written their paper in MS Word and
            did
            not appreciate having to learn how to use the annotation tools in Acrobat Reader.
            (We
            use eXtyles to apply structure to authors' Word files. After copyediting, we again
            use
            eXtyles to export JATS XML.) So, the ideal system will give authors a set of tools
            similar to those they are accustomed to in word processing programs.
         </div>
         <div class="para e45">Editors must review the corrections made by authors, and to do so, they need an
            accurate change-tracking mechanism. In addition, they need a way to accept or reject
            the
            changes that an author has made to their proof. A likely solution, and the one we
            tried
            first, is XML differencing. However, XML differencing must work around the longest
            common subsequence problem
            (
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e46" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Longest_common_subsequence_problem" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Longest_common_subsequence_problem</div>). Whatever the
            solution arrived at, for example, applying a semantic cleanup or a cleanup based on
            string length
            (
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e47" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://neil.fraser.name/software/diff_match_patch/svn/trunk/demos/demo_diff.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://neil.fraser.name/software/diff_match_patch/svn/trunk/demos/demo_diff.html</div>), XML
            differencing can only tell you how two versions of a piece of text are different,
            it
            cannot tell you what was done to make the versions different. Thus, editors would
            be
            faced with accepting or rejecting these differences, not the actual edits made by
            the
            author.
         </div>
         <div class="para e48"> A problem particular to publication services companies is accommodating the wide
            variations in journal style across their publisher-customers. The DTDs based upon
            the
            NISO Journal Article Tag Suite 1.0 (JATS 1.0) (
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e49" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://jats.niso.org/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://jats.niso.org/</div>) are to varying degrees descriptive, not prescriptive.
            They are silent, for example, on questions of what symbols to use in footnotes, whether
            to use numbered or author-date reference citations, and whether items in ordered lists
            should have labels or not. Another complication arises from the needs of the different
            online hosts that a publication services company must deliver XML to. One online host
            may require that a &lt;glossary&gt; appear within the &lt;back&gt; element, whereas another
            may want it within the &lt;notes&gt; in the &lt;front&gt;.
         </div>
      </div><a name="UserInterfaceANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e50">
         <div class="title e51">User Interface</div>
         <div class="para e52">The great majority of proof corrections made by authors and editors are simple text
            edits: insertions, deletions, and formatting changes. As ProofExpress is intended
            to be
            a web-delivered application, SDL LiveContent Create (formerly Xopus;
            
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e53" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.sdl.com/products/livecontent/create.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.sdl.com/products/livecontent/create.html</div>) was a natural choice to base the
            system upon. LiveContent Create is a continuously validating XML editing environment
            that allows authors to make text corrections using tools familiar to users of word
            processing programs. They can insert and delete text without having to enter a
            particular text editing mode. They can cut, copy, paste, and format text using toolbar
            buttons or keyboard shortcuts. They can insert new paragraphs and sections. All of
            these
            edits can be made without any knowledge of the underlying XML structure.
         </div>
         <div class="para e54">To allow authors to add or edit more complex XML structures such as citations,
            references, and links, we not surprisingly settled on a form-based approach. In its
            simplest implementation, fields in the forms correspond directly correspond to elements
            that will be added to the XML. Rather than using element names for the field labels,
            ProofExpress uses natural language labels that authors are likely to interpret
            correctly. When the author completes and submits the form, the system adds the correctly
            structured XML to the file.
            <div class="figure e55">
               <div class="title e56">Insert Journal Reference Form</div>
               <div class="para e57">The form for adding references uses natural language labels such as Journal
                  Title and Page Range rather than element names such as &lt;source&gt; and
                  &lt;fpage&gt;/&lt;lpage&gt;, respectively.
               </div>
               <div class="mediaobject e58">
                  <div class="imageobject e59">
                     <div class="metaBox e60"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e104').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e104" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e60'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol11/graphics/OConnor01/OConnor01-001.png'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e61">In addition to providing a way for authors to add more complex XML structures to an
            article, forms can also restrict author input to choices that make sense in the context
            of the particular article. That is, when the author wants to add a cross-reference
            to
            some other part of the document, the system can examine the relevant nodes and offer
            a
            list of choices in a dropdown. The form can then give feedback to the author to confirm
            the correct choice. For example, the Add/Edit Reference Citation tool reads the list
            of
            available citations and puts identifying information into the dropdown. When the author
            chooses a reference and submits the form, the system adds the cross-reference. Standard
            variable items that the author should not be expected to keep track of, for example,
            in
            this case, the correct rid attribute, are added by the system.
            <div class="figure e62">
               <div class="title e63">Add/Edit Reference Citation Form</div>
               <div class="para e64">The add/edit reference citation form offers the author a list of references to
                  choose from. When the author chooses from the list, the full reference is shown
                  below in a read-only box as a confirmation that the correct reference has been
                  chosen. This confirmation is especially important because multiple references
                  can share the same authors and years.
               </div>
               <div class="mediaobject e65">
                  <div class="imageobject e66">
                     <div class="metaBox e67"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e114').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e114" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e67'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol11/graphics/OConnor01/OConnor01-002.png'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            
         </div>
      </div><a name="ChangeTrackingANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e68">
         <div class="title e69">Change Tracking</div>
         <div class="para e70">The one absolutely essential feature of any proofing system is change tracking.
            Editors must have the ability to see exactly what corrections authors have made, not
            only to ensure that these corrections conform to journal style, but also to confirm
            that
            the authors have made no changes to data or to claims that would require the article
            to
            undergo another round of peer review. A great advantage can be gained if the
            change-tracking feature also includes an easy way to accept and reject changes. Although
            such features are available in desktop XML editors such as Arbortext (
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e71" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ptc.com/products/arbortext/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ptc.com/products/arbortext/</div>), no online XML editor has a change
            tracking feature that is adequate for the task. LiveContent Create itself has a change
            tracking feature, but it's features are rather limited. It tracks insertions and
            deletions, but not formatting changes. In fact, as we discovered when we tried to
            build
            upon the native feature, deletions of text that include formatted text are not tracked
            at all.
         </div><a name="TheLimitationsofXMLDifferencingANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e72">
            <div class="title e73">The Limitations of XML Differencing</div>
            <div class="para e74">When we first started building ProofExpress, we naturally gravitated towards
               differencing to serve as the basis for our change-tracking feature. This method
               promised to be accurate while placing no burden on the user's perception of the
               performance of the application. However, we soon ran into difficulties related to
               how differencing engines work around the longest common subsequence problem. If we
               take the raw output of a differencing engine, we may get an accurate representation
               of the difference between the original and edited versions of the text, but it may
               not tell us what the author actually did. For example, if an author changes the
               sentence "I say cheese to you" to read "I say oh pleeze to you", the engine will
               depict the change as "
               <div class="subscript e75">c</div>
               <div class="emphasis e76" role="under">o</div>h
               
               <div class="emphasis e77" role="under">pl</div>ee
               <div class="subscript e78">s</div>
               <div class="emphasis e79" role="under">ze</div>" (where underline=insertion and subscript=deletion).
               This is not only difficult to read, but it gives the editor multiple changes to
               accept or reject, instead of one deletion and one insertion, inviting the
               possibility of introducing error during review.
            </div>
            <div class="para e80">Attempting to overcome this problem by applying a cleanup parameter or otherwise
               grouping changes can lead to a loss in the granularity of changes. Changes within
               changes will not be marked individually as changes, which is a problem if they
               should be dealt with discretely. For example, if you take "&lt;p&gt;hello
               world&lt;/p&gt;", italicize it and add text in the middle to form
               "&lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;hello silly italic world&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/p&gt;", the XML differencing
               engine DeltaXML (
               <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e81" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.deltaxml.com" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.deltaxml.com</div>) will accurately identify the former as the
               original text and the latter as the revised text. What it will not tell you
               specifically is that two changes have occurred: text has been italicized and text
               has been added. An editor rejecting the italic formatting of the text could
               inadvertently reject the insertion as well.
            </div>
            <div class="figure e82">
               <div class="title e83">Results from the DeltaXML "Sandbox"</div>
               <div class="para e84">The original node, &lt;p&gt;hello world&lt;/p&gt;, was revised to &lt;p&gt;&lt;italic&gt;hello silly
                  italic world&lt;/italic&gt;&lt;/p&gt;. The diff presented by DeltaXML is correct, but
                  it does not serve journal production workflows because it does not mark the
                  internal insertion as a discrete change.
                  <div class="mediaobject e85">
                     <div class="imageobject e86">
                        <div class="metaBox e87"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e154').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e154" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                              &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e87'
                                 </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol11/graphics/OConnor01/OConnor01-003.png'
                                 </span>
                              &gt;
                              
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div><a name="RuleEngineforChangesAcceptanceandRejectionANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e88">
            <div class="title e89">Rule Engine for Changes Acceptance and Rejection</div>
            <div class="para e90">Editors must not only be able to see the changes made by authors, but they must
               have an easy way to accept or reject these changes. So, we built a widget that lists
               all of the changes and allows the editor to accept or reject them. (This feature is
               also available to corresponding authors that share editing with colleagues.) All
               decisions about acceptance or rejection are considered provisional until the article
               moves to the next stage in the workflow, making it easy for the editor to reverse
               a
               decision if necessary.
            </div>
            <div class="para e91">A potential problem arises when accepting and rejecting changes. If the system
               does not enforce an order of decision making, then the process may break the XML.
               Consider this case: Author1 adds some text to a paragraph. Author2 deletes the
               entire node where this paragraph resides. If the editor accepts both the insertion
               of the text and the deletion of the node, the text would be left outside of its
               proper parent node, breaking the XML structure. To alleviate this problem, we group
               nested changes together and force editors to act upon the outer change before they
               can act on the inner change. According to our rule engine, a particular action by
               the user on an outer change may or may not force the accept/reject decision on the
               inner change. In this case, acceptance of the outer deletion forces the rejection
               of
               the inner insertion. Rejection of the outer deletion would allow either rejection
               or
               acceptance of the inner insertion. These rules can be applied through multiple
               layers of nesting.
               <div class="figure e92">
                  <div class="title e93">Acceptance and Rejection of Edits</div>
                  <div class="para e94">Unless a rule engine is imposed, the process of accepting and rejecting
                     changes could break the XML. In this case, accepting the deletion of the
                     paragraph node forced rejection of an internal insertion (indicated by the
                     entry being grayed out). 
                  </div>
                  <div class="mediaobject e95">
                     <div class="imageobject e96">
                        <div class="metaBox e97"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e169').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e169" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                              &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e97'
                                 </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol11/graphics/OConnor01/OConnor01-004.png'
                                 </span>
                              &gt;
                              
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div><a name="CustomElementsandXMLDenormalizationANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e98">
            <div class="title e99">Custom Elements and XML Denormalization</div>
            <div class="para e100">To create a change-tracking system that notes not just the difference between the
               original file and the edited version, but actually records what the author did, we
               used the extensive set of event handlers in LiveContent Create to add custom
               elements to the XML on the fly. Doing so turned out to be rather more difficult than
               it first seemed, as there can be many ways to perform the same edit. For example,
               there are many ways to delete text. You can delete character-by-character using the
               Backspace or Delete keys. You can select a text range and use Backspace or Delete.
               You can select and Cut or select and type over. All of these methods of deletion
               should be presented in the same way to the user, but they had to be dealt with
               individually through the event handlers.
            </div>
            <div class="para e101">The changes that we made to the JATS schema to accommodate our track changes
               feature reflect the different ways an edit can be performed as well. Again using the
               example of deletion, the LiveContent Create event handlers provide different
               information depending on whether deletions are done to a block of text at once or
               are done character-by-character and, in addition, whether the text being deleted
               contains a formatting node or not. As a consequence, we use one deletion tag for
               deletions that are done character-by-character and contain formatting nodes and
               another tag for deletions done to blocks of selected text or text that does not
               include a formatting node. Another modification of the JATS schema is the addition
               of "unformatting" nodes. If a user makes text bold, the system naturally adds a
               &lt;bold&gt; tag. If another user removes the formatting from that text, an &lt;unbold&gt;
               tag is applied.
            </div>
            <div class="para e102">When the track changes elements are added to the XML, a set of attributes are
               added as well. These give the system information about who made the change at what
               time, whether the change has been accepted or rejected by the editor, etc. In the
               example of different users toggling on and off formatting, the element reflects the
               current state of the formatting while attributes contain the history of how the
               current state was arrived at. These attribute values also inform the XSLTs that are
               run when a user toggles on the Track Changes Show mode. These XSLTs perform a
               variety of functions, for example, merging contiguous insertions or deletions made
               by the same author that may have been performed using different methods.
            </div>
            <div class="figure e103">
               <div class="title e104">Toggling Formatting On and Off</div>
               <div class="para e105">In this example, user "cl1" made the text bold, user "cl2" removed the
                  bold, user "cl3 reapplied the bold, and user "ca", finally, removed the bold.
                  The element &lt;unbold&gt; reflects the final state. The attribute @fmhist records
                  the users who applied bold, while @unfmhist records the users who removed bold. 
               </div>
               <div class="mediaobject e106">
                  <div class="imageobject e107">
                     <div class="metaBox e108"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e186').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e186" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e108'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol11/graphics/OConnor01/OConnor01-005.png'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="para e109">Changes made by an author should not always be merged; sometimes they need to be
               broken up. For our accept/reject rule engine to work properly, the Track Changes
               tool must show how changed nodes are nested within each other. Also, insertions and
               deletions should always be the outside changes when they occur in relation to
               changes in formatting, because the acceptance or rejection of an outside formatting
               change should have no effect on an internal insertion or deletion. To achieve the
               desired result, the XSLTs that are run on toggling to Track Changes Show mode
               denormalize nodes related to Track Changes and move insertions/deletions to the
               outside of formatting nodes. 
            </div>
            <div class="figure e110">
               <div class="title e111">Denormalization of Formatting Nodes</div>
               <div class="para e112">Formatting nodes are denormalized and placed on the inside of insertion or deletion
                  nodes to serve the functioning of the accept/reject rule engine.
               </div>
               <div class="mediaobject e113">
                  <div class="imageobject e114">
                     <div class="metaBox e115"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e196').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e196" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e115'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol11/graphics/OConnor01/OConnor01-006.png'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="figure e116">
               <div class="title e117">Denormalized Nodes in the Track Changes Tool</div>
               <div class="para e118">Acceptance or rejection of a formatting change should have no effect on the status
                  of insertions and deletions. Therefore, formatting changes should appear
                  "inside" insertions and deletions.
               </div>
               <div class="mediaobject e119">
                  <div class="imageobject e120">
                     <div class="metaBox e121"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e204').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e204" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e121'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol11/graphics/OConnor01/OConnor01-007.png'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div><a name="CustomizationANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e122">
         <div class="title e123">Customization</div>
         <div class="para e124">A publication services company, DJS delivers XML for over a hundred journals from
            different publishers. These journals differ in the style they use for everything from
            the casing of headings to the italicization of foreign words. Many of these differences
            must be accounted for in ProofExpress. For example, some journals use numbered citations
            while others use author-date citations. Among those that use author-date citations,
            some
            list one author before "et al." while others list six, some place a comma before the
            year while others do not, some put citations in brackets while others put them in
            parentheses, etc. The tool used for adding and editing citations must know not only
            the
            correct elements and attributes to add, it must know what the text content of the
            citation will be. Adding an additional level of complication, DJS delivers XML to
            several online hosts, and each of these has its own requirements that must be
            accommodated as well.
         </div>
         <div class="para e125">To customize ProofExpress, each article is transmitted by our production management
            system with a set of configuration files. In addition to XSLTs and CSS file that control
            display of the article, a set of XML files (naturally!) controls the output of the
            program's editing tools. A good example of a tool that requires configuration is the
            Add/Edit Footnote/Affiliation/Correspondence tool. Journals can use numbers, letters,
            or
            symbols to cite footnotes. The numbers used for citations may start with affiliations,
            continue through the correspondence line, and be used for author footnotes as well,
            or
            different citation schemes could be used for each. The same type of footnote may appear
            in the &lt;author-notes&gt; wrapper in one journal but in an &lt;fn-group&gt; in the &lt;back&gt;
            in another. The following is a snippet from a footnote configuration file that describes
            a financial disclosure footnote:
            <div class="inlinemediaobject e126">
               <div class="imageobject e127">
                  <div class="metaBox e128"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e214').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e214" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e128'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol11/graphics/OConnor01/OConnor01-008.png'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            
         </div>
         <div class="para e129">This snippet tells the system what kind of footnote this is, what fn-type attribute
            to
            apply, where it is placed and where it can be cited, what formatting, if any, should
            be
            applied to the &lt;xref&gt; (tag abuse!), and the prefix used in its id attribute. However,
            description of the footnote is not sufficient; the order that footnotes are assigned
            indicators and placed in each respective group must be spelled out: 
            <div class="inlinemediaobject e130">
               <div class="imageobject e131">
                  <div class="metaBox e132"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e220').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e220" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e132'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol11/graphics/OConnor01/OConnor01-009.png'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e133">When different citation indicators can be used together, such as in the author line,
            the system needs to know the order to place them: 
            
            <div class="inlinemediaobject e134">
               <div class="imageobject e135">
                  <div class="metaBox e136"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e225').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e225" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e136'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol11/graphics/OConnor01/OConnor01-010.png'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e137">Finally, when symbols such as asterisks and daggers are used, their order of use must
            also be specified: 
            <div class="inlinemediaobject e138">
               <div class="imageobject e139">
                  <div class="metaBox e140"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e230').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e230" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                        &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e140'
                           </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol11/graphics/OConnor01/OConnor01-011.png'
                           </span>
                        &gt;
                        
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e141">The use of XML files for configuration of ProofExpress provides distinct advantages.
            The files are easily generated and allow very granular control of elements of style.
            Use
            of configuration files obviates the building and maintenance of a complex administrative
            interface. New elements can be added as new configuration points are uncovered. As
            a
            bonus, we are looking into developing XSLTs that will pull information from these
            configuration files and construct Schematron rules to ensure that articles coming
            into
            the system conform to the same style points specified by the configuration.
         </div>
      </div><a name="ConclusionANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e142">
         <div class="title e143">Conclusion</div>
         <div class="para e144">Designing and building a browser-based XML article proofing system has been a
            challenge. ProofExpress must let users with no prior knowledge of XML easily make
            any
            possible edit. It must track every change, and give editors a tool to review the changes
            and accept or reject each one individually without breaking the XML. The same tools
            used
            across all journals must be configured to output different XML to accommodate the
            styles
            of each.
         </div>
         <div class="para e145">The rewards of having such a system are great as well, and we may eventually expand
            its usage to copyediting (though not to authoring; we have no control over authors
            until
            their articles are accepted and in our production workflows). By allowing all work
            to be
            done on a single file, ProofExpress increases efficiency as it removes potential sources
            of error. Schematron validation can be applied during the correction cycle instead
            of
            after back-end conversion, when the errors it uncovered would be more expensive to
            fix.
            In addition, having such a system opens up new possibilities in the journal production
            workflow. Notably, ProofExpress enables us to add fully automated page generation
            to our
            workflows, even when the system that creates the PDF cannot "round-trip" the XML.
            A new
            PDF of the article can be generated at any stage, simply by feeding the revised XML
            to
            the page-generation system. This capability puts the entire production process where
            it
            should be, in the hands of authors and editors.
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>