<div id="mainContainerTOC">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTOC" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTOC').toggle('1000');">Table of Content</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTOC" style="display:none;">
      <div class="headedContainerTOC">
         <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#QualityControlofPMCContent:ACaseStudyANCHOR" name="QualityControlofPMCContent:ACaseStudyTOC">Quality Control of PMC Content: A Case Study</a></div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ThePromiseofMarkedupContentANCHOR" name="ThePromiseofMarkedupContentTOC">The Promise of Marked-up Content</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#PMCIngestWorkflowANCHOR" name="PMCIngestWorkflowTOC">PMC Ingest Workflow</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#PMCPhilosophyofTextProcessingANCHOR" name="PMCPhilosophyofTextProcessingTOC">PMC Philosophy of Text Processing</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#TheDataEvaluationProcessANCHOR" name="TheDataEvaluationProcessTOC">The Data Evaluation Process</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ProductionQAANCHOR" name="ProductionQATOC">Production QA</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ConclusionsANCHOR" name="ConclusionsTOC">Conclusions</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#AcknowledgmentsANCHOR" name="AcknowledgmentsTOC">Acknowledgments</a></div>
         </div>
         <div class="headedContainerTOC">
            <div class="headedContainerTitleTOC"><a href="#ReferencesANCHOR" name="ReferencesTOC">References</a></div>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerTERMS">
   <div id="mainContainerTitleTERMS" onclick="$('#mainContainerEntriesTERMS').toggle('1000')">Index of Terms</div>
   <div id="mainContainerEntriesTERMS" style="display:none;">
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">a</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">August 6, 2012</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">b</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Beck</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">c</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Christopher</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">d</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">e</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">f</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">g</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">h</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">i</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">j</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Jeff</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">k</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Kelly</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">l</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">m</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">n</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">o</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">p</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">PMC Production Team Lead</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">q</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">r</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">s</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">t</div>
         <div class="singletermTERMS">Technical Information Specialist</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">u</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">v</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">x</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">y</div>
      </div>
      <div class="letterContainerTERMS">
         <div class="letterlableTERMS">z</div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div id="mainContainerIML"><a name="QualityControlofPMCContent:ACaseStudyANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="article e0" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3">
      <div class="title e1">Quality Control of PMC Content: A Case Study</div>
      <div class="info e2">
         <div class="confgroup e3">
            <div class="conftitle e4">International Symposium on Quality Assurance and Quality Control in XML</div>
            <div class="confdates e5">August 6, 2012</div>
         </div>
         <div class="abstract e6">
            <div class="para e7">PubMed Central (PMC) is the US National Library of Medicine's digital archive of life
               sciences journal literature. On average the PMC team processes 14,000 articles per
               month.
               All of the articles are submitted to the archive by publishers in an agreed-upon markup
               format, and the articles are transformed to a common article model. To help reduce
               the
               number of content- or markup-related problems encountered, PMC puts new participating
               journals through an evaluation period that includes both automated and manual checks.
               
            </div>
            <div class="para e8">Once a journal has passed the evaluation stage, it sends its content to PMC on a regular
               production schedule. The production content is processed automatically when it arrives,
               with
               any processing problems generating expected error messages. Although most of the content
               sent to PMC has been through production systems and QA when it was published, we've
               found
               that there is still a level of manual content checking that needs to be done on the
               production content. Any problems found must be investigated to determine if they result
               from
               a problem in the source content, a problem with the PMC ingest transforms, or simply
               a
               problem with our rendering of the normalized XML content. 
            </div>
            <div class="para e9">Having the content in XML certainly has advantages: it can be validated against a
               schema
               and easily manipulated and processed, but XML doesn't solve all of the problems. A
               sharp eye
               and attention to detail are still needed by the production team as they would be for
               any
               publishing process. 
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e10">
            <div class="personname e11">
               <div class="firstname e12">Christopher</div>
               <div class="surname e13">Kelly</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e14">
               <div class="para e15"></div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e16">
               <div class="jobtitle e17">PMC Production Team Lead</div>
               <div class="orgname e18">National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI), National Library of Medicine
                  (NLM), National Institutes of Heath (NIH)
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="author e19">
            <div class="personname e20">
               <div class="firstname e21">Jeff</div>
               <div class="surname e22">Beck</div>
            </div>
            <div class="personblurb e23">
               <div class="para e24">Jeff has been involved in the PubMed Central project at NLM since 2000. He has been
                  working journal publishing since the early 1990s.
               </div>
            </div>
            <div class="affiliation e25">
               <div class="jobtitle e26">Technical Information Specialist</div>
               <div class="orgname e27">National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI), National Library of Medicine
                  (NLM), National Institutes of Heath (NIH)
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="legalnotice e28">
            <div class="para e29">Author's contribution to the Work was done as part of the Author's official duties
               as an NIH employee and is a Work of the United States Government. Therefore, copyright
               may not be established in the United States. 17 U.S.C. § 105. If Publisher intends
               to disseminate the Work outside the U.S., Publisher may secure copyright to the extent
               authorized under the domestic laws of the relevant country, subject to a paid-up,
               nonexclusive, irrevocable worldwide license to the United States in such copyrighted
               work to reproduce, prepare derivative works, distribute copies to the public and perform
               publicly and display publicly the work, and to permit others to do so. 
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div class="para e30">PubMed Central 
         <div class="citation e31" linkend="PMC01">[PMC01]</div> is the U.S. National Institutes
         of Health's free digital archive of full-text biomedical and life sciences journal
         literature.
         Content is stored in XML at the article level. and is displayed dynamically from the
         archival
         XML each time that a user retrieves an article. 
      </div>
      <div class="para e32">PubMed Central was started in 1999 to allow free full-text access to journal articles.
         Participation by journals is voluntary. From the beginning there has always been a
         requirement
         that participating journals provide their content to NCBI marked up in some "reasonable"
         SGML or
         XML format 
         <div class="citation e33" linkend="Beck01">[Beck01]</div> along with the highest-resolution
         images available, PDF files (if available), and all supplementary material. Complete
         details on
         the PMC's file requirements are available 
         <div class="citation e34" linkend="PMC02">[PMC02]</div>.
      </div><a name="ThePromiseofMarkedupContentANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e35">
         <div class="title e36">The Promise of Marked-up Content</div>
         <div class="para e37">Building a full-text journal article repository seemed like a pretty straightforward
            task
            in when PMC was conceived in 2000. After all, participating journals already had their
            content
            in SGML or XML that they were putting online or sending to a vendor to be put online.
            All we
            would need to do would be to get the marked-up content, render it in PMC, and store
            it. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e38">But we soon found out that the content we were receiving was not of the same quality
            as
            the articles that had been printed or even as the articles showing on the journals'
            websites.
            This seemed odd; the SGML was created for the online product, and this SGML was delivered
            to
            PMC for the archive. At the turn of the century, XML-first publishing workflows (where
            the
            articles are authored in XML or converted to XML as soon as they were submitted to
            a journal
            and then processed as XML) were not the norm. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e39">The workflow that we encountered generally went something like this: 
            <div class="orderedlist e40">
               <div class="listitem e41">
                  <div class="para e42">article is written, submitted, peer reviewed, revised, and accepted as a Word
                     document (or more specifically, a printout of a Word document).
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e43">
                  <div class="para e44">accepted article copyedited in the Word file (to capture the author's
                     keystrokes).
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e45">
                  <div class="para e46">copyedited Word file is ingested into a typesetting system and made into
                     pages.
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e47">
                  <div class="para e48">any changes in the author proof cycle are made in the typesetting system under the
                     direction of copyeditors or proofreaders. 
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e49">
                  <div class="para e50">typesetting files are built into issues, checked by copyeditors or proofreaders and
                     sent for printing. 
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e51">
                  <div class="para e52">typesetting files are then converted to SGML/XML - generally to a model defined by
                     the online service.
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e53">
                  <div class="para e54">SGML/XML files are converted to HTML, and the HTML is checked for errors.</div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e55">
                  <div class="para e56">HTML is corrected so that the online article represents the printed article.</div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e57">
                  <div class="para e58">SGML/XML files are stored away - never to be thought of again.</div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e59">Things were going pretty well in that workflow up through item 5. The author's keystrokes
            had been used from the original word processing files&amp;#x2014;reducing errors that
            would
            have been introduced by rekeying the article; a person familiar with the content (usually
            at
            least two of a copyeditor, proofreader, or author) checked the files and any changes
            at each
            stage until it was sent off to press. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e60">At this point it is out of the hands of the content folks and into the hands of the
            data
            converters. In step 6, the typesetting files used as the source for the transformation
            contained some information about the structure of the article, but it certainly was
            not enough
            to build a proper SGML/XML representation of the article. Assumptions are made during
            the
            transformation, and a surprising amount of hand tagging - copy and paste - was done
            to create
            the files. The problem areas are not surprising: metadata, tables, and math.
         </div>
         <div class="para e61">From the PMC point of view, the real tragedy in this (generalized and non-specific)
            workflow happens at step 8, when the files are reviewed by a proofreader but corrections
            are
            made to the output HTML files and not back in the source SGML files. Once we started
            processing those SGML files in the young PMC system, we took a close look at the output
            of our
            rendering of the files to identify any problems with the way our system was handling
            the
            files. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e62">We started to find a good number of problems with the supplied SGML that were not
            in the
            HTML version available on the web - and a surprising number that were incorrect on
            the web.
            Unfortunately we did not count the errors that we encountered at this point. We simply
            fixed
            them, reported them to the publisher so that any that also appeared on their site
            could be
            fixed, and moved on the the next article or issue. This is when we knew we would have
            to have
            a team of content specialists checking all of the content we get in PMC.
         </div>
      </div><a name="PMCIngestWorkflowANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e63">
         <div class="title e64">PMC Ingest Workflow</div>
         <div class="para e65">The PMC processing model has been addressed in detail previously 
            <div class="citation e66" linkend="Beck01">[Beck01]</div>. Briefly it is diagrammed in 
            <div class="xref e67" linkend="F1"></div>. For
            each article, we receive a set of files that includes the text in SGML or XML, the
            highest
            resolution figures available, a PDF file if one has been created for the article,
            and any
            supplementary material or supporting data. The text is converted to the current version
            of the
            NISO Archiving and Interchange Tag Set 
            <div class="citation e68" linkend="JATS01">[JATS01]</div>, and the
            images are converted to a web-friendly format. The source SGML or XML, original images,
            supplementary data files, PDFs, and NLM XML files are stored in the archive. Articles
            are
            rendered online using the NLM XML, PDFs, supplementary data files, and the web-friendly
            images. 
            <div class="figure e69" xml:id="F1" xreflabel="Fig. 1">
               <div class="title e70">PMC Processing Model</div>
               <div class="mediaobject e71">
                  <div class="imageobject e72">
                     <div class="metaBox e73"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e123').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e123" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e73'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol9/graphics/Beck01/Beck01-001.png'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='png'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e74">For purposes of this paper, we will concentrate on the text processing.</div>
      </div><a name="PMCPhilosophyofTextProcessingANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e75">
         <div class="title e76">PMC Philosophy of Text Processing</div>
         <div class="para e77">There are four main principals to the PMC philosophy of text processing</div>
         <div class="para e78">First, we expect to receive marked-up versions of an article that are well-formed,
            valid,
            and accurately represents the article as it was published. We do not go so far as
            requiring
            that the content be true or correct as Syd Bauman illustrates 
            <div class="citation e79" linkend="Bauman01">[Bauman01]</div>, merely that the article represents the version of record.
         </div>
         <div class="para e80">The question of what is the "Version of Record" is left up to the publisher. It may
            be a
            printed copy, a PDF version, or the journal's website. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e81">Unlike the early days of PMC as described above, we do not correct articles or files.
            That
            is, we will not fix something that is wrong in the version of record nor will we make
            a
            correction to an XML file. All problems found in either processing or QA of files
            are reported
            back to the publisher to be corrected and resubmitted. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e82">Thirdly, the goal of PMC is to represent the content of the article and not the formatting
            of the printed page, the PDF, or the journal's website. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e83">And finally, we must run a Quality Assessment on content coming into PMC to ensure
            that
            the content in PMC accurately reflects the article as it was published. Our QA is
            a
            combination of automated checks and manual checking of articles. To help ensure that
            the
            content we are spending time ingesting to PMC is likely to be worthwhile, journals
            must pass
            through an evaluation process before they can send content to PMC in a regular production
            workflow.
         </div>
      </div><a name="TheDataEvaluationProcessANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e84">
         <div class="title e85">The Data Evaluation Process</div>
         <div class="para e86">The data evaluation process has been described previously 
            <div class="citation e87" linkend="Beck01">[Beck01]</div>, but it is integral in ensuring the quality of content that is being
            submitted to PMC.
         </div>
         <div class="para e88">Journals joining PMC must pass two tests. First, the journal must pass PMC's scientific
            quality standard, which means that the journal must be approved for the NLM collection
            by
            NLM's Selection and Acquisitions section 
            <div class="citation e89" linkend="NLM01">[NLM01]</div>. This
            check ensures that the journal's content is "in scope" for a medical library and is
            of
            sufficient scientific quality for the archive.
         </div>
         <div class="para e90">Next the journal must go through a technical evaluation to "be sure that the journal
            can
            routinely supply files of sufficient quality to generate complete and accurate articles
            online
            without the need for human action to correct errors or omissions in the data." 
            <div class="citation e91" linkend="PMC03">[PMC03]</div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e92">For the data evaluation, a journal supplies a set of sample files for approximately
            50
            articles. These files are put through a series of automated and human checks to ensure
            that
            the XML is valid, accurately reflects the publication model of the journal (publication
            dates,
            for example) and is a complete and accurate representation of the published articled.
            There is
            a baseline set of "Minimum Data Requirements" that must be met before the evaluation
            proceeds
            to the more human-intense content accuracy checking 
            <div class="citation e93" linkend="PMC04">[PMC04]</div>. These minimum criteria are listed briefly below:
            <div class="orderedlist e94">
               <div class="listitem e95">
                  <div class="para e96">Each sample package must be complete: all required data files (XML/SGML, PDF if
                     available, image files, supplementary data files) for every article in the package
                     must
                     be present and named correctly.
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e97">
                  <div class="para e98">All XML files must conform to an acceptable journal article DTD.</div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e99">
                  <div class="para e100">All XML/SGML files must parse according to their DTD.</div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e101">
                  <div class="para e102">Regardless of the XML/SGML DTD used, the following metadata information must be
                     present and tagged with correct values in every sample file: 
                     <div class="itemizedlist e103">
                        <div class="listitem e104">
                           <div class="para e105">Journal ISSN or other unique Journal ID</div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="listitem e106">
                           <div class="para e107">Journal Publisher</div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="listitem e108">
                           <div class="para e109">Copyright statement (if applicable)</div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="listitem e110">
                           <div class="para e111">License statement (if applicable)</div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="listitem e112">
                           <div class="para e113">Volume number</div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="listitem e114">
                           <div class="para e115">Issue number (if applicable)</div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="listitem e116">
                           <div class="para e117">Pagination/article sequence number</div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="listitem e118">
                           <div class="para e119">Issue-based or Article-based publication dates. Articles submitted to PMC must
                              contain publication dates that accurately reflect the journal’s publication
                              model.
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div class="listitem e120">
                  <div class="para e121">All image files for figures must be legible, and submitted in high-resolution TIFF
                     or EPS format, according to the PMC Image File Requirements.
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e122">These seem like simple and obvious things - xml files must be valid - but the minimum
            data
            requirements have greatly reduced the amount of rework that the PMC Data Evaluation
            group has
            to do. Certainly it helps to be explicit about even the most obvious of things.
         </div>
         <div class="para e123">During the data evaluation, PMC reviews 100% of the sample articles by eye.</div>
      </div><a name="ProductionQAANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e124">
         <div class="title e125">Production QA</div>
         <div class="para e126">The PMC production team is made up of a set of Journal Managers who are responsible
            for
            the processing and checking of content for the journal titles that are assigned to
            them. We
            use a combination of automated processing checks and manual checking of articles to
            help
            ensure the accuracy of the content in PMC. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e127">We can leverage the fact that all content is sent to us in SGML or XML to eliminate
            any
            article files that are not well-formed (if XML) or valid to the model they claim to
            be valid
            against. 100% of not-well-formed or invalid files are returned to the provider to
            be corrected
            and resubmitted.
         </div>
         <div class="para e128">The PMC Style Checker (
            <div class="citation e129" linkend="Beck01">[Beck01]</div>) is used during the ingest process to ensure that all content flowing
            into PMC is in the PMC common XML format for loading to the database. The errors provided
            by
            the Style Checker provides us with a level of automated checking on the content itself
            that
            can highlight problems, but it only goes so far. For example, the Style Checker can
            tell you
            if an electronic publication date is tagged completely to PMC Style (contains values
            in year,
            month, and day elements) in a file, but it can't tell you if the values themselves
            are correct
            and actually represent the electronic publication date of the article. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e130">PMC also has a series of automated data integrity checks that run once content is
            loaded
            to the database which can identify, among other things,  problems like duplicate articles
            submitted to the system, and potential discrepancies in issue publication dates for
            a group of
            articles in the same issue.
         </div>
         <div class="para e131">Early in the PMC project the questions of "what and how much to check?" were left
            to the
            discretion of the Journal Manager. But we soon found out that certain things had to
            be checked
            more frequently. All articles with marked-up math (in MathML or LateX) get a close
            review
            because the quality of marked up math has been one of the problem areas since the
            beginning of
            the project. In addition, all published corrections and retractions needed to be checked
            closely to ensure that the tagging provided in the source XML allows PMC to build
            a link
            between the correction/retrction and the article being corrected/retracted. We also
            check the
            ever PDF that we generate for manuscripts being tagged for the NIH Public Access Project
            
            <div class="citation e132" linkend="NIH01">[NIH01]</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="para e133">As the project began to grow, both in terms of the amount of content coming into PMC
            and
            the number of Journal Managers required to manage the content, it became obvious that
            we
            needed to quantify the QA process. First, the production team compiled a "Content
            QA
            checklist" which was a collection of some of the most common (and serious) errors
            encountered
            over the years. Next, we built a system that shows each Journal Manager the journals
            that are
            assigned to him, and which articles need to be checked 
            <div class="xref e134" linkend="F2"></div>. The system
            selects a percentage of articles from each "batch" of new content deposited by the
            journal as
            they are processed and loaded to the PMC database. The number of articles in each
            batch is
            determined by the publication model and participation mode of the journal itself.
            Traditional
            journals which deposit a whole issue at a time into PMC will normally have a "batch"
            consisting of all the articles in the issue. Journals which publishing on a continuous
            basis
            and send content to PMC article-by-article will have batches which reflect how much
            content is
            deposited during a given day.
         </div>
         <div class="para e135">While it would be nice to be able to check 100% of the articles being loaded into
            the PMC
            database, this is generally not reasonable because of resources. So, once an journal
            has
            passed the tightly monitored data evaluation period, and has demonstrated over a period
            of
            time after moving into production that it can provide generally error-free data, QA
            is done on
            more of a spot check basis. By default, new journals that come out of data evaluation
            and move
            into production are set with a higher threshold of articles selected for QA in the
            system.
            Once PMC's Journal Manager is confident in the journal's ability to provide good,
            clean, data,
            the article-selection percentages are lowered over time. Journals with a proven track
            record
            of providing error-free data into PMC generally have lower percentage of articles
            checked for
            QA. If the Journal Manager begins to see problems on an ongoing basis, the percentage
            of
            articles checked may be increased.
            <div class="figure e136" xml:id="F2" xreflabel="Fig. 2">
               <div class="title e137">QA System Dashboard</div>
               <div class="mediaobject e138">
                  <div class="imageobject e139">
                     <div class="metaBox e140"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e241').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e241" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e140'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol9/graphics/Beck01/Beck01-002.jpg'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='jpg'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e141">The system includes the original list of standard errors that was compiled as the
            first
            "Content QA checklist"; this list has grown the years as new errors are encountered.
            PMC
            Article Errors are grouped into eight major categories: Article Information, Article
            Body,
            Back Matter, Figures and Tables, Special Characters and Math, Generic Errors, Image
            Quality,
            and PDF Quality. Within each of these major categories, there may be one or more
            sub-categories. For example, in the "Article Body" section there is a subcategory
            for
            "Sections and Subsections", containing errors for mising sections, or sections that
            have been
            nested incorrectly in the flow of the body text. In 
            <div class="xref e142" linkend="F3"></div> the errors specific
            to Article Information are shown in the purple box. If a Journal Manager finds that
            the
            "Publication date is missing or does not match the version of record", then he or
            she simply
            checks that box and that error is recorded for that article. Of course, there is always
            a text
            box available to allow a Journal Manger to enter an unforeseen error.
            <div class="figure e143" xml:id="F3" xreflabel="Fig. 3">
               <div class="title e144">Article Errors List</div>
               <div class="mediaobject e145">
                  <div class="imageobject e146">
                     <div class="metaBox e147"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e251').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e251" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e147'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol9/graphics/Beck01/Beck01-003.jpg'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='jpg'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e148"> Processing can be done either on the issue level or on a group of articles that arrives
            at PMC in a given time period. Each error is classified as "severe" or "normal" and
            as a "PMC
            Error" or a "Data Error". See the purple box in 
            <div class="xref e149" linkend="F4"></div> for an example of a
            totaled batch of articles. 
            <div class="figure e150" xml:id="F4" xreflabel="Fig. 4">
               <div class="title e151">Error Totals</div>
               <div class="mediaobject e152">
                  <div class="imageobject e153">
                     <div class="metaBox e154"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e261').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e261" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e154'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol9/graphics/Beck01/Beck01-004.jpg'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='jpg'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div class="para e155">At any time, the Journal Manager can review the accumulated errors for a batch as
            seen in
            
            <div class="xref e156" linkend="F5"></div>. This report can be output in RTF format so it can be sent to the
            publisher as a Word file (
            <div class="xref e157" linkend="F6"></div>&gt;). 
            <div class="figure e158" xml:id="F5" xreflabel="Fig. 5">
               <div class="title e159">Batch Errors</div>
               <div class="mediaobject e160">
                  <div class="imageobject e161">
                     <div class="metaBox e162"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e273').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e273" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e162'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol9/graphics/Beck01/Beck01-005.jpg'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='jpg'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            
            <div class="figure e163" xml:id="F6" xreflabel="Fig. 6">
               <div class="title e164">Batch Error Report</div>
               <div class="mediaobject e165">
                  <div class="imageobject e166">
                     <div class="metaBox e167"><img src="resources/manbluflag.jpg" class="metaImage" onclick="$('#d1e280').toggle('1000');" alt="Marker: click here for details..." title="Marker: click here for details..."><div id="d1e280" class="metaSource" style="display:none;">                
                           &lt;imagedata<span class="metaAttribute">class='e167'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">fileref='../../../vol9/graphics/Beck01/Beck01-006.jpg'
                              </span><span class="metaAttribute">format='jpg'
                              </span>
                           &gt;
                           
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            
         </div>
      </div><a name="ConclusionsANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e168">
         <div class="title e169">Conclusions</div>
         <div class="para e170">The automated QA system has greatly improved both the Quantity and the Quality of
            the QA
            work that is being done for the PMC project, but we find that even this long after
            the 10-year
            anniversary of the invention of XML that there is still a need for manual review of
            article
            files. 
         </div>
         <div class="para e171">Fortunately we are able to sort out the deepest structural problems with XML tools,
            but
            questions of accuracy of content still need to be addressed by eye.
         </div>
      </div><a name="AcknowledgmentsANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="section e172">
         <div class="title e173">Acknowledgments</div>
         <div class="para e174">This work was supported by the Intramural Research Program of the NIH, National Library
            of
            Medicine, National Center for Biotechnology Information.
         </div>
      </div><a name="ReferencesANCHOR" href="#mainContainerTitleTOC" class="anchor">toc</a><div class="bibliography e175">
         <div class="title e176">References</div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e177" xml:id="PMC01">PubMed Central, 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e178" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e179" xml:id="Beck01">Beck, Jeff. “Report from the Field: PubMed Central, an XML-based
            Archive of Life Sciences Journal Articles.” Presented at International Symposium on
            XML for
            the Long Haul: Issues in the Long-term Preservation of XML, Montréal, Canada, August
            2, 2010.
            In 
            <div class="emphasis e180">Proceedings of the International Symposium on XML for the Long Haul: Issues in
               the Long-term Preservation of XML
            </div>. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 6
            (2010). doi:
            <div class="biblioid doi e181">10.4242/BalisageVol6.Beck01</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e182" xml:id="PMC02">How to Join PMC, 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e183" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/about/pubinfo.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/about/pubinfo.html</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e184" xml:id="JATS01">NISO Journal Article Tag Suite (JATS), 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e185" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e186" xml:id="Bauman01">Bauman, Syd. (2010) "The 4 Levels of XML Rectitude", Balisage
            2010, poster.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e187" xml:id="NLM01">NLM Collection Development and Acquisitions, 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e188" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.nlm.nih.gov/tsd/acquisions/mainpage.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.nlm.nih.gov/tsd/acquisions/mainpage.html</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e189" xml:id="PMC04">Minimum Criteria for PMC Data Evaluation Submissions, 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e190" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/pmcdoc/mindatareq.pdf" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/pmcdoc/mindatareq.pdf</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e191" xml:id="PMC03">How to Join PMC, 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e192" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/about/pubinfo.html" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/about/pubinfo.html</div>.
         </div>
         <div class="bibliomixed e193" xml:id="NIH01">National Institutes of Health Public Access 
            <div xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" class="link e194" xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://publicaccess.nih.gov/" xlink:show="new" xlink:type="simple">http://publicaccess.nih.gov/</div>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>