<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2"><title>The XML Chip at 6 Years</title><info><confgroup><conftitle>International Symposium on Processing XML Efficiently: Overcoming Limits on Space, Time, or Bandwidth</conftitle><confdates>August 10, 2009</confdates></confgroup><abstract><para>The XML chip is now more than six years old. The diffusion of this technology has been very
limited, due, on the one hand, to the long period of evolutionary development needed to develop hardware
capable of accelerating a significant portion of the XML computing workload and, on the other hand, to the 
fact that the chip was invented by start-up Tarari in a commercial context which required, for business reasons,
a minimum of public disclosure of its design features. It remains, nevertheless, a significant
landmark that the XML chip has been sold and continuously improved for the last six years. From the
perspective of general computing history, the XML chip is an uncommon example of a successful
workload-specific symbolic computing device. With respect to the specific interests of the XML community,
the XML chip is a remarkable validation of one of its core founding principles: normalizing on
a data format, whatever its imperfections, would enable the developers to, eventually, create tools to 
process it efficiently.</para><para>This paper was prepared for the International Symposium on Processing XML Efficiently:
Overcoming Limits on Space, Time, or Bandwidth, a day of discussion among, predominately, software
developers working in the area of efficient XML processing. The Symposium is being held as a workshop 
within Balisage, a conference of specialists in markup theory. Given the interests of the audience this paper does not
delve into the design features and principles of the chip itself; rather it presents a dialectic on 
the motivation for the development of an XML chip in view of related and potentially competing developments in 
scaling as it is commonly characterized as a manifestation of Moore's Law, parallelization through
increasing the number of computing cores on general purpose processors (multicore Von Neumann architecture),
and optimization of software.</para></abstract><author><personname><firstname>Michael</firstname><surname>Leventhal</surname></personname><personblurb><para>
 Michael Leventhal has co-led the XML acceleration program at LSI (formerly Tarari) for the last six 
 years. Mr. Leventhal has been active in the XML developer community since its inception, published 
 many articles on XML, wrote the first book on the use of XML for the Internet, and participated in 
 W3C workgroups. He holds a degree in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science from U.C. Berkeley.
                </para></personblurb><affiliation><jobtitle>
Senior Product Line Manager
                </jobtitle><orgname>
LSI Corporation
                </orgname></affiliation></author><author><personname><firstname>Eric</firstname><surname>Lemoine</surname></personname><personblurb><para>
Eric Lemoine has co-led the XML acceleration program at LSI (formerly Tarari) for the last six years. 
Dr. Lemoine is the lead inventor of many XML hardware-related patents. His main research interest is 
the creation of very high performance purpose-built devices for machine-to-machine interoperability. 
He received his PhD from the Université de Montpellier for his work on Reconfigurable Hardware, 
working closely with pioneers in the field such as Professor Jean Vuillemin.
                </para></personblurb><affiliation><jobtitle>
XML Architect
                </jobtitle><orgname>
LSI Corporation
                </orgname></affiliation></author><legalnotice><para>Copyright © 2009 by the authors.  Used with
			permission.</para></legalnotice><keywordset role="author"><keyword>software performance</keyword><keyword>XML acceleration</keyword><keyword>XML chip</keyword><keyword>hardware acceleration</keyword><keyword>multicore</keyword><keyword>latency</keyword><keyword>power consumption</keyword></keywordset></info><section><title>
Introduction
        </title><para>The XML chip is purpose-built silicon for high performance XML processing. It has the potential 
to reduce server costs, to reduce power consumption, and to reduce latency. The paper compares the 
performance of the XML chip (hybrid specialized hardware and software) with optimized XML software for 
a number of operations. The benefits of the XML chip increase as CPUs get faster, especially with the 
introduction of multi-core technology. There are challenges, notably the cost of copying data to and 
from the co-processor, but the challenges can be overcome. Results show that the use of an XML 
co-processor can reduce CPU cycles per byte of XML processed by amounts ranging from a factor of 3 to 
a factor of 50 depending on the workload, while power consumption can be reduced by a factor of 7.
</para><para>The purpose of the XML chip is not so much to make XML processing efficient as it is to make server 
usage more efficient and cost-effective. Bandwidth can always be increased by multiplying the number 
of servers but it may not be cost effective to do so. Latency reducation, on the other hand, is another 
prime objective for the XML chip since latency is not improved either by multiplying cores or multiplying 
servers. From the point of view of server efficiency XML is interesting to accelerate because it is the 
closest thing there is to a ubiquitious computing workload. XML is the de facto choice for virtually all 
communication between applications including web traffic (HTML, XHTML, and POX (plain old XML)), inter- 
and intra-enterprise software (Web Services, REST and SOAP styles and POX, transaction processing (e.g., 
financial, health records, government services), and identity management. Jon Bosak of Sun once famously 
said “XML exists to give Java something to do.” Java and .NET as well as a plethora of popular scripting 
languages all prominently feature XML APIs and the vast enterprise applications are constructed with XML 
as the external – and sometimes internal – interface.
		</para></section><section><title>Is there economic benefit to a special-purpose chip for XML processing?</title><blockquote><para><emphasis>Assertion:</emphasis> Significant acceleration/offload of XML processing would improve the efficiency and value proposition of 
business-grade standard servers.</para></blockquote><para>
Metrics on the percentage of time spent processing XML on servers are, 
frankly, not fiable. However, our studies of major enterprise software applications has demonstrated a 
clear potential benefit to XML acceleration for the important class of servers dedicated to this task. 
There is an experimentally-demonstrable argument that XML acceleration will enable important classes of 
applications that clearly consume an unacceptable number of CPU cycles. These include: message-level 
security, federated identity management, and message transformation for inter-application communication. 
These XML-based technologies are key to addressing deep problems in security and identity and will further 
an open, cloud-based flexible computing model. The value of enabling ultra-low cost XML processing cannot 
be fully appreciated only by looking at the computing environment that exists where ulta-low cost XML 
processing capabilities do not exist.
		</para><para>
The specific value-related benefits that can be realized from XML acceleration include:
			<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Less CPU power needed as processing is offloaded onto a more effective special-purpose 
			processing unit. <emphasis>Lower unit cost.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para>Lower power consumption as the XML processing unit is more energy-efficient on XML 
			workloads. <emphasis>Lower operating costs.</emphasis></para><figure xml:id="powerstudy" floatstyle="0"><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="jpg" fileref="../../../vol4/graphics/Leventhal01/Leventhal01-001.jpg" width="100%"/></imageobject><caption><para>Power Consumption over XML Workload</para></caption></mediaobject></figure></listitem><listitem><para>Higher core utilization. Much of the hard work of parallelizing 
			applications to take advantage of multicore applications has been done in the XML chip 
			in the controller and software interface layer between the application software and hardware. 
			<emphasis>Reduction in the number of servers needed for peak loads.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para>Simplifies implementation and maintenance and management through ability 
			to meet peak loads, reduction in number of servers, elimination of bottlenecks, less 
			programming effort to parallelize applications. <emphasis>Lowers failure rate and cost overruns of major 
			IT projects.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist>
		</para></section><section><title>
Isn't XML acceleration in hardware an unproven approach?
	</title><blockquote><para><emphasis>Assertion:</emphasis> LSI’s Tarari group has successfully delivered XML acceleration co-processors for over six years. These 
products have been used in high-performance, specialized XML processing appliances.
	</para></blockquote><para>This technology is not a flash-in-the-pan; it has been proven by demanding customers of Tarari 
	over six years, processing billions of XML messages. It is a remarkable success story for 
	hardware-based acceleration, albeit, not generally well-known due to its initial targeting to the 
	niche market of specialized, network-oriented, XML processing appliances. The work on XML acceleration 
	actually goes back 4 years earlier, originating in a company acquired by Intel. Thus a total of ten 
	years of R&amp;D has been invested in this technology leading to successful commercialization.
	</para><para>
	The Tarari XML processor was used in web services gateways, application-oriented networking devices, 
	and security appliances. Tarari was bought by LSI Corporation in October of 2007. LSI continues to sell 
	an XML processor and to develop the technology. In  May of 2009 HP announced an appliance product 
	integrating the LSI Tarari XML chip and associated software with SAP’s integration platform software 
	NetWeaver PI. This product is first use of the XML chip directly integrated with a major enterprise 
	application software package, as opposed to prior experience with special-purpose XML acceleration 
	appliances and network devices. This development may be an important step in the mainstreaming of XML 
	acceleration hardware.
	</para></section><section><title>
Isn't an XML chip destined to quick obsolesence due to frequency scaling (Moore's Law) and parallelization 
(multicore)?
	</title><blockquote><para><emphasis>Assertion:</emphasis> The XML chip has increased in value with improvements in CPUs. The value proposition has greatly improved 
with the introduction of multicore.
	</para></blockquote><para><emphasis>Moore's Law:</emphasis> Debatable, of course, but the scientists and engineers
	in the chip making business seem to mainly agree that we've hit the limitations of physics in process
	technology. Which is why frequency is now increasing very slowly (or even decreasing)and every chipmaker
	is now focused on parallelization through multiple cores.</para><para><emphasis>Multicore:</emphasis> Again, plenty of room for disagreement, but a critical 
	mass of scientists and engineers caution that multiplying cores is not the new equivalent to Moore's 
	Law because parallelization is difficult - and also, often, labor intensive as many computer processing
	tasks must be redesigned by algorithmists and reprogrammed by engineers.</para><para>
While bearing the above viewpoints in mind, which strengthens the case for workload-specific computing
solutions, it is also our experience that the XML chip benefits from whatever improvement can still be
eked out from the remaining life in Moore’s Law; as frequency has scaled the relative value of the 
accelerator increases. This is because the chief bottleneck in use of the accelerator is the ability to 
feed the beast – that is, to get enough data fast enough from the network interface to the XML 
co-processor. Same is true for multicore. Multicore helps the accelerator and the XML chip also helps 
multicore because much of the hard work of parallelizing applications to take advantage of multicore 
applications has been done in the XML chip in the controller and software interface layer between the 
application software and hardware.
	</para><para>
Intel, among many other chip manufacturers, promotes the use of workload-specific "cores" or accelerators 
as a complementary part of its multicore strategy. The authors of this paper have joined with Intel the
last couple of years at IDF (Intel Developer Forum), showing the integration of the XML accelerator with
Intel multicore platforms. The figure below is based on the Intel view of the respective domains of
monocore, multicore, and multicore with additional, workload-specific cores such as an XML accelerator.
Multicore + the accelerator is needed to get to the upper right quadrant of efficiency and performance.
</para><figure xml:id="multicore" floatstyle="0"><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="jpg" fileref="../../../vol4/graphics/Leventhal01/Leventhal01-002.jpg" width="80%"/></imageobject><caption><para>Multicores and Workload-Specific Cores</para></caption></mediaobject></figure></section><section><title>
The successes with acceleration coprocessors have been few and far between. Graphics, floating point, 
cryptography, RAID, TOE – against many failures. Why will the XML chip be one of those rare exceptions?
	</title><blockquote><para><emphasis>Assertion:</emphasis> The success of the XML chip may be said
 	to be unexpected as it is a symbolic-computing device and not a number cruncher, the primary domain 
	where acceleration has been successful. Unique factors have contributed to make this the right
	technology to succeed at this time.</para></blockquote><para>
	First, a ubiquitious symbolic computation data format was a pre-condition, not just success in the
	technology, but just for justification for enough R&amp;D dollars to create the possibility of an XML
	chip. The success of XML might have run counter to expectations as well, but perhaps may have become
	inevitable once the a worldwide information infrastructure became a reality.</para><para>Second, the evolution of FPGA technology that has taken place was another game-changer without
	which the success of the XML chip would have been impossible. The choice of reconfigurable logic has 
	permitted the designers to pursue an evolutionary development path of approximately two major design 
	iterations per year and countless minor revisions over the lifetime of the product. This has been very 
	advantageous in an area where there was little hard science and engineering history to guide us. It 
	also permitted us to closely track the rapid evolution of microprocessor architecture and technology 
	instead of following one to two years in the wake of new general purpose processor introductions. 
	FPGA has also been the most cost-effective choice at the relatively low production volumes 
	characteristic of the early years of the introduction of a new infrastructure technology.</para><para>Author Lemoine was a student of the great pioneer of reconfigurable logic, Jean Vuillemin, 
	who demonstrated in the late 1980 and early 1990s that the programmable active memory could be used 
	to implement any computing function and serve as universal hardware co-processor coupled with the 
	host computer.</para><para>XML processing, a byte-oriented symbolic computing problem, is, in the application domain, 
	not an obvious choice for FPGA technology, Symbolic computing is difficult due to the lack of known 
	algorithms for acceleration in this area and a readily reducible problem space where bottlenecks have 
	been identified. The strategy, therefore, had to be evolutionary based on iterative and modular design 
	as experience was accumulated and also as the price-performance and capacity of FPGAs has improved, 
	expanding potential capabilities. It became evident that the development program would only have been 
	feasible with the use of reconfigurable logic; having now spanned 6 years,it has consistently yielded 
	progressively better results and a wider functional footprint.</para><para>
Finally, the proof of success is shown simply in the fact that we are still here. The XML chip technology 
has shown staying power, with 10 years of R&amp;D and a solid position in 
the niche market of XML network appliances. It is already a limited success and is ready to enter a wider 
market.
	</para><para>
The potential for a broader success is predicated on advances which, effectively, lower the payoff range 
for the added cost the co-processor and the continued use of XML as the ubiquitious language of 
computer-to-computer communication. Further expansion of XML use in the emerging IT landscape will help 
with new XML-intensive workloads in message-level security, identity management, inter-application message 
transformation and control-plane management of the cloud.
	</para></section><section><title>
Don’t all “transformation” accelerators have the fundamental problem that the acceleration value is 
largely neutralized by the copy-in, copy-out overhead? At least until you have cache coherence and 
accelerators have access to memory as equal citizens with the CPUs.
	</title><blockquote><para><emphasis>Assertion:</emphasis> Getting the data to and from the board
	is indeed among the major challenges; in the early years the XML chip was often a marginal solution
	because of it. With advances in the chip, it is rarely a major challenge today.</para></blockquote><para>
Copy-in, copy-out is certainly among the challenges with the current generation of accelerators. The XML 
chip is not strictly a transformation processor; many the processing problems it solves involve a computed 
result on the input and may save the copy-out step. Where a full copy-in, copy-out sequence is required 
very high acceleration values may still be obtained in most cases because of the goodness of the output 
structures produced by the accelerator. These structures would be prohibitively costly to construct with 
a software process but once they are constructed by the hardware they can be used to greatly accelerate 
subsequent processing of the XML content in software.
	</para><para>
The key to understanding this is to understand that the XML chip produces only limited acceleration for 
many of the established approaches to constructing XML processing software where copy-in, copy-out remains
a serious problem and produces remarkable levels of acceleration for equally-valid approaches that have 
been little exploited in the past due to their inefficiency without purpose-build XML hardware. The LSI 
XML chip has an extensive API which enables easy construction of applications using approaches essentially 
unique to performance characteristics obtainable using its special features.</para><para>
An example of a well-established XML processing approach which yields only limited 
acceleration with the XML chip is use of the Document Object Model (DOM). The DOM is memory intensive, 
constructing a tree-structure model of the XML document prior to navigating the document to extract the 
desired data. The cost of construction of the tree may be amortized in a long-lived document which is 
scanned repeatedly and deeply but is generally a poor performer in typical transactional applications.  
The vast majority of XML applications are implemented using the DOM due to the number of robust free 
tools. In some cases an underlying DOM representation can be replaced by our Random Access XML (RAX) API. 
This is the strategy we employed in creating our own version of an XSLT engine, RAX-XSLT.
	</para><para>
We would, however, like very much to accelerate "inefficient" software processes to enable acceleration
with the XML chip to be applied to legacy applications. There are developments in computer architecture
that may make this feasible. Cache-coherent accelerator-friendly architectures may be the next wave for 
special purpose co-processors.  While the integration between the XML accelerator and CPU has been designed successfully 
around the memory-copy problem, eliminating this problem will certainly enable new approaches to 
co-processing.
	</para></section><section><title>
Prove to me you can’t do accelerated XML with a Von Neumann core.
	</title><blockquote><para><emphasis>Assertion:</emphasis> It is the guaranteed structure of that
	enables a non-Von Neumann micro-parallelism which gets much more work done on a single tick. The
	question really is can a special-purpose device created by a handful of people from the most
	efficient design possible beat a general computing device at the same task when thousands have
	labored to make that device as fast as possible? The success of the XML chip seems to lie in
	XML itself, which challenges the Von Neumann architecture yet has proven highly tractable to
	alternate approaches.</para></blockquote><para>
Nonetheless, there are many things we cannot do at the scale of effort put into the XML chip and for this 
reason our strategy has always been to <emphasis>accelerate</emphasis> the software running on the
host processor. Simply in terms of logic components, We can’t implement that much XML processing on our
chip. The XML chip, asan XML software accelerator, is expressly designed to improve the performance of 
software run on a Von Neumann core.  While we continue to carve more and more of the XML processing 
problem into hardware the problem remains too general and hence too large that we would anticipate that a 
chip will ever fully offload XML processing. The intelligence of our design rests in the way we have 
integrated special-purpose XML hardware with the XML software stack to fully leverage the value of the 
capability of the hardware again and again in software processes.
	</para><para>
The strongest evidence the hybrid of special-purpose hardware with a 
non-Von Neumann architecture and software running on a Von Neumann architecture is in the comparative 
results obtained with highly optimized XML software and also with our own software which emulates the 
exact functionality of the hardware. XML has been use for over a decade and there have been many attempts 
to create high-performance XML software components. We test our hardware against these continuously. Our 
software which emulates the hardware tends to perform in the higher range, comparable to the best of 
software-only approaches.
	</para><para>
The following table compares the performance of hardware (hybrid specialized hardware and software) versus 
optimized XML software for a number of operations. The measurement is normalized into host cycles per byte 
of processed XML. These are numbers with the current LSI product. 
	</para><table border="1" pgwide="1"><caption><para>
Hardware/Software Compared to Software-Only (Von Neumann architecture) Performance
	</para></caption><thead><tr><td rowspan="2">
XML Operation
	</td><td rowspan="2">
Description
	</td><td colspan="2">
Host Cycles/Byte
	</td></tr><tr><td>
Chip
	</td><td>
Optimized SW
	</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
Parser Attack Checks
	</td><td>
Parallel to parsing; detects buffer overflow and resource exhaustion attacks against parser
	</td><td rowspan="3">
10
	</td><td>
N/A
	</td></tr><tr><td>
Well-formed Checks
	</td><td>
Parser-based well-formed check
	</td><td>
80-400
	</td></tr><tr><td>
Message-based anomaly detection
	</td><td>
Detects messages which deviate from statistical norm; adaptive; stronger than schema validation
	</td><td>
N/A
	</td></tr><tr><td>
Parsing
	</td><td>
Token-based parsing with sequential and random-access to all XML objects
	</td><td>
20
	</td><td>
SAX 80 DOM 400
	</td></tr><tr><td>
Content-based Routing
	</td><td>
Routing decisions based on large XPath sets
	</td><td>
30
	</td><td>
500-1600
	</td></tr><tr><td>
Schema Validation
	</td><td>
XML Schema Validation
	</td><td>
40
	</td><td>
600-2000
	</td></tr><tr><td>
XSLT
	</td><td>
XSLT
	</td><td>
400-900
	</td><td>
1200-10000
	</td></tr><tr><td>
XML Security
	</td><td>
XML-based Authentication based on XML and WS Security specifications
	</td><td>
450-800
	</td><td>
1400-2600
	</td></tr></tbody></table></section><section><title>
If I start a project to use an XML chip won’t I find that after 3 years of planning and development 
that “Moore’s cores blew up our tailpipe again”?
	</title><blockquote><para><emphasis>Assertion:</emphasis> You sort of have already asked this. 
	The XML chip has been a bold experiment, not, until today, for the faint of heart. But it is starting
	to look like a safe choice.</para></blockquote><para>
The XML chip, as an XML software accelerator, increases in acceleration value as CPUs get faster. Since 
we began commercialization of the technology CPU frequencies have doubled and the number of cores has 
quadrupled while the acceleration value of the co-processor has steadily increased with each advance in 
CPU architecture and performance. We're still here.
	</para></section></article>