<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3" xml:id="Bal2011sall0227"><title>Determining the Impact of Eric Clapton on Music Using RDF Graphs</title><subtitle>Selected Challenges of Semantics Across and Within Datasets</subtitle><info><confgroup><conftitle>Balisage: The Markup Conference 2011</conftitle><confdates>August 2 - 5, 2011</confdates></confgroup><abstract><para>
                As music is a topic of interest to many, it is no surprise that 
                developers have applied web and semantic technology to provide various RDF datasets 
                for describing relationships among musical artists, albums, 
                songs, genres, and more. As avid fans of blues and rock music, we 
                wondered if we could construct SPARQL queries to examine properties and 
                relationships between performers in order to answer global questions 
                such as "Who has had the greatest impact on rock music?" Our primary 
                focus was Eric Clapton, a musical artist with a decades-spanning career 
                who has enjoyed both a very successful solo career as well as having 
                performed in several world-renowned bands.
                </para><para>The application of semantic technology to a public 
                dataset can provide useful insights into how similar approaches can be 
                applied to realistic domain problems, such as finding relationships 
                between persons of interest. Clearly understood semantics of available 
                RDF properties in the dataset is of course crucial but is a substantial 
                challenge especially when leveraging information from similar yet 
                different data sources.</para><para>This paper explores the use of DBpedia and MusicBrainz data sources 
                using OpenLink Virtuoso Universal Server with a Drupal frontend. Much 
                attention is given to the challenges we encountered, especially with 
                respect to relatively large datasets of community-entered open data sources of varying quality
                and the strategies we employed or recommend to overcome the challenges.               
            </para></abstract><author><personname><firstname>Ronald</firstname><othername>P.</othername><surname>Reck</surname></personname><personblurb><para> For over a decade Ronald P. Reck has operated the consulting company, <link xlink:href="http://www.rrecktek.com/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">RRecktek LLC</link>, outside of
                    Washington DC metropolitan area. RRecktek LLC has enjoyed over one hundred
                    contracts ranging from the data warehousing of state, local, and federal law
                    enforcement incident reports outside of submarine bases for The Navy Criminal
                    Investigative Service (NCIS) to vocabulary projects for the management and
                    dissemination of controlled vocabularies for the Directorate of National
                    Intelligence (DNI) as a member of the Intelligence Community Metadata Working
                    Group staff and a "simple" content management system for build out drawings for
                    global telecom company. Among the companies served include Nextel, Winstar, ANS
                    +COre, AOL, Standard &amp; Poors, The Federal Communications Commission,
                    Kiplingers Newletter, Radio Free Asia, Eastman Kodak, The United States
                    Information Agency, The Council of Better Business Bureaus, Department of
                    Defense Health Affairs and others. He prides himself on developing scalable,
                    open source architectural strategies for difficult problems. Ron resides with his
                    lovely wife Olga and the best son in the entire world. 
                </para></personblurb><affiliation><jobtitle>Principal</jobtitle><orgname>RRecktek LLC.</orgname></affiliation><email>rreck@rrecktek.com</email></author><author><personname><firstname>Kenneth</firstname><othername>B.</othername><surname>Sall</surname></personname><personblurb><para> Ken Sall has been supporting the US federal government in XML efforts since
                    1998. His customers include NASA, General Services Administration (GSA),
                    Department of Homeland Security (DHS), and the Intelligence Community. Sall has been
                    an active contributor to XML and data standardization efforts including the Federal
                    Enterprise Architecture - Data Reference Model (FEA DRM), the National Information
                    Exchange Model (NIEM), and the Intelligence Community Metadata Standards for
                    Publication (IC MSP), as well as participating in several federal XML and data
                    management working groups. As the author of 
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/XML-Family-Specifications-Practical-Guide/dp/0201703599/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">XML Family of Specifications: A
                    Practical Guide</link> (Addison-Wesley, 2002), he basks in the glory of quarterly
                    statements from his publisher that no longer include payments. Music is his
                    passion. XML too. 
                </para></personblurb><affiliation><jobtitle>Principal Systems Engineer/XML Data Analyst</jobtitle><orgname>Ken Sall Consulting</orgname></affiliation><email>kensall@gmail.com</email></author><author><personname><firstname>Wendy</firstname><othername>A.</othername><surname>Swanbeck</surname></personname><personblurb><para>
                    Wendy Swanbeck has worked as a software engineer for over 20 years. In the
                    past she has worked on a variety of projects including graphical design
                    programs, mainframe control systems, and CAD design software for commercial and
                    government projects. More recently she has been working at Eastman Kodak Company
                    writing software for networking systems, color management and photo manipulation
                    GUI software. She also donates some of her time creating websites for groups
                    that need it. Her passion is to architect and write clean, flexible and robust
                    software using the right tools for the job.
                </para></personblurb><affiliation><jobtitle>Principal</jobtitle><orgname>Wendy Swanbeck</orgname></affiliation><email>Wendy.Swanbeck@verizon.net</email></author><legalnotice><para>Copyright © 2011 Ronald P. Reck, Kenneth B. Sall, Wendy A. Swanbeck.  All rights reserved.</para></legalnotice><keywordset role="author"><keyword>RDF</keyword><keyword>SPARQL</keyword><keyword>OWL</keyword><keyword>semantics</keyword><keyword>Semantic Web</keyword><keyword>ontology</keyword><keyword>Open Data</keyword><keyword>LOD</keyword><keyword>SVG</keyword><keyword>Graphviz</keyword><keyword>Drupal</keyword><keyword>music</keyword></keywordset></info><!-- Filename guidelines: Bal2011sall0227.xml --><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="png" fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-001.png" width="90%"/></imageobject></mediaobject><section><title>Introduction and Pre-History</title><para>A long, long time ago in a galaxy much like our own, one of the authors, Ken Sall,
            was fascinated by the number of musicians who had played with John Mayall. <footnote xml:id="intro01"><para>He believes it was circa 1972 in Buffalo, New York. But his recollection
                    of the Seventies is much like his recollection of the Sixties.</para></footnote>          
            Armed only with paper, pencil and lots of record album jackets, he drew a diagram 
            with Mayall at the center and arcs pointing to musicians who played with him, such as
            Eric Clapton, Peter Green, Mick Taylor, etc. Then he drew arcs from these musicians to others they
            had played with. Soon he reached the limit of the paper. Since this was prior to the 
            emergence of the PC, there was no option to scroll or easily copy to a larger drawing
            area. But Ken held onto this labor of trivia for nearly 40 years.
            (<emphasis role="ital">See </emphasis><xref linkend="mayall"/>.)
            Meanwhile, Pete Frame developed far more detailed and visually appealing 
            rock family trees <xref linkend="pframe"/>, 
            some of which appeared in various publications such as Rolling Stone magazine
            and the <emphasis role="ital">Encyclopedia of Rock</emphasis>. 
        </para><para>
            Nearly everyone is familiar with the Six Degrees of Kevin Bacon
            trivia game <xref linkend="kbacon"/>.
            The Bacon number is based on a game where actors were rated on distance they were away from the actor
            Kevin Bacon. Actors who appeared in a movie with Kevin Bacon were given a Bacon number of 1, and actors
            having only been in movies with actors with a Bacon number of 1 were given a Bacon number of 2.
            Each degree of separation lead to increasing the Bacon number by 1.
            The object is to connect any movie star to Mr. Bacon with no more than six hops based on 
            two people appearing in either the same movie or commercial.        
            This is a popular special case
            of the more general Six Degrees of Separation <xref linkend="sixDegrees"/>
            also known as the <quote>Human Web</quote>. The idea is that any two people on the planet can be
            connected by no more than six hops.
            According to Wikipedia," Mathematicians use an analogous notion of collaboration distance".
        </para><figure xml:id="mayall"><title>John Mayall Connections</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="jpg" fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-002.jpg" width="100%"/></imageobject></mediaobject><caption><para>Dozens of musicians are within a few degrees of separation from John Mayall (circa 1972).</para></caption></figure></section><section><title>Problem Statement</title><para> 
            Using semantic technology, we can certainly improve upon hand copying of data from
            record album jackets. If we can refer to a recording artist with all the associations to
            other musicians and to the albums they appeared on together, we can produce more
            complete graphs than what is shown in <xref linkend="mayall"/>.
            <!-- If we had access to all the detailed information 
            about rock and blues musicians and who played with whom, we could construct an RDF dataset 
            perhaps spanning multiple graphs that could
            be queried using SPARQL to draw fascinating (at least to these authors) conclusions about relatedness. -->
            As avid fans of blues and rock music, we wondered if we could construct SPARQL queries
            to examine properties and relationships between performers in order to answer global
            questions such as "Who has had the greatest impact on rock music?" Our primary focus was
            Eric Clapton, a musical artist with a decades-spanning career who has enjoyed both a
            very successful solo career as well as having performed in several world-renowned bands.
            Then using Drupal and SVG to visualize the results, we could traverse the musician
            graphs in a straightforward manner. 
        </para><para>This paper explores the use of DBpedia and MusicBrainz data sources using OpenLink
            Virtuoso Universal Server with a Drupal frontend. Much attention is given to the
            challenges we encountered, especially with respect to community-entered open data
            sources and the strategies we employed to overcome the challenges.
            One such challenge we encountered was that there were several properties by which an artist
            could be connected to another and the semantics were not well-defined, as discussed later.
        </para><para>
           We should be able to draw inferences from the data. According to Dean Allemang and Jim Hendler:</para><blockquote><para>In the context of the Semantic Web, inferencing simply means that given some stated information,
                we can determine other related information that we can also consider as if it had been stated.              
            </para><attribution><xref linkend="SemWebBook"/></attribution></blockquote><para>For example, ultimately we plan to use RDF and SPARQL to address questions such as these:
            <orderedlist xreflabel="Problems" xml:id="problemList"><listitem><para>Which recording artist has directly played with the most musicians?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which recording artist has the most connections within six degrees?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which musician has been a session man for the most number of artists?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which recording artist was most active during a particular decade?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Among all artists of a particular genre, who has played with the most other musicians?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which rock artist's extended graph has the most other artists in 2 degrees? 3 degrees? 4 degrees?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Who has appeared on the most albums?</para></listitem><listitem><para>If we weight results by the length of time a band stays together, how does that impact other queries?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Can we distinguish between legitimate releases and unofficial releases?</para></listitem><listitem><para>What additional inferences can be made when multiple graphs are queried?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Can results be corroborated by comparing results to ground truths (i.e. documented in <link xlink:href="http://recordresearch.com/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Joel Whitburn's Billboard books</link>)?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which musician-related properties are reversible (inverse makes sense)?</para></listitem><listitem><para>How can we differentiate between a musician's playing in a band, being associated with other musicians, 
                    starring together in a live show, and others collaborating with the musician?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Does total number of songs or album released correlate with other measures of success?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Who created the most songs?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which song has been recorded the most times by any artists? 
                    ("Yesterday" and "White Christmas" are typically cited.)</para></listitem><listitem><para>Is there a predominant record label in the music world?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which solo artist has had the longest career?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which band has been together (in some form) the longest time?</para></listitem><listitem><para>What is the average age of a musician when he/she first joined a band?</para></listitem><listitem><para>For bands with changing membership, can we conclude which configuration lasted the longest?</para></listitem><listitem><para>What is the "Eric Clapton number" (a la Kevin Bacon number) for various musicians?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Can we use our own knowledge of Eric Clapton to clarify some of the semantics behind some of the RDF data we encounter?</para></listitem></orderedlist>                
        </para><para>
            Our notion of a musical artist's activity and impact can be explained in general terms. We consider
            <emphasis role="ital">activity</emphasis> to be correlated with the number of recordings produced. 
            Another factor that we chose not to consider is an artist's concert performances 
            unless they resulted in a commercially available recording.
            An artist's <emphasis role="ital">impact</emphasis> is more subjective. The greater the number of
            musicians that play with a performer (the greater the number of associations), the greater the
            potential impact of the performer, provided that the performer is not simply a session man. 
            Another measure that would have proved extremely helpful in determining both
            activity and impact in a more quantitative manner would be the use of Billboard chart data.
            Unfortunately, use of Billboard data is not royalty free.<footnote><para>
                    According to <xref linkend="billboardAlbums"/>, 
                    Clapton released 41 albums (including reissues) from 1970 to 2005. (He has released three more as of July 2011.) 
                    This includes eleven Top 10 albums
                    and three number 1 albums. Whitburn devised a formula for ranking artists by their chart success,
                    with rankings per decade and overall. According to Whitburn's calculations as of 2006, 
                    Clapton ranked #10 in the 1990's and ranked #12 all-time; he ranks #21 in most charted albums.
                </para></footnote>
        </para><para>
            Furthermore, our working definitions  of activity and impact is primarily based on commercial recordings of an artist.
            We acknowledge that some artists tend to perform numerous live concerts and yet have produced
            relatively few commerical recordings; many of these concerts may be available on bootleg recordings.
            The argument could easily be made that the number of concerts and/or number of bootleg recordings
            are correlated with activity and/or impact. We have chosen not to consider these factors at this time.
        </para></section><section xml:id="dataSources" xreflabel="Data Sources"><title>Data Sources</title><para>Fortunately in 2011, there is a tremendous wealth of information about musicians freely
            available on the Web either in structured markup, especially triples, that lends itself to
            SPARQL queries. For example, Wikipedia tells us that Eric Clapton <xref linkend="eclapton"/> is associated with:
            Dire Straits, The Yardbirds, John Mayall &amp; the Bluesbreakers, Powerhouse, Cream, Free Creek, 
            The Dirty Mac, Blind Faith, J.J. Cale, The Plastic Ono Band, Delaney, Bonnie &amp; Friends, Derek and the Dominos, and T.D.F.
            By comparison, Ringo Starr <xref linkend="rstarr"/> is associated with The Beatles, Rory Storm and the Hurricanes, 
            Ringo Starr &amp; His All-Starr Band, and Plastic Ono Band. On the surface, Ringo's direct associations are fewer,
            but actually Ringo Starr &amp; His All-Starr Band has had 11 different lineups (to date)
            with a total of 42 unique musicians, most of whom have a number of associations as well. <xref linkend="allStarBand"/>
        </para><para>The various data sources we leveraged are discussed in the following subsections.</para><section xml:id="wikipediaSection" xreflabel="Wikipedia Section"><title>Wikipedia and Infoboxes</title><para>
                The primary (although indirect) source for our RDF data was Wikipedia which
                is a major source of detailed information about musicians, among many other things. To understand both
                the kinds of properties available and their open community origins, some details about
                Wikipedia are in order.
            </para><para>
                As illustrated by the excerpt from <xref linkend="claptonWikipedia"/> below, 
                the <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric_Clapton" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">main page</link> for a musical artist
                contains an abstract at the top, a contents navigation box below the abstract with a variable number
                of section links pointing to the main content of the page, 
                and a so-called <emphasis role="ital">infobox</emphasis> in the upper right.
                In addition to a main page,
                most musical artists with more than a handful of albums or singles have a separate 
                <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric_Clapton_discography" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">discography page</link> with
                varying amount of detail and organization regarding studio albums, live albums, compilations, singles, etc.
                The discography is linked to the musician's main page and vice versa.
            </para><figure xml:id="claptonWikipedia" xreflabel="Clapton's Wikipedia page"><title>Eric Clapton's Wikipedia Page (excerpt with Infobox on right)</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="png" fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-003.png" width="100%"/></imageobject></mediaobject><caption><para>Wikipedia. "Eric Clapton -- Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia". 2011.</para></caption></figure><para> An <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:Infobox" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">infobox</link> is
                a fixed-format table designed to be added to the top right-hand corner of Wikipedia
                articles to consistently and concisely present a summary of some common aspects that
                the articles of the same category (i.e., musical artist) share, as well as to
                improve navigation to other interrelated articles (i.e., music genres). Infoboxes
                are an instance of MediaWiki's template feature; there are numerous infobox
                templates arranged by broad <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Infobox_templates" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">categories</link> such as <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Arts_and_culture_infobox_templates" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">arts and culture infobox templates</link>, which is further divided into 10
                subcategories including templates for film, fictional characters, and music. There
                are over 50 templates in the subcategory <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Music_infobox_templates" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">music
                    infobox templates</link> of which the most relevant to our work is the <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_musical_artist" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">template for the infobox of musicial artists</link>. (See the right side of
                    <xref linkend="infoboxTable"/> below.) This infobox template is used by
                Wikipedia authors to create infoboxes such as Clapton's, shown in the left side of the table. The
                correspondence between the template and the resultant infobox is apparent when
                viewed side by side. Most of the properties that we used in our queries (e.g., name,
                genres, associated acts, etc.) are based on the contents of the infobox, with the
                notable exception of albums (from the discography page).
            </para><table xml:id="infoboxTable" xreflabel="Table 1" cellspacing="50"><caption><para>Clapton's Infobox (left) and Generic Musical Artist Infobox Template (right) [cited 03 Apr 2011]</para></caption><tbody align="center"><tr align="center"><td>
                            <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-004.png"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>                          
                        </td><td>
                            <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-005.png"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>                           
                        </td></tr></tbody></table><para>
                The wiki source markup of the infobox is shown in <xref linkend="infoboxMarkup"/>. For a much more complete
                explanation of the Wikipedia extraction process employed by DBpedia including a discussion of 
                the design and development of infobox templates,
                see <xref linkend="Auer1"/> and <xref linkend="Auer2"/>.
                <figure xml:id="infoboxMarkup" xreflabel="Figure 3"><title>Wiki Source Markup for Clapton Infobox</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-006.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject><caption><para>Compare markup to rendering shown in Table 1.</para></caption></figure>
            </para></section><section xml:id="dbpediaSection" xreflabel="DBpedia Section"><title>DBpedia</title><para>
                One of the two primary dataset we used was DBpedia 3.6 en (English) based on Wikipedia dumps from October/November 2010.
                DBpedia <xref linkend="dbp01"/> is a community effort to provide sophisticated query access to the structured content of
                Wikipedia, thereby allowing a small group of researchers and developers to enhance Wikipedia by linking to additional datasets.
                The DBpedia 3.6 release announcement
                describes the content in detail:            
                <blockquote><para>
                    "The new DBpedia dataset <xref linkend="dbp02"/> describes more than 3.5 million things, of which
                    1.67 million are classified in a consistent ontology, including 364,000
                    persons, 462,000 places, 99,000 music albums, 54,000 films, 16,500 video
                    games, 148,000 organizations, 148,000 species and 5,200 diseases.
                    
                    The DBpedia dataset features labels and abstracts for 3.5 million things in
                    up to 97 different languages; 1,850,000 links to images and 5,900,000 links
                    to external web pages; 6,500,000 external links into other RDF datasets, and
                    632,000 Wikipedia categories.
                    
                    The dataset consists of 672 million pieces of information (RDF triples) out
                    of which 286 million were extracted from the English edition of Wikipedia
                    and 386 million were extracted from other language editions and links to
                    external datasets."
                    </para></blockquote>
            </para><para>  The DBpedia Ontology <xref linkend="dbp03"/> is a cross-domain ontology 
                    created from the most commonly used infoboxes within Wikipedia. 
                    The ontology currently covers over 272 classes with 1,300 different properties and 1.667 million resources,
                    364,000 of which are Persons.  
                    DBpedia predicate IRIs <footnote><para>IRI is Internationalized Resource Identifier, a generalization of the Uniform Resource Identifier (IRI) 
                            enabling the use of Unicode. In this paper, we refer to IRI rather than URI since SPARQL
                        technically permits IRIs.</para></footnote> begin with either <code>http://dbpedia.org/ontology</code> or 
                <code>http://dbpedia.org/property</code>; entitites are designated 
                by <code>http://dbpedia.org/resource</code>.
                </para><para>
                    We initially used a simple SPARQL query <xref linkend="sparql01"/> to determine what properties are relevant to a musician
                    as shown in the following two listings. Some musicians had less than the 23 properties shown;
                    others had more. Note that the <code>resource</code> IRI designating the musician is a straightforward rendering of
                    the artist's name in English with underscores replacing spaces: 
                    <code>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton</code>.
                   <figure><title>Display Properties Defined for Eric Clapton (as object)</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                       
            SELECT DISTINCT (?predicate) WHERE {
                ?s ?predicate &lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&gt;.
            } ORDER BY ?predicate         
                       
                       </programlisting></figure>             
                    <figure xml:id="ClaptonPropertiesV1" xreflabel="Clapton's DBpedia Properties - Version 1"><title>Clapton's DBpedia Properties - Version 1 (23 Predicates)</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/artist
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedBand
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedMusicalArtist
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/composer
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/musicComposer
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/musicalArtist
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/musicalBand
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/partner
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/producer
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/spouse
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/starring
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/wikiPageDisambiguates
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/writer
                http://dbpedia.org/property/associatedActs
                http://dbpedia.org/property/before
                http://dbpedia.org/property/currentMembers
                http://dbpedia.org/property/music
                http://dbpedia.org/property/pastMembers
                http://dbpedia.org/property/producer
                http://dbpedia.org/property/spouse
                http://dbpedia.org/property/starring
                http://dbpedia.org/property/writer
                http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#sameAs
                    </programlisting></figure>
                    In a later section, we discuss alternative property-related queries with different results.
                </para><para>Wikipedia-like categories can also be specified in queries. The following query returns
                    the short list of musical artists who have three distinctions: Grammy Award winners, Rock and Roll Hall of Fame inductees, and
                    MTV Video Music Awards winners.
                </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
        SELECT  ?allAwards
        { 
         ?allAwards &lt;http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject&gt; 
                              &lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Grammy_Award_winners&gt;.
         ?allAwards &lt;http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject&gt; 
                              &lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Rock_and_Roll_Hall_of_Fame_inductees&gt;.
         ?allAwards &lt;http://purl.org/dc/terms/subject&gt; 
                              &lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:MTV_Video_Music_Awards_winners&gt;
        } ORDER BY ?allAwards                
                
            </programlisting><para>The thrice-honored, distinguished musical artists are:
            <footnote><para>If we add one more clause to the query asking also for 
                    <code>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:English_rock_guitarists</code>, 
                    then Eric Clapton is the only result.</para></footnote>
            </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Aerosmith
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Bruce_Springsteen
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Elton_John
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Johnny_Cash
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Madonna_%28entertainer%29
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Metallica
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Michael_Jackson
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/R.E.M.
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/The_Beatles
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/The_Rolling_Stones
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/U2
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Van_Halen                
                
            </programlisting><para>
                The <link xlink:href="http://mappings.dbpedia.org/server/ontology/classes/MusicalArtist" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">full list of predicates relating to MusicalArtist</link> 
                is quite large. The figure below is a partial view of the <link xlink:href="http://dbpedia.org/page/Eric_Clapton" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">DBpedia "About: Eric Clapton"</link> page.
                    The IRI <code>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton</code> forwards to this page.
                        <figure><title>Dereferencing the Eric Clapton DBpedia IRI (excerpt)</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="png" fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-007.png" width="100%"/></imageobject><imageobject><imagedata format="png" fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-008.png" width="100%"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure>            
                </para></section><!-- end DBpedia --><section xml:id="musicbrainzSection" xreflabel="MusicBrainz Section"><title>MusicBrainz</title><para>MusicBrainz <xref linkend="musicBrainz"/> is another comprehensive public database for musician information; it
                contains detailed data about artists, release groups, releases, tracks, record labels and many relationships between them.
                As described in the <link xlink:href="http://musicbrainz.org/doc/MusicBrainz_Database#Data_Overview" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">database overview</link>,
                MusicBrainz defines artist attributes including the artist's name, aliases, GUID, annotation, type (individual or group), and
                begin and end dates (birth/death of an individual or formation/disbanding for a group).  A release group is a logical grouping
                of variant releases (deluxe/limited editions, reissues/remasters, international variations, box sets, etc.). One example is
                the release group describing several 
                <link xlink:href="http://musicbrainz.org/release-group/ced848a4-b94b-3f34-b08b-6dc8bf8aed8f.html" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">variants of Clapton's 461 Ocean Boulevard album</link>.
                Each release group is identified by type (album, single, EP, compilation, soundtrack, live, etc.), as well as by artist, title, and ID.
                An individual release has the same properties as a release group as well as status (official, bootleg, etc.), Amazon ASIN,
                annotation, language, release event (date, country, format, label, etc.) and more. Each track has properties such as
                duration (in milliseconds) and PUID (the MusicIP acoustic fingerprint identifier for the track) as well as artist, title, and ID.
                Record labels are also described with a number of detailed attributes. 
            </para><para>
                Every MusicBrainz ID (MBID) is a permanent GUID. There is a direct relationship between an artist's MBID, a IRI that
                identifies the artist, and a web page that collects information about the artist. For example:
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Eric Clapton's MBID is 618b6900-0618-4f1e-b835-bccb17f84294</para></listitem><listitem><para>Eric Clapton's IRI is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://musicbrainz.org/mm-2.1/artist/618b6900-0618-4f1e-b835-bccb17f84294</link> (points to basic RDF metadata)</para></listitem><listitem><para>His MusicBrainz page is <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://musicbrainz.org/artist/618b6900-0618-4f1e-b835-bccb17f84294.html</link></para></listitem></itemizedlist>            
            </para><para> Below is a screenshot of the
                <link xlink:href="http://musicbrainz.org/artist/618b6900-0618-4f1e-b835-bccb17f84294.html" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Eric Clapton MusicBrainz page</link>.
                MusicBrainz offers a tremendous amount of detail about releases as exemplified by the page for Clapton's classic
                <link xlink:href="http://musicbrainz.org/show/release/relationships.html?releaseid=3923" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">From the Cradle</link> blues album.
                    <figure><title>Eric Clapton's MusicBrainz Main Page</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="png" fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-009.png" width="100%"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure>                     
            </para><para>
                MusicBrainz also provides a <link xlink:href="http://wiki.musicbrainz.org/XML_Web_Service" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">web service interface</link> to its extensive database.
                Requests may be English-like such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://musicbrainz.org/ws/1/artist/?type=xml&amp;name=Eric+Clapton</link> or
                may contain MBIDs such as <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://musicbrainz.org/mm-2.1/album/1301e027-b038-4017-9b4c-7655bff78f6b</link> for the 
                "461 Ocean Boulevard" album, shown below. (Release dates of 1974 and three from 1996 are collapsed 
                in the screenshot.)
                <figure><title> Web Service Result - Query for 461 Ocean Boulevard</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="png" fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-010.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure>   
            </para><para>
                MusicBrainz maintains numerous <link xlink:href="http://musicbrainz.org/statistics" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">database statistics</link>,
                a small sampling of which appear below. It is interesting to note that in the three months since the draft version
                of this paper, although the number of Recordings increased by approximately 37,000,
                the Artist count dropped by roughly 8,000.  This seems to suggest the dynamic nature of the data both in terms
                of quantity and in how recordings are categorized. (For example, artists may have appeared under variant name 
                spellings.) We could not find a definition for the new term <emphasis role="ital">Works</emphasis> in the
                <link xlink:href="http://musicbrainz.org/doc/MusicBrainz_Terminology" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">terminology page</link> or other
                <link xlink:href="http://musicbrainz.org/doc/MusicBrainz_Documentation" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">MusicBrainz documentation</link>.
            </para><table frame="border"><caption><para><emphasis role="bold">Selected MusicBrainz Statistics</emphasis> [accessed 10 April 2011; updated 26 June 2011]</para></caption><tbody><tr><td>Artists</td><td>612,428</td></tr><tr><td>Release Groups</td><td>787,918</td></tr><tr><td>Releases</td><td>952,743</td></tr><tr><td>Disc IDs</td><td>460,876</td></tr><tr><td>Recordings [tracks]</td><td>10,307,311</td></tr><tr><td>Labels</td><td>52,156</td></tr><tr><td>Works</td><td>276,864</td></tr><tr><td>Relationships [links]</td><td>3,160,096</td></tr></tbody></table><para>
                The MusicBrainz <link xlink:href="http://musicbrainz.org/doc/Data_Quality" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest"> data quality</link> page
                states that one of the goals is "Establish a method to determine the quality of an artist and the releases that belong to that artist. 
                This provides consumers of MusicBrainz a clue about the relative quality rating of the data in the database."
                The page explains the connection between the quality number, voting periods, and strictness regarding edits.
            </para><blockquote><para>To accomplish these goals, this feature will allow editors to indicate the quality for a given artist. 
                    An artist can be of unknown, low, medium or high data quality. The data quality indicator determines what 
                    level of effort is required to change the artist information or to add/remove albums from an artist. 
                    An artist with unknown or medium quality will roughly require the amount of effort that MusicBrainz currently 
                    requires to edit the database. An artist with low data quality will make it easier to add/remove albums or
                    to change the artist information (name, sortname, aliases). And an artist with high data quality will 
                    require more effort to add/remove albums or the change the artist information. 
                    The data quality concept also applies to releases in the same manner. Changing a release with low data
                    quality will be easier than changing a release with high data quality.
                </para></blockquote></section><!-- end MusicBrainz --><section xml:id="freebaseSection" xreflabel="Freebase Section"><title>Freebase</title><para> Initially we considered using music data from Freebase <xref linkend="freebaseHome"/>, an open, community-based, Creative Commons licensed
                repository of structured data describing millions of entities (i.e., person, place,
                thing) which are connected as a graph. Freebase IDs can be used to uniquely identify
                entities from any web-reachable source. At the time of this writing, the 1.22 GB
                (uncompressed) music segment of Freebase contained 9 million topics and 33 million
                facts. The music category contains classical, opera, and many other genres in
                addition to blues and rock music. Data is formatted as approximately 50 separate Tab
                Separated Values files with filenames such as group_member.tsv,
                group_membership.tsv, musical_group.tsv, guitarist.tsv, album.tsv, artist.tsv,
                release.tsv, and track.tsv (the largest file at roughly 671 MB). A total of over
                151,000 groups are listed in musical_group.tsv. <footnote><para>The full Freebase data set in TSV format is 1.3 GB compressed. The entire
                        Freebase data dump is also available as quadruples in a 3.36 GB download.
                        When uncompressed, the single file freebase-datadump-quadruples.tsv is 27.3
                        GB. </para></footnote>
            </para><para> Freebase data can be used in several ways. MQL (Metaweb Query Language) <xref linkend="mql"/> is a query API analogous to SPARQL for RDF. MQL uses JSON
                objects as queries via standard HTTP requests and responses. For example, the IRI
                below will return all the genres associated with Eric Clapton (line breaks added for
                readability). <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                       
        http://api.freebase.com/api/service/mqlread?query={%20%22query%22:
        {%20%22active_start%22:null,%20%22genre%22:[],%20%22name%22:%22Eric%20Clapton%22,
        %20%22type%22:%22/music/artist%22%20}%20}                   
                    
                </programlisting> will produce the following result,
                indicating all the genres associated with Eric Clapton: </para><para>
                <figure><title>Freebase Genre Results for Eric Clapton</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                {
                  "code": "/api/status/ok",
                  "result": {
                    "active_start": null,
                    "genre": [
                      "Blues",
                      "Rock music",
                      "Blues-rock",
                      "Pop rock",
                      "Hard rock",
                      "Psychedelic rock",
                      "Reggae"
                    ],
                    "name": "Eric Clapton",
                    "type": "/music/artist"
                  },
                  "status": "200 OK",
                  "transaction_id": "cache;cache03.p01.sjc1:8101;2011-01-26T22:45:13Z;0054"
                }
                </programlisting></figure> We will see later that this list of genres differs from other data
                sources. </para><para>For any given group, band members are non-sequential within the
                group_membership.tsv file. The relevant lines for the members of Blind Faith are
                collected in the table below.</para><table><caption><para><emphasis role="bold">Members of Blind Faith - from
                        Freebase</emphasis></para></caption><thead><tr><th>id</th><th>member</th><th>group</th><th>(role)</th><th>start</th><th>end</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>/m/01tfhrr</td><td>Ginger Baker</td><td>Blind Faith</td><td> </td><td>1968</td><td>1969-10</td></tr><tr><td>/m/01tfhry</td><td>Steve Winwood</td><td>Blind Faith</td><td> </td><td>1968</td><td>1969-10</td></tr><tr><td>/m/01wvwr8</td><td>Ric Grech</td><td>Blind Faith</td><td> </td><td>1968</td><td>1969-10</td></tr><tr><td>/m/01tfhrk</td><td>Eric Clapton</td><td>Blind Faith</td><td> </td><td>1968</td><td>1969-10</td></tr></tbody></table><para> The group_membership.tsv file contains dozens of entries for Clapton, one line
                for each band or other association in which he participated. Each entry (line) is
                identified by a different ID. For example:
                <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       /m/01t73cp	Eric Clapton	Derek and the Dominos                   
                </programlisting>
            </para><para><link xlink:href="http://www.freebase.com/view/en/eric_clapton" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Eric Clapton's
                    main Freebase page</link> is shown below. The IRI format for Clapton as a topic
                is <code>http://www.freebase.com/view/en/eric_clapton</code>. <figure><title>Eric Clapton's Freebase Page</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="png" fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-011.png" width="100%"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure>
            </para><para>Ultimately we elected not to use Freebase as a data source because we, like
                others, were unable to locate the complete Freebase dataset rendered as RDF and
                determined that the conversion process would be non-trivial. In fact, we found
                mailing list and forum messages with others expressing the same problem. Initially
                we had downloaded the dataset in its native format and considered converting it into
                RDF. This would have been possible although many of the lines contained a fourth
                element consisting of a number of values concatenated together; it was unclear how
                that could be cleanly converted into a named graph. After the rough draft of our
                paper was submitted, we discovered that RDF data is available manually by following
                a link labeled "RDF" near the bttom of each Freebase page. It appears that
                this RDF is rendered at execution time since there is a slight delay in the display
                of the RDF. For example, follow the <link xlink:href="http://rdf.freebase.com/rdf/en.eric_clapton" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">RDF link on the Eric
                    Clapton page</link>. Had we discovered this sooner we might have attempted to
                obtain the Freebase RDF for Rock and Roll stars using some automated process.
            </para></section><!-- end Freebase --></section><!-- end Data Sources --><section><title>Methodology</title><para>In this section, we discuss our frontend and backend development platform, a few term definitions,
        and details concerning the Graphviz visualization which is still under development as of this July writing.
        </para><section><title>Development Environment</title><para>The front end to our SPARQL queries was a guest virtual machine running under Sun
                VirtualBox 3.1.6_OSE. on a Dell Inspiron with an Intel Core 2 Quad CPU Q9400 running
                at 2.66GHz. The guest operating system is the 10.10 server release of Ubuntu Linux.
                <!-- The host operating system is the 10.04 server release of Ubuntu Linux.  --> The
                database machine leverages 2 Intel Xeon X5650 CPUs overclocked to 3.12GHz with 48
                gigabytes of RAM. From the perspective of the 10.10 Ubuntu Desktop operating system,
                the 2 hexcore processors are regarded as 24 processors (149867.81 BogoMIPS). </para><para>
                Our RDF store was the open source (freely-available) version of
                OpenLink Virtuoso Universal Server <xref linkend="virtuoso"/> (Version 06.01.3127) running in "Full Mode". Configuration changes were made to 
                maximize use of available RAM by making a change to the <code>virtuoso.ini</code> file: 
                "NumberOfBuffers = 7000000".
            </para><para>
                On the frontend, our queries were facilitated by Drupal 6.18 with the modules listed in the
                <xref linkend="drupalModules"/> appendix.
                It was necessary to configure PHP to allow Drupal more memory, so "memory_limit = 512M" 
                was added to <code>/etc/php5/apache2/php.ini</code>.
            </para><para>Drupal 7.0 became available during 2011, but we elected not to migrate to that version.
                Although Drupal 7.0 does have substantially better support for RDF data than earlier 
                versions, that is likely to only effect people publishing information that was
                authored or stored inside Drupal. Our use of Drupal was for collaborative development of and storing of
                queries, as well as for the visualization capabilities.</para></section><section xml:id="workingDefs" xreflabel="Working Definitions"><title>Working Definitions of Key Properties</title><para>The definition list below presents our current thinking about several key concepts that
            are covered in details in later sections; some refer to <xref linkend="openCyc"/>.
            </para><variablelist><varlistentry><term><link xlink:href="http://dbpedia.org/ontology/musicalArtist" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">dbpedia-owl:musicalArtist</link></term><listitem><para>a person who is either a musician who plays one or more instruments,
                        or is a singer, or is a music composer; similar (but not identical) to
                        <code>http://musicbrainz.org/mm/mm-2.1#Artist</code></para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term><link xlink:href="http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedMusicalArtist" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">dbpedia-owl:associatedMusicalArtist</link></term><listitem><para>both the subject and object of this predicate are musicians;
                        similar to <code>http://musicbrainz.org/ar/ar-1.0#collaboratedWith</code></para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term><link xlink:href="http://dbpedia.org/property/associatedActs" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">dbpprop:associatedActs</link></term><listitem><para>this is mapped either to associatedBand (for subjects who are individual artists) or
                        associatedMusicalArtist (for bands)</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term><link xlink:href="http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedBand" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">dbpedia-owl:associatedBand</link></term><listitem><para>
                            OpenCyc: An element of <link xlink:href="http://sw.opencyc.org/concept/Mx4rvgEZGJwpEbGdrcN5Y29ycA" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Band_MusicGroup</link> 
                            is a (small or large) group of musicians who play 
                            non-Classical music together on either a regular or intermittent schedule. 
                        </para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term><link xlink:href="http://dbpedia.org/ontology/genre" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">dbpedia-owl:genre</link></term><listitem><para>a categorization of music into types that can be distinguished from other types of music;
                    can be applied to a musical artist, a band, an album, or individual songs.</para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist></section><!-- NOT USED
        <section>
            <title>IRI vs. IRI</title>
            <para>SPARQL requires IRIs rather than IRIs.</para>
        </section> 
        end NOT USED --><section><title>RDF Visualization Coding</title><para>
                In order to better understand our result sets a form of visualization was 
                implemented as a custom Drupal module, written in PHP.  
                The front end was a simple HTML form with JQuery and AJAX for displaying the information.  
                Main processing was handled by the PHP module setup to intercept a post to a particular URL.  
                The PHP module first accesses the POST data and extracts the input search term which became the subject of the following SPARQL query:
             <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                 
                 SELECT DISTINCT ?predicate ?object 
                 WHERE {&lt;" . $subject . "&gt; ?predicate ?object } 
                 ORDER BY ?predicate
                 
             </programlisting> 
                where in our initial implementation <code>$subject</code> is replaced by the musician subject requested by the user.
                XML output is specified by the request as the desired return format.
            </para><para>
                The next step was to convert the XML results output from the query to the
                Graphviz input format <link xlink:href="http://www.graphviz.org/content/dot-language" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">DOT language</link>. 
                Graphviz <xref linkend="graphvizHome"/> is open source graph visualization software that converts
                descriptions of graphs in a simple text language either to diagrams in various formats 
                (e.g., images, SVG, PDF, Postscript) or for display in an interactive graph browser.
            </para><para>
                Using the <code>SimpleXMLElement</code> class (from the PHP library), the code loops through the 
                results of the SPARQL query &lt;binding&gt; elements, accessing the “name” attribute of each one. 
                If the name attribute is ‘predicate’ (from the ?predicate variable in our SPARQL query), 
                the predicate is obtained from the &lt;uri&gt; subelement.  
                If the name attribute is ‘object’ (from the ?object variable in the query), 
                the value is obtained from the &lt;uri&gt; subelement or the &lt;literal&gt; subelement, 
                depending on which is present in the XML output of the query.  
                If the &lt;uri&gt; subelement is found, we use the uri target for display, 
                but use the complete uri for the link, for use in future queries that the user can select.
                
            </para><para> The Graphviz text input file is constructed incrementally by adding Graphviz
                format input statements for each &lt;binding&gt; element. Since Graphviz defines
                links and colors in a separate section of the file, the XML &lt;binding&gt; elements
                are searched a second time to create the Graphviz <code>[label]</code> entries. (To
                improve performance, we may do this in a single loop populating two sections of the
                Graphviz input at once.) A static set of predefined colors is defined in the module.
                As new predicates (i.e., artist, associatedMusicalArtist, associatedBand,
                musicComposer, producer, writer, etc.) are encountered, new colors are assigned by
                taking the next one from the list and associating it with the new predicate.
                Use of an associative array allows predicates of the same type to be assigned the same color.
                The Graphviz input string is completed when all the &lt;binding&gt; elements have
                been processed and a header and footer are added. 
            </para><para> The SVG data is created by sending the Graphviz input string to the
                graphviz_filter_process method available by means of a Graphviz filter module
                installed on the Drupal site. The SVG description is serialized by the filter
                module. At this point the return information is structured using the Drupal function
                    <code>drupal_json</code> to create JSON formatted data. The SVG data and the XML
                data are each added as named elements of the JSON data and returned to the caller.
            </para><para> To use this module, an HTML page with a short embedded JQuery script invokes the
                module and displays the results. The HTML defines an input text field, a search
                button and two &lt;div&gt; elements which initially contain no content. They are
                given the IDs outputGraph and outputTable so content can be associated later using
                JavaScript (JQuery).The user interface is a simple text field into which the user
                types the name of the musician subject and then presses a search button which runs a
                JQuery function that posts the input field to the module previously described using
                AJAX. The AJAX method waits for the data to be returned from the module in JSON
                format. When the JSON data arrives, the returned SVG data and XML data are assigned
                to the &lt;div&gt; elements with the correct IDs. 
            </para><para>The figure below shows one of the Graphviz digraphs.
                
            <figure xml:id="digraphFig" xreflabel="Graphviz SVG Digraph"><title>Sample Graphviz SVG Digraph (linebreaks added for readability)</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
digraph G {
/*
* @title = CLAPTON
* @formats = svg
*/
rankdir=LR
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Unplugged_(Eric_Clapton_album)&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Just_One_Night_(album)&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Behind_the_Sun_(Eric_Clapton_album)&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Journeyman_(album)&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Back_Home_(Eric_Clapton_album)&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Reptile_(album)&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Live_in_Japan_(George_Harrison_album)&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;August_(album)&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Steppin&amp;#039;_Out_(Eric_Clapton_album)&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Edge_of_Darkness_(soundtrack)&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Backless&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;461_Ocean_Boulevard&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;No_Reason_to_Cry&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Slowhand&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;Pilgrim_(Eric_Clapton_album)&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;From_the_Cradle&amp;quot;[ label = &amp;quot;artist&amp;quot; ]
&amp;quot;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&amp;quot;-&amp;gt;&amp;quot;One_More_Car,_One_More_Ride] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[log] =&gt; [] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[revision_timestamp] =&gt; [1300136539] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[format] =&gt; [4] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[name] =&gt; [wendy] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[picture] =&gt; [] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[data] =&gt; [a:1:{s:13:&amp;quot;form_build_id&amp;quot;;s:37:&amp;quot;form-18d527e00db0361bf4cea1b231176078&amp;quot;;}] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: green;"&gt; 
[rdf] =&gt; array ( &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: green;"&gt; ) &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: green;"&gt; 
[path] =&gt; [content/claptonsvg] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;);&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/fieldset&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;fieldset class="toggler"&gt;
&lt;legend&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="#"&gt;&lt;em&gt;view&lt;/em&gt; $node-&gt;112&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/legend&gt;
&lt;div class="content" style="display: none;"&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;$node = (&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; 
&lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[nid] =&gt; [112] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[type] =&gt; [graph] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[language] =&gt; [] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[uid] =&gt; [3] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[status] =&gt; [1] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt;
[created] =&gt; [1300117673] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[changed] =&gt; [1300136539] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[comment] =&gt; [0] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[promote] =&gt; [1] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[moderate] =&gt; [0] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[sticky] =&gt; [0] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[tnid] =&gt; [0] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[translate] =&gt; [0] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[vid] =&gt; [112] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[revision_uid] =&gt; [3] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt; 
[title] =&gt; [claptonSvg] &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span style="color: black;"&gt;
[body] =&gt; [&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;graphviz graphviz-&amp;quot;svg&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;object type=&amp;quot;image/svg+xml&amp;quot;
data=&amp;quot;http://www.vocabutek.com/sites/default/files/graphviz/ca80a36e3d121526b2b93ec1f1e076a3.svg&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;embed type=&amp;quot;image/svg+xml&amp;quot; 
  src=&amp;quot;http://www.vocabutek.com/sites/default/files/graphviz/ca80a36e3d121526b2b93ec1f1e076a3.svg&amp;quot;
  pluginspage=&amp;quot;http://www.adobe.com/svg/viewer/install/&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/object&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
]                
                
                </programlisting></figure>
                The SVG graphic produced by this Graphviz DOT file was too large to present here.
                See <xref linkend="vocabutek"/>.
            </para></section><!-- end RDF Visualization Coding --><section><title>Interface Screenshots</title><para>
                A sampling of our interface on <xref linkend="vocabutek"/> is presented in the following figures.
                As of this writing, the Graphviz visualization is expected to undergo changes.
                <xref linkend="qEntry"/> illustrates how we entered queries in the Drupal interface to test.
            </para><figure xml:id="qEntry"><title>Query Entry</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-012.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para><xref linkend="qResult"/> displays the result of executing the query shown in <xref linkend="qEntry"/>.</para><figure xml:id="qResult"><title>Query Result</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-013.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para>We used the Drupal adminstration content management to organize queries into cascading menus, as shown
            in <xref linkend="qAdmin"/>.</para><figure xml:id="qAdmin"><title>Query Administration - Menu Organization</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-014.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para>The result of the query organzation is shown in <xref linkend="qMenus"/></para><figure xml:id="qMenus"><title>Cascading Menus</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-015.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para><xref linkend="qVisualize"/> illustrates the interface for running a query to send to Graphviz for
            rendering in SVG. Pre-tested queries can be copy/pasted into a single string (topmost text field) or new
            queries can be entered. The subject defaults to Eric Clapton but any musician can be entered.</para><figure xml:id="qVisualize"><title>Visualize a Query - Copy/Paste or Enter</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-016.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para>Finally, <xref linkend="qGraphviz"/> depicts part of the SVG resulting from a query, as 
            rendered by Graphviz. (This is one aspect we plan to improve over time.)</para><figure xml:id="qGraphviz"><title>Graphviz AssociatedBand SVG</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol7/graphics/Sall01/Sall01-017.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></section><!-- end Interface Screenshots --></section><!-- end Methodology --><section xml:id="results" xreflabel="Challenges and Results"><title>Challenges and Results</title><para>Our results were hampered by various anomalies or complications discovered in the data sources
            especially in terms of semantics. 
            In this section, we present some of the problems we encountered and either how they were solved or how they might be approached
            in the future.
        </para><section><title>Properties of a Musical Artist</title><para>We next consider a different view of Clapton predicates.
                The query below returns properties with an object value that contains the string "Eric Clapton".</para><para>
                <figure><title>Find Predicates for Which Clapton is (all or part of) the Object</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                            
        SELECT DISTINCT ?predicate  WHERE  {
            ?s ?predicate ?o.
            FILTER regex(?o, "Eric Clapton").
        } ORDER BY ?predicate                       
                                                     
                      </programlisting></figure>
            </para><para>
                Compare the result below to that presented in figure <xref linkend="ClaptonPropertiesV1"/>.
                
                <figure xml:id="claptonPropertiesV2" xreflabel="Clapton's DBpedia Properties - Version 2"><title>Clapton's DBpedia Properties - Version 2 (44 Predicates)</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/abstract
                http://dbpedia.org/ontology/alias
                http://dbpedia.org/property/after
                http://dbpedia.org/property/album
                http://dbpedia.org/property/alias
                http://dbpedia.org/property/allWriting
                http://dbpedia.org/property/altArtist
                http://dbpedia.org/property/artist
                http://dbpedia.org/property/associatedActs
                http://dbpedia.org/property/aux
                http://dbpedia.org/property/before
                http://dbpedia.org/property/caption
                http://dbpedia.org/property/chronology
                http://dbpedia.org/property/composer
                http://dbpedia.org/property/cover
                http://dbpedia.org/property/description
                http://dbpedia.org/property/extra
                http://dbpedia.org/property/founders
                http://dbpedia.org/property/fromAlbum
                http://dbpedia.org/property/img
                http://dbpedia.org/property/imgCapt
                http://dbpedia.org/property/label
                http://dbpedia.org/property/lastAlbum
                http://dbpedia.org/property/lyrics
                http://dbpedia.org/property/music
                http://dbpedia.org/property/musicalguests
                http://dbpedia.org/property/name
                http://dbpedia.org/property/namedAfter
                http://dbpedia.org/property/nextAlbum
                http://dbpedia.org/property/note
                http://dbpedia.org/property/notes
                http://dbpedia.org/property/partner
                http://dbpedia.org/property/pastMembers
                http://dbpedia.org/property/producer
                http://dbpedia.org/property/recordedBy
                http://dbpedia.org/property/shortDescription
                http://dbpedia.org/property/starring
                http://dbpedia.org/property/text
                http://dbpedia.org/property/thisAlbum
                http://dbpedia.org/property/title
                http://dbpedia.org/property/writer
                http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/title
                http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label
                http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/name                           
                        </programlisting></figure>
            </para><para>
                When we subsequently connected the DBpedia and MusicBrainz data sources as discussed in
                <xref linkend="bridgingSources"/> below, we obtained a third view of Clapton's properties,
                shown in figure <xref linkend="claptonPropertiesCombined"/>.
            </para></section><!-- end Properties --><section><title>Along Comes the Association</title><para>
                The paramount requirement in determining an Eric Clapton Number is the ability to
                unambiguously identify those musicians with whom he directly worked. Originally we
                thought this would be rather straightforward. Properties that seemed relevant to
                making that determination included:
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para><code>http://dbpedia.org/property/associatedActs</code></para></listitem><listitem><para><code>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedBand</code></para></listitem><listitem><para><code>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedMusicalArtist</code></para></listitem><listitem><para><code>http://dbpedia.org/property/starring</code></para></listitem><listitem><para><code>http://dbpedia.org/property/musicalguests</code></para></listitem></itemizedlist>
                The <code>musicalguests</code> property was eliminated because it relates only to variety shows such as 
                "The Late Show". The <code>starring</code> property also proved to be unreliable since multiple
                musicians might have all been considered stars of a performance but might not have played together.
                One case in point is the <link xlink:href="http://dbpedia.org/page/The_Concert_for_Bangladesh" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">The Concert for Bangladesh</link>; 
                a query returned Klaus Voorman, Billy Preston,
                Bob Dylan, Eric Clapton, George Harrison, Leon Russell, Ravi Shankar, and Ringo Starr. While
                most of these performers did share the stage at one time during the concert, Ravi Shankar did not
                perform with the others. Furthermore, members of the band Badfinger did play with most of the
                others, but they were not returned by the query although we note that Badfinger is cited in the abstract of
                the Wikipedia article in the list of stars of the supergroup.  On the other hand, if we look at the infobox
                on the <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concert_For_Bangladesh" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">concert's Wikipedia page</link>, 
                Badfinger is not listed as one of the stars.
            </para><para>
                We considered the <code>associatedActs</code> property since that is the term used in the infobox.
                As seen in <xref linkend="infoboxTable"/>, the infobox on <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric_Clapton" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Clapton's Wikipedia page</link> 
                lists these associated acts:
                "The Yardbirds, John Mayall &amp; the Bluesbreakers, Powerhouse, Cream, Free Creek, The Dirty Mac,
                Blind Faith, J.J. Cale, The Plastic Ono Band, Delaney, Bonnie &amp; Friends, Derek and the Dominos".        
            </para><para> Our initial attempt to retrieve these artists was a little surprising. Our query
                was: <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                    
        SELECT DISTINCT  ?who
        {  &lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/property/associatedActs&gt; ?who.
        } ORDER BY ?who                    
                    
                </programlisting> The result, shown below, was one long string
                <footnote><para>Technically this is an object value comprised of a number of strings concatenated into a single field.</para></footnote>
                the contents of which represented a superset of the associated acts on the
                Wikipedia page. The additional associated acts are underlined below.
                <programlisting xml:space="preserve">  
        "The Yardbirds, John Mayall &amp; the Bluesbreakers, Powerhouse, Cream, Free Creek, Dire Straits, 
        <emphasis role="under">George Harrison</emphasis>, The Dirty Mac, Blind Faith, <emphasis role="under">Freddie King, Phil Collins</emphasis>, 
        J.J. Cale, The Plastic Ono Band, Delaney, Bonnie &amp; Friends, Derek and the Dominos, 
        <emphasis role="under">T.D.F., Jeff Beck, Paul McCartney, Steve Winwood, B.B. King, The Beatles, The Band</emphasis>"@en
                </programlisting>
                It is unclear how there could be this disparity since the DBpedia data is derived
                from Wikipedia. Although several of the underlined performers played with Clapton,
                they were not in bands together (as far as we could determine). Furthermore, several
                of the bands listed on the original Wikipedia page are arguably not exactly bands in
                the general sense since they existed only briefly and for a specific purpose. The Dirty
                Mac were a supergroup consisting of Eric Clapton, John Lennon, Keith Richards and
                Mitch Mitchell that came together for The Rolling Stones' TV special. Free Creek was
                a band composed of many musical artists, including Eric Clapton, Jeff Beck, Keith
                Emerson, for one super-session album. Powerhouse only recorded a few songs, only three of
                which were released on a compilation album. These "bands" are certainly not
                on a par with the others in the infobox since they were never intended to exist beyond
                their stated purpose.
            </para><para>
                Perhaps our interpretation of the <code>associatedActs</code> property was incorrect? Further
                examination of the DBpedia and Wikipedia documentation pointed us to the 
                <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_musical_artist" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">template for the infobox of musicial artists</link>, 
                shown on the right side of <xref linkend="infoboxTable"/> in the earlier Wikipedia section.       
                The template <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_musical_artist#associated_acts" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">description of associated_acts</link>
                from Wikipedia follows. (Numbers have been added for ease of reference and 
                the text has been reformatted.)
                <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
            This field is for professional relationships with other musicians or bands
            that are significant and notable to this artist's career.                  
            This field can include, for example, any of the following:           
            a1) For individuals: groups of which he or she has been a member
            a2) Other acts with which this act has collaborated on multiple occasions, 
               or on an album, or toured with as a single collaboration act playing together
            a3) Groups which have spun off from this group
            a4) A group from which this group has spun off            
            Separate multiple entries with commas. 
            
            The following uses of this field should be avoided:           
            b1) Association of groups with members' solo careers
            b2) Groups with only one member in common
            b3) Association of producers, managers, etc. (who are themselves acts) 
               with other acts (unless the act essentially belongs to the producer, 
               as in the case of a studio orchestra formed by and working exclusively 
               with a producer)
            b4) One-time collaboration for a single, or on a single song
            b5) Groups that are merely similar
                </programlisting>
                Based on (a1), (a2) and (b4), it would seem that Powerhouse and arguably The Dirty Mac and Free Creek
                should be eliminated from the list of groups of which Clapton was a member.
                <footnote><para>We believe this is indicative of the 
                        <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_world_assumption" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">open world assumption</link> in formal logic.</para></footnote>
                
            </para><para>
                Further investigation brought us to the numerous
                <link xlink:href="http://mappings.dbpedia.org/index.php?title=Special%3AAllPages&amp;from=&amp;to=&amp;namespace=204" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">DBpedia Infobox Mappings</link>
                and specifically to the <link xlink:href=" http://mappings.dbpedia.org/index.php/Mapping:Infobox_musical_artist" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">ontology mapping for the Infobox for Musical Artists</link>.
                The (infobox) template property <code>Associated_acts</code> maps to two ontology properties,
                <code>associatedBand</code> and <code>associatedMusicalArtist</code>, meaning that the infobox property
                can refer to either a group (case (a3) and (a4) above) or to an individual (cases (a1) and (a2)).
            </para><para>
                Therefore we turned our attention to queries involving the ontology properties
                <code>associatedBand</code> and <code>associatedMusicalArtist</code>. The following query
                asks for the bands in which Clapton was a member.
                <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                    
        SELECT DISTINCT  ?who WHERE
        {&lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedBand&gt; ?who.
        } ORDER BY ?who                    
                    
                </programlisting>
                The results are shown below. Note that the results are nearly identical to the string superset 
                shown earlier. (The only exception is X-sample and a few band name variations.)
                The same results are obtained if the predicate is replaced by <code>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedMusicalArtist</code>.
                <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                    
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/B.B._King
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Blind_Faith
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Cream_%28band%29
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Delaney,_Bonnie_&amp;_Friends
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Derek_and_the_Dominos
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Dire_Straits
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton%27s_Powerhouse
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Freddie_King
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Free_Creek_%28band%29
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/George_Harrison
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/J.J._Cale
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Jeff_Beck
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/John_Mayall_&amp;_the_Bluesbreakers
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Paul_McCartney
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Phil_Collins
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Steve_Winwood
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/The_Band
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/The_Beatles
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/The_Dirty_Mac
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/The_Plastic_Ono_Band
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/The_Yardbirds
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/X-sample                    
                    
                </programlisting>
            </para><para>
                When we reverse the order of the subject and object, the results can be interpreted as musicians who have
                played on Clapton's albums. The query:
                <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                    
      SELECT DISTINCT  ?who WHERE
      {?who &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedBand&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&gt;.
      } ORDER BY ?who              
                    
                </programlisting>
                yields these results:
                <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                    
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Aashish_Khan
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Alan_Clark_%28keyboardist%29
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Albert_Lee
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Andy_Fairweather_Low
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/B.B._King
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Billy_Preston
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Bobby_Keys
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Chris_Stainton
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Chuck_Leavell
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Dave_Carlock
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Dave_Mason
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Doyle_Bramhall_II
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Freddie_King
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Ian_Wallace_%28drummer%29
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Jamie_Oldaker
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Jeff_Beck
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Jesse_Ed_Davis
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Jim_Gordon_%28musician%29
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Leon_Russell
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Mac_and_Katie_Kissoon
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Marc_Benno
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Marcella_Detroit
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Nathan_East
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Otis_Spann
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/P._P._Arnold
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Phil_Collins
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Phil_Palmer
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Pino_Palladino
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Plastic_Ono_Band
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Ray_Cooper
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Reverend_Zen
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Richard_Cole
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rita_Coolidge
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rob_Fraboni
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Sheryl_Crow
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Steve_Ferrone
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Steve_Jordan_%28musician%29
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Stevie_Ray_Vaughan
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/The_Shaun_Murphy_Band
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Yvonne_Elliman                    
                    
                </programlisting>
                The same results are obtained if the predicate is replaced by <code>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedMusicalArtist</code>.
            </para><para>
                How are <code>associatedBand</code>, <code>associatedMusicalArtist</code>, and <code>associatedActs</code> related? 
                We believe the relationship varies across performers depending upon how individual collaborators interpreted the terms.
                Consider the following similar queries and their very different results, including many performers who are
                unfamiliar to all of the present authors.  
              <figure><title>Comparsion of associatedBand, associatedActs and associatedMusicalArtist</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
  
   SELECT  ?artist (count (?who) as ?count) {  
      ?artist  &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedBand&gt; ?who.         
   }  ORDER BY DESC (?count) LIMIT 10 
   
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Stan_Levey                                            80
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Frank_Fenter                                          46
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Gary_Kellgren                                         42
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Norman_Granz                                          42
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Tim_&amp;_Bob                                             39
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Frankie_Banali                                        38
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Neil_Cooper_%28ROIR%29                                37
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Ian_Wallace_%28drummer%29                             34
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Tha_Dogg_Pound                                        34
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/DonGuralEsko                                          31   
    ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

   SELECT  ?artist (count (?who) as ?count) {  
      ?artist  &lt;http://dbpedia.org/property/associatedActs&gt; ?who. 
   }  ORDER BY DESC (?count) LIMIT 10   
   
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Gary_Kellgren                                         42
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Johnny_Goudie                                         36
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Even_Steven_Levee                                     33
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Shelter_%28band%29                                    29
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Emmylou_Harris                                        29
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Conny_Plank                                           27
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Exit-13                                               27
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/K.Will                                                27
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Warren_Zevon                                          27
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Damian_LeGassick                                      25  
    ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

   SELECT ?person (count(?person) as ?count) {
      ?artist &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedMusicalArtist&gt; ?person.
   } ORDER BY DESC (?count) LIMIT 10

    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Snoop_Dogg                                            81
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Ozzy_Osbourne                                         63
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Wu-Tang_Clan                                          56
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Dr._Dre                                               52
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Guns_N%27_Roses                                       52
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Lil_Wayne                                             51
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Morning_Musume                                        50
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Jay-Z                                                 50
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Bob_Dylan                                             48
    http://dbpedia.org/resource/Miles_Davis                                           48
  
              </programlisting></figure>
            </para></section><!-- END Associated Acts --><section xml:id="bridgingSources" xreflabel="Bridging Data Sources"><title>Bridging the Data Sources</title><para>
                In order to address some of the more difficult questions or compare results between data sources,
                we needed a way to combine the RDF datasets, or at least to connect musical artist identifiers
                across DBpedia and MusicBrainz. 
            </para><!-- programlisting>
                        Our initial solution was the query shown below, but 
                        this proved to be inadequate.
                    <![CDATA[
                    select * {
                    ?s <http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#type> <http://dbpedia.org/ontology/MusicalArtist>.
                    ?s <http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label> ?dbpedianame.
                    ?mbiri <http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#type> <http://musicbrainz.org/mm/mm-2.1#Artist>.
                    ?mbiri <http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/title> ?mbname.
                    FILTER (regex(?mbname, ?dbpedianame))
                    }            
                    ]]>
                   </programlisting --><para> We employed the OpenLink Virtuoso Universal Server <xref linkend="virtuoso"/> as
                an RDF store. While there are other very good RDF stores such as <link xlink:href="http://4store.org/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">4store</link>, the Virtuoso Universal Server <footnote><para>The OpenLink Virtuoso Universal Server supports relational data
                        management, XML and RDF data management, free text content management with
                        full text indexing and web services, and functions as a document web server,
                        linked data server and web application server.</para></footnote> is compelling because it supports reasoning. <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backward_chaining" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Backward-chaining
                    reasoning</link> is the ability to derive new information based on existing
                information at run time. This contrasts with forward chaining reasoning in which derived information
                is expressed explicitly. An example of forward chaining reasoning would be creating
                and adding triples that represented new information that was inherent in information the
                datastore already contained. 
                <footnote><para>"Inference is moreso the means or mechanisms by which reasoning
                        occurs. Reasoning is the 'goal' whereas inferencing is the
                        'implementation'". -- From <link xlink:href="http://answers.semanticweb.com/questions/3036/whats-the-difference-between-reasoning-and-inferencing" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">answers.semanticweb.com</link>. </para></footnote> 
                There are two major costs to leveraging backward chaining reasoning. The
                first and foremost cost is that derived information is created each time it is needed; it is therefore quite likely
                that the same information is derived repeatedly at run time. The advantage, however,
                is that the derived information does not take up any space in the database. The
                second requirement for leveraging backward chaining reasoning in Virtuoso is the use
                of specific predicates, none of which were available in the native datasets with
                which we worked. 
            </para><para> 
                Given that the IRI for Eric Clapton was different in DBPedia and MusicBrainz, we used forward
                chaining to express the relatedness between these two IRI’s and thereby facilitating
                backward chaining reasoning in queries. We used the SPARQL
                <code>INSERT</code> directive to create new statements which made
                assertions explicit as a forward-chaining reasoning strategy. Specifically, the
                assertions we added leveraged the <code>owl:sameAs</code><footnote><para><link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/owl-ref/#sameAs-def" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">owl:sameAs</link> is often used in establishing mappings between two or more ontologies.</para></footnote> predicates 
                <link xlink:href="http://docs.openlinksw.com/virtuoso/rdfsparqlrule.html#rdfsameas" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Virtuoso defines</link> to empower
                reasoning. The
                following query was used to create an assertion stating that the DBpedia Subject IRI of type
                <code>http://dbpedia.org/ontology/MusicalArtist</code> corresponds to the MusicBrainz Subject IRIs of type
                <code>http://musicbrainz.org/mm/mm-2.1#Artist</code> whenever the DBpedia
                <code>rdf-schema#label</code> matches the MusicBrainz <code>dc:title</code>
                exactly. <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                    
            SPARQL INSERT in GRAPH inference/sameAs&gt; 
            {?mbiri &lt;http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#sameAs&gt; ?s} 
            WHERE { 
            ?s &lt;http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#type&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/MusicalArtist&gt;. 
            ?s &lt;http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label&gt; ?dbpedianame. 
            ?mbiri &lt;http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#type&gt; &lt;http://musicbrainz.org/mm/mm-2.1#Artist&gt;. 
            ?mbiri &lt;http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/title&gt; ?mbname. 
            FILTER (str(?mbname) = str (?dbpedianame)) };    
                    
                </programlisting>
                This query resulted in the addition of 16,029 <code>owl:sameAs</code> assertions to our datastore which took 
                109,692,665 msec (30.47 hours) to complete.
            </para><para>Since neither these assertions nor the DBpedia and MusicBrainz assertions were in
                the same <code>NAMED GRAPH</code>, it was necessary to use another unique
                capability of the Virtuoso Universal Server called <code>GRAPH GROUPs</code>. 
                This enabled us to refer to multiple <code>NAMED GRAPHs</code> as if they were one. First we
                created a <code>GRAPH GROUP</code> with the following command: 
            </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
            DB.DBA.RDF_GRAPH_GROUP_CREATE ('http://group.dbpedia.inference','1'); 
            </programlisting><para>
                Then we placed the previously created <code>owl:sameAs</code> assertions, as well as
                the <code>NAMED GRAPHs</code> containing DBpedia assertions and the MusicBrainz assertions 
                into the <code>GRAPH GROUP</code>:   
            </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
            DB.DBA.RDF_GRAPH_GROUP_INS('http://group.dbpedia.inference' , 'inference/sameAs'); 
            DB.DBA.RDF_GRAPH_GROUP_INS('http://group.dbpedia.inference' , 'http://mytest.com');
            DB.DBA.RDF_GRAPH_GROUP_INS('http://group.dbpedia.inference' , 'http://musicbrainz.com');                
            </programlisting><para>
                To demonstrate that the <code>owl:sameAs</code> assertions we are indeed
                intersecting the two datasets, consider the following query that determines the properties
                connecting Eric Clapton to resources. Compare this to the figure
                <xref linkend="ClaptonPropertiesV1"/>.
            </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
            DEFINE input:same-as "yes" 
            SELECT DISTINCT ?predicate  
            FROM &lt;http://group.dbpedia.inference&gt; WHERE 
             {  
             ?s ?predicate &lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&gt;.             
             } ORDER BY ?predicate 
                
            </programlisting><para>
                The result of this query is 30 properties which is 7 more than the result when querying only DBpedia,
                6 of which come from MusicBrainz. Compare this result to the previous query results shown in
                figures <xref linkend="ClaptonPropertiesV1"/> and <xref linkend="claptonPropertiesV2"/>.
            </para><figure xml:id="claptonPropertiesCombined" xreflabel="Clapton's Properties Combined"><title>Clapton's Properties in Combined Datastore (DBpedia and MusicBrainz) (30 predicates)</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
            http://dbpedia.org/ontology/artist
            http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedBand
            http://dbpedia.org/ontology/associatedMusicalArtist
            http://dbpedia.org/ontology/composer
            http://dbpedia.org/ontology/musicComposer
            http://dbpedia.org/ontology/musicalArtist
            http://dbpedia.org/ontology/musicalBand
            http://dbpedia.org/ontology/partner
            http://dbpedia.org/ontology/producer
            http://dbpedia.org/ontology/spouse
            http://dbpedia.org/ontology/starring
            http://dbpedia.org/ontology/wikiPageDisambiguates
            http://dbpedia.org/ontology/writer
            http://dbpedia.org/property/associatedActs
            http://dbpedia.org/property/before
            http://dbpedia.org/property/currentMembers
            http://dbpedia.org/property/music
            http://dbpedia.org/property/pastMembers
            http://dbpedia.org/property/producer
            http://dbpedia.org/property/spouse
            http://dbpedia.org/property/starring
            http://dbpedia.org/property/writer
            http://musicbrainz.org/ar/ar-1.0#composer
            http://musicbrainz.org/ar/ar-1.0#instrument
            http://musicbrainz.org/ar/ar-1.0#performer
            http://musicbrainz.org/ar/ar-1.0#producer
            http://musicbrainz.org/ar/ar-1.0#toArtist
            http://musicbrainz.org/ar/ar-1.0#vocal
            http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/creator
            http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#sameAs                
                
            </programlisting></figure><para>
                Any queries that benefit from using a single IRI to refer to the same artist in both datasets 
                becomes available by adding <code>DEFINE input:same-as "yes"</code> before our result clause.
            </para><para>
                The same 30 results can be obtained with the <code>UNION</code> query below. However, this query
                requires knowledge of the GUID-based MusicBrainz IRI for each musician of interest,
                whereas the above query takes advantage of the previously established
                correspondence between the methods of artist identification in DBpedia and MusicBrainz.
                Therefore, the <code>owl:sameAs</code> approach is clearly the better solution.
            </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
            SELECT DISTINCT ?predicate WHERE {
             { 
             ?s ?predicate &lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&gt;.             
             } 
            UNION
             { 
             ?s ?predicate &lt;http://musicbrainz.org/mm-2.1/artist/618b6900-0618-4f1e-b835-bccb17f84294&gt;.             
             } 
            } ORDER BY ?predicate                
                                
            </programlisting></section><!-- end Bridging the Data Sources --><section><title>You Say It's Your Birthday?</title><para> Given the ability to bridge the two datasets, we can now issue queries that
                compare data values across the sets. The query below obtains the birthdates for each
                musical artist in both sources and returns the discrepancies. </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
         DEFINE input:same-as "yes" select ?musician ?DBPdate  ?MBdate 
         {
          ?s &lt;http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#type&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/MusicalArtist&gt;. 
          ?s &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/birthDate&gt; ?DBPdate . 
          ?s &lt;http://musicbrainz.org/mm/mm-2.1#beginDate&gt; ?MBdate. 
          ?s &lt;http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#label&gt; ?musician. 
          FILTER (str(?MBdate) != str (?DBPdate))
         } 
        ORDER BY ?musician               
                
            </programlisting><para> A sampling of the nearly <emphasis role="ital">one thousand</emphasis> mismatched
                birthdates follows. Typically the differences are one day, one month, or one year,
                but note several major differences. We have yet to independently verify all of the
                discrepancies, but we note that the birthday of George Harrison is incorrect in
                MusicBrainz. In fact, MusicBrainz often uses "00-00" dates indicating only the year
                is known. It is probably safe to conjecture that Courtney Love is not 21 and Five
                For Fighting (singer-songwriter John Ondrasik) is not 14, so these birthdates are
                more likely when their musical careers started. Wikipedia confirms that 1997 is indeed
                the first "year active" for Five For Fighting, but Love's initial "year
                active" is 1982. Clearly the interpretation of MusicBrainz's <code>beginDate</code> property
                varies across artists.
                Our tentative conclusion is that DBpedia is more accurate than
                MusicBrainz with respect to birthdates. </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
            musician            DBPdate 	 MBdate
        50 Cent                1975-07-06 	1976-07-06
        Andy Partridge         1953-11-11 	1953-12-11
        Astrud Gilberto        1940-03-29 	1940-03-30
        Blind Willie Johnson   1897-01-22 	1902-00-00     [5 year difference]
        Blind Willie McTell    1898-05-05 	1901-05-05     [3 year difference]
        Carl Perkins           1932-04-09 	1928-08-16     [4 year difference]
        Courtney Love          1964-07-09 	1990-00-00     [extremely different!]
        David Lee Roth         1954-10-10 	1955-10-10
        Eddie Van Halen        1955-01-26 	1956-01-26
        Edgar Winter           1947-12-28 	1946-12-28
        Five for Fighting      1965-01-07 	1997-00-00     [extremely different!]
        Frankie Valli          1934-05-03 	1937-05-03     [3 year difference]
        George Harrison        1943-02-25 	1943-02-24
        Jennifer Lopez         1969-07-24 	1970-07-24
            </programlisting></section><section><title>Top Record Labels</title><para>
                One of our original questions was "Is there a predominant record label in the music world?"
                The following query answers that question.
            </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
               
          SELECT ?label (count(?label) as ?count)
           {
           ?artist &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/recordLabel&gt; ?label
           } 
          ORDER BY DESC (?count) LIMIT 20      
                
            </programlisting><para>The results are shown below.</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Columbia_Records         5762
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/EMI                      4215
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Warner_Bros._Records     3518
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Epic_Records             3509
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Atlantic_Records         3502
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Capitol_Records          3264
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Virgin_Records           2926
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/RCA_Records              2590
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/MCA_Records              1975
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Mercury_Records          1919
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Island_Records           1800
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/A&amp;M_Records              1697
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Sony_BMG                 1513
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Elektra_Records          1480
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Reprise_Records          1406
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Arista_Records           1382
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Geffen_Records           1372
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Universal_Music_Group    1339
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Universal_Records        1277
        http://dbpedia.org/resource/Interscope_Records       1226  
            
            </programlisting></section><section xml:id="genres" xreflabel="Musical Genres"><title>Musical Genres</title><para>In order to determine which artist is most influential in rock music, we needed to be able to
                reliably specify the genre of interest. However, formulating queries involving genres is more difficult than it would seem. DBpedia (and presumably Wikipedia)
            defines 2,887 musical genres of which 330 contain "rock" in their label. Rock-related genres literally run the gamut
            from A to Z -- Aboriginal_rock to Zulu_rock (really!). To our surprise, the single concept of "rock and roll music"
            is represented by 18 distinctly different IRIs, as determined by the following query.
            <footnote><para>Actually, there is a 19th IRI if the query is not constrained to require the string "roll": 
                    <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_music</link>. This link redirects to a page which among other things lists 
                    many subgenres of rock.
                </para></footnote>
            </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
            SELECT DISTINCT (?genre)
              {
              ?album &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/genre&gt; ?genre.
              ?album &lt;http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#type&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/Album&gt;.
              FILTER regex (?genre, "[Rr]ock") .
              FILTER regex (?genre, "[Rr]oll") .
              }
             ORDER BY ?genre                
                
            </programlisting><para>The variants of "rock and roll" are:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/British_Rock_and_Roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Real_Rock_and_Roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock%27n%27Roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock%27n%27roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock%27n_roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_%27N%27_Roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_%27n%27_Roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_%27n%27_roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_%27n_Roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_&amp;_Roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_&amp;_roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_N%27_Roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_and_Roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_and_Roll_music
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_and_roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_n%27_Roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_n_Roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Spanish_language_rock_and_roll               
                
            </programlisting><para>The first and last results above could be considered outliers since they are 
                narrowings of the generic rock and roll classification.</para><para>
                Although Clapton is identified by only a few genres on Wikipedia, his albums fall into 18 genres,
                as determined by the query:
            </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
            SELECT DISTINCT (?genre) WHERE 
            	{
            	?s &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/artist&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&gt;.
            	?s &lt;http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#type&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/Album&gt;.
            	?s &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/genre&gt; ?genre
            	}
            ORDER BY ?genre                
                
            </programlisting><para>Genres associated with Clapton's albums follow. Note four variants each for the 
                concepts "blues-rock" and "rock and roll".</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Acoustic_blues
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Blues
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Blues-Rock
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Blues-rock
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Blues_Rock
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Blues_rock
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/British_Blues
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Electric_blues
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Folk_music
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Jazz
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Orchestral
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Pop_music
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Reggae
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_%28music%29
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_and_Roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_and_roll
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Rock_music
            http://dbpedia.org/resource/Soul_blues    
                 
            </programlisting><para>For any given album, more than one genre may apply. For example, the 1975 album 
                "There's One in Every Crowd" is classified as both reggae and blues-rock.
            For those wondering which Clapton album could possibly be considered jazz or orchestral, that distinction
            belongs to the first "Lethal Weapon" soundtrack, which is also designated as blues. 
            However, the genre query above does not capture all genres associated with Clapton. For example,
            the genre for "Lethal Weapon 3" soundtrack is simply "soundtrack".
            <!-- TBD what query did we use for this? -->
            </para><para>
            If we wish to display all of Clapton's blues and rock albums, we could use a query such as:
            </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
            SELECT DISTINCT (?genre) ?album WHERE 
            	{
            	?album &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/artist&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&gt;.
            	?album &lt;http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#type&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/Album&gt;.
            	?album &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/genre&gt; ?genre .
                FILTER ( regex (?genre, "[Rr]ock") ||  regex (?genre, "[Bb]lues"))
            	}
            ORDER BY ?album                
                
            </programlisting><para>
                To display all of Clapton's albums and their associated genre(s), we used the following query:
            </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
            SELECT ?album ?genre WHERE 
            	{
            	?album &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/artist&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&gt;.
            	?album &lt;http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#type&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/Album&gt;.
            	?album &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/genre&gt; ?genre .
            	}
            ORDER BY ?album                
                
            </programlisting><para>
                The result including albums with several genres listed follows. (The common portion of the IRI,
                <code>http://dbpedia.org/resource/</code> has been removed from each resource to make the results 
                more readable.)
            </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
                                 album                                         genre
            24_Nights                                                       Rock_music
            24_Nights                                                       Blues
            461_Ocean_Boulevard                                             Blues-rock
            Another_Ticket                                                  Blues-rock
            August_%28album%29                                              Rock_music
            August_%28album%29                                              Pop_music
            Back_Home_%28Eric_Clapton_album%29                              Blues-Rock
            Backless                                                        Rock_and_roll
            Backtrackin%27                                                  Rock_%28music%29
            Behind_the_Sun_%28Eric_Clapton_album%29                         Rock_music
            Behind_the_Sun_%28Eric_Clapton_album%29                         Pop_music
            Blues_%28Eric_Clapton_album%29                                  Blues-rock
            Clapton_%282010_album%29                                        Blues-rock
            Clapton_Chronicles:_The_Best_of_Eric_Clapton                    Rock_and_Roll
            Crossroads_%28Eric_Clapton_album%29                             Blues-rock
            Crossroads_2:_Live_in_the_Seventies                             Blues-rock
            E._C._Was_Here                                                  Blues-rock
            Eric_Clapton%27s_Rainbow_Concert                                Blues-rock
            Eric_Clapton_%28album%29                                        Rock_and_Roll
            From_the_Cradle                                                 Blues
            From_the_Cradle                                                 Electric_blues
            From_the_Cradle                                                 Soul_blues
            From_the_Cradle                                                 British_Blues
            Guitar_Boogie                                                   Rock_and_roll
            Guitar_Boogie                                                   Blues-rock
            Journeyman_%28album%29                                          Blues-rock
            Just_One_Night_%28album%29                                      Blues-rock
            Lethal_Weapon_%28soundtrack%29                                  Jazz
            Lethal_Weapon_%28soundtrack%29                                  Blues
            Lethal_Weapon_%28soundtrack%29                                  Orchestral
            Live_in_Hyde_Park_%28Eric_Clapton_album%29                      Rock_music
            Live_in_Hyde_Park_%28Eric_Clapton_album%29                      Blues
            Live_in_Japan_%28George_Harrison_album%29                       Rock_and_roll
            Me_and_Mr._Johnson                                              Blues
            Money_and_Cigarettes                                            Blues-rock
            No_Reason_to_Cry                                                Rock_and_roll
            One_More_Car,_One_More_Rider                                    Blues-rock
            Pilgrim_%28Eric_Clapton_album%29                                Rock_music
            Pilgrim_%28Eric_Clapton_album%29                                Blues
            Pilgrim_%28Eric_Clapton_album%29                                Pop_music
            Reptile_%28album%29                                             Rock_music
            Reptile_%28album%29                                             Blues
            Riding_with_the_King_%28B._B._King_and_Eric_Clapton_album%29    Blues-rock
            Riding_with_the_King_%28B._B._King_and_Eric_Clapton_album%29    Blues_rock
            Slowhand 	                                                    Rock_music
            Steppin%27_Out_%28Eric_Clapton_album%29 	                    Blues-rock
            The_Cream_of_Clapton                                            Rock_music
            The_Cream_of_Clapton                                            Blues_Rock
            The_Cream_of_Eric_Clapton 	                                    Rock_music
            The_History_of_Eric_Clapton                                     Rock_music
            The_History_of_Eric_Clapton                                     Blues
            There%27s_One_in_Every_Crowd                                    Reggae
            There%27s_One_in_Every_Crowd                                    Blues-rock
            Time_Pieces:_The_Best_of_Eric_Clapton                           Blues_Rock
            Unplugged_%28Eric_Clapton_album%29 	                            Folk_music
            Unplugged_%28Eric_Clapton_album%29 	                            Acoustic_blues
                
            </programlisting><para>
                However, if we omit a reference to genre and simply ask for Clapton's albums
                using the query:              
            </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
                
            SELECT ?album WHERE 
            	{
            	?album &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/artist&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eric_Clapton&gt;.
            	?album &lt;http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#type&gt; &lt;http://dbpedia.org/ontology/Album&gt;.
            	}
            ORDER BY ?album                  
                
            </programlisting><para>
                then the results contain 7 additional albums (below). We have not been able to determine the 
                reason for this disparity since there is genre information for each of them when we dereference
                their IRIs on the DBpedia site.
            </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
        Clapton_%281973_album%29                dbpprop:genre    Rock       
        [compilation from 1973]
        
        Complete_Clapton                        dbpprop:genre    Blues      
        [compilation from 2007]
        
        Edge_of_Darkness_%28soundtrack%29       dbpprop:genre    Soundtracks 
        [18 minute 1985 soundtrack for British TV series]
        
        Eric_Clapton_at_His_Best                dbpprop:genre    Rock         
        [compilation from 1972]
        
        Lethal_Weapon_3_%28soundtrack%29        dbpprop:genre    Orchestral, Jazz, and Blues   
        [Wikipedia soundtrack entry shares page with the movie; 2 infoboxes]
        
        Live_from_Madison_Square_Garden_%28Eric_Clapton_and_Steve_Winwood_album%29  dbpprop:genre  Blues/Rock            
        [note the slash]
        
        Rush_%28soundtrack%29                   dbpedia-owl:type dbpedia:Soundtrack  
        [Wikipedia soundtrack entry shares page with the movie; but no album infobox]                
            </programlisting><para> 
                A better solution for managing the permutations between the
                representations for the genre concept "Rock and Roll" as well as its narrowings would be to
                again use reasoning. The semantically equivalent variant genres could be represented as 
                <code>rdfs:subProperties</code> of one
                another, thereby enabling a single genre representation to refer to many. <footnote><para>However, we chose to use <code>rdfs:subClassOf</code> because it was the most appropriate RDFS property that the 
                        Virtuoso database reasoner supported.</para></footnote> This would
                require analogous steps to where we created and loaded assertions, defined a graph,
                define a graph group, and in this case define a <code>rule_set</code> in Virtuoso. Then, using the
                proper syntax we could query using that <code>rule_set</code> to include exactly the genres we
                intend to use in our queries. A less elegant approach would be to enumerate them one by one and construct a
                <code>UNION</code> of results. 
            </para></section><!-- END Musical Genres --></section><!-- END Challenges and Results --><section><title>Limitations and Further Efforts</title><para>We recognize several limitations in our work to date:
            <itemizedlist><listitem><para>data inconsistencies</para></listitem><listitem><para>need for further RDF visualization work</para></listitem><listitem><para>need to address more of the original problems</para></listitem><listitem><para>constructing queries across datasets</para></listitem></itemizedlist>  
            Each is discussed in the following subsections.
        </para><section><title>Data Inconsistencies</title><para>While we would wish the source RDF data could be regarded as ground truth, we realize there are
            several problems with our sources.
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Errors of omission: </emphasis> Since the original data in Wikipedia is community-entered,
                    it is predictable that certain facts will be missing from the data but are in fact true. Some
                    of thes facts may be obscure while others may be more obvious to a subject matter expert 
                    for the given topic. For example, what if Eric Clapton were to enter his own data about himself?</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Poor data curation: </emphasis> In some cases, Wikipedia data may
                    have been present and complete, but there might have been problems in the extraction process from Wikipedia
                    to DBpedia.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Erroneous data: </emphasis> Such problems are due to simple data entry errors, 
                        unintentional errors in stating what the data entry person considers facts,
                    or possibly intentional falsehoods or unsubstantiated facts.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>                
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Unclear semantics: </emphasis> The various properties which were of importance to us were
                    generally not defined in the ontology, as discussed in <xref linkend="workingDefs"/>. We struggled to interpret
                    these terms in a consistent manner. It is possible that individuals who care less about the precision of 
                    information may have entered relationships not necessarily using the correct semantics.
                    We believe that the ambiguity of the musician-related properties was the most significant
                    problem with the reliability of the data and therefore the biggest challenge in testing our
                    hypothesis.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
            </para></section><section><title>Further RDF Visualization Work</title><para> Since AJAX facilitates updating a web page without reloading the entire page,
                we plan to insert additional links within the SVG graphic to add more
                interactivity, invoking additional queries. Links could also be added during the
                module processing. CSS and XSLT could also be used to enhance the XML
                presentation. </para><para> The current visualization graph is quite wide and long, making it difficult to
                view in a web browser without additional panning and zooming capabilities. Useful
                visualization of the result set is difficult but we intend to improve the
                visualization to facilitate traversing the dataset using hyperlinks. The
                hyperlinks are there now, but there is currently a problem with the JavaScript
                <code>POST</code> method. 
            </para></section><section><title>Further Attempts to Address the Original Problems</title><para>
                We initially formulated nearly two dozen questions [see <xref linkend="problemList"/>]
                that we believed we could use the DBpedia and MusicBrainz
                RDF  datasets to answer. As of this July writing, few of these questions have been answered definitively. 
                If properly bounded, the following are the questions we should be able to address in the future.
            </para><orderedlist><listitem><para>Which recording artist has directly played with the most musicians?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which recording artist has the most connections within six degrees?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which musician has been a session man for the most number of artists?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which recording artist was most active during a particular decade?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Among all artists of a particular genre, who has played with the most other musicians?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which rock artist's extended graph has the most other artists in 2 degrees? 3 degrees? 4 degrees?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Who has appeared on the most albums?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which musician-related properties are reversible (inverse makes sense)?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Who created the most songs?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which song has been recorded the most times by any artists? 
                    ("Yesterday" and "White Christmas" are typically cited.)</para></listitem><listitem><para>What is the average age of a musician when he/she first joined a band?</para></listitem></orderedlist><para>
                Other questions we may potentially be able to address include:
            </para><orderedlist><listitem><para>If we weight results by the length of time a band stays together, how does that impact other queries?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Does total number of songs or album released correlate with other measures of success?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which solo artist has had the longest career?</para></listitem><listitem><para>Which band has been together (in some form) the longest time?</para></listitem><listitem><para>For bands with changing membership, can we conclude which configuration lasted the longest?</para></listitem><listitem><para>What is the "Eric Clapton number" (a la Kevin Bacon number) for various musicians?</para></listitem></orderedlist></section><section><title>Queries Across Datasets</title><para>
               Since we have established a mechanism to 
               refer to a given artist in both datasets using a single IRI,
               we are prepared to ask queries that span the datasets, including
               queries that would not be possible without both sources. A few such queries are as follows:
           </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Which albums of a given artist occur in one dataset but not the other?
                   Since we are using Virtuoso which does not support the SPARQL 1.1 <code>MINUS</code> construct,
                   we would need to use OpenLink's proprietary approach. <footnote><para>It is possible that <code>NOT EXISTS</code> in SPARQL 1.0 would be sufficient.</para></footnote></para></listitem><listitem><para>Which albums that occur in both datasets have the same title and record producer but different release dates?
                   This might be difficult to determine because of differences in representation of the record producer name.
               </para></listitem><listitem><para>For a given artist, return their spouse(s) and children even if they themselves were not
               musical artists. MusicBrainz only has names of children if they themselves are artists (e.g., has
               John Lennon's sons but not Paul McCartney's children).</para></listitem></itemizedlist></section><section><title>Put the LOD Right on Me</title><para>
               Regrettably, we focused most of our attention on DBpedia, MusicBrainz and Freebase web sites, rather than 
               casting a broader net to the <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/wiki/SweoIG/TaskForces/CommunityProjects/LinkingOpenData" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Linking Open Data</link> 
               community effort initiated by the  W3C's (now closed) Semantic Web Education and Outreach (SWEO) Interest Group.
               As we were finalizing this paper, we discovered several key 
               resources that could prove extremely useful in answering some of our original
               questions; we hope to explore resources such as the following over the next year:
           </para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><link xlink:href="http://www.delicious.com/kidehen/linked_data_demo" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Demos including DBpedia and MusicBrainz</link> (and many others)</para></listitem><listitem><para><link xlink:href="http://wiki.dbpedia.org/Downloads32" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">DBpedia Extended Datasets</link> 
                       for MusicBrainz and Freebase</para></listitem><listitem><para><link xlink:href="http://richard.cyganiak.de/2007/10/lod/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">LOD cloud diagram</link>, an imagemap showing datasets published in Linked Data format (maintained by Richard Cyganiak and Anja Jentzsch)</para></listitem><listitem><para><link xlink:href="http://ckan.org/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Comprehensive Knowledge Archive Network (CKAN)</link>
                       web-based software for storage and distribution of data supported by the 
                       <link xlink:href="http://okfn.org/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Open Knowledge Foundation</link></para></listitem><listitem><para><link xlink:href="http://musicontology.com/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Music Ontology</link> especially 
                       <link xlink:href="http://musicontology.com/#term_MusicArtist" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">MusicArtist</link>, 
                       <link xlink:href="http://musicontology.com/#term_musicbrainz_guid" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">musicbrainz_guid</link> and
                       <link xlink:href="http://musicontology.com/#term_supporting_musician" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">supporting_musician</link></para></listitem><listitem><para><link xlink:href="http://linkeddatabook.com/book" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Linked Data: Evolving the Web into a Global Data Space</link>,  
                       a new book by Tom Heath and Christian Bizer (2011)</para></listitem></itemizedlist></section></section><!-- end Limitations and Future --><section><title>Advantages and Disadvantages</title><para>Next we offer our subjective opinion about the relative advantages and disadvantages of our approach
            as compared to simply using the <link xlink:href="http://dbpedia.org/sparql" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">DBpedia SPARQL endpoint</link> 
            (which also runs on a Virtuoso server).
        </para><section><title>Advantages of Our Approach</title><para>
                Our Drupal frontend to a dedicated Virtuoso server under our fine-grained control afforded us several advantages
                <footnote><para>We note, however, that the 
                        <link xlink:href="http://blog.dbpedia.org/2011/01/31/dbpedia-36-ami-available/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">DBpedia Amazon Machine Instance (AMI)</link> 
                        released earlier in 2011 shares several of the advantages discussed in this section.</para></footnote>, namely:
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">No execution timeout -</emphasis> Time-intensive queries were allowed to run
                            to completion rather than being subject to an externally specified time limit on a shared server.
                        </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Higher limits -</emphasis> SPARQL endpoints shared by multiple users are
                            often constrained to a limited number of results (i.e., 2000 for DBpedia endpoint). We did not
                            need to limit the number of results returned since our number of "users" never exceeded three.
                        </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Direct access to raw RDF at command line level -</emphasis> When results
                            were not as expected or did not seem to make sense, the ability to examine the actual RDF files
                            (which had been ingested into our datastore) in our Linux environment was invaluable.
                        </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Collaborative SPARQL development for saving queries in Drupal -</emphasis>
                            As the three authors worked remotely, it was quite helpful to enter our SPARQL queries into
                            a Drupal interface, run the queries, save the queries, and optionally enter them into a cascading
                            menu system for each other to try so we could discuss results.
                        </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">More precise SPARQL timing metrics -</emphasis> Again, since we could
                            control which other processes were running and other variables that would otherwise impact
                            timing metrics, we could more accurately time our queries. For example, we found it took
                            on average 3477.6 msec for a query with one <code>FILTER</code> statement comprised of two 
                            <code>regex</code> expressions joined by "&amp;&amp;" compared to only
                            731 msec for a similar query in which each <code>regex</code> expression was the parameter of
                            a separate <code>FILTER</code> statement. See the first example in the <xref linkend="genres"/> section.
                        </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Test harness for repeatedly running the same query -</emphasis> We employed
                            a perl test harness for iterative execution and averaging of results. For example, the previously
                            mentioned <code>FILTER</code> and <code>regex</code> tests were run 1,000 times.
                        </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Examination of error messages -</emphasis> We had access to server logging
                            of error messages.
                        </para></listitem></itemizedlist>                
            </para></section><section><title>Disadvantages of Our Approach</title><para>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Static datastore -</emphasis> After we ingested the RDF files, our datastore
                            did not change so it could not take advantage of possible improvements in the DBpedia and Musicbrainz 
                            data throughout the first half of 2011. On the other hand, this was also an advatange since it meant
                            we were not subject to subtle changes that might have impacted previous queries.
                        </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="ital">Limited knowledge of inner workings -</emphasis> Since we were not members
                            of either the DBpedia or Musicbrainz developer communities, we were not privy to any internal documentation
                            that might have answered some of the questions we raised and helped us to address some of the problems we
                            encountered. In a volunteer developer collaborative environment, it is likely that user-facing 
                            documentation may lag behind actual implementation changes; relevant examples may also be lacking.
                        </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
            </para></section></section><!-- end Advantages and Disadvantages  --><section><title>Recommendations</title><para>
            The problems we encountered suggest several recommendations we would like to share with the DBPedia and MusicBrainz communities:
            <orderedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Publish example SPARQL queries:</emphasis> Although sample data is readily available
                        on the music sites, we did not find SPARQL queries, just endpoints to explore.
                    </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Provide detailed explanation of IRI conventions and property semantics:</emphasis> We
                        found that it was not always obvious what the significance was for IRI differences, nor what non-alphabetic
                        characters should be used in multi-word IRIs. For example, what is the difference between
                        <code>http://dbpedia.org/ontology</code> and  <code>http://dbpedia.org/property</code> IRIs?
                    </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Include examples of intersecting graphs from other music-oriented sites:</emphasis>
                        In the spirit of <link xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/wiki/SweoIG/TaskForces/CommunityProjects/LinkingOpenData" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Linking Open Data</link>, 
                        it would be helpful if both DBpedia and MusicBrainz created and posted
                        demos (or links to demos) on their sites to illustrate linking of their data sources to other popular music data stores.
                    </para></listitem></orderedlist>
        </para></section><!-- end Recommendations --><section><title>Conclusions</title><para>
            Although at this time we have fallen far short of our lofty goal of answering two dozen complex questions
            by means of RDF and SPARQL, we believe we have uncovered several significant challenges 
            regarding the consistency of the data sources and the interpretation of the semantics
            underlying various key properties of musical artists. We believe similar problems would be
            encountered with using other large community-entered datasets of relatively low quality.
        </para><para>
            While Wikipedia editors often focus on crafting the most accessible presentation of encyclopedic 
            information for human consumption, there are other factors to consider. Individuals working with data at the
            semantic level could improve the semantic representation by isolating outliers, as in
            the case of multiple representations of the "Rock and Roll music" genre concept.
            Data quality and therefore utility would be greatly enhanced
            by making the necessary modifications to "normalize" or decrease
            spurious diversity that is not based on any actual or intended semantic distinction.
            <footnote><para>For example, see <link xlink:href="http://pedantic-web.org/" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">The Pedantic Web</link>,
                    especially <link xlink:href="http://pedantic-web.org/fops.html" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Frequently Observed Problems on the Web of Data</link>.</para></footnote>         
        </para><para>
            In the end, any accurate measure of impact a given musician has on a genre is likely to be the product of a
            weighted measurement of several variables and is therefore largely subjective. The number
            of bands someone played with, the number of songs they wrote, the number of albums they
            produced or the length of time they were active are only part of the equation. An artist
            who wrote a single song that has enjoyed frequent airplay for decades and/or was covered by artists in many
            different genres clearly demonstrates a substantial impact. Other measurements not available in
            the RDF datasets are likely to be even more revealing of an artist's true impact, such as the
            number of concerts they played, the number of people who recognize their name, and their
            success on music charts (i.e., Billboard).
        </para><para>
            By the same token, a strong argument could be made that an individual musician whose
            career lasted only a short time with a limited repertoire but perhaps created or
            influenced a new genre could be regard to have a major impact. Therefore, one
            would have to somehow compare Eric Clapton to early genre pioneers. For example, Robert
            Johnson, a major influence on Clapton, recorded only 29 songs and basically enjoyed only
            a 2-year (1936-37) recording career. Yet Clapton himself has called Johnson "the
            most important blues singer that ever lived".<footnote><para>Booklet accompanying Johnson's <emphasis role="ital">Complete Recordings</emphasis> box set, 
                    Stephen LaVere, Sony Music Entertainment, 1990, Clapton quote on p. 26.</para></footnote>    
            Johnson was ranked fifth in <emphasis role="ital">Rolling Stone's</emphasis> list of 100 Greatest Guitarists of All Time.
        </para><para> 
            Given our knowledge and supporting resources surrounding Eric Clapton's career, we believe
            that some of what we perceive as errors are indeed just that -- mistakes. Whether those
            mistakes are based on individuals simply being incorrect, or not understanding the
            semantics really does not matter in the final analysis. What this highlights, for us, 
            is a limitation induced
            by the <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_World_Assumption" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">Open World Assumption</link>. 
            When an assertion is not made, we cannot also assume its
            negation. Having assertions stating that Clapton created 30 albums does not mean he did
            not create 45. Likewise, because we know that Clapton did participate in collaboration
            efforts like Powerhouse, The Dirty Mac and Free Creek, we cannot state unequivocally that
            it happened only a
            single time and therefore violates the semantics of the <code>associatedActs</code> predicate.
        </para></section><!-- BEGIN APPENDIX --><appendix xml:id="triplesCounts" xreflabel="Triples Counts"><title>Triple Counts</title><programlisting xml:id="musicbrainzTriples" xreflabel="Musicbrainz Triples Count" xml:space="preserve">
	      <emphasis role="bital">Musicbrainz Triples Count</emphasis> 
            
        4301998 albums.rdf
        1824953 albums_tracklists.rdf
        1712434 artists.rdf
         427027 relations_artist_to_artist.rdf
         292955 albums_tags.rdf
         188708 tracks.rdf
         114285 relations_album_to_artist.rdf
        --------------------------------------
        8,862,360 total triples            
        </programlisting><programlisting xml:id="dbpediaAssertions" xreflabel="DBPedia Assertions" xml:space="preserve">
	      <emphasis role="bital">DBpedia Assertions</emphasis> 
            
         130166251 page_links_en.nt
          43640719 infobox_properties_en.nt
          23917050 wikipedia_links_en.nt
          13795664 mappingbased_properties_en.nt
          12161691 article_categories_en.nt  
           9485630 revisions_en.nt
           9485630 page_ids_en.nt
           7972385 labels_en.nt
           6173940 instance_types_en.nt
           5907507 external_links_en.nt
           4615815 images_en.nt
           4503651 redirects_en.nt
           3261096 short_abstracts_en.nt
           3261096 long_abstracts_en.nt
           2529082 skos_categories_en.nt
           1745873 persondata_en.nt
           1544820 geo_coordinates_en.nt
            928708 disambiguations_en.nt
            910517 article_related_geo_countries_en.nt
            632615 category_labels_en.nt
            414195 homepages_en.nt
            387336 specific_mappingbased_properties_en.nt
             81602 infobox_property_definitions_en.nt
              1555 pnd_en.nt 
        ---------------------------------------------------	  
         287,524,428 total assertions           
        </programlisting></appendix><appendix xml:id="drupalModules" xreflabel="Drupal Modules"><title>Drupal 6.18 Modules</title><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
        Admin role 6.x-1.3
        Administration menu 6.x-1.6
        Advanced help 6.x-1.2
        Backup and Migrate 6.x-2.4
        Colorpicker 6.x-2.1
        Content Construction Kit (CCK) 6.x-2.9
        Date 6.x-2.7
        Devel 6.x-1.23
        Drupal For Firebug 6.x-1.4
        Google Visualization API 6.x-1.3
        Graphviz Filter 6.x-1.6
        Graphviz Styles 6.x-1.0
        jQuery Update 6.x-2.0-alpha1
        Masquerade 6.x-1.5
        Node export 6.x-2.24
        Node import 6.x-1.0
        Pathauto 6.x-1.5
        RDF CCK 6.x-2.x-dev (2011-Feb-25)
        Resource Description Framework (RDF) 6.x-1.0-alpha8
        SPARQL 6.x-1.0-alpha1
        Includes: SPARQL API
        Sphinx (Sphinx search integration) 6.x-1.3
        Tagadelic 6.x-1.2
        Taxonomy import/export via XML 6.x-1.3
        Taxonomy Manager 6.x-2.2
        Taxonomy Menu 6.x-2.9
        Token 6.x-1.15
        Views 6.x-2.12      
        </programlisting></appendix><bibliography><title>Bibiography</title><bibliomixed xml:id="Auer1" xreflabel="Auer and Lehmann 2007">
            Auer, Sören; Lehmann, Jens: 
            <emphasis role="ital">What Have Innsbruck and Leipzig in Common? Extracting Semantics from Wiki Content.</emphasis>
            ISBN-13: 978-3-540-72666-1. Springer Verlag. © 2007.
            Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 2007, Volume 4519/2007, pp. 503-517, DOI: 10.1007/978-3-540-72667-8_36.
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.springerlink.com/content/3131t21p634191n2/</link> and
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.71.1314&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf</link>.
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Auer2" xreflabel="Auer et al 2007">
            Auer, Sören; Bizer, Christian; Kobilarov, Georgi; Lehmann, Jens; Cyganiak, Richard; Ives, Zachary:
            <emphasis role="ital">DBpedia: A Nucleus for a Web of Open Data.</emphasis>
            ISBN-13: 978-3-540-76297-3.  Springer Verlag. © 2007.
            Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 2007, Volume 4825/2007, pp. 722-735, DOI: 10.1007/978-3-540-76298-0_52.
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.springerlink.com/content/rm32474088w54378/</link> and
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.informatik.uni-leipzig.de/~auer/publication/dbpedia.pdf</link>.
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="SemWebBook" xreflabel="Allemang and Hendler 2008">
            Allemang, Dean; Hendler, James A.:
            <emphasis role="ital">Semantic Web for the Working Ontologist: Effective Modeling in RDFS and OWL.</emphasis>
            ISBN-13: 978-0-12-373556-0. Elsevier Inc. © 2008.
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.workingontologist.org/index.html</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="kbacon" xreflabel="Bacon">
            <emphasis role="ital">Six Degrees of Kevin Bacon</emphasis>. [online]. [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Six_Degrees_of_Kevin_Bacon</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="butcher" xreflabel="Butcher 2010">
            Butcher, Matt et al. <emphasis role="ital">Drupal 7 Module Development.</emphasis> 
            ISBN-10: 1849511160. First edition.
            Packt Publishing © 2010. [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.amazon.com/Drupal-Module-Development-Matt-Butcher/dp/1849511160/</link>  
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="eclapton" xreflabel="Clapton">
            <emphasis role="ital">Eric Clapton's Wikipedia page</emphasis>. [online]. [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric_clapton</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="claptonFAQ" xreflabel="Clapton FAQ">
            <emphasis role="ital">Eric Clapton Frequently Asked Questions</emphasis>,
            part of <emphasis role="ital">The Eric Clapton Fan Club Magazine</emphasis>. [online]. [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.whereseric.com/eric-clapton-faq</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="dbp01" xreflabel="DBpedia Dataset">
            <emphasis role="ital">The DBpedia Dataset</emphasis>. [online]. [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://wiki.dbpedia.org/Datasets</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="dbp03" xreflabel="DBpedia Ontology">
            <emphasis role="ital">The DBpedia Ontology</emphasis>. [online]. [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://wiki.dbpedia.org/Ontology</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="dbp02" xreflabel="DBpedia Release">
            <emphasis role="ital">DBpedia 3.6 released</emphasis>. [online]. [cited 08 Apr 
            2011]. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://blog.dbpedia.org/2011/01/17/dbpedia-36-released/</link>.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="sparqlByExample" xreflabel="Feigenbaum and Prud'hommeaux 2008">
            <emphasis role="ital">SPARQL By Example - A Tutorial</emphasis>. [online] [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            Feigenbaum, Lee and Prud'hommeaux, Eric. Cambridge Semantics, 2008. Updated 2011-01-25.
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.cambridgesemantics.com/2008/09/sparql-by-example/</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="sparqlCheatSheet" xreflabel="Feigenbaum 2008">
            <emphasis role="ital">SPARQL by Example: The Cheat Sheet</emphasis>. [online] [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            Feigenbaum, Lee. Cambridge Semantics, 2008.
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.slideshare.net/LeeFeigenbaum/sparql-cheat-sheet</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="pframe" xreflabel="Frame 1983">
            <emphasis role="ital">Peter Frame's Rock Family Trees</emphasis>. [online and 3 books]. [cited 08 Apr
            2011]. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.familyofrock.com/browse/details/trees.html</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="freebaseHome" xreflabel="Freebase">
            <emphasis role="ital">Freebase home page</emphasis>. [online]. [cited 08 Apr 
            2011]. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.freebase.com/</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="freebaseData" xreflabel="Freebase Data Dumps">
            <emphasis role="ital">Freebase Data Dumps</emphasis>. [online]. [cited 08 Apr 
            2011]. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://wiki.freebase.com/wiki/Data_dumps/</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="graphvizHome" xreflabel="Graphviz">
            <emphasis role="ital">Graphviz home page</emphasis>. [online]. [cited 08 Apr 
            2011]. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.graphviz.org/</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="mql" xreflabel="MQL">
            <emphasis role="ital">Metaweb Query Language</emphasis>. [online]. [cited 08 Apr 
            2011]. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://wiki.freebase.com/wiki/MQL</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="musicBrainz" xreflabel="MusicBrainz">
            <emphasis role="ital">MusicBrainz home page</emphasis>. [online]. [cited 08 Apr 2011]. 
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://musicbrainz.org/</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="newman" xreflabel="Newman 2010">
            Newman, Mark. <emphasis role="ital">Networks - An Introduction.</emphasis> 
            ISBN-10: 9780199206650. First edition.
            Oxford University Press, USA © 2010. [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.amazon.com/Networks-Introduction-Mark-Newman/dp/0199206651/</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="openCyc" xreflabel="OpenCyc for the Semantic Web">
            <emphasis role="ital">OpenCyc for the Semantic Web</emphasis>. [online]. [Cited 26 Jun 2011].
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://sw.opencyc.org/</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="sixDegrees" xreflabel="Six Degrees">
            <emphasis role="ital">Six Degrees of Separation</emphasis>. [online]. [Cited 08 Apr 2011].
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Six_degrees_of_separation</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="sparql01" xreflabel="SPARQL 1.0">
            <emphasis role="ital">SPARQL Query Language for RDF</emphasis>. [online] [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            W3C Recommendation 15 January 2008. W3C © 2006-2007
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-sparql-query/</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="rstarr" xreflabel="Starr">
            <emphasis role="ital">Ringo Starr's Wikipedia page</emphasis>. [online] [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ringo_Starr</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="allStarBand" xreflabel="Ringo Starr &amp; His All-Starr Band">
            <emphasis role="ital">Ringo Starr &amp; His All-Starr Band Wikipedia page</emphasis>. [online] [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ringo_Starr_%26_His_All-Starr_Band</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="vandykWestgate" xreflabel="VanDyke and Westgate 2007">
            VanDyk, John K and Westgate, Matt <emphasis role="ital">Pro Drupal Development.</emphasis> 
            ISBN-10: 1590597559. First edition.
            APress © 2007. [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.amazon.com/Pro-Drupal-Development-John-VanDyk/dp/1590597559/</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="virtuoso" xreflabel="Virtuoso Universal Server">
            <emphasis role="ital">OpenLink Virtuoso Universal Server</emphasis>. [online]. [cited 08 Apr 
            2011]. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://virtuoso.openlinksw.com/</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="virtuosoSparql" xreflabel="Virtuoso SPARQL Tutorial">
            <emphasis role="ital">Virtuoso SPARQL Tutorial, Part 2</emphasis>. [online]. [cited 08 Apr 
            2011]. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://virtuoso.openlinksw.com/presentations/SPARQL_Tutorials/SPARQL_Tutorials_Part_2/SPARQL_Tutorials_Part_2.html</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="vocabutek" xreflabel="Vocabutek Web Site">
            <emphasis role="ital">Ron Reck's demo site</emphasis>. [online] [cited 08 Apr 2011].
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.vocabutek.com/</link>
        </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="billboardAlbums" xreflabel="Whitburn 2006">
            Whitburn, Joel. <emphasis role="ital">The Billboard Albums</emphasis>. 
            ISBN-13 0-89820-166-7. Sixth edition.
            Record Research Inc. © 2006. 
            [Data from 1956-2006; other editions are entitled <emphasis role="ital">Top Pop Albums</emphasis>.]
            <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">https://www.recordresearch.com</link>
        </bibliomixed></bibliography></article>