<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.2"><title>A Streaming XSLT Processor</title><info><confgroup><conftitle>Balisage: The Markup Conference 2010</conftitle><confdates>August 3 - 6, 2010</confdates></confgroup><abstract><para>Existing XSLT implementations build a tree representation of the source document in memory, and
are therefore limited to processing of documents that fit in memory. With many transformations, however,
there is a direct correspondence between the order of information in the output, and the order of the
corresponding information in the input. In such cases it ought to be possible to perform the transformation
without allocating memory to the entire source tree.</para><para>The XSL Working Group within W3C has been working on a new version of the language designed
    to make streamed implementations feasible, and the author, who is editor of that specification, has
    at the same time been working on the implementation of streaming in the Saxon XSLT processor. This paper
    describes how far this work has progressed, and the way in which the implementation is structured.
    It adopts a chronological approach to the exposition, explaining how the streaming features have gradually
    developed from small beginnings.</para></abstract><author><personname><firstname>Michael</firstname><surname>Kay</surname></personname><personblurb><para>Michael Kay is the editor of the W3C XSLT specification, and is a member of the XQuery
and XML Schema Working Groups. He is the developer of the Saxon XSLT, XQuery, and XML Schema processor.
He is the author of <quote>XSLT Programmer's Reference</quote> (now in its fourth edition) and a contributor
to many other books.</para><para>He is a member of the Advisory Board for Balisage 2010.  In 2009, he chaired the associated Symposium
on Processing XML Efficiently.</para></personblurb><affiliation><jobtitle>Director</jobtitle><orgname>Saxonica Limited</orgname></affiliation><email>mike@saxonica.com</email></author><legalnotice><para>Copyright © Michael Kay 2010</para></legalnotice><keywordset role="author"><keyword>XML</keyword><keyword>Streaming</keyword><keyword>Push</keyword><keyword>Program Inversion</keyword></keywordset></info><section><title>Streaming: an Introduction</title><para>The architecture of most XSLT processors is as shown in Figure 1. The XML parser is used
      to build a tree representation of the source document in memory. XSLT instructions are then
      executed, which cause the evaluation of XPath expressions, which select nodes from the source
      tree by navigating around this tree. Because the XPath axes (child, descendant, parent,
      ancestor, preceding-sibling, and so on) allow navigation around this tree in arbitrary
      directions, it is necessary for the entire tree to be held in memory for the duration of the
      transformation. For some XML documents, this is simply not feasible: even sample datasets
    representing virtual 3D city models run to 44Gbytes in size (<xref linkend="CityGML"/>).</para><figure xml:id="fig1"><title>Fig 1: Architecture of an XSLT Processor</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol5/graphics/Kay01/Kay01-001.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject><caption><para>In this schematic, arrows represent flow of control (not data flow). Thus the two
          controlling components (outlined bold) are the Parser and the XSLT engine; the parser
          writes the source tree and the XSLT engine reads it (via the XPath engine). The serializer
          is invoked by the XSLT engine to process one result tree event at a time, which means that
          the result tree does not actually need to be materialized in memory.</para></caption></figure><para>By contrast, there is no need to hold the result tree in memory. Although the semantics of
      the language speak of a result tree, a naive execution of XSLT instructions causes nodes to be
      written to the result tree in document order, which means that data can be serialized (to
      lexical XML or HTML) as soon as it is generated. So the result tree is a fiction of the
      specification, and does not occupy real memory in a typical implementation.</para><para>It has long been recognized that the need to hold the source tree in memory is a serious
    restriction for many applications. Researchers have made a number of attempts to tackle the problem:</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>Some have concentrated on streaming XPath processors (<xref linkend="Barton2003"/>,
            <xref linkend="BarYossef2004"/>, <xref linkend="Joshi"/>). The focus here is on
          rewriting the reverse axes (such as preceding-sibling) in terms of forwards axes. There
          has been significant progress demonstrated in these projects, though they all leave out
          some of the most awkward features of the language, such as the <code>last()</code>
          function. However, streamed evaluation of a single XPath expression during a single pass
          of a source document does not help much with streamed evaluation of XSLT, since a
          stylesheet contains many XPath expressions, and the starting point for one is typically
          dependent on the nodes found by another.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Other projects have concentrated on streamed evaluation of XQuery (<xref linkend="Florescu2003"/>, <xref linkend="Li2005"/>). Again these projects rely heavily
          on rewriting the execution plan. These results are difficult to translate to XSLT, because
          XQuery has the luxury of a flow-of-control that is fully statically analyzable (there is
          no polymorphism or dynamic despatch). In XQuery, the compiler can look at a function call
          and know which function it is calling; it can therefore determine what navigation is
          performed by the called function. Template rules in XSLT, by contrast, are fired
          dynamically based on input data.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Guo et al (<xref linkend="Guo2004"/>) describe an approach to streamed XSLT processing that restricts the supported
          XSLT constructs to a small core. This core language is DTD-aware, and restricts match patterns to those
          that can be uniquely ascribed to an element declaration in the DTD grammar. XPath expressions appear only
          in the <code>xsl:apply-templates</code> instruction, and always select downwards by element name. As a result,
          the call hierarchy becomes statically tractable, as in the XQuery case.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Zergaoui (<xref linkend="Zergaoui2009"/>) observes that many transformations
      are intrinsically non-streamable, because the events representing the result tree appear in a different
      order from the events from the source tree on which they depend. He therefore suggests that pure
      (zero-memory) streaming is an impractical goal, and that practical engineering solutions should
      strive rather to minimize the amount of buffering needed, without restricting the expressive
      capabilities of the transformation language.
             </para></listitem><listitem><para>Echoing this, Dvorakova (<xref linkend="Dvorakova2008"/>, <xref linkend="Dvorakova2009a"/>,
            <xref linkend="Dvorakova2009b"/>) and her colleagues describe an approach that supports
          a rather larger subset of the XSLT language, though it still contains some serious limitations:
          match patterns in template rules are simple element names, path expressions can select
          downwards only, recursive structures in the schema are not allowed. Their approach,
          implemented in the Xord framework, is based on static analysis of the XSLT code in the
          context of a schema to determine the extent to which streaming can be employed, and the
          scope of input buffering needed to handle constructs (for example, non-order-preserving
          constructs) where pure streaming is not possible. (An implicit assumption of their
          approach, which sadly is not true in real life, is that an element name appearing in the
          match pattern of a template rule can be used to identify unambiguously a schema definition
          of the structure of the elements that match this rule.)</para></listitem><listitem><para>Others have adopted the approach that if XSLT cannot be streamed, then a different language
            is needed. STX <xref linkend="STX"/> is one example of an alternative transformation language, designed explicitly for streaming.
          Another is the INRIA XStream project (<xref linkend="Frisch2007"/>) (not to be confused with other projects of the same name).
          STX abandons the attempt to be purely declarative, instead giving the programmer access to mutable
          variables which can be used to remember data from the input document that might be needed later in the transformation;
          this means that the responsibility for controlling memory usage rests entirely on the programmer.
          XStream, by contrast, is a purely functional language that relies heavily on partial evaluation of functions
          as soon as relevant inputs are available; the buffering of input is thus represented by the pool of partially-evaluated
          function calls, and the efficiency of the process depends strongly on the programmer having a good
          understanding of this execution model.
          </para></listitem></orderedlist><para>What all this activity makes clear is that streaming of the XSLT language as currently defined is seriously
    difficult; it is unreasonable to treat streaming as a mere optimization that implementors can provide if they
    choose to apply themselves to the task.</para><para>Since 2007 the W3C XSL Working Group has been working on enhancements to the XSLT language designed
    to make streaming a feasible proposition. A first working draft of XSLT 2.1 has been published (<xref linkend="Kay2010b"/>), 
      and an overview
    of the design approach is available in <xref linkend="Kay2010a"/>.</para><para>This paper describes how streaming is implemented in the Saxon XSLT processor (<xref linkend="Saxonica"/>). This is influenced
    by the work of the W3C specification, but it is by no means an exact match to the specification in its current form:
    many features that should be streamable according to the specification are not yet streamable in Saxon, while Saxon
    succeeds in streaming some constructs that are non-streamable according to XSLT 2.1.</para><para>Streaming facilities in Saxon have been developed over a number of years, and have become
      gradually more sophisticated in successive releases. In order to aid understanding, the
      facilities are therefore presented as a narrative, describing enhancements as they were
      introduced in successive releases. This includes features that have been implemented but not
      yet released at the time of writing, in what is destined to be Saxon 9.3.</para></section><section><title>Streamed XPath in the Schema Validator</title><para>Since version 8.0, released in June 2004, Saxon has incorporated an XML Schema 1.0
      processor. This was introduced to underpin the schema-aware capabilities of the (then draft)
      XSLT 2.0 and XQuery 1.0 specifications, but can also be used as a freestanding validator in
      its own right.</para><para>XML Schema 1.0 (XSD 1.0) allows uniqueness and referential constraints to be expressed by
      means of XPath expressions. For example, in a schema describing XSLT stylesheet documents, the
      constraint that every <code>with-param</code> element within an <code>call-template</code>
      element must have a distinct value for its <code>name</code> attribute might be expressed as
      follows:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
      &lt;xs:element name="call-template" type="call-template-type"&gt;
        &lt;xs:unique&gt;
          &lt;xs:selector xpath="xsl:with-param"/&gt;
          &lt;xs:field xpath="@name"/&gt;
        &lt;/xs:unique&gt;
      &lt;/xs:element&gt;
    </programlisting><para>In this example the two XPath expressions are very simple. XSD 1.0 allows them to be rather
      more complicated than these examples, but they are still restricted to a very small subset of
      XPath: downward selection only; no predicates; union operator allowed at the top level only.
      The specification explicitly states the reason why the subset is so small:</para><blockquote><para>In order to reduce the burden on implementers, in particular implementers of streaming processors, 
    only restricted subsets of XPath expressions are allowed in {selector} and {fields}. </para></blockquote><para>It was important to the designers of XML Schema 1.0 that a validator should be able to process its input document
    in a pure streaming manner with no buffering, and a subset of XPath was chosen to make this viable.</para><para>Accordingly, Saxon 8.0 included in its schema processor a streamed implementation of this XPath subset.</para><para>For various reasons, the schema validator in Saxon was implemented as a push pipeline
      (<xref linkend="Kay2009"/>); the component for evaluating uniqueness and referential constraints
      forms one of the steps in this pipeline. A SAX XML parser generates a sequence of parsing
      events (startElement, endElement, etc) which are piped into the validator, which in turn
      passes them on to the next stage in the process, whatever that might be. Streamed XPath
      evaluation therefore operates in push mode, and this design choice continues to affect the way
      the design evolves today. One of the great advantages of a push pipeline is that it is easy to
      direct parsing events to many different consumers: this is particularly useful with uniqueness
      constraints because many such constraints can be under evaluation at any one time, scoped to
      the same or different parent elements.</para><para>The despatching of events to the listeners involved in evaluating a uniqueness constraint is handled by a component
      called the <code>WatchManager</code>; each of the listening components is called a <code>Watch</code>. For the example
      constraint given, the process is as follows:</para><orderedlist><listitem><para>When the startElement event for the <code>xsl:call-template</code> element is notified by the
          parser, the validator for the <code>xsl:call-template</code> element is fired up. This
          creates a <code>SelectorWatch</code> for the uniqueness constraint. The
            <code>SelectorWatch</code> maintains a table of key values that have been encountered
          (initially empty) so that it can check these for uniqueness.</para></listitem><listitem><para>All parsing events are now notified to this <code>SelectorWatch</code>. For each event, it
          checks whether the ancestor path in the document matches the path given in the
            <code>xs:selector</code> element. In this case this is simply a test whether the event
          is a startElement event for an <code>xsl:with-param</code> element. More generally, it is
          essentially a match of one list of element names against another list of element names,
          taking account of the fact that the <code>//</code> operator can appear at the start of
          the path to indicate that it is not anchored to the root <code>xsl:call-template</code>
          element. When the matching startElement event is encountered, the
            <code>SelectorWatch</code> instantiates a <code>FieldWatch</code> to process any nodes
          that match the expression in the <code>xs:field</code> element.</para></listitem><listitem><para>The <code>FieldWatch</code> is now notified of all parsing events, and when the
            <code>@name</code> attribute is encountered, it informs the owning
            <code>SelectorWatch</code>, which checks that its value does not conflict with any value
          previously notified. This process is more complex than might appear, because there can be
          multiple <code>xs:field</code> elements to define a composite key, and furthermore, the
          field value can be an element rather than an attribute, in which case it may be necessary
          to assemble the value from multiple text nodes separated by comments or processing
          instructions. It is also necessary to check that the <code>FieldWatch</code> fires exactly
          once. (A simplifying factor, however, is that XSD requires the element to have simple
          content.) </para></listitem><listitem><para>After detecting a <code>startElement</code> event that matches its path expression, the
            <code>SelectorWatch</code> must remain alert for further matching events. Before the
          corresponding <code>endElement</code> event is encountered, another matching
            <code>startElement</code> might be notified. This cannot happen in the above example.
          But consider the constraint that within each section of a chapter, the figure numbers must
          be unique: </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
      &lt;xs:element name="chapter" type="call-template-type"&gt;
        &lt;xs:unique&gt;
          &lt;xs:selector xpath=".//section"/&gt;
          &lt;xs:field xpath=".//figure"/&gt;
        &lt;/xs:unique&gt;
      &lt;/xs:element&gt;
      </programlisting><para>It is entirely possible here for chapters to be nested within chapters, and for
          sections to be nested within sections. (It is not possible for figures to be nested within
          figures, however: the node selected by the <code>xs:field</code> element must have simple
          content.) The <code>WatchManager</code> may therefore be distributing events
          simultaneously to a large number of <code>Watch</code> instances, even for a single
          uniqueness constraint; at the same time, of course, other uniqueness constraints may be
          active on the same elements or on different elements at a different level of the source
          tree.</para></listitem></orderedlist></section><section><title>Streaming Copy</title><para>The next step in Saxon's journey towards becoming a streaming XSLT processor was to
      exploit the mechanisms described in the previous section in contexts other than schema
      validation. This was introduced in Saxon 8.5, released in August 2005, and subsequently
      extended. The facility used standard XSLT 2.0 syntax, but required the user to write code in a
      highly stereotyped way for streaming to be possible.</para><section><title>Initial implementation of Streaming Copy</title><para>Typically, the user would write code like this:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
      
&lt;xsl:function name="f:customers"&gt;
  &lt;xsl:copy-of select="doc('customers.xml')/*/customer"
       saxon:read-once="yes" xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"/&gt;
&lt;/xsl:function&gt;

&lt;xsl:template name="main"&gt;
  &lt;xsl:apply-templates select="f:customers()"/&gt;
&lt;/xsl:template&gt;

    </programlisting><para>Without the processing hint expressed by the <code>saxon:read-once</code> attribute, this
        code would parse the source document <code>customers.xml</code> and build a tree
        representation of the document in memory. It would then search the tree for the elements
        matching the path <code>/*/customer</code>, and for each of these in turn it would create a
        copy of the subtree rooted at this element, returning it from the function and then applying
        templates to it.</para><para>It is easy to see that in this operation, building the tree representation of the large
          <code>customers.xml</code> document is unnecessary; it can be bypassed if the elements
        matching <code>/*/customer</code> can be recognized in the event stream issuing from the XML
        parser. Instead of one large tree, the processor can build a series of smaller trees, each
        representing a single customer record. So long as the size of the customer record is kept
        within bounds, there is then no limit on the number of customer records present in the input
        document. This is sometimes referred to as <emphasis>windowing</emphasis> or
          <emphasis>burst-mode streaming</emphasis>: the source document is processed as a sequence
        of small trees, rather than as one large tree.</para><para>The use of the <code>xsl:copy-of</code> instruction here is significant. In the implementation, there is no physical
    copying taking place, because the original whole-document tree is never built. But the result is equivalent to the result
    of building the whole-document tree and then copying the sequence of subtrees. In particular, the nodes in one subtree
    are not linked in any way to the nodes in other subtrees; there is no way the application can navigate outside the boundaries
    of a subtree. Attempting to retrieve the ancestors or siblings of the <code>customer</code> element returns nothing,
    just as it would with a true subtree copy.</para><para>Saxon implements this construct by reusing the <code>WatchManager</code> machinery
        described in the previous section. Having analyzed the <code>select</code> attribute of the
          <code>xsl:copy-of</code> instruction to confirm that it satisfies the constraints on
        streamable XPath expressions, the document <code>customers.xml</code> is then processed
        using a SAX parser which sends parsing events to a <code>WatchManager</code> which in this
        case notifies a new kind of <code>Watch</code>, a <code>CopyWatch</code>, of the start and
        end of elements matching the path expression; between these start and end events, the
          <code>CopyWatch</code> is notified of all intermediate events and uses these to build a
        tree representing the <code>customer</code> element.</para><para>Note again that two elements matching the path can be active at the same time. This cannot happen with the example above, because
    the path <code>/*/customer</code> has a fixed depth. But change the example to <code>//section</code>, and it is clear that
    the set of <code>section</code> elements selected by the path can include one section that is a subtree of another. This situation
    requires some internal buffering: the language semantics require that the sections are delivered in document order, which means that
    the outermost section must be delivered before its nested sections. The trees representing the nested sections must therefore
    be held in memory, to be released for processing only when the <code>endElement</code> event for the outermost section is
    notified. The code is written so that it is always prepared to do this buffering; in practice, it is very rarely needed, and
    no extra costs are incurred in the case where it is not needed. In some cases it would be possible to determine statically
    that no buffering will be needed, but this knowledge confers little benefit.</para><para>The reader may be puzzled by the choice of name for the attribute
          <code>saxon:read-once="yes"</code>. Although the implementation of the
          <code>xsl:copy-of</code> instruction in streaming mode is very different from the
        conventional execution plan, the functional behaviour is identical except in one minor
        detail: there is no longer a guarantee that if the <code>customers.xml</code> file is read
        more than once within the same transformation, its contents will be the same each time. At
        the time this feature was first implemented, the XSLT 2.0 conformance rules required
        implementations to deliver stable results in this situation. The streaming implementation
        necessarily departed from this rule (the only practical way to enforce the rule is to make
        an in-memory copy of the tree), so the <code>saxon:read-once</code> attribute was provided
        as a way for the user to assert that the file would not be read more than once, thus
        licensing the non-conformance in the case where the assertion was not honoured. In the final
        version of the XSLT 2.0 specification, there was explicit provision that implementations
        were allowed to provide a user option to waive the stability requirement for the
          <code>doc()</code> function, thus making this extension conformant.</para><para>A further complication in the implementation is caused by the fact that the
          <code>CopyWatch</code> component delivers its results (the sequence of small
          <code>customer</code> trees) using a push interface (it calls the next component in the
        pipeline to deliver each one in turn), whereas the <code>xsl:apply-templates</code>
        instruction that calls the user-defined function expects to use a pull interface (it calls
        the XPath engine to deliver each one in turn). There is thus a push-pull conflict, which is
        resolved using the design described in <xref linkend="Kay2009"/> and shown in Figure 2. The push
        code operates in one thread, writing the sequence of <code>customer</code> trees to a cyclic
        buffer, which is then read by a parallel thread delivering the trees in response to requests
        from the <code>xsl:apply-templates</code> instruction.</para><figure><title>Figure 2: Two-thread processing model</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol5/graphics/Kay01/Kay01-002.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject><caption><para>Thread One contains the parser and the push-mode evaluation of the streaming path
            expression (the WatchManager and CopyWatch). This emits a sequence of small trees (each
            representing one customer record) to the cyclic butter, from where they are read by the
            pull-mode XPath engine running in Thread Two. Arrow represent flow of control.</para></caption></figure></section><section><title>Refinements of the Streaming Copy feature</title><para>In releases subsequent to Saxon 8.5, the streaming copy mechanism described in the previous section was enhanced in a number of ways,
    without changing its fundamentals.</para><para>In Saxon 8.8 (September 2006) two changes were made. Firstly, the set of XPath expressions
        that could be handled in streaming mode was extended, to include union expressions and
        simple predicates. Secondly, the need for the two-thread model was eliminated in cases where
        no further processing of the copied subtrees was required: for example, in a transformation
        whose output contained these subtrees without modification.</para><para>In Saxon 9.1 (July 2008) the mechanism was extended to XQuery, via a new extension
        function <code>saxon:stream()</code>, which was also made available in XSLT. This might be
        regarded as a pseudo-function: the call
          <code>saxon:stream(doc('customers.xml')/*/customer)</code> delivers a copy of the value of
        its argument (that is, a sequence of <code>customer</code> subtrees), but it requires its
        argument to conform to the syntax of streamable path expressions. <footnote><para>Looking at this syntax, one might reasonably ask whether a pull pipeline would not
            deliver the result with less complexity. For this example, it probably would. The push
            code was used primarily because it already existed and could be reused. But I think this
            is no accident: I tend to the view that components implemented with a push model are
            likely to be reusable in a wider variety of configurations. For more details on push
            versus pull pipelines, see <xref linkend="Kay2009"/>.</para></footnote></para><para>In Saxon 9.2 (August 2009) a further refinement was introduced to allow the processing of
        the input stream to terminate prematurely. For example, the query
          <code>saxon:stream(doc('customers.xml')/*/@version)</code> will return the value of the
          <code>version</code> attribute from the outermost element of the document, and will read
        no further once this has been seen. This makes it possible to obtain information from near
        the start of an XML document in constant time, regardless of the document size, which is
        especially useful in a pipeline when making decisions on how to route a document for
        processing based on information in its header. (It's a moot point whether this is consistent
        with the requirement in the XML 1.0 specification that all well-formedness errors in a
        document must be reported to the application. But the facility is so useful that we can
        ignore the standards-lawyers on this one.)</para></section><section><title>Streaming with Retained State</title><para>A limitation of the streaming copy approach as outlined above is that there is no way of
        using the information in a subtree once the processing of that subtree has finished; so
        there is no way that the processing of one subtree can influence the processing of
        subsequent subtrees. (Saxon always had a workaround to this problem, the deprecated
          <code>saxon:assign</code> instruction which introduces mutable variables to the language;
        but this plays havoc with optimisation).</para><para>An answer to this problem was found in the form of the <code>xsl:iterate</code>
        instruction defined in the XSLT 2.1 working draft. This was implemented in Saxon 9.2 in the
        Saxon namespace (as <code>saxon:iterate</code>), but I will present it using the W3C syntax,
        which becomes available in Saxon 9.3.</para><para>Consider the problem of processing a sequence of <code>transaction</code> elements, and outputting the
        same sequence of elements but with an additional attribute holding the running balance on the account, obtained
        by accumulating the values of all the preceding transactions.</para><para>The classic solution to this would use sibling recursion:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
        &lt;xsl:template match="transaction"&gt;
          &lt;xsl:param name="balance" as="xs:decimal"/&gt;
          &lt;transaction value="{@value}" balance="{$balance + @value}"/&gt;
          &lt;xsl:apply-templates select="following-sibling::transaction[1]"&gt;
             &lt;xsl:with-param name="balance" select="$balance + @value"/&gt;
          &lt;/xsl:apply-templates&gt;
        &lt;/xsl:template&gt;</programlisting><para>There are a number of difficulties with this approach. Firstly, everyone who has taught
        XSLT appears to agree that students have considerable difficulty producing the code above as
        the solution to this exercise, despite its brevity and apparent simplicity. Secondly, it
        relies rather heavily on the XSLT processor implementing tail call optimization; if you run
        this on a variety of popular XSLT processors, many of them will run out of stack space after
        processing 500 or so transactions, showing that they do not implement this optimization.
        Finally, the analysis needed to demonstrate that a streaming implementation of this code is
        feasible is far from easy, and one suspects that minor departures from this particular way
        of writing the code will invalidate any such analysis.</para><para>For all these reasons, XSLT 2.1 introduces a new instruction <code>xsl:iterate</code>, which allows the solution to
      be expressed as follows:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
        &lt;xsl:iterate select="transaction"&gt;
          &lt;xsl:param name="balance" as="xs:decimal" select="0"/&gt;
          &lt;transaction value="{@value}" balance="{$balance + @value}"/&gt;
          &lt;xsl:next-iteration&gt;
             &lt;xsl:with-param name="balance" select="$balance + @value"/&gt;
          &lt;/xsl:next-iteration&gt;
        &lt;/xsl:iteration&gt;</programlisting><para>This has the appearance of a simple loop rather than functional recursion; it behaves like
        the familiar <code>xsl:for-each</code> instruction with the added ability to set a parameter
        after the processing of one value which is then available for use when processing the next.
        A key difference compared with the recursive solution is that the set of transactions to be
        processed is identified in one place, the <code>select</code> attribute of the
          <code>xsl:iterate</code> instruction, rather than being the product of a sequence of
        independent calls on <code>following-sibling</code>. A useful consequence of this difference
        is that termination is guaranteed.</para><para>Another way of looking at <code>xsl:iterate</code> is as syntactic sugar for the
          <code>foldl</code> higher-order function found in many functional programming languages:
        this applies a user-supplied function (the body of <code>xsl:iterate</code>) to each item of
        an input sequence (the value of the <code>select</code> expression), with each iteration
        delivering an accumulated value of some kind, which is made available as a parameter to the
        user-supplied function when called to process the next item.</para><para>Saxon 9.2 implements this new instruction (albeit in its own namespace) and allows the
          <code>select</code> expression to select the stream of subtrees arising from a streaming
        copy operation: for example <code>&lt;xsl:iterate
          select="saxon:stream(doc('transactions'xml')/*/transaction"&gt;</code>. By this means,
        information computed while processing one input transaction can be made available while
        processing the next. The implementation of <code>xsl:iterate</code> in fact knows nothing
        about streaming; it is processing the sequence of subtrees just as it would process any
        other sequence of items.</para></section><section><title>Limitations of Streaming Copy</title><para>The streaming copy feature has enabled many applications to be written using Saxon that
        would otherwise have been impossible because of the size of the input document. Many of the
        streaming use cases published by the W3C Working Group (<xref linkend="Cimprich2010"/>) can be implemented using
        this feature. But despite the various refinements that have been described, there are some
        serious limitations:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>There is no way of getting access to part of the streamed source document other than
      what is contained in the copied subtrees. This problem can be mitigated by using a union expression to select
      all the data that is needed. However, the programming then becomes rather complex.</para></listitem><listitem><para>The design pattern works well with "hedge-like" source documents: those where the hierarchy
            fans out quickly to a large number of small subtrees. But there are many large source
            documents that do not fit into this pattern - this arises particularly with
            "document-oriented" XML, but also for example with GML (Geography Markup Language) [gml]
            where individual geographical features represented in the data stream can each be of
            considerable size.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>These limitations arise because streaming copy treats the input document as a flat
        sequence of elements, not really as a hierarchy. To address these limitations, it is
        necessary to restore the ability to process the input tree using recursive descent using
        template rules. The way in which template rules can be made to work in a streaming manner is
        the subject of the next section.</para></section></section><section><title>Streaming Templates</title><para>Consider a stylesheet containing the following two rules:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
      &lt;xsl:template match="*"&gt;
        &lt;xsl:copy&gt;
          &lt;xsl:apply-templates/&gt;
        &lt;/xsl:copy&gt;
      &lt;/xsl:template&gt;
      
      &lt;xsl:template match="note"/&gt;
      </programlisting><para>This follows a familiar coding pattern: first a generic template which acts as the default processing for all
    elements in the source document (this example copies the element to the output, sans attributes, and uses the
    <code>xsl:apply-templates</code> instruction to invoke recursive processing of its children); then one or more templates
    for specific named elements to process them in a way that differs from the general rule. The effect of this stylesheet
    is to copy the source document to the result document unchanged except for the loss of all attributes, and of elements
    named <code>note</code> together with their descendants.</para><para>It is easy to see how this stylesheet could be implemented in a single pass over the
      source document, without building an in-memory tree. A simple filter can be applied to events
      emanating from the parser before passing them on to the serializer: all events are passed on
      unchanged, except for (a) events representing attribute nodes and (b) events that occur
      between the <code>startElement</code> event and corresponding <code>endElement</code> event
      for a <code>note</code> element.</para><para>In XSLT 2.1 streamability is a property of a <emphasis role="ital">mode</emphasis> (<xref linkend="Kay2010a"/>). 
      If a mode is declared to be streamable, then all the template rules in that mode must
      obey the restrictions placed on streamable templates. The analysis defined in the XSLT 2.1
      specification to determine streamability is rather complex; the rules currently implemented in
      Saxon are much simpler (and in most cases, more restrictive), while still allowing a wide
      class of transformations to be expressed. I will present first the Saxon 9.2 implementation,
      which is relatively easy to understand, and then the Saxon 9.3 extensions, which add
      considerable complexity and power.</para><section><title>Streaming Templates in Saxon 9.2</title><para>Saxon 9.2 follows the principle that streamability is a property of a mode, though its
        restrictions on streamable templates are far more severe than those in the XSLT 2.1 draft.
        The rules for streamable templates can be summarised (in simplified form) as follows:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>The match pattern must contain no predicates.</para></listitem><listitem><para>The template body may contain at most one <emphasis>drill-down construct</emphasis>. This may
            be an <code>xsl:apply-templates</code> instruction with defaulted <code>select</code>
            expression, or one of the following expressions or instructions applied to the context
            node: <code>xsl:copy-of</code>, <code>xsl:value-of</code>, <code>string()</code>,
              <code>data()</code> (or implicit atomization), or one of a small number of other
            constructs.</para></listitem><listitem><para>The drill-down construct may have only the following as its containing (ancestor)
            instructions: <code>xsl:element</code>, literal result elements,
              <code>xsl:value-of</code>, <code>xsl:attribute</code>, <code>xsl:comment</code>,
              <code>xsl:processing-instruction</code>, <code>xsl:result-document</code>,
              <code>xsl:variable</code>, <code>xsl:sequence</code>.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Apart from the drill-down construct and its ancestors, any expression within the template that
            has a dependency on the context item must fall into one of the following categories: (a)
            a function (for example, <code>local-name()</code> or <code>exists()</code>) that
            returns a local property of the node, or of one of its attributes or ancestors, or of an
            attribute of an ancestor; (b) an expression that returns the string value or typed value
            of an attribute of the node or an attribute of one of its ancestors.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>The effect of these rules is that the stylesheet given above, with the addition of the declaration 
    <code>&lt;xsl:mode streamable="yes"/&gt;</code><footnote><para>In Saxon 9.2, the element is in the Saxon namespace as <code>saxon:mode</code></para></footnote>,
    is fully streamable.</para><para>These rules allow a wide variety of transformations to be expressed. However, they impose
        many arbitrary restrictions. For example, a template cannot contain the instruction
          <code>&lt;xsl:value-of select=". + 3"/&gt;</code>, because an addition expression
          (<code>+</code>) is not an acceptable ancestor of the implicit drill-down construct
          <code>data(.)</code>. To get around this restriction, it is possible to bind a variable to
        the value of <code>data(.)</code> and then perform the addition using the value of the
        variable.</para><para>To understand the reason for such arbitrary restrictions, it is necessary to understand
        something of the architecture of the implementation: whose explanation, indeed, is the main
        purpose of this paper.</para><para>Traditionally, Saxon constructed the source tree using a push pipeline. XSLT instructions
        were then interpreted, and by-and-large, they evaluated their XPath subexpressions using a
        pull pipeline of iterator objects navigating the source tree, and generated output
        (including temporary trees) by pushing SAX-like events to a serializer or tree builder
        pipeline. To implement streaming templates, this model has been turned upside-down, almost
        literally. During streamed evaluation, everything operates in push mode, driven by events
        coming from the XML parser. In effect, the code implementing a template rule operating in
        push mode is a Jackson inversion (<xref linkend="Kay2009"/>) of the code used to implement
        the same template rule in the traditional architecture. This inversion is analogous to
        rewriting a top-down parser as a bottom-up parser: instead of the application being in
        control and making <code>getNextInput()</code> calls to the parser, the application becomes
        event-driven and is called when new input is available. In consequence, the application has
        to maintain its own stack to represent the current state; it can no longer rely on the call
        stack maintained by the compiler of the implementation language.</para><para>The inverted code for a template is generated by the XSLT compiler, and consists (in Saxon
        9.2) of a sequence of pre-descent actions, a drill-down action, and a sequence of
        post-descent actions. The pre-descent actions generally involve writing
          <code>startElement</code> events or evaluating complete instructions; the post-descent
        actions similarly involve either complete instructions or <code>endElement</code> actions.
        These correspond to the instructions that are permitted as ancestors of the drill-drown
        construct: mainly instructions such as <code>xsl:element</code>, which are classified as
          <emphasis role="ital">divisible</emphasis> instructions representing the fact that their
        push-mode execution can be split into two halves, realised by the entry points
          <code>processLeft()</code> and <code>processRight()</code>. The drill-down action is one
        of <code>apply</code>, <code>copy-of</code>, <code>value-of</code>, or <code>skip</code>,
        and indicates what is to be done with the content of the matched element (the events that
        occur after the <code>startElement</code> that activates the template rule and before the
        corresponding <code>endElement</code>). The value <code>skip</code> causes these events to
        be skipped, and arises when the template rule contains no drill-down construct. The value
          <code>copy-of</code> indicates that a subtree is to be built from these events;
          <code>value-of</code> indicates that a string is to be constructed by concatenating the
        text nodes and ignoring everything else. Finally, the value <code>apply</code> indicates
        that the events should be matched against template rules for the relevant mode; when a match
        occurs, the selected template rule will then receive the events until the matching
          <code>endElement</code> event occurs.</para><para>This is all implemented using the a <code>StreamingDespatcher</code> that despatches events
        to the relevant template rules. This functions in a very similar way to the
          <code>WatchManager</code> described earlier, and in the current Saxon 9.3 code base the
        two despatching classes have been combined into one.</para></section><section><title>Streamable Templates in Saxon 9.3</title><para>Saxon 9.3 (not yet released at the time of submitting this paper) extends streamable templates to handle a much
      larger subset of the XSLT language, while still falling a little short of the capabilities defined in the XSLT 2.1 draft.</para><para>The first extension is in the area of match patterns for templates. Saxon 9.3 integrates the two concepts of a match pattern
        and a streamable XPath expression. This makes sense because both are implemented by testing to see whether a given
        node matches the pattern; the only difference is that with an XSLT match pattern in non-streaming mode, the predicates can
        contain XPath expressions that perform arbitrary tree navigation. For XSD selector and field expressions, the parsing still
        artificially restricts the path expression to conform to the XSD-defined XPath subset, but the object that results from the parsing,
        and that is used at run-time, is a <code>Pattern</code> object equivalent that used when starting from an XSLT match pattern.
        The pattern used in a streamable template rule can be any XSLT pattern provided it does not contain a predicate that is
        positional (for example, is numeric or calls <code>position()</code> or <code>last()</code>) or that uses
        the child, descendant, descendant-or-self, following, following-sibling, preceding, or preceding-sibling axes.</para><para>The body of the template rule is inverted in the same way as with Saxon 9.2, but the
        rules for what it may contain are less restrictive. There is still a rule that only one
        downward selection is allowed: more specifically, in the expression tree (abstract syntax
        tree) representing the body of the template rule, there must be only one leaf node whose
        path to the root of the expression tree contains a downwards selection. This path through
        the expression tree is referred to as the <emphasis role="ital">streaming route</emphasis>.
        This rule is relaxed in the case where the template contains a conditional instruction such
        as <code>xsl:choose</code>; in this case each branch of the conditional may make downwards
        selections. Unlike the XSLT 2.1 draft, Saxon does not currently allow a node in the streamed
        input document to be bound to a variable, or passed as a parameter to another template or
        function. A further rule is that the template must not return a node in the streamed
        document (for example, <code>&lt;xsl:sequence select="."/&gt;</code>) - this is because there
        is no way of analyzing what the caller attempts to do with such a node.</para><para>It is also possible, of course, for the template rule to make no downward selection at all: this results in the subtree
        below the matched node being skipped.</para><para>All the expressions that appear on the streaming route must be capable of push
        evaluation, that is, they must have an implementation that is event-driven. Saxon supports
        push evaluation at two different levels of granularity (<xref linkend="Kay2009"/>),
        parse-event granularity and item granularity; the corresponding event streams are referred
        to respectively as decomposed or composed streams. In the first case the expression
        evaluator is notified every time a parse event occurs (for example, startElement and
        endElement). In the second case, it is notified only for complete XDM items (nodes or atomic
        values). The <code>sum()</code> function supports push evaluation at the item level, which
        means that given the expression <code>sum(.//value)</code>, each descendant
          <code>value</code> element is assembled as a complete node, which is then atomized, and
        the resulting atomic values are notified one by one to the sum implementation, which adds
        each one in turn to the running total. By constrast, the functions <code>count()</code> and
          <code>exists()</code> have implementations that work at the parse-event level, which means
        that there is no need to build the nodes being counted as trees in memory: thus
          <code>count(.//employee)</code> merely tallies the startElement events that match its
        argument expression <code>.//employee</code> without ever building a tree representation of
        an <code>employee</code> element.</para><para>A push component that takes a composed stream (XDM items) as input is referred to as a <emphasis role="ital">feed</emphasis>; an evaluator 
        that works on a decomposed stream (parse events) is referred to as a <emphasis role="ital">watch</emphasis>. This classification
        is based on the nature of the input stream. Orthogonally, the component may deliver its result as either a composed or
        decomposed stream: so there are four categories overall: a composing and decomposing Watch, and a composing and decomposing Feed.
        Examples of the four categories are shown in the table below:
      </para><table><thead><tr><th>Input/Output</th><th>Composed</th><th>Decomposed</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Composed</td><td>remove($in, 3)</td><td>&lt;e&gt;{$in}&lt;/e&gt;</td></tr><tr><td>Decomposed</td><td>data($in)</td><td>&lt;xsl:for-each select="$in"/&gt;</td></tr></tbody></table><para>In general, the flow is that decomposed events arrive from the source XML parser. After
        some processing they are turned into composed items; these are then further processed, and
        eventually decomposed into events to be sent to the serializer. To make this more concrete
        consider the streaming template:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
        &lt;xsl:template match="emp"&gt;
          &lt;employee name="{@name}" nr="{@empNr}"&gt;
            &lt;xsl:value-of select="distinct-values(skills/skill)"/&gt;
          &lt;/employee&gt;
        &lt;/xsl:template&gt;
        </programlisting><para>The streaming route here contains a literal result element (<code>employee</code>), the
          <code>xsl:value-of</code> instruction, the <code>distinct-values()</code> function call,
        and the path expression <code>skills/skill</code>. It also contains expressions added by the
        compiler, reflecting the implicit atomization and type checking performed by the
          <code>distinct-values()</code> function, and the implicit call on
          <code>string-join()</code> that is performed to insert separator spaces on behalf of the
          <code>xsl:value-of</code> instruction. The full expression tree is shown in Figure 3, with
          the streaming route highlighted.</para><figure xml:id="fig03"><title>Figure 3: The expression tree of a template, showing the streaming route</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../../vol5/graphics/Kay01/Kay01-003.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject><caption><para>The expression tree omits some nodes, for example type-checking operators, for clarity. The
          highlighted "path" node acts as the Watch, looking for events coming from the parser that match the
          pattern <code>skills/skill</code>. The <code>data()</code> node composes these events into strings
          representing the typed value of the <code>skill</code> elements; these are fed through the operators
          found on the streaming route until they reach the <code>&lt;employee&gt;</code> element
          constructor, which delivers a stream of events representing the newly constructed element. Typically
          these events go straight to the serializer. The parts of the expression tree that are not on the streaming
          route (the two attribute constructors) are evaluated in pull-mode as normal.</para></caption></figure><para>The <code>distinct-values()</code> function implicitly atomizes its input. So the first
        thing that happens to the incoming data is that it is sent to a TypedValueWatch: this takes
        in a decomposed sequence of events and outputs a composed sequence of atomic values
        representing the typed values of the <code>skill</code> elements. This is piped into a type
        checker that checks that the values in this sequence are all strings. The type-checked
        csequence is then piped into the component that evaluates the <code>distinct-values()</code>
        function, which again outputs a composed stream (this being identical to its input stream
        except that values are removed from the stream if they have been encountered before). The
          <code>xsl:value-of</code> instruction is initially compiled into a pipeline of primitive
        instructions that first joins adjacent text nodes, then atomizes, then inserts separators
        between adjacent strings, then converts the resulting string to a text node; in this case
        the optimizer knows from type analysis that the first two steps are superfluous, so we are
        left with a pipeline that takes a composed sequence of strings as its input, and produces a
        composed sequence comprising a single text node as its output. Finally, the component
        representing the literal result element <code>employee</code> takes this composed input, and
        produces decomposed output consisting of a startElement event, two attribute events, a text
        node event, and an endElement event. Typically these events will be sent directly to the
        serializer.</para><para>An expression, of course, may have more than one sub-expression, and it may be capable
        of push evaluation in respect of some of those sub-expressions but not others. All
        expressions support push evaluation in respect of sub-expressions that are singletons
        (cardinality zero-or-one). Thus, for example, the expression <code>(sum(.//value) +
          1)</code> is streamable, because although there is no specific support for evaluating the
        addition in push mode, the system is capable of constructing the two singleton arguments and
        using the conventional pull-mode addition. Many expressions also benefit from a generic
        implementation in cases where an argument is a non-singleton sequence. This generic
        implementation buffers the argument sequence in memory and then uses the pull-mode
        implementation once the sequence is complete. This of course is not pure streaming, but it
        provides useful scaffolding to enable less commonly used expressions to appear in a
        streaming template while awaiting a pure streaming implementation. Currently this mechanism
        is used for comparison expressions such as <code>.//value = 17</code> (recall that in XPath,
        this returns true if at least one of the <code>value</code> elements is equal to 17); there
        is no technical reason that prevents the creation of a pure push-mode implementation of a
        general comparison expression with respect to either argument, but it has not yet been
        implemented, and it is not a top priority because in the vast majority of cases the
        arguments actually turn out to be singletons.</para><para>The compile-time template inversion process operates by means of a recursive walk of the
        expression tree. At every level there must be at most one branch that performs downward
        selection; this branch is taken, and by this means the streaming route is identified. The
        process then attempts to identify the longest suffix of the streaming route that constitutes
        a streamable pattern. For example, if the body of the template is <code>&lt;xsl:value-of
          select="sum(.//value) + 1"/&gt;</code>, the streamable pattern is <code>.//value</code>. The
        immediate parent of this pattern on the streaming route must always be an expression that
        can be evaluated as a Watch. The number of expressions implemented as a Watch is suprisingly
        small:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para><code>TypedValueWatch</code> handles all expressions that use the atomized value of the
            selected nodes.</para></listitem><listitem><para><code>StringValueWatch</code> handles all expressions that use the string value of the
            selected nodes.</para></listitem><listitem><para><code>CountWatch</code> handles the <code>count()</code>, <code>exists()</code>, and
              <code>empty()</code> functions.</para></listitem><listitem><para><code>CopyWatch</code> (the one we met earlier) handles <code>xsl:copy-of</code>.</para></listitem><listitem><para><code>VoidWatch</code> is used for templates or branches of a conditional that make no
            downwards selection.</para></listitem><listitem><para><code>SimpleContentWatch</code> implements the rules for instructions such as
              <code>xsl:value-of</code> and <code>xsl:attribute</code>; specifically, it
            concatenates adjacent text nodes, removes empty text nodes, and reduces all other nodes
            to string values.</para></listitem><listitem><para><code>ApplyTemplatesWatch</code> is used where the downwards selection appears in the select
            expression of an <code>xsl:apply-templates</code> instruction, and also supports
              <code>xsl:apply-imports</code> and <code>xsl:next-match</code>.</para></listitem><listitem><para><code>ForEachWatch</code> is used where the downwards selection appears in the select
            expression of an <code>xsl:for-each</code> instruction.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>Most of these Watch implementations are composing: they emit a sequence of XDM items. 
        The two exceptions are the <code>ForEachWatch</code> and the <code>ApplyTemplatesWatch</code>, which
        emit a sequence of parse events.</para><para>We have already seen the <code>CopyWatch</code> earlier in the paper: it is used for a
        simple streaming copy, as well as for <code>xsl:copy-of</code> instructions appearing within
        a streaming template. When it receives a startElement event representing an element selected
        by its controlling pattern (we'll assume to keep things simple that it is watching for
        elements), it starts building a tree. All subsequent parse events until the matching
        endElement are directed to this tree builder. When the tree is complete, the node at the
        root of the tree is emitted to the Feed that implements the parent of the
          <code>xsl:copy-of</code> instruction, that is, the parent expression in the streaming
        route through the expression tree. </para><para>The <code>StringValueWatch</code> and <code>TypedValueWatch</code> work in a very
        similar way, except that instead of building a tree from the incoming events, they construct
        the string value or typed value of the node by concatenating the values of those events that
        represent text nodes.</para><para>All these Watch implementations have a complication that has already been mentioned for Streaming Copy: a startElement
      event for a matching element might be notified while an existing matching element is already being processed; that is, the
      pattern that the Watch matches may select a node that is a descendant of another matched node. For this reason, the Watch
      does not actually construct the tree (or string value or typed value) directly; instead it creates an event receiver
      dedicated to this task, which it passes back to the WatchManager; the WatchManager then notifies all events to all active
      event receivers to do the necessary work, taking care of deactivating them when needed. When the endElement event occurs,
      the Watch passes the constructed tree to the next Feed in the streaming route only if the matched element has no matching
      ancestors; for an inner matched node, the tree is held in a queue until the outer tree is complete, since the outer tree
      comes first in document order and must therefore be notified to the waiting Feed before the inner trees. This queue
      again represents a departure from pure streaming; the XSLT 2.1 draft has an open issue on this question.</para><para>The <code>ApplyTemplatesWatch</code> is similarly notified of the startElement event for
        a node that matches the select expression of the <code>xsl:apply-templates</code>
        instruction. It responds to this by searching for a matching template rule — this is
        possible because the constraints on match patterns in a streamable template ensure that the
        pattern can be evaluated when positioned at the startElement event (the object representing
        the event, it should be mentioned, provides methods to get local properties of the node such
        as the name and type annotation, and also to navigate to the node's ancestors and their
        attributes). Having identified the template to be applied, which because it is in a
        streaming mode will always have been compiled with template inversion, it then gets the
        Watch expression identified during the analysis of the called template, and nominates this
        Watch expression to the WatchManager. All events up to the corresponding endElement will
        therefore be sent by the WatchManager to the called template, where the same process
        continues recursively. At the same time, the same events are being sent to the calling
          <code>ApplyTemplatesWatch</code>, because as with <code>xsl:copy-of</code>, it is entirely
        possible for the <code>select</code> expression of <code>xsl:apply-templates</code> to
        select an element that is a descendant of another element already being processed; the
        results of the processing of such nested elements will again be buffered.</para><para>The <code>ForEachWatch</code> operates in a very similar way to the
          <code>ApplyTemplatesWatch</code>, except that there is no need to search for a matching
        template. Rather, the body of the <code>xsl:for-each</code> instruction is compiled directly
        as an inverted template and is invoked unconditionally for each startElement event matching
        a selected node.</para><para>A similar streaming implementation has been written for <code>xsl:iterate</code>; none
        is yet available for <code>xsl:for-each-group</code>, but it is expected that it will follow
        the same principles.</para></section></section><section><title>Conclusions</title><para>Streaming of XSLT transformations has long been an aspiration, and many partial solutions have
  been developed over the years. It has proved difficult or impossible to create streaming implementations
  of the full XSLT language as defined by W3C.</para><para>The draft XSLT 2.1 specification has been developed as a solution to this problem. It
      defines a subset of the full XSLT language that is intended to be streamable without requiring
      unknown magic on the part of the implementation, and at the same time it provides extensions
      to the language (such as <code>xsl:iterate</code>) that make it possible to write powerful
      transformations without straying from the streamable subset. The design of the language is
      informed by experience with both XSLT 2.0 and STX, and by a large collection of use cases
      describing problems that benefit from a streamed implementation.</para><para>Successive releases of Saxon, some predating this work and some influenced by it, have provided partial
  solutions to the streaming challenge with increasing levels of sophistication. At the time of writing, there are
  many ideas in the specification that are not yet implemented in Saxon, and there are some features in the Saxon
  implementation that are not yet reflected in the specification. Nevertheless, development of the language
  standard and of an industrial implementation are proceeding in parallel, which is always a promising indicator
  that standards when they arrive will be timely and viable. Both the language and the implementation, however,
  still need a lot more work.</para><para>Saxon's approach to the problem is based on using a push architecture end-to-end, to eliminate the
  source tree as an intermediary between push-based XML parsing/validation and pull-based XPath processing.
  Implementing the entire repertoire of XPath expressions and XSLT instructions in an event-based pipeline
  is challenging, to say the least. However, enough has been completed to show that the undertaking is viable,
  and a large enough subset is already available to users to enable some serious large-scale transformation
  tasks to be performed.</para></section><bibliography><title>Bibliography</title><bibliomixed xml:id="Barton2003" xreflabel="Barton2003">Charles Barton et al.
    An Algorithm for Streaming XPath Processing with Forward and Backward Axes.
    In Proc. 19 Int Conf Data Eng, Banagalore, India, 5-8 March 2003. ISBN: 0-7803-7665-X 
    <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.research.ibm.com/xj/pubs/icde.pdf</link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="BarYossef2004" xreflabel="BarYossef2004">Ziv Bar-Yossef, Marcus Fontoura, and Vanja Josifovski.
    On the Memory Requirements of XPath Evaluation over XML Streams.
    J Comp Sys Sci Vol 73 Iss 3 pp 391-441, May 2007, ISSN 0022-0000 
    <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.almaden.ibm.com/cs/people/fontoura/papers/pods2004.pdf</link>.
    doi: <biblioid class="doi">10.1016/j.jcss.2006.10.002</biblioid>.  
  </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Cimprich2010" xreflabel="Cimprich2010">Petr Cimprich (ed). 
  Requirements and Use Cases for XSLT 2.1. W3C Working Draft 10 June 2010. 
    <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt-21-requirements/</link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="CityGML" xreflabel="CityGML">Exchange and Storage of Virtual 3D City Models.
    Thomas H Kolbe (ed). <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.citygml.org/</link>. Retrieved 2010-07-10.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Dvorakova2008" xreflabel="Dvirakova2008">Jana Dvořáková.
    A Formal Framework for Streaming XML Transformations.
    PhD Thesis, Comenius University, Bratislava, Slovenia, 2008.
  </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Dvorakova2009a" xreflabel="Dvorakova2009a">Jana Dvořáková.
    Automatic Streaming Processing of XSLT Transformations Based on Tree Transducers.
    Informatica: An International Journal of Computing and Informatics, 
    Special Issue - Intelligent and Distributed Computing, Slovene Society Informatika, 2009   
  </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Dvorakova2009b" xreflabel="Dvorakova2009b">Jana Dvořáková and F Zavoral.
    Using Input Buffers for Streaming XSLT Processing, 
    Proceedings of the International Conference on Advances in Databases - GlobeNet/DB 2009, 
    Gosier, IEEE Computer Society Press, 2009.
    doi: <biblioid class="doi">10.1109/DBKDA.2009.25</biblioid>.  
  </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Florescu2003" xreflabel="Florescu2003">Daniela Florescu et al.
    The BEA/XQRL Streaming XQuery Processor. In Proc. 29 VLDB, 2003, Berlin, Germany, pp 997-1008. ISBN:0-12-722442-4
    <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.vldb.org/conf/2003/papers/S30P01.pdf</link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Frisch2007" xreflabel="Frisch2007">Alain Frisch and Keisuke Nakano. Streaming
      XML transformations using term rewriting. PLAN-X 2007 Nice, France, 20 Jan 2007 pp 2-13.
        <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://yquem.inria.fr/~frisch/xstream/long.pdf</link>
  </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="GML">OpenGIS Geography Markup Language (GML) Encoding Standard.
    OGC (Open Geospatial Consortium). <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/gml</link>. Retrieved 2010-07-10.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Guo2004" xreflabel="Guo2004">Zhimao Guo, Min Li, Xiaoling Wang, and Aoying Zhou.
    Scalable XSLT Evaluation. In Proc 6 Asia-Pacific Web Conf, Hangzhou, China, 14-17 April 2004. ISBN 3-540-21371-6
    <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://arxiv.org/pdf/cs.DB/0408051</link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Kay2009" xreflabel="Kay2009">Michael Kay.
    You Pull, I’ll Push: on the Polarity of Pipelines.
    Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Montréal, Canada, August 11 - 14, 2009.
    In Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3 (2009).
    doi: <biblioid class="doi">10.4242/BalisageVol3.Kay01</biblioid>.
  </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Kay2010a" xreflabel="Kay2010a">Michael Kay.
  Streaming in XSLT 2.1. 
  Proc XML Prague 2010. 13-14 March 2010, Prague, Czech Rep.
    <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.xmlprague.cz/2010/files/XMLPrague_2010_Proceedings.pdf</link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Kay2010b" xreflabel="Kay2010b">Michael Kay (ed). XSL Transformations (XSLT) Version 2.1.
    W3C Working Draft 11 May 2010. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt-21/</link>. </bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Li2005" xreflabel="Li2005">Xiaogang Li and Gagan Agrawal.
    Efficient evaluation of XQuery over streaming data. 
    In Proc. 31 VLDB, 2005, Trondheim, Norway, pp 265-276. ISBN 1-59593-154-6
    <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.vldb2005.org/program/paper/wed/p265-li.pdf</link></bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Joshi" xreflabel="Joshi">Amruta Joshi and Oleg Slezburg.
    CS276B Project Report: Streaming XPath Engine. Undated. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www-cs-students.stanford.edu/~amrutaj/work/papers/xpath.pdf</link>
    Retrieved 2010-04-12</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Saxonica" xreflabel="Saxonica">The Saxon XSLT and XQuery Processor.
    <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.saxonica.com/</link> Retrieved 2010-07-10.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="STX" xreflabel="STX">Streaming Transformations for XML (STX).
    <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://stx.sourceforge.net/</link> Retrieved 2010-07-10. Contains links to articles and presentations by Tobias Trapp,
    Oliver Becker, and Petr Cimprich.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="Zergaoui2009" xreflabel="Zergaoui2009">Mohamed Zergaoui. Memory management in
      streaming: Buffering, lookahead, or none. Which to choose? Int Symp on Processing XML
      Efficiently. 10 Aug 2009, Montreal, Canada. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 4
      (2009). doi: <biblioid class="doi">10.4242/BalisageVol4.Zergaoui02</biblioid>.
        <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol4/html/Zergaoui02/BalisageVol4-Zergaoui02.html</link>
    </bibliomixed></bibliography></article>