<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3"><title>The Ontologist</title><subtitle>Controlled Vocabularies and Semantic Wikis</subtitle><info><confgroup><conftitle>Balisage: The Markup Conference 2012</conftitle><confdates>August 7 - 10, 2012</confdates></confgroup><abstract><para>This paper covers the design details of the Ontologist, a MarkLogic based project
                for using RDF triples, XQuery search capabilities and RESTful services to provide
                controlled vocabularies, taxonomy management and semantic wikis. </para></abstract><author><personname><firstname>Kurt</firstname><surname>Cagle</surname></personname><personblurb><para>Kurt Cagle is an author, editor, and information architect working for Avalon Consulting, LLC.
                He is the author of a number of books and articles focused on XML and web technologies, and he has
                been active as a W3C Invited Expert, technology evangelist and consultant in the XML and development
                communities for more than two decades. Clients have included the ObamaCare Health Insurance Exchange system,
                the US National Archives, the Library of Congress, Harvard Business School and the Canadian Research
                Consortium. He has most recently been focused on XQuery and Semantic Web Development.</para></personblurb><affiliation><jobtitle>Information Architect</jobtitle><orgname>Avalon Consulting, Ltd.</orgname></affiliation><email>kurt.cagle@gmail.com</email><link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.avalonconsult.com</link></author><legalnotice><para>Copyright © 2012 Kurt Cagle</para></legalnotice></info><section><title>Overview</title><para>The Ontologist began its existence as a way of dealing with one of the more vexing
            problems of modern distributed applications - dealing with controlled vocabularies. This
            paper and talk will explore the design of the Ontologist at an application and
            theoretical level, and illustrate how it provides a synergy between XQuery and SPARQL
            development in order to build everything from list managers to knowledge management
            systems. </para></section><section><title>Controlled Vocabularies and Data Feeds</title><para>A <emphasis>controlled vocabulary</emphasis> typically appears at first as an
            enumerated set of terms (with the obvious temptation by schema designers to encode these
            terms in XSD schemas as enumerated simple types). </para><para>However, unlike a "normal" enumeration, controlled vocabulary terms have a number of
            properties which can make such a temptation a costly trap. In most cases such controlled
            vocabularies have a number of key characteristics: <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis>Distinct labels and codes.</emphasis> The displayed value of the
                        item in question will more than likely not be the same as the underlying
                        code value that references the term in question. For instance, a set of
                        colors might have the color name but use RGB notation for identifying the
                        resources at a system level.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Temporality.</emphasis> Items may be added or removed from the
                        underlying set over time, the values of given sets may change, or the
                        preferred ordering of the set may change depending upon context. For
                        instance, if your enumerated set contains the names of stores in a given
                        region, this list may change as stores are added or closed, or as regions
                        are redefined. </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Subordinate Lists.</emphasis> A list of terms may themselves
                        identify lists of terms. In this respect, there is a
                            <emphasis>relationship</emphasis> (formal or implicit) that connects the
                        parent term (or <emphasis>context</emphasis>) and the child terms. A list of
                        countries, for instance, may contain a list of states, regions or
                        provinces.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Uniqueness.</emphasis> The combination of label
                        and code act as a defacto unique key for a given term. </para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis>Multiple representations.</emphasis> The set of metadata about a
                        term exists independently of the representations used for those terms - a
                        list of controlled vocabulary terms can be displayed as an XML construct of
                        various flavors, JSON, CSV, HTML lists or tables or any other underlying
                        format. </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para>Significantly, these are also characteristics that are found within the notion of both
            Semantic and REST oriented <emphasis>resources</emphasis>. In effect, the terms of a
            controlled vocabulary can be thought of as having an associated URI that identifies each
            term and that also identifies the context. Indeed, in all cases, the context for a list
            will be a term itself.</para><para>One other subtle point that brings the conflation of RESTful services and semantics
            full circle is the fact that conceptually each term in the given list can consequently
            be thought of as a reference to a resource, with an associated metadata bundle. That is
            to say, the URI (a semantic construct) for the term is also either itself or can be
            associated one-to-one with a unique URL (a RESTful construct) for the term.</para><para>Put another way, the context term and its correlated "child" terms are in effect a
                <emphasis>data feed</emphasis>. The term feed in this case is in fact intended to
            conflate with the notion of "news feed" - an Atom feed and an RSS feed are in fact both
            subclasses of data feeds in which the child nodes are "articles" that are returned in a
            date descending order, are paged, and may actually contain summary content (or even the
            full content) of the associated article as part of each feed entry.</para><para>More formally a data feed can be identified conceptually as the following</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Feed<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Feed URI - This identifies the context term's "address" and
                                systemic or global name.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Feed Label - This gives the "user centric" label that identifies
                                the feed.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Feed Code - This is an identifier or "value" that establishes the
                                internal (or local) state for the context term. </para></listitem><listitem><para>Feed Description - This is used to provide a more detailed
                                description of the context term, and could be anything from a few
                                lines of text to the body of a web page.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Feed Timestamp - This provides one or more timestamp entities that
                                identify the age of the context term.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Context Content - This is effectively the document payload
                                corresponding to the term in question. This will be a representation
                                of the resource indicated by the context item, and may be optional
                                (not all terms necessarily have content payloads, and not all
                                representations need to transmit those payloads if they do).</para></listitem><listitem><para>Relationship - This is a (potentially implicit) term identifying
                                the relationship of the context item with its associated entryset.
                                In a folder/file relationship, this will usually be implicit, but in
                                a semantic relationship, this will typically be the predicate of a
                                triple.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Entry Set - This is a set of entries that satisfy the relationship
                                between the context term and the associated child items in the
                                ontological space.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Entry URI - This identifiest the entry term's address and
                                        systemic or global name.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Feel Label - This gives the "user-centric" label that
                                        identifies the entry.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Entry Code - This provides the value for the entry
                                        term.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Entry Description - This provides a detailed description
                                        of the entry term.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Entry Timestamp - This provides one or more timestamp
                                        entities that identify the age of the entry term.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Entry Content - This is a representation of the entry
                                        term's corresponding resource.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem></itemizedlist>
                </para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>In theory, such a construct could be recursive, but ultimately it's worth
            understanding that any context term may in fact have multiple relationships that
            identify the subordinate entries, and that as some of these relationships are themselves
            orthogonal the ultimate structure that is conceptually described here is not a recursive
            descent tree, but is rather a graph that may ultimately end up resolving to multiple
            "roots". </para><para>Note that while the above may be seen as being a description of an atom or RSS feed,
            it is also, not accidentally, the structure of a typical "search" page, such as the
            results of a Google search query. In this case, the "context" term is the query
            expression passed. Typing in "Balisage", for instance, will establish the context for
            search to be the term "Balisage", while the relationship is implicitly those items that
            have some contextual relevance to the search. The search results will typically contain
            as a label the name of the site and the description being a short summary of the site
            itself as a snippet, with one or more links to different representations of that same
            resource as hypertext links. </para></section><section><title>URIs, CURIEs and Triplexes</title><para>There is a subtle distinction here - the URI of the resource is effectively the
            primary URL, but secondary links are still links to different representations of the
            same conceptual resource. Similarly an "image" search is in fact a feed that establishes
            its primary representation of resources as image URLs that are then rendered in a table
            or sequences of hyperlinked images. This only highlights the fact that the feed
            structure is in fact orthogonal to its representation. </para><para>In a typical website, the relationships between pages (which can be thought of as
            terms) have until fairly recently followed the folder/file model of containment that
            reflected the underlying file system that stored the relevant web-page resources. This
            meant that URIs typically tended to follow a containment format as well. However, over
            the course of the last decade the balance of development has shifted from a file system
            model to a database model for the storing and generation of web content, which has in
            turn shifted the URI structures for such resources to a more key oriented one.</para><para>This has led to some confusion about the construction of URIs and how they relate to
            REST. From a purely REST standpoint, a GUID can effectively identify a resource in a
            data-centric environment. The URL</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">http://www.myserver.com/term/AFD23C2F559A412C</programlisting><para>has one major benefit - it is globally unique. A URL rewriter script could do a lookup
            on the term and retrieve that particular key with very little parsing overhead. On the
            other hand, it tells the person requesting the term next to nothing about it, and it is
            arguable that, in many cases, being able to readily identify such a term by an easily
            interpretable string outweighs the parsing cost of that string.</para><para>After considerable experimentation (which went into the design of the Ontologist), all
            URIs were designed with the following convention:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">http://www.myserver.com/<emphasis>domainName</emphasis>/<emphasis>className</emphasis>/<emphasis>instanceName</emphasis>.<emphasis>faceName</emphasis></programlisting><para>The notation is broken into a domain, a class, and a instance, along with a
                <emphasis>face</emphasis> that identifies which particular representation to use for
            displaying the term feed. The class name establishes the category within a given domain,
            while the instance name establishes a human readible unique name for a given resource.
            For instance, the color blue would be given as "color/blue". Because classes themselves
            are also terms, they would be in the "class" category - "class/color".</para><para>The domain name arose from a realisation after working with a client who wanted to
            have classes that might be used by multiple different groups or customers. That is to
            say, there might be a "class/article" for multiple potential vendors, as well as the
            possibility of common classes that could be used by all vendors. While it is possible to
            pass these in parametrically, it was such a useful term for a number of reasons that it
            was made part of the key description.</para><para>Consequently, the Ontologist makes use of a triplex notation of the form</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve"><emphasis>domainName</emphasis>:<emphasis>className</emphasis>:<emphasis>instanceName</emphasis></programlisting><para>which uniquely identified each term in the system, <emphasis>relative</emphasis> to
            the server host. These were not universal because the application was ported over
            various servers, from development to staging to deployment, and as a consequence the
            specific URI could not correspond to a physical server.</para><para>It should be pointed out that these triplexes do have a direct correspondance with a
            qname. For server myserver.com, the corresponding qname for the color blue in the common
            domain would look like:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">{http://myserver.com:8050/common/color/}blue</programlisting><para>where everything within the brackets corresponds to the qualifying category term and
            everything after is the instance term, or conceptually, <code>common:color:</code>
            represents the qualifying category, and <code>blue</code> again represents the instance
            term. Similarly, the class of <code>color</code> would be in <code>common:class:</code>,
            corresponding to </para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">{http://myserver.com:8050/common/class/}color</programlisting><para>This notation is odd at first glance (its easy to get confused about the distinction
            between triplexes and CURIEs), but if you realize that a CURIE such as
                <code>commonColor:blue</code> corresponds to the triplex
                <code>common:color:blue</code>, it makes working with these resources in a semantic
            turtle notation somewhat more intuitive. </para><note><para>It's easy to worry about such "plexes" getting out of control, but in practice
                none of the applications that have been built on top of the ontologist has ever
                needed more than three such terms. The combination of domain, class and instance,
                along with the realization that everything else can be built with these, seems to
                suffice in limiting the size of such plexes.
        </para></note></section><section><title>Terms and Assertions</title><para>Every term in the system is represented internally as an XML document with a structure
            very similar to that of the feed format, albeit not quite identical. Listing 1 gives an
            example of such a entry.</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
&lt;entry xmlns="http://www.avalonconsult.com/xmlns/entry"&gt;
    &lt;metadata&gt;
        &lt;id&gt;common:color:Blue&lt;/id&gt;
        &lt;url&gt;/common/color/Blue&lt;/url&gt;
        &lt;class&gt;common:class:color&lt;/class&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;#0000FF&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;domain&gt;app:domain:Common&lt;/domain&gt;
        &lt;label key="label"&gt;Blue&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;description key="description" xml:space="preserve"&gt;Item 'Blue' with code '#0000FF' is in 
        class 'Color'.&lt;/description&gt;
        &lt;lastModified&gt;2012-05-02T19:02:51.361676-07:00&lt;/lastModified&gt;
    &lt;/metadata&gt;
    &lt;assertions&gt;
        &lt;assert subject="common:color:Blue" predicate="app:rel:instanceOf"
            object="common:class:Color"/&gt;
        &lt;assert subject="common:color:Blue" predicate="app:rel:domain" object="app:domain:Common"/&gt;
        &lt;assert subject="common:color:Blue" predicate="app:rel:termOf" object="app:class:Term"/&gt;
        &lt;assert subject="common:color:Blue" predicate="app:rel:workflow"
            object="app:workflow:Active"/&gt;
        &lt;assert subject="common:color:Blue" predicate="app:rel:label" object="#label"/&gt;
        &lt;assert subject="common:color:Blue" predicate="app:rel:description" object="#description"/&gt;
    &lt;/assertions&gt;
&lt;/entry&gt;
        </programlisting><para>This particular term establishes the color blue in the collection common:colors. The
            metadata block holds the context information. If there was a need for a payload it would
            be in a content element, though here there isn't any. What's perhaps most important is
            the assertion elements in the assertions set. </para><para>Each assertion is, in effect, an RDF triple, with a subject, predicate and object. In
            most cases the subject will be the id of the term. The predicate will be a term as well,
            usually one of a class of relationships that are defined within either the application
            domain, (part of app:rel:) or in some other domain (such as geo:rel:). The object will
            be another term resource in the system (the assumption here is that the system is
            self-contained).</para><para>The first predicate is especially worth studying. This defines the instanceOf
            relationship between the color blue and the class color within the common domain. In
            effect, this is a directed named vertex pointing to the common:class:Color term.
            Relative to the color:Blue term, this is an outbound relationship, relative to the
            class:color term, this is an inbound relationship (that is to say, class:Color does not
            have any corresponding outbound vector to the color blue). Thus, for the class:Color
            object, there is a SPARQL query statement of the form</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">?color app:rel:instanceOf common:class:Color.</programlisting><para>that identifies the set of subjects that have an outbound instanceOf assertion to
            class:Color.</para><para>This is a fairly reasonable operation for a triple store. What makes the Ontologist
            useful is that it provides a set of libraries for doing the same type of operations
            within an XQuery context in an XML data store such as MarkLogic (though it could do the
            same in eXist or other fourth generation XML databases). </para><note><para>A question that has been asked by reviewers of this paper is why RDF-XML wasn't employed for
                this. As it turns out, RDF-XML was explored as a potential vehicle to support this
                within the Ontologist initially, but it's structure generally does not index well
                within XML databases  - the queries involved are not especially complex but they are
                involved enough that indexing optimizations becomes a major factor. </para><para>Additionally, there is a certain degree of deliberate redundancy in the system
                because more traditional XQuery searches are also permitted on the Ontologist set,
                both to order the sequence of returned objects and to create filtered subsets. Given
                the advantages inherent for optimized searching and indexing, this generally
                outweighs the cost of maintaining redundant data in multiple forms (and is typical
                of XQuery applications).  </para></note><para>The structure of a class term can provide some additional insight into the
            application.</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
&lt;entry xmlns="http://www.rtis.com/xmlns/vocabulary"&gt;
    &lt;metadata&gt;
        &lt;qname&gt;common:class:color&lt;/qname&gt;
        &lt;url&gt;/common/class/color&lt;/url&gt;
        &lt;class&gt;common:class:fda_list&lt;/class&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;color&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;domain&gt;app:domain:Common&lt;/domain&gt;
        &lt;label key="label"&gt;Color&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;description xml:space="preserve" key="description"&gt;A vocabulary of colors as defined by 
        the FDA.&lt;/description&gt;
        &lt;lastModified&gt;2012-05-02T19:02:51.361676-07:00&lt;/lastModified&gt;
    &lt;/metadata&gt;
    &lt;assertions&gt;
        &lt;assert subject="common:class:color" predicate="app:rel:subClassOf"
            object="common:class:Class"/&gt;
        &lt;assert subject="common:class:color" predicate="app:rel:domain" object="app:domain:Common"/&gt;
        &lt;assert subject="common:class:color" predicate="app:rel:defaultRel"
            object="app:rel:instanceOf"/&gt;
        &lt;assert subject="common:class:color" predicate="app:rel:label" object="#label"/&gt;
        &lt;assert subject="common:class:color" predicate="app:rel:description" object="#description"/&gt;
        &lt;assert subject="common:class:color" predicate="app:rel:workflow"
            object="app:workflow:Active"/&gt;
    &lt;/assertions&gt;
&lt;/entry&gt;
        </programlisting><para>In this case, the term class:color is treated as a subclass of class:Class, which can
            be thought of as a folder of classes in the common domain. The term is also an item in
            the domain app:domain:Common (domain "sweeps" can include a fairly large number of
            terms. The third assertion, however, is one of the most powerful. The defaultRel
            predicate is used to determine, when no formal predicate is specified for the
            Ontologist, what predicate should be used. It is in fact used as in the following SPARQL
            query:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
 $term         app:rel:defaultRel ?relationship.
 ?child-terms  ?relationship      $term.
        </programlisting><para>$term here is the term from the XQuery invoking this call (such as
            common:class:color), ?relationship is the predicate determined by the default
            relationship and ?child-terms are the ones that satisfy this relations.</para><para>A similar
            relationship can be used to walk "up" the tree of default terms as if it was an
            inheritance tree (it typically is).</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
 $child-term   ?relationship      ?parent-term.
 ?parent-term  app:rel:defaultRel ?relationship.
        </programlisting><para>Although it should be noted that it is possible that a given term may in fact have
            more than one such relationship, meaning again that this system, while tending towards
            hierarchies in its structures, is still very much graphlike in the bigger
            picture.</para></section><section><title>Faces, Presentations and Ingestors</title><para>One consequence of the use of such XML embodiments of terms is that <emphasis>the entries involved can not only contain
                assertion pointers, but can also identify and invoke the representations used to
                both present content and to ingest it</emphasis>. An example can illustrate how this
            works.</para><para>A face, as indicated earlier, is identified by an extension (although it can also be
            identified parametrically from a query string parameter). The face is also identified as
            being tied in with an HTTP verb - PUT, POST, GET, or DELETE. Within an entry there is an
            optional &lt;pipelines&gt; element that can include maps of the form:</para><programlisting xml:space="preserve">
&lt;pipelines&gt;
    &lt;error href="/modules/app/class/Error/error.xq"/&gt;
    &lt;method match="GET"&gt;
        &lt;face match="html"&gt;
            &lt;action href="/path/to/class/get-html.xq"&gt;
                &lt;search ref="s1"/&gt;
            &lt;/action&gt;
        &lt;/face&gt;
        &lt;face match="keys.xml"&gt;
            &lt;action href="/path/to/class/get-html.xq"&gt;
                &lt;search ref="s1"/&gt;
            &lt;/action&gt;
            &lt;action href="/path/to/class/transform-to-keys-xml.xq"&gt;
                &lt;search ref="s1"/&gt;
            &lt;/action&gt;            
        &lt;/face&gt;
        &lt;face match="xml"&gt;
            &lt;action href="/path/to/class/get-html.xq"&gt;
                &lt;search ref="s1"/&gt;
            &lt;/action&gt;
        &lt;/face&gt;
        ..
    &lt;/method&gt;
&lt;/pipelines&gt;
        </programlisting><para>With the combination of method and face, it becomes possible to select a particular
            pipeline of actions for processing, along with the ability to retrieve additional
            parameters (not shown here). This uses a somewhat complex inheritance model. The
            Ontologist processor looks first in the term's XML to see if it has a processor. If it
            does, this is used. If it doesn't (or if the processor passes the modified object up the
            chain) the class corresponding to that term is queried, then the default rel for that
            term (in most cases, these are the same thing). This continues until either a match is
            found or the app:class:Term object (the root object in the system) is reached, which
            contains defaults for all potential views. </para><para>A particularly significant result of this of this is that a generic viewer can be created for terms, but that
            more specialized viewers can be built for specific classes - for instance, everything in
            a given domain may have different logos, arrangement of elements and even
            interpretations of content, and dedicated classes may be able to provide customized
            viewers or editors for specific types of payloads. This benefit extends to ingesters as
            well - input formats can be customized for specific class content, so that what gets
            saved may be processed from other sources. As an example, posting to a json face might
            take JSON content and convert it into XML before saving the resource, while posting to a
            zip face would unzip the content, for that particular class, and do some kind of post
            processing on the individual items in the file.</para></section><section><title>Summary</title><para>By combining such post processing with the creation of relevant assertions (though
            some editor interface) makes it possible for this system to effectively function as a
            semantic wiki or knowledge management system, with each term effectively being the same
            as one entry in the space. It is this piece which I plan on demonstrating at
            Balisage.</para><para>The Ontologist was written on MarkLogic Server 5.0, but it could reasonably work on
            any document-centric database, including XML databases such as eXist, JSON databases
            such as CouchDB, and Semantic Triple Stores that combine SPARQL and XQuery. The more
            important aspect of this is that it has the potential to be used in a wide variety of
            circumstances, from managing controlled vocabularies to hosting encyclopedic websites to
            acting as a Linked Data repository with queryable interfaces.</para></section><bibliography><title>Bibliography</title><bibliomixed xml:id="fielding2000" xreflabel="Roy Fielding 2000">Fielding, Roy Thomas<emphasis role="ital">Architectural Styles and the Design of Network-based Software Architectures, 
                PhD Dissertation Thesis</emphasis>, Chapter 5. Representational State Transfer. University of California, Irvine 
                © 2000. <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://www.ics.uci.edu/~fielding/pubs/dissertation/top.htm</link>.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed xml:id="semantics2011" xreflabel="Semantics for the Working Ontologist 2011">Allemang, Dean and Hendler,
                James<emphasis role="ital">Semantics for the Working Ontologists, Effective Modeling
                in RDFS and OWL</emphasis> Morgan Kaufmann, 2nd Edition © 2011.
                <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest">http://workingontologist.org</link>.</bibliomixed></bibliography></article>